<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.3//EN" 
	"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.3/docbookx.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % xinclude SYSTEM "../../libs/xinclude.mod">
%xinclude;
<!ENTITY % globalent SYSTEM "../../libs/global.ent">
%globalent;
]>
<chapter id="systemconfiguration-timedate">
    <title>Time &amp; Date</title>
    <para>Using the <guimenuitem>Time &amp; Date</guimenuitem> menu item you can change the
        time, date and timezone of your system. Just enter the hour, the minute and the second in
        the <guilabel>Time</guilabel> row to set the new time. The current date can be chosen in the
        calendar view below. If you need to change the years or month then just click on the arrows.
        It will not be changed before you confirm your settings by clicking on
        <guibutton>OK</guibutton>. </para>
    <para>If the <guilabel>Time Zone</guilabel> is set incorrectly just click on the
            <guilabel>Select Time Zone</guilabel> button. Your current geographical location will
        blink. Clicking into the map with the left mouse button zooms you into the map to make it
        easier to choose your location. The right mouse button gets you back to the world view.
        Please note that not every city is displayed on the map. Just choose the city that is
        closest to your location and within your time zone. If you do not like the world view you
        will find a selection field below where you can choose the city from a large list. </para>
    <para>If you have a frequent connection to the internet you should rather use public time
        servers. If you check the box labeled <guilabel>Synchronize clock with Internet
        servers</guilabel> your system will synchronize its time automatically every now and then.
        Click on <guibutton>Select Servers</guibutton> and select a server that is close to you.
        Although you can connect to multiple time servers it does not help you much. If you wonder
        what 127.127.1.0 is - this refers to your local system clock. If the server on the internet
        would be giving you wrong time information then your own clock will also be taken into
        account. </para>
    <important>
        <para>If you get an error message saying, &quot;NTP support is not running&quot;
            when you try to check the box to automatically synchronize your clock then you need to
            install the <application>ntp-server</application> package first. Please use Synaptic to
            install this package.
            <!-- todo: link to the synaptic section -->
        </para>
    </important>
</chapter>
