<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.3//EN" 
	"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.3/docbookx.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % xinclude SYSTEM "../../libs/xinclude.mod">
%xinclude;
<!ENTITY % globalent SYSTEM "../../libs/global.ent">
%globalent;
]>
<chapter id="systemconfiguration-loginscreen">
    <title>Login Screen</title>
    <para>The <interface>Login Screen</interface> is what you see when your system has started up.
        It allows you to log into your system. To make you feel even more at home you may change the
        appearance of that login dialog. </para>
    <para>When you select the <emphasis>Login Screen</emphasis> menu item, you are prompted for
        <emphasis>your</emphasis> password. Remember, there is no administrator password. If you
        need special privileges to change system-wide settings and you get asked for a password -
        then it is always your own password. </para>
    <para>Once the <interface>Login Screen Setup</interface> window appears you will see different
        tabs on the top. You can see that there is a difference between the <interface>Standard
        Greeter</interface> and the <interface>Graphical Greeter</interface>. Basically the
            <interface>Standard Greeter</interface> is a simple login window which does not look
        very fancy. It's hardly used. The <interface>Graphical Greeter</interface> instead is the
        login dialog that Ubuntu uses by default. It can have background images and there are a
        large number of so called themes that allow you to customise the look. </para>
    <para>Let us go through the tabs one by one: </para>
    <sect1>
        <title>General</title>
        <para>In the first section you can choose the type of greeter (standard or graphical) for
            local or remote sessions. <guilabel>Local</guilabel> means that you are sitting at the
            PC and want to login. In addition, you can allow other people to access your workstation
            from remote. A remote session means that all data that is usually displayed on your
            screen needs to be sent through the network. So it is advised to use the
                <interface>Standard Greeter</interface> which is more lightweight and therefore
            faster because it contains less fanciness.</para>
        <para>Unless you are living in a country that divides the day into <emphasis>a.m.</emphasis>
            and <emphasis>p.m.</emphasis> you are advised to set the <guilabel>always use 24 hour
                clock format</guilabel> option. </para>
        <para>The <guilabel>welcome string</guilabel> is the text that will be displayed on the
            login screen when you use the standard greeter. Equally the <guilabel>remote welcome
            string</guilabel> will be printed on the screen when you are logging in from other
            workstations. It will not be shown if you use the graphical greeter. </para>
        <para>Another nice but also dangerous feature is the <guilabel>automatic login</guilabel>.
            This will make the selected user to be logged in automatically. So you will hardly see
            the login screen but will be forwarded directly to the Gnome desktop. Please keep in
            mind that the login screen is for your own security and prevents that someone powers on
            your workstation and plays with your data. Even if you are usually the only person that
            uses your system you better do not use this feature. </para>
    </sect1>
    <sect1>
        <title>Standard Greeter</title>
        <para>As explained above the standard greeter is a more fanciless way to log into your
            system. The default is still the graphical greeter for local logins. If you chose to use
            the standard greeter you can customize the look and feel here. In the logo part on the
            left you can click on <guibutton>Browse</guibutton> and choose another image to be
            displayed on the login screen. </para>
        <para>On the bottom left there is a checkbox to enable the <guilabel>face
            browser</guilabel>. If properly configured it will display a photo for every user that
            can log into your system instead of just the user names. </para>
        <para>On the right side you can choose how you want the background to look. You may select
            no background, just a single color or a selectable image (which may be stretched or
            shrunk if it does not exactly match the screen size). </para>
    </sect1>
    <sect1>
        <title>Graphical Greeter</title>
        <para>working... </para>
    </sect1>
</chapter>
