<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.3//EN" 
	"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.3/docbookx.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % xinclude SYSTEM "../../libs/xinclude.mod">
%xinclude;
<!ENTITY % globalent SYSTEM "../../libs/global.ent">
%globalent;
]>
<chapter id="systemconfiguration-networking">
    <title>Networking</title>
    <para>The <interface>Network settings</interface> window helps you control your network card
        and IP address settings. You will see four tabs: </para>
    <sect1>
        <title>Connections</title>
        <para>In the <guilabel>Connections</guilabel> tab you see a list of your network cards that
            Ubuntu can use. If you want to change your IP address settings then please click on the
            <guibutton>Properties</guibutton> button and enter the appropriate information in the
                <interface>Interface properties</interface> window. There you can choose whether the
            device will be activate when your system starts. And you can either choose to set the IP
            address, subnet mask and gateway address manually (you enter it and it will not be
            changed automatically) or it will be set automatically using the BOOTP or DHCP servers
            in your local network. Please ask your network administrator whether your network
            provides DHCP. </para>
        <para>At the bottom you can choose from a list of <guilabel>Current network
            profiles</guilabel> that you can enter. Profiles are useful when you have a portable
            computer like a notebook and need to connect to different networks (like at home and at
            work). It can remember your current settings in a profile and have it set automatically
            by choosing the desired profile from the list. </para>
        <para>Add... </para>
    </sect1>
    <sect1>
        <title>General</title>
        <para>Text</para>
    </sect1>
    <sect1>
        <title>DNS</title>
        <para>Text</para>
    </sect1>
    <sect1>
        <title>Hosts</title>
        <para>Text</para>
    </sect1>
</chapter>
