<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.3//EN" 
	"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.3/docbookx.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % globalent SYSTEM "../../../libs/global.ent">
%globalent;
<!ENTITY % cdo-C SYSTEM "../../../libs/cdo-C.ent">
%cdo-C;
<!ENTITY % gnome-menus-zh_CN SYSTEM "../../../ubuntu/libs/gnome-menus-zh_CN.ent">
%gnome-menus-zh_CN;
<!ENTITY % xinclude SYSTEM "../../../libs/xinclude.mod">
%xinclude;
<!ENTITY language "en">
<!ENTITY ubuntu '<phrase>Ubuntu</phrase>'>
]>
<chapter id="add-applications" status="complete">
	<title>添加、删除和更新应用程序</title>

	<sect1 id="add-applications-introduction" status="complete">
		<title>What is a package manager?</title>
		<para>To add or remove applications in Ubuntu, you need to use a <emphasis>package manager</emphasis>. This is a program that installs and uninstalls software, and keeps track of all the components each piece of software needs.
		</para>
		<para>There are three main package managers you can use in Ubuntu:</para>
		<itemizedlist>
			<listitem><para><link linkend="gnome-app-install"><application>Add/Remove Programs</application></link> - The easiest way to install and uninstall programs.</para></listitem>
			<listitem><para><link linkend="synaptic"><application>Synaptic</application></link> - Advanced control of software and other system components.</para></listitem>
			<listitem><para><link linkend="apt"><application>Apt</application></link> - For if you prefer using the Terminal.</para></listitem>
		</itemizedlist>
		<para>If you open more than one of these programs at once, they may not work. Close them all and open just one.</para>
		<para>You need administrative access to use any of these programs.</para>
		<itemizedlist>
			<listitem><para><xref linkend="root-and-sudo"/></para></listitem>
		</itemizedlist>
	</sect1>
  <sect1 id="gnome-app-install" status="complete">
		<title>添加/删除应用程序</title>
		<para>With the <guimenuitem>Add/Remove…</guimenuitem> item in the <guimenu>Applications</guimenu> menu, you can install programs to do new things with Ubuntu. You can also remove programs you don’t want. You need administrative access to use <application>Add/Remove Programs</application>.</para>
		<itemizedlist>
			<listitem><para><xref linkend="root-and-sudo"/></para></listitem>
		</itemizedlist>
		<para>If you know the name of a program you want to install, enter it in the <guilabel>Search</guilabel> field. Otherwise, begin by choosing a software category on the left.</para>
		<para>Programs that are already installed begin with a check mark next to their name. Uncheck a program if you want to remove it from your computer.</para>
		<para>When you click <guibutton>Apply</guibutton> or <guibutton>OK</guibutton>, any new software will be downloaded from the Internet, and Ubuntu will make the changes you selected. If you have not activated the online package archive, you may be asked to insert your Ubuntu CD-ROM to install some packages.</para>
		<para>Some software cannot be installed or removed using <application>Add/Remove Applications</application>. If you cannot find the package you are looking for, click <guibutton>Advanced</guibutton> to open Synaptic.
		</para>
	</sect1>
	<sect1 id="synaptic" status="complete">
		<title>Synaptic 软件包管理器</title>
		<para><application>Synaptic</application> is an advanced package management application that can install and remove every package available to your system. The interface is graphical like <application>Add/Remove Applications</application>, but presents much more information and gives you complete control over the software on your computer.</para>
		<para>To launch <application>Synaptic</application>, from the <guimenu>System</guimenu> menu choose  
			<menuchoice>
				<guisubmenu>Administration</guisubmenu>
				<guimenuitem>Synaptic Package Manager</guimenuitem>
			</menuchoice>.
			You need administrative access to use <application>Synaptic</application>.</para>
		<itemizedlist>
			<listitem><para><xref linkend="root-and-sudo"/></para></listitem>
		</itemizedlist>
		<para>If you know the name of the package you want to install or remove, click the <guibutton>Search</guibutton> button, and enter the package name or a short search term. You can also search for packages by description (for example, you can find all packages mentioning <quote><wordasword>arcade</wordasword></quote> or <quote><wordasword>mathematics</wordasword></quote>).</para>
		<para>Use the categories on the left to filter the list of packages. To return to the list of categories after doing a search, click <guibutton>Sections</guibutton>.</para>
		<para>To install a package, click the box next to it and choose <guimenuitem>Mark for installation</guimenuitem>. If you change your mind, choose <guimenuitem>Unmark</guimenuitem>. To remove a package that is already installed, choose <guimenuitem>Mark for Removal</guimenuitem>.</para>
		<para>When you’ve finished, click <guibutton>Apply</guibutton> and Ubuntu will make the changes you selected. If you don’t want to make any changes, close the window instead.</para>
	</sect1>
	<sect1 id="apt" status="complete">
		<title>Command-Line Package Management With APT</title>
		<para>If you are comfortable using the Terminal, you can use <application>apt</application> (Advanced Packaging Tool) to install or remove software. You need administrative access to use <application>apt</application>.</para>
		<itemizedlist>
			<listitem><para><xref linkend="root-and-sudo"/></para></listitem>
		</itemizedlist>
		<para>
			To update the local list of packages, enter in a Terminal:
			<screen>sudo apt-get update</screen>
		</para>
		<para>
			To install all available updates:
			<screen>sudo apt-get upgrade</screen>
		</para>
		<para>
			To install a package:
			<screen>sudo apt-get install <emphasis>package</emphasis></screen>
		</para>
		<para>
			To remove a package:
			<screen>sudo apt-get remove <emphasis>package</emphasis></screen>
		</para>
		<para>
			To list other <application>apt</application> commands and options:
			<screen>apt-get help</screen>
		</para>
		<para>For more information, see <ulink url="&debian-apt;">Debian’s <application>apt</application> manual</ulink>.</para>
	</sect1>
	<sect1 id="install-file" status="complete">
		<title>安装单个软件包文件</title>
		<para>The preferred method of installing programs is via the package managers described in this chapter. However, although the Ubuntu package archives are very large, it is possible that you may wish to install a package that is not available in the Ubuntu archives. If this happens, you can also download and install files from websites.</para>
					<caution>
						<para>在您安装文件之前确认您所下载的文件来自一个安全的源是重要的。</para>
					</caution>
		<para>There are many different kinds of Linux package files. Most of these are associated with the package managers of specific Linux distributions. Examples are <emphasis>Debian Package</emphasis> files (<emphasis>.deb</emphasis> files), <emphasis>RPM Package Manager</emphasis> files (<emphasis>.rpm</emphasis> files), and <emphasis>Tarballs</emphasis> (<emphasis>.tar</emphasis> files).</para>
		<para>本部分内容将介绍如何安装这些单个文件。</para>
		<warning><para>无法保证这些文件将与您系统兼容，如果您安装这些文件的话，您也将无法得到安全更新。有鉴于此，如果您想安装程序的话，请尽可能通过软件包管理器来安装由 Ubuntu 自身提供的应用程序软件包。</para></warning>

		<sect2 id="install-deb" status="complete">
			<title>安装/卸载 <emphasis>.deb</emphasis> 文件</title>
					<para>这些是<emphasis>Debian 软件包</emphasis>。这些与 Ubuntu 相关的软件包文件使用 <emphasis>.deb</emphasis> 后缀是因为 Ubuntu 与 Debian GNU/Linux 发行版有着紧密的关系。您将需要管理权限来安装 <emphasis>.deb</emphasis> 文件 (参见 <xref linkend="root-and-sudo"/>)。</para>
						<para>To install a <emphasis>.deb</emphasis> file, double-click on it. If you prefer using the Terminal, enter:
						<screen>sudo dpkg -i package_file.deb</screen>
						</para>
						<para>To uninstall a <emphasis>.deb</emphasis> file, deselect it in your package manager. Or from a Terminal, enter:
						<screen>sudo dpkg -r package_name</screen>
						</para>
		</sect2>
		<sect2 id="alien" status="complete">
			<title>将 <emphasis>.rpm</emphasis> 文件转为 <emphasis>.deb</emphasis> 文件</title>
					<para>另一种软件包文件是 <emphasis>.rpm</emphasis>为后缀的 <emphasis>Red Hat 软件包管理器</emphasis>文件。我们并不建议在 Ubuntu 系统中安装它们。在绝大多数情况下，Ubuntu 自身的 <emphasis>.deb</emphasis> 软件包是可用的。然而，如果绝对必要，可以使用程序 <application>alien</application> 将 <emphasis>.rpm</emphasis> 文件转化为<emphasis>.deb</emphasis> 文件。</para>
						<para>
							In a terminal, enter:
							<screen>sudo alien <emphasis>package_file.rpm</emphasis></screen>
						</para>
						<para>
							If you get a <quote>command not found</quote> or similar error, install <application>alien</application> before trying again:
							<screen>sudo apt-get install alien</screen>
							
						</para>
			</sect2>
			<sect2 id="tarballs" status="complete">
				<title>安装 <emphasis>tarballs</emphasis></title>
					<para>以 <emphasis>.tar.gz</emphasis> 或 <emphasis>.tar.bz2</emphasis> 作为后缀名的文件是在 Linux 和 Unix 中被广泛使用的 <emphasis>tarballs</emphasis> 的打包文件。</para>
					<para>如果在任何 Ubuntu 软件库中都没有 Ubuntu 的软件包，您可以按照软件包自带的指示使用命令行来安装和卸载 Tarball 文件。</para>
					<para>Tarballs 通常包括程序的源代码，并且需要 <emphasis>编译</emphasis> 才能使用。要做到这一点，一般需要其它软件 (参见 <xref linkend="build-essential"/>)。</para>
		</sect2>
	</sect1>
	    <sect1 id="extra-repositories" status="complete">
		<title>Software Repositories</title>
			<sect2 status="review"><title>什么软件库</title>
			<para>Ubuntu 能够安装成千上万个程序。这些程序被放在软件库 (<emphasis>软件库 /emphasis&gt;)  emphasis&gt;MainRestricted /emphasis&gt;Universe  Multiverse</emphasis></para> 
			<para>软件分类原则基于以下两个因素：</para>
				<itemizedlist>
					<listitem>
						<para>软件开发团队对软件的支持程度</para>
					</listitem>
					<listitem>
						<para>The level of compliance the program has to the <ulink url="&ubuntu-philosophy;">Free Software Philosophy</ulink>.</para>
					</listitem>
				</itemizedlist>
			<para>You can find more information about the Repositories available <ulink url="&ubuntu-components;">on the website</ulink>.</para>
			<para>标准 Ubuntu 安装 CD 包括来自 <emphasis>Main</emphasis> 和 <emphasis>Restricted</emphasis> 类的一些软件。一旦您的系统知道这些软件库在 Internet 上的位置，就可以安装更多的软件程序。使用在您系统中已经安装软件包管理工具，您可以直接在 Internet 上搜索、安装和更新软件的任何部分，而无需 CD。</para>
		</sect2>
		<sect2 status="complete">
			<title>添加其它软件库</title>
			<para>To install software from the <quote>Universe</quote> or <quote>Multiverse</quote> repositories:</para>
			<procedure>
				<step>
					<para>Open &software-properties;.</para>
				</step>
				<step>
					<para>选择 <guibutton>添加</guibutton></para>
				</step>
				<step>
					<para>To use the <quote>Universe</quote> repository, turn on <guilabel>Community Maintained (Universe)</guilabel>.</para>
					<note>
						<para>添加这个软件库将意味着世界上大多数的自由软件都可以安装在您系统中。该软件被 Ubuntu 社区自愿者中选出的小组支持，但并不被 Ubuntu核心开发团队支持，同时也许没有包括安全更新。</para>
					</note>
				</step>
				<step>
					<para>To use the <quote>Multiverse</quote> repository, turn on <guilabel>Non-free (Multiverse)</guilabel>.</para>
					<warning>
						<para>添加这个软件库将意味着被归为 <emphasis>非自由</emphasis> 类的软件可以安装在您系统中。该软件可能在某些区域可能不被允许。当从该软件库中安装每一个软件包时，您将确保您国家的法律允许您使用它。重覆一遍，该软件也许没有包括安全更新。</para>
					</warning>
				</step>
				<step><para>点击 <guibutton>Close</guibutton> 按钮保存所作的更改然后退出。</para>
				</step>
			</procedure>
			</sect2>
		</sect1>
	    <sect1 id="updates" status="complete">
		<title>更新</title>
			<para>有时 Ubuntu 开发人员会为 Ubuntu 系统中的应用程序和软件包发布特性和安全更新。</para>
			<para>当有新的升级时，Ubuntu 将在您的通知区域中弹出一个红色图标。要更新您的系统，点击红色按钮，输入密码并点击 <guibutton>确定</guibutton>。</para>
			<para><application>更新管理器</application>程序会列出可用的升级或补丁：点击<guibutton>安装更新</guibutton>即可下载并安装这些更新。Ubuntu 会自动通过网络下载并安装这些更新。</para>
			<para>待<application>更新管理器</application>完成系统更新后，点击<guibutton>关闭</guibutton>按钮关闭弹出窗口，然后关闭<application>更新管理器</application>结束系统更新。</para>
			<note>
				<para>当安装某些重要的更新后，有可能需要重启计算机。这时，Ubuntu就会通过通知区的弹出信息框和图标来告知您这一点。</para>
			</note>
	   </sect1>
</chapter>

