<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.1.2//EN" 
	"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.1.2/docbookx.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % globalent SYSTEM "../../../libs/global.ent">
%globalent;
<!ENTITY % cdo-C SYSTEM "../../../libs/cdo-C.ent">
%cdo-C;
<!ENTITY % gnome-menus-C SYSTEM "../../libs/gnome-menus-C.ent">
%gnome-menus-C;
<!ENTITY language "&EnglishAmerican;">
<!ENTITY language "en">
]>
<?db.chunk.max_depth 0?>
<?yelp:chunk-depth 0?>
<article id="art-about-ubuntu" status="complete" lang="ku">
<articleinfo>
  <title>Ubuntu - Ji bo mirovan Linux!</title>
	<legalnotice id="Credits-And-License">
	    <title>Amadekar û Peyman</title>
	    <para>Nivîskarên koma pelgekirina Ubuntu yên jêr ev pelde destek kirin:</para>
		 <itemizedlist>
			<listitem>
		    <para>Matthew East</para>
			</listitem>
		 </itemizedlist>
	    <para>Kesên navê wan li jêr alîkariya vê pelgeyê kirin:</para>
		 <itemizedlist>
			<listitem>
		    <para>Mark Shuttleworth</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
		    <para>Robert Stoffers</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
		    <para>Jerome Gotangco</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
		    <para>Brian Burger</para>
			</listitem>
		</itemizedlist>
	    <para>Ev pelge li gor peymana dualî hatiye halekî ku dikare bête bikaranîn (GNU Free Documentation License (GFDL) ve Creative Commons ShareAlike 2.0 License (CC-BY-SA)).</para>
	    <para>Ubuntu koda çavkaniya pelgekirinê li gor van peymanan dikare biguhere, pêşde bixe û firehtir bike. Xebatên jêzayî divê li bin banê herdu peymanan jî were pêşkêşkirin.</para>
	    <para>Bi armanca sûde jê were girtin ev pelde tê belavkirin, lê tu GARANTIYA WÊ NÎN E; tew WEKÎ DI FERAXETNAMEYÊ DE HATIYE GOTIN garantiya wê nîn e ku DIKARE JI BO BAZIRGANIYÊ  AN JÎ ARMANCEKE DIN bête bikaranîn.</para>
	    <para>Jibergirên van peymanan di lehêqên vê pirtûkê de cih digire. Ji bo wergerê du dikarî ji URL ya jêrîn xwe bigihînî guhertoyên online.</para>
	    <itemizedlist>
	        <listitem>
	            <para>&fdl-url;</para>
	        </listitem>
	        <listitem>
	            <para>&cc-attrib;</para>
	        </listitem>
	    </itemizedlist>
	</legalnotice>
        &copyright;<copyright><year>2006</year><holder>Rêzan Tovjîn (rezan@bername.net)</holder></copyright>
	<authorgroup>
		&author-ubuntu-documentation-project;
	</authorgroup>
        <abstract>
            <para>Ev pelge destpêkeke Ubuntu ye. Felsefe û koka Ubuntu tîne zimên, agahiyê dide ku tu çawa dikarî alîkariya Ubuntu bikî û çawa alîkariyê ji Ubuntu wergirî.</para>
        </abstract>
        &disclaimer;
        &publisher;
  </articleinfo>
    <para>
        <inlinemediaobject>
            <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref="../../libs/img/ubuntuheader.png" format="PNG"/>
            </imageobject>
  <textobject>
    <phrase>Logoya Ubuntu</phrase>
  </textobject>
        </inlinemediaobject>
    </para>
            <para>Thank you for your interest in Ubuntu &distro-rev;
                - the <emphasis>&distro-version;</emphasis> - released in &distro-release-date;.
				</para> 
		<para>Ubuntu is an entirely open source operating system built around the 
		  <emphasis>Linux</emphasis> kernel. The Ubuntu community is built around the ideals enshrined in the <ulink url="&ubuntu-philosophy;">Ubuntu Philosophy</ulink>: that software should be
                available free of charge, that software tools should be usable
                by people in their local language and despite any disabilities,
                and that people should have the freedom to customize and alter
                their software in whatever way they see fit. For those reasons: 
                <itemizedlist>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Ubuntu her dem wê belaş be. Ji bo "guhertoyên saziyan" wê tu pere neyê stendin, em heman azadiyan ji bo her kesî pêşkêş dike û encamên baş pêşkêş dike.</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Ubuntu, heta ku pêkan be ji bo bêhtir kes bikaribin bi kar bînin, wergerên herî baş ên civata nivîsbariya azad û bingeha pêwendiya wan dihundirîne.</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Ubuntu bi pergal û pêşî diyar dike dûre diweşîne; ji her şeş mehan carekê weşana nû derdikeve bazarê. Tu dikarî weşana wê ya heyî ya baş û weşana wê ya pêşde diçe ya heyî bi kar bînî. Her weşan bi kêmanî 18 mehan tê destekirin.</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Ubuntuyê xwe bi tevahî daye zagonên pêşxistina nivîsbariya çavkanî azad; em mirovan teşwîk dikin ji bo nivîsbariya çavkanî azad bi kar bînin, pêşde bixin û di vê riyê de bimeşin.</para>
                    </listitem>
                </itemizedlist>
            </para>
		<para>Ji bo agahiyên zêdetir bibînî here <ulink url="&ubuntu-web;">Malpera Ubuntu </ulink>.</para>

            <sect1 id="about-ubuntu-name" status="complete">
                    <title>Der barê nav de</title>
							<para>Ubuntu is a South African ethical ideology focusing on
                        people's allegiances and relations with each other. The
                        word comes from the Zulu and Xhosa languages. Ubuntu
                        (pronounced "oo-BOON-too") is seen as a
                        traditional African concept, is regarded as one of the
                        founding principles of the new republic of South Africa
                        and is connected to the idea of an African Renaissance.
							</para>
							<para>Zagona Ubuntu, bi awayekî hêsan dikare wekî "li hember yên din mirovatî" bête wergerandin. Wergereke din jî dikare "Baweriya bi pêwendiya parvekirina navnetewî ya hemû mirovahiyê dike yek" be.</para>
			<blockquote><attribution>Serpîskopos Desmond Tûtû</attribution>
				<para>"A person with ubuntu is open and available to others, affirming of others, does not feel threatened that others are able and good, for he or she has a proper self-assurance that comes from knowing that he or she belongs in a greater whole and is diminished when others are humiliated or diminished, when others are tortured or oppressed."
				</para>
			</blockquote>
                    	<para>As a platform based on Linux, the Ubuntu
                        operating system brings the spirit of ubuntu to the software
                        world.
							</para>
		</sect1>
                <sect1 id="free-software" status="complete">
                    <title>Nivîsbariya Azad</title>
                    		<para>Projeya Ubuntu, bi tevahî xwe daye zagonên pêşxistina çavkaniya azad; şexs ji bo bikaranîna çavkaniya azad, pêşxistina wê û belavkirina wê tên teşîkirin. Ev jî wateya ku dê Ubuntu her dem belaş be.</para>
                    <para>However, this means more than just being available at zero cost. The philosophy of free software is that people should be free to use software in all the ways that are "socially useful". "Free software" doesn't just mean that you shouldn't have to pay for it, it also means that you should be able to use the software in any way you wish: the code that makes up free software is available for anyone to download, change, fix, and use in any way. So apart from the fact that free software is often available without charge, this freedom also has technical advantages: when programs are developed, the hard work of others can be used and built upon. With non-free software, this cannot happen and when programs are developed, they have to start from scratch. For this reason the development of free software is fast, efficient and exciting!
                    </para>
			<para>You can find out more about the philosophy of free software <ulink url="&gnu-philosophy;">here</ulink>.
			</para>
                </sect1>
                <sect1 id="ubuntu-difference" status="complete">
                    <title>Cudahî</title>
                    	<para>There are many different operating systems based on Linux:
 	                 Debian, SuSE, Gentoo, RedHat, and Mandriva are examples. 
			   Ubuntu is yet another contender in what
                        is already a highly competitive world. So what makes
                        Ubuntu different?
							</para>
                    	<para>Based on Debian, one of the most widely acclaimed,
                        technologically advanced, and well-supported
                        distributions, Ubuntu
                        aims to create a distribution that provides
                        an up-to-date and coherent Linux system for desktop and
                        server computing. Ubuntu includes a number of carefully
                        selected packages from the Debian distribution and
                        retains its powerful package management system which
                        allows easy installation and clean removal of programs. Unlike most
                        distributions that ship with a large amount of software
                        that may or may not be of use, Ubuntu's list of packages
                        is reduced to a number of important applications of high
                        quality.
							</para>
                    	<para>By focusing on quality, Ubuntu produces a robust and
                        feature-rich computing environment that is suitable for
                        use in both home and commercial environments. The
                        project takes the time required to focus on finer
                        details and is able to release a version featuring the
                        latest and greatest of today's software once every 6
                        months. Ubuntu is available in flavours for the i386
                        (386/486/Pentium(II/III/IV) and Athlon/Duron/Sempron
                        processors), AMD64 (Athlon64, Opteron, and new 64-bit
                        Intel processors), and PowerPC (iBook/Powerbook, G4 and
                        G5) architectures.
							</para>
                </sect1>
                <sect1 id="ubuntu-desktop" status="complete">
                    <title>Sermase</title>
                    	<para>The default desktop environment for Ubuntu is <ulink url="&gnome;">GNOME</ulink>, a leading UNIX and
                        Linux desktop suite and development platform.
							</para>
                    	<para>Another leading UNIX and Linux desktop is <ulink url="&kde;">KDE</ulink>. The <ulink url="&kubuntu-main;">Kubuntu</ulink> project
                        offers Ubuntu users an alternative choice
                        to the default GNOME desktop environment. Thanks
                        to the efforts of the Kubuntu team, Ubuntu users are now
                        able to install and use the KDE desktop easily on their
                        system. To get a working install of Kubuntu on an Ubuntu
			 install, install the <application>kubuntu-desktop</application> package. 
			Once kubuntu-desktop is installed, one 
			can choose to use either a Gnome or KDE desktop environment.
							</para>
                </sect1>
                <sect1 id="version-numbers" status="complete">
                    <title>Hejmarên guherto û weşanê:</title>
                    	<para>The Ubuntu version numbering scheme is based on the
                        date we release a version of the distribution. The
                        version number comes from the year and month of the
                        release rather than reflecting the actual version of the
                        software. Our first release (Warty Warthog) was in
                        October 2004 so its version was 4.10. This version (&distro-version;) was
                        released in &distro-release-date; so its version number is &distro-rev;.
							</para>
                </sect1>
                <sect1 id="ubuntu-backing-support" status="complete">
                    <title>Alîkarî û destek</title>
                    	<para>Ubuntu is maintained by a quickly growing community.
                        The project is sponsored by <ulink url="&canonical-url;">Canonical Ltd.</ulink>, a
                        holding company founded by Mark Shuttleworth. Canonical
                        employs the core Ubuntu developers and offers support and consulting services
                        for Ubuntu.
							</para>
			<para>Canonical Ltd also sponsors a number of other Open Source software projects, about which more information can be found on the <ulink url="&canonical-url;">Canonical website</ulink>.
			</para>
                </sect1>
            <sect1 id="about-linux" status="complete">
            <title>Linux çi ye?</title>
            <para>The <ulink url="&kernel;">Linux kernel</ulink>, pronounced
		'lee-nucks' is the heart of the Ubuntu operating system.
		  A kernel is an important part of
                any operating system, providing the communication bridge between 
                hardware and software.
				</para>
            <para>Linux, di sala 1991'ê de ji aliyê xwendevanekî Finî yê bi navê Linus Torvalds ve hate pêşxistin. Wê demê tenê li ser pergala i386 dixebitî û bi rastî wê demê ji bo avantaja mîmariya i386 bi dest bixe hatibû avakirin û jibergirtiyeke dendika UNIX bû ku serbixwe hatibû afirandin.</para>
            <para>Di v3e demê de ji ber çalakiyên bikêrhatî ên pêşdebirinê ji alî gelek kesan ji seranserê cîhanê, Divê ku Ubuntu li ser hemû sepanên nûjen bixebite.</para>
            <para>The Linux kernel has gained an ideological importance as well as a technical one.
		  There is an entire community of people who believe in the ideals
                of free software and spend their time helping to make open
                source technology as good as it can be.
				</para>
            <para>People in this community gave rise to initiatives such as
                Ubuntu, standards committees that shape the development of the
                Internet, organizations like the Mozilla Foundation, responsible
                for creating Mozilla Firefox, and countless other software
                projects from which you've certainly benefited in the past.
				</para>
            <para>The spirit of open source, commonly attributed to Linux, is
                influencing software developers and users everywhere to drive
                communities with common goals.
				</para>
        </sect1>
        <sect1 id="about-gnu" status="complete">
            <title>GNU çi ye?</title>
            <para>The <emphasis>GNU Project</emphasis>, pronounced “guh-noo”, was
		  launched in 1984 to develop a complete
                UNIX style operating system which is comprised of free software: the GNU
                system. Variants of the GNU operating system,
                which use the Linux kernel, are now widely used.
				</para>
            <para>Projeya GNU bi heta bi dawî bi felsefeya bernameyên azad re girêdayî ye û dibe navenda projeyên jêderk, yên mîna Ubuntu. Ev Şîroveya bernameyên azad e <xref linkend="free-software"/>.</para>
			</sect1>

</article>

