<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.3//EN" 
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.3/docbookx.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % globalent SYSTEM "../../../libs/global.ent">
%globalent;
<!ENTITY % cdo-C SYSTEM "../../../libs/cdo-C.ent">
%cdo-C;
<!ENTITY % kde SYSTEM "../../libs/kde.ent">
%kde;
<!ENTITY % kde-general SYSTEM "/usr/share/apps/ksgmltools2/customization/obsolete/general.entities">
%kde-general;
<!ENTITY % xinclude SYSTEM "../../../libs/xinclude.mod">
%xinclude;
<!ENTITY language "en">
]>
<chapter id="introduction" status="review">
    <title>Introdução</title>
    <para>Este capítulo apresenta alguma informaçãod e fundo sobre o Kubuntu, como obtê-lo e como encontrar ajuda com o Kubuntu.</para>
    <sect1 id="about-kubuntu" status="complete">
        <title>Sobre o Kubuntu</title>
        <para>Thank you for your interest in Kubuntu &distro-rev;
            - the <emphasis>&distro-version;</emphasis> release.</para> 
        <para>Kubuntu is an entirely open source operating system built around the 
            Linux kernel. The Kubuntu community is built around the ideals
            enshrined in the <ulink url="&ubuntu-philosophy;">Ubuntu 
                Philosophy</ulink>: that software should be
            available free of charge, that software tools should be usable
            by people in their local language and despite any disabilities,
            and that people should have the freedom to customize and alter
            their software in whatever way they see fit. For those reasons: 
            <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Kubuntu will always be free of charge, and there is
                        no extra fee for the "enterprise
                        edition," we make our very best work
                        available to everyone on the same Free terms.
                    </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>O Kubuntu inclui a melhor infra-estrutura de suporte a traduções e acessibilidade que a comunidade de aplicações informáticas livres ("Free Software") tem para oferecer, de modo a tornar o Ubuntu utilizável pelo maior número possível de pessoas.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>O Kubuntu é lançado de modo regular e previsível; todos os seis meses é lançada uma nova versão. Pode utilizar a versão estável corrente ou a versão que está actualmente em desenvolvimento. Cada versão é suportada, pelo menos, durante 18 meses.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>O Kubuntu respeita os princípios do desenvolvimento do software de código aberto; todos são encorajados a utilizar software de código aberto,a melhorá-lo e a divulgá-lo.</para>
                </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
        </para>
        <para>A comunidade do Kubuntu é feita de criadores de aplicações informáticas, escritores de documentação, tradutores, artistas gráficos, tradutores, pessoas que testam o sistema, e o mais importante, as pessoas que usam o Kubuntu diariamente. Nós convidamo- lo a juntar-se a esta comunidade e a ajudar a tornar o Kubuntu o sistema operativo que você, a sua família, amigos e colegas gostarão de utilizar. Ajude-nos a traduzir o Kubuntu para o seu idioma, experimente-o em hardware novo ou fora do comum, melhore a experiência de outros utilizadores com dicas, respostas a perguntas frequentes, ou ajude a definir a direcção do Kubuntu dando a sua opinião sobre o software que mais prefere.</para>
        <para>Descubra mais no <ulink url="&kubuntu-web;">sitio web do Kubuntu</ulink>.</para>
        <sect2 id="about-kubuntu-name" status="complete">
            <title>Sobre o Nome</title>
            <para>Kubuntu is based on the Ubuntu system, but with the latest KDE packages. Kubuntu
                means "towards humanity" in Bemba. Kubuntu is pronounced
                "koo-boon-too". </para> 
            <!-- Needs some word foo -->
            <para>Ubuntu é uma ideologia ética Sul Africana que se foca nas alianças e relações entre as pessoas. A palavra vem dos idiomas Zulu e Xhosa. Ubuntu (pronunciado "oo-BOON-too") é visto como um conceito tradicional africano, visto também como um dos princípios fundadores da nova república da África do Sul estando ligado à ideia de um Renascimento Africano.</para>
            <para>Uma tradução aproximada do princípio de Ubuntu é "humanidade para com os outros". Outra tradução poderia ser: "a crença numa ligação universal de partilha que conecta toda a humanidade".</para>
            <blockquote><attribution>Arcebispo Desmond Tutu</attribution>
                <para>"Uma pessoa com ubuntu é aberta e disponível para os outros, apoia os outros, não se sente ameaçada quando os outros são bons e capazes, porque ele ou ela tem uma confiança própria que advém de saber que ele ou ela pertence a um todo que é diminuído quando os outros são humilhados ou diminuídos, quando os outros são torturados ou oprimidos."</para>
            </blockquote>
            <para>
                As a platform based on Linux, the Kubuntu
                operating system brings the spirit of ubuntu to the software
                world.
            </para>
        </sect2>
        <sect2 id="free-software" status="complete">
            <title>Software Livre</title>
            <para>O projecto Kubuntu está totalmente comprometido com os princípios de desenvolvimento de software livre; as pessoas são encorajadas a utilizar software livre, a melhorá-lo e divulgá-lo. Isto significa que o Kubuntu é e será sempre gratuito.</para>
            <para>
                However, this means more than just being available at
                zero cost. The philosophy of Free Software is that
                people should be free to use software in all the ways
                that are "socially useful". "Free
                software" not only means that you shouldn't have
                to pay for it, it also means that you should be able to
                use the software in any way you wish.  The code that
                makes up Free Software is available for anyone to
                download, change, fix, and use in any way. So apart
                from the fact that Free Software is often available
                without charge, this freedom also has technical
                advantages: when programs are developed, the hard work
                of others can be used and built upon. This cannot
                happen with non-free Software, and when programs are
                developed, they have to start from scratch. For this
                reason the development of Free Software is fast,
                efficient and exciting!
            </para>
            <para>You can find out more about the philosophy of Free Software
                <ulink url="&gnu-philosophy;">here</ulink>.</para>
        </sect2>
        <sect2 id="kubuntu-difference" status="complete">
            <title>A Diferença</title>
            <para>
                There are many different operating systems based on Linux:
                Debian, SUSE, Gentoo, RedHat, and Mandriva for example. 
                Kubuntu is yet another contender in what
                is already a highly competitive world. So what makes
                Kubuntu different?</para>
            <para>
                Based on Debian, one of the most widely acclaimed,
                technologically advanced, and well-supported
                distributions, Kubuntu
                aims to create a distribution that provides
                an up-to-date and coherent Linux system for desktop and
                server computing. Kubuntu includes a number of carefully
                selected packages from the Debian distribution and
                retains its powerful package management system, which
                allows easy installation and clean removal of programs. Unlike most
                distributions that ship with a large amount of software
                that may or may not be of use, Kubuntu's list of packages
                is reduced to a number of important applications of high
                quality.
            </para>
            <para>
                By focusing on quality, Kubuntu produces a robust and
                feature-rich computing environment that is suitable for
                use in both home and commercial environments. The
                project takes the time required to focus on finer
                details and is able to release a version featuring the
                latest and greatest of today's software once every 6
                months. Kubuntu is available in flavors for the i386
                (386/486/Pentium(II/III/IV) and Athlon/Duron/Sempron
                processors), x86_64 (Athlon64, Opteron, and new 64-bit
                Intel processors), and PowerPC (iBook/Powerbook, G4 and
                G5) architectures.</para>
        </sect2>
        <sect2 id="sect-kubuntu-desktop" status="complete">
            <title>O Ambiente de Trabalho</title>
            <para>The default desktop environment for Kubuntu is <ulink url="&kde;">KDE</ulink>, a leading UNIX and
                Linux desktop suite and development platform.</para>
            <para>Another leading UNIX and Linux desktop is <ulink url="&gnome;">Gnome</ulink>. Kubuntu does not 
                make use of the Gnome desktop by default. However, the
                <ulink url="&ubuntu-main;">Ubuntu</ulink> project offers
                Kubuntu users a choice between these two excellent desktop
                environments. Thanks to the efforts of the Ubuntu team,
                Kubuntu users are able to install and use the Gnome
                desktop easily on their system. The Gnome desktop can 
                be found in and downloaded from the main Ubuntu archive.
                The easiest way to get a working install of Ubuntu is
                <command>sudo apt-get install ubuntu-desktop</command>.
                This will install the different packages required and set
                everything up correctly.</para>
            <para>Após estar tudo instalado, pode escolher o ambiente a ser utilizado: tanto KDE como Gnome.</para>
        </sect2>
        <sect2 id="version-numbers" status="complete">
            <title>Versões e Números de Lançamento</title>
            <para>
                The Kubuntu version numbering scheme is based on the date we
                release a version of the distribution. The version number comes from the year
                and month of the release rather than reflecting the actual revision of the
                software. So, our first release (Hoary Hedgehog) was in April 2005, so its
                version was 5.04. The second release (Breezy Badger) was in October 2005, so
                its version number was 5.10, and our third release (Dapper Drake) was released in June 2006
		so its version number was 6.06. This version (&distro-version;) was released in
                &distro-release-date;, so its version number is &distro-rev;.
            </para>
        </sect2>

        <sect2 id="kubuntu-backing-support" status="complete">
            <title>Apoio e Suporte</title>
            <para>Kubuntu is maintained by a quickly growing community.
                The project is sponsored by <ulink url="&canonical-url;">Canonical Ltd.</ulink>, a
                holding company founded by Mark Shuttleworth. Canonical
                employs the core Ubuntu developers and offers support and consulting services
                for Ubuntu.</para>
            <para>Canonical Ltd also sponsors a number of other open source software projects, more information about which can be found on the <ulink url="&canonical-url;">Canonical website</ulink>.</para>
        </sect2>
        <sect2 id="about-linux" status="complete">
            <title>O que é o Linux?</title>
            <para>The <ulink url="&kernel;">Linux kernel</ulink>, pronounced
                "lee-nucks" is the heart of the Kubuntu operating system.
                A kernel is an important part of
                any operating system, providing the communication bridge between 
                hardware and software.</para>
            <para>O Linux nasceu em 1991 pela mão de um estudante Finlandês chamado Linus Torvalds. Nessa altura, apenas podia ser executado em sistemas i386, e era essencialmente um clone do kernel UNIX criado independentemente, destinado a tirar partido da então nova arquitectura i386.</para>
            <para>Hoje em dia, graças ao substancial esforço de desenvolvimento por pessoas de todo o mundo, o Linux corre virtualmente em qualquer máquina moderna.</para>
            <para>The Linux kernel has gained an ideological importance as well as a technical one.
                There is an entire community of people who believe in the ideals
                of Free Software and spend their time helping to make open
                source technology as good as it can be.</para>
            <para>As pessoas nesta comunidade lançam iniciativas como o Ubuntu, comités de standards que ajudam a definir o desenvolvimento da Internet, organizações tal como a Fundação Mozilla, responsável por criar o Mozilla Firefox, e inúmeros projectos de software dos quais já certamente beneficiou no passado.</para>
            <para>O espírito do software livre, habitualmente atribuído ao Linux, está a influenciar programadores e utilizadores em todo o lado a conduzir comunidades com objectivos comuns.</para>
        </sect2>
        <sect2 id="about-gnu" status="complete">
            <title>O que é o GNU?</title>
            <para>The <emphasis>GNU Project</emphasis>, pronounced "guh-noo", was
                launched in 1984 to develop a complete
                UNIX-style operating system which is comprised of Free Software: the GNU
                system. Variants of the GNU operating system,
                which use the Linux kernel, are now widely used.</para>
            <para>The GNU project is closely linked to the philosophy of free
                software, which is central to the projects that derive from it, 
                such as Ubuntu. The concept of Free Software is explained 
                at <xref linkend="free-software"/>.</para>
        </sect2>
    </sect1>
    <sect1 id="get-kubuntu" status="complete">
        <title>Obter o Kubuntu</title>
        <para>There are a number of methods you may use to obtain a
            copy of Kubuntu, all of which are described on the Kubuntu
            Web site <ulink url="&kubuntu-download;">download
                page</ulink>.</para>
        <para>The first method is to download an ISO image from a
            mirror server near you and make an CD to install Kubuntu. Two types of CDs are available:</para>
				<itemizedlist>
					<listitem><para><emphasis>Desktop CD</emphasis> - the desktop CD allows you to try Kubuntu without changing your computer at all, and at your option to install it permanently later. This type of CD is what most people will want to use.</para></listitem>
					<listitem><para><emphasis>Text-mode install CD</emphasis> - the text-mode install CD allows you to perform certain specialist installations of Kubuntu. This type of CD is intended for cases such as creating pre-configured OEM systems or setting up automated deployments; it can also be used as a package source for upgrading older installations.</para></listitem>
				</itemizedlist>
        <para>If you don't have a CD burner or you have limited or expensive bandwidth,
            we can send you pressed copies of the "Desktop
            CD" free of charge. You may request CDs via
            <ulink url="&ubuntu-shipit;">Shipit</ulink>, the Ubuntu CD Distribution System.</para>
        <tip>
            <para>CDs pedidos podem demorar algumas semanas a sair do armazém até serem enviados, e pode demorar vários meses a chegar.</para>
        </tip>
        <para>Another method of obtaining Kubuntu is to join a local
            Linux Users Group (LUG) and ask if somebody with Kubuntu
            would mind making a Kubuntu CD for you. Normally, you
            will have to replace the CDs used for the duplication
            and reimburse any postage or delivery costs.</para>
        <para>If you do not know of an LUG near you, a list can be
            found at <ulink url="&lugww;">Linux Users Groups
                Worldwide</ulink>.</para>
    </sect1>
    <sect1 id="getting-help" status="review">
        <title>Obter Ajuda</title>
        <para>Existem vários locais onde pode obter ajuda com o seu sistema Kubuntu, que incluem:</para>
        <sect2 id="help-system" status="writing">
            <title>Centro de Ajuda do KDE</title>
            <para>
                Kubuntu comes with a inbuilt help system, which can be accessed
                by choosing 
                <menuchoice>
                    <guimenu>K Menu</guimenu>
                    <guimenuitem>Help</guimenuitem>
                </menuchoice> 
                from the desktop menu system. 
                The <application>KDE Help Center</application> is the central
                location to all documentation available on your system. 
            </para>
            <para>Um bom local para começares a aprender mais sobre o KDE é <ulink url="help:/khelpcenter/quickstart/index.html">KDE Guia de Iniciação Rápido</ulink>, que te vai familiarizar com algumas funções básicas do KDE.</para>
        </sect2>
        <sect2 id="application-help" status="review">
            <title>Ajuda com uma Aplicação</title>
            <para>A forma mais fácil de obter ajuda sobre uma aplicação é ler o seu handbook que é acessível a partir do menu <emphasis>Ajuda</emphasis> na barra de ferramentas do programa.</para> 
        </sect2>
        <sect2 id="online-help" status="complete">
            <title>Find Help Online</title>
            <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para>
                        <ulink url="&ubuntu-documentation;">The Ubuntu Documentation Website</ulink> contains HTML and PDF versions of this guide, and other guides produced by the Ubuntu Documentation Team for Ubuntu and Kubuntu.</para></listitem>
                <listitem> <para>Pode comprar este guia no formato de livro na <ulink url="&lulu-store;">nossa loja Lulu</ulink>. Apenas pagará despesas de impressão e envio</para> </listitem> <listitem>
                    <para>
                        <ulink url="&wiki-UserDocumentation;">The Ubuntu Wiki</ulink> - this contains many other community maintained guides</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>
                        <ulink url="&kubuntu-forums2;">Kubuntu</ulink> and <ulink url="&ubuntu-forums;">Ubuntu</ulink> Community Forums - here you can ask questions on a forum and receive answers from the forum community.
                    </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para><ulink url="&kubuntu-lists;">Mailing Lists</ulink> - here you can ask questions by email, and receive answers from the mailing list community.
                    </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem><para>IRC chat: <phrase>&kubuntu-irc;</phrase> - chat in realtime with the Kubuntu community.</para></listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para><ulink url="&kubuntu-web;">Homepage do Kubuntu</ulink> - Receba as últimas noticias do Kubuntu.</para>
                </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
            <para>Para mais informação, visite a página wiki <ulink url="&wiki-HowToGetHelp;">Como Ter Ajuda</ulink>.</para>
        </sect2>
    </sect1>
</chapter>

