<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.1.2//EN" 
	"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.1.2/docbookx.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % globalent SYSTEM "../../libs/global.ent">
%globalent;
<!ENTITY % gnome-menus-C SYSTEM "../../libs/gnome-menus-C.ent">
%gnome-menus-C;
<!ENTITY language "&EnglishAmerican;">
<!ENTITY language "en">
]><article>
	<articleinfo>
		<title>
			USB Startup Disk Creator
		</title>
		&legalnotice;
	</articleinfo>
	
	<para>
		This section provides instructions for using <application>USB Startup Disk Creator</application>.
	</para>
	
	<sect1 id="introduction">
		<title>
			Introduction
		</title>
		
		<para>
			<application>USB Startup Disk Creator</application> is a utility in Ubuntu that creates a persistent Ubuntu 
			image on a USB disk. This is called a &quot;Live USB&quot;. You can use the 
			Live USB to install Ubuntu on your computer or to run Ubuntu 
			without affecting your system hardware. The advantages to using a 
			Live USB to install or test Ubuntu include: 
			<itemizedlist>
				<listitem>
					<para>
						Less waste. A Live USB can be overwritten when a new version of 
						Ubuntu comes out.
					</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>
						Persistence. Changes made to the USB disk are saved, unlike a Live CD. 
					</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>
						No CD Drive required. Computers lacking a CD drive usually have a USB drive.
					</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>
						Safe computing environment. Boot your computer from a Live USB to 
						protect your system when accessing unsecured public networks or 
						testing unstable functionality. 
					</para>
				</listitem>
			</itemizedlist>
		</para>
	</sect1>
	
	<sect1 id="requirements">
		<title>
			Requirements
		</title>
		
		<para>
			<application>USB Startup Disk Creator</application> requires the following:
			<itemizedlist>
				<listitem>
					<para>
						Ubuntu 8.10 or later 
					</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>
						USB disk 1 GB or larger
					</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>
						Ubuntu Desktop Edition image
					</para>
				</listitem>
			</itemizedlist>
		</para>
		
		<para>
			Currently <application>USB Startup Disk Creator</application> only runs on Ubuntu systems 8.10 or later. If 
			you don’t have access to an Ubuntu system, you can create a Live 
			USB from a system that can boot from an Ubuntu Live CD. You can also 
			install Ubuntu into a virtualization program like VirtualBox and 
			create the Live USB from a virtual Ubuntu installation. 
		</para>
		
		<para>
			The USB drive capacity should minimally be large enough to hold the 
			contents of the Ubuntu download image and any additional data you 
			plan to store. The minimum recommendation is 1 GB, however 2 GB is suggested. 
		</para>
	</sect1>
	
	<sect1 id="making-a-live-usb">
		<title>
			Making a Live USB
		</title>
		
		<sect2 id="download-the-ubuntu-image">
			<title>
				Download the Ubuntu Image
			</title>
			
			<para>
				Download Ubuntu from <ulink url="&ubuntu-download;">the Ubuntu website</ulink>. 
			</para>
			
			<para>
				Use the standard Desktop Ubuntu installation with <application>USB Startup Disk Creator</application>. 
				Other versions like Server and the Netbook Remix have additional 
				system requirements that are not compatible with <application>USB Startup Disk Creator</application>. 
			</para>
			
			<para>
				The downloaded image file will end with the suffix &quot;.iso&quot;. 
			</para>
		</sect2>
		
		<sect2 id="ubuntu-system">
			<title>
				Ubuntu System
			</title>
			
			<para>
				<orderedlist>
					<listitem>
						<para>
							Plug your USB disk into your computer’s USB drive. Make sure 
							your computer recognizes the USB disk before proceeding.
						</para>
					</listitem>
					<listitem>
						<para>
							To launch <application>USB Startup Disk Creator</application>, choose &usb-creator;
						</para>	 
					</listitem>
					<listitem>
						<para>
							Under <guilabel>Source Disk Image</guilabel> click the <guibutton>Other...</guibutton> button and specify 
							the Ubuntu image you downloaded in the previous step. If you are 
							creating the USB disk from a Live CD, insert the Live CD and <application>USB Startup Disk Creator
							</application> will automatically recognize it. 
						</para>
					</listitem>
					<listitem>
						<para>
							Under <guilabel>USB Disk to use</guilabel> your USB disk is highlighted. If you have 
							more than one item in the list, select the USB disk you want to use for your Live USB. 
						</para>
					</listitem>
					<listitem>
						<para>
							To make the Live USB a writeable disk, indicate how much memory 
							to use for extra storage. If you don’t want the Live USB to be 
							modifiable, select the second option, <guilabel>Discarded on Shutdown</guilabel>. 
						</para>
					</listitem>
					<listitem>
						<para>
							Click <guibutton>Make Startup Disk</guibutton> to make a Live USB.
						</para> 
					</listitem>
				</orderedlist>
			</para>
			
			<warning>
				<para>
					<application>USB Startup Disk Creator</application> will erase any data on the USB disk. Back up any 
					 files you don’t want deleted. 
				</para>
			</warning>
		</sect2>
		
		<sect2 id="non-ubuntu-system">
			<title>
				Non-Ubuntu System
			</title>
			
			<para>
				If you don’t have access to a system running Ubuntu, it is still 
				possible to use <application>USB Startup Disk Creator</application> to create a Live USB. 
				
				You can boot from a Live CD and run <application>USB Startup Disk Creator</application> from the Live CD environment. 
				Alternatively, you can install Ubuntu into a virtual environment like VirtualBox. 
			</para>
			
			<sect3 id="live-usb-from-live-cd">
				<title>
					Create a Live USB from a Live CD
				</title>
				
				<para>
					<orderedlist>
						<listitem>
							<para>
								Copy the Ubuntu image to a location on your hard drive that you 
								 have access to while running the Live CD environment. You 
								 can copy the image file into a publicly accessible folder 
								 on your hard drive or you can copy it onto a second external drive.
							</para>
						</listitem> 
						<listitem>
							<para>
								Once you have verified that you can access the Ubuntu image 
								while booted into the Live CD, follow the steps outlined in 
								the previous section to create a Live USB. 
							</para>
						</listitem>
					</orderedlist>
				</para>
			</sect3>
			
			<sect3 id="live-usb-in-vm">
				<title>
					Create a Live USB in a Virtual Ubuntu Environment
				</title>
				
				<orderedlist>
					<listitem>
						<para>
							Copy the Ubuntu image to a directory shared by both the 
							virtual environment and your system. To set up shared folders, 
							see specific instructions in your virtualization program. You 
							can also use a Live CD as long as the virtual environment has 
							access to your CD drive. 
						</para>
					</listitem>
					<listitem>
						<para>
							Insert the USB Disk. Make sure the virtual environment can mount 
							the USB disk. 
						</para>
					</listitem>
					<listitem>
						<para>
							Once you have verified that you can access both the Ubuntu image 
							and the USB disk from the virtual Ubuntu installation, follow 
							the steps outlined in the previous section to create a Live USB. 
						</para>
					</listitem>
				</orderedlist>
				
			</sect3>
			
		</sect2>
	</sect1>
	
	<sect1 id="booting-from-the-live-usb">
		<title>
			Booting from the Live USB
		</title>
		
		<para>
			While some computers automatically recognize the USB drive when 
			starting up, others need to be configured to recognize the Live USB. 
			If your system does not recognize the Live USB on boot, you need to 
			set boot options in the basic configuration of your computer, known 
			as the &quot;BIOS&quot;. 
		</para>
		
		<para>
			To set boot options using the BIOS: 
			<orderedlist>
				<listitem>
					<para>
						Press the key specified on the startup screen to enter BIOS setup. 
						This key is usually an F key, such as F1, F2, or a key like Delete 
						or Escape. If no information is available on the startup screen, 
						consult your hardware manufacturer’s documentation.
					</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>
						Set the USB disk to the primary boot device and save the changes. 
					</para>
				</listitem>
			</orderedlist>
		</para>
		
		
		<note>
			<para>
				Remember to unplug your USB disk or reset the boot order if you no 
				longer want to boot from the Live USB. 
			</para>
		</note>
	</sect1>
	
	<sect1 id="troubleshooting">
		<title>
			Troubleshooting
		</title>
		
		<para>
			If your system won’t boot from the USB disk, try the following: 
			<itemizedlist>
				<listitem>
					<para>
						Insert the USB disk after starting your computer to make sure your 
						system recognizes it. Some systems might not recognize mini USB disks.
					</para>
				</listitem> 
				<listitem>
					<para>
						Enter the BIOS Setup and verify the boot order is set correctly. 
						Make sure the USB disk is the first item on the list. See your 
						hardware manufacturer’s instructions for more information on 
						your system’s BIOS settings.
					</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>
						The system might use a boot selector. Hit the Escape key on boot 
						and select USB disk from the boot menu. 
					</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>
						Boot from the USB disk on another machine. If the machine boots 
						successfully, it is possible that your computer cannot boot from a 
						Live USB. 
					</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>
						If the above solutions are unsuccessful, you may need to use a 
						different method than <application>USB Startup Disk Creator</application> to create a Live USB.
					</para>
				</listitem>
			</itemizedlist>
		</para>
				
		<tip>
			<para>
				Visit an <ulink url="&ubuntu-support;">Ubuntu Support</ulink> resource for more troubleshooting 
				assistance.
			</para>
		</tip> 
	</sect1>	
</article>
