<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.1.2//EN" 
	"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.1.2/docbookx.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % xinclude SYSTEM "../libs/xinclude.mod">
%xinclude;
<!ENTITY % globalent SYSTEM "../libs/global.ent">
%globalent;
]>
<article id="art-about-ubuntu" status="complete">
    <title>
        <inlinemediaobject>
            <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref="../images/IconUbuntu.png" format="PNG"/>
            </imageobject>
        </inlinemediaobject>
    </title>
    <subtitle>Welcome to Ubuntu Linux &distro-rev;: The &distro-version; Release.</subtitle>
    <para id="about1">Ubuntu Linux is a complete open source operating system built around the Linux
        kernel. The Ubuntu community is made up of software developers, translators, folks who love
        to write documentation, and most importantly the people who use Ubuntu every day. We invite
        you to join this community and help to make Ubuntu the operating system your family,
        friends, and office colleagues will love to use. Help to translate Ubuntu into your own
        language, test it on new laptops, servers and other exciting hardware, improve the web site
        with hints, tips and FAQ's, or help to define the set of software that is installed by
        default for future Ubuntu releases.</para>
    <para id="about2">The Ubuntu community is built on the ideas enshrined in the Ubuntu Manifesto:
        that software should be available free of charge, that software tools should be usable by
        people in their local language and despite any disabilities, and that people should have the
        freedom to customize and alter their software in whatever way they see fit. For those
        reasons:</para>
    <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
                <para>Ubuntu will always be free of charge, and there is no extra fee for the
                    &quot;enterprise edition,&quot; we make our very best work available to
                    everyone on the same Free terms.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Ubuntu includes the very best in translations and accessibility infrastructure
                    that the Free Software community has to offer, to make Ubuntu usable for as many
                    people as possible.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Ubuntu is released regularly and predictably; a new release is made every six
                    months. You can use the current stable release or the current development
                    release. Each release is supported for at least 18 months.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Ubuntu is entirely committed to the principles of open source software
                    development; we encourage people to use open source software, improve it and
                    pass it on.</para>
            </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
    <para id="about3">Find out more at &ubuntu-web; or take a look at some of the following:</para>
    <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
                <para>The Ubuntu <ulink url="&ubuntu-lists;">Mailing Lists</ulink>, where the
                    community discusses new ideas and issues with Ubuntu.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>The <ulink url="&ubuntu-wiki;">Ubuntu Wiki</ulink>, where we collaborate
                    on the policies and strategy documents that define the direction Ubuntu will
                    follow.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Chat with the community on Freenode IRC Channel: #ubuntu .</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Access Ubuntu's local on line help by clicking the life preserver icon on the
                    top panel of your desktop.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>The Ubuntu <ulink url="&ubuntu-documentation-site;">Documentation</ulink>
                    Web Site.</para>
            </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
    <sect1 id="wonderful-linux" status="complete">
        <title>The Wonderful World of Linux</title>
        <para>Ubuntu uses the &quot;Linux&quot; kernel, the software which has come to
            define the worldwide movement to embrace open source software. Find out about Linux at
                <ulink url="&linuxorg;">Linux.org</ulink>.</para>
        <sect2 id="sect-ubuntu-difference" status="complete">
            <title>The Difference</title>
 	    <para>There are many GNU/Linux distributions (e.g., Redhat, SuSE, Debian, Mandrake)but
                    Ubuntu distinguishes itself as a different kind of distribution.</para>
            <para>Built on the solid and advanced base of Debian, the Ubuntu team aims to create a
                distribution that provides an up-to-date and coherent GNU/Linux system for
                desktop and server computing. Ubuntu includes a number of selected packages from the
                Debian distribution and is based on its powerful &quot;APT&quot; package management system.
                APT allows easy installation and clean removal of programs, as well as
                automatic download of extra packages to satisfy dependencies. Unlike most
                distributions that ship a wide range of software packages that may or may not be of
                quality, Ubuntu's core list of packages is reduced to only the important applications.
                (Although for maximum choice, you may choose from the full list, rather than being
                limited to the high quality core.)
            </para>
            <para>By focusing on quality, Ubuntu produces a robust and feature rich computing
                environment that is flexible for use in home and commercial environments. The
                project has more time to spend on the finer details and is able to release a version
                featuring the latest and greatest of today's software, every 6 months. Ubuntu ships
                with versions for i386 (Pentium CPUs / IBM-compatible PCs), AMD-64 (Hammer) and
                PowerPC (iBook/Powerbook, G4 and G5) architectures.</para>
        </sect2>
        <sect2 id="sect-ubuntu-desktop" status="complete">
            <title>The Desktop</title>
            <para>The default desktop environment for Ubuntu is <ulink url="&gnome;"
                >GNOME</ulink>, a leading Unix and Linux desktop suite and development platform.</para>
            <para>Another leading Unix and Linux desktop is <ulink url="&kde;">KDE</ulink>.
                Ubuntu does not install the KDE desktop by default. The project
                currently lacks the resources to maintain both KDE and GNOME desktops with a high
                level of quality. However, you will find all the KDE packages you could want in 
                the universe component of Ubuntu.  In the future, Ubuntu users will have
                a choice between these most excellent desktops. Work on this front is being done by 
                the Kubuntu team.
            </para>
        </sect2>
        <sect2 id="sect-ubuntu-ooo" status="complete">
            <title>OpenOffice.org</title>
            <para>Ubuntu includes the excellent <application>OpenOffice.org</application> Business
                Productivity software suite. This includes a word processor, spreadsheet and
                presentation combination that is largely compatible with other widely used Office
                software. Read more about the OpenOffice.org project at <ulink url="&ooo;"
                    >OpenOffice.org</ulink>.</para>
        </sect2>
    </sect1>
</article>
