<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE bookinfo PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.3//EN" 
	"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.3/docbookx.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % globalent SYSTEM "../../../libs/global.ent">
%globalent;
<!ENTITY % cdo-C SYSTEM "../../../libs/cdo-C.ent">
%cdo-C;
<!ENTITY % pg-common SYSTEM "../pg-common.ent">
%pg-common;
<!ENTITY % xinclude SYSTEM "../../../libs/xinclude.mod">
%xinclude;
<!ENTITY language "en">
<!ENTITY ubuntu '<phrase>Ubuntu</phrase>'>
]>
<bookinfo>
	<title>Guia de Empacotamento do Ubuntu</title>
	<legalnotice id="Credits-And-License">
	    <title>Créditos e Licença</title>
	    <para>The following Ubuntu Documentation Team authors maintain this
		 document:</para>
		 <itemizedlist>
			<listitem>
		    <para>Jordan Mantha</para>
			</listitem>
		</itemizedlist>
		<para>The Ubuntu Packaging Guide is also based on the contributions of:</para>
		<itemizedlist>
			<listitem>
		    <para>Alexandre Vassalotti</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
	            <para>Jonathan Patrick Davies</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para>Ankur Kotwal</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para>Rapha&euml;l Pinson</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para>Daniel Chen</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para>Martin Pitt</para>
			</listitem>
		</itemizedlist>

		<para>Portions of the Ubuntu Packaging Guide are derived from the
			Debian New Maintainer's Guide and the Debian Policy Manual.</para>
		
		<para>This document is made available under the GNU General Public License (GPL).</para>
	    <para>You are free to modify, extend, and improve the Ubuntu documentation source code under the
 	       terms of this license. All derivative works must be released under this license.</para>
	    <para>This documentation is distributed in the hope that it will be useful, but WITHOUT ANY
	        WARRANTY; without even the implied warranty of MERCHANTABILITY or FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR
	        PURPOSE AS DESCRIBED IN THE DISCLAIMER.</para>
	    <para>Copies of the license are available in the appendices section of this book
			and online at <ulink url="http://www.gnu.org/licenses/gpl.html">GNU General Public License</ulink>.</para>
	</legalnotice>
        
<copyright>
    <year>2004, 2005, 2006</year>
    <holder>Canonical Ltd. and members of the Ubuntu Documentation Project</holder>
</copyright>

        <authorgroup>
            
<corpauthor>Ubuntu Documentation Project <emphasis>&lt;ubuntu-doc@lists.ubuntu.com&gt;</emphasis>
</corpauthor>

        </authorgroup>
        <abstract>
            <para>The Ubuntu Packaging Guide is an introduction to packaging programs for Ubuntu and other Debian based distributions</para>
        </abstract>
        
<legalnotice>
    <title>Disclaimer</title>
    <para>Every effort has been made to ensure that the information compiled in this publication is
        accurate and correct. However, this does not guarantee complete accuracy. Neither
        Canonical Ltd., the authors, nor translators shall be held liable for possible errors or
        the consequences thereof.</para>
    <para>Some of the software and hardware descriptions cited in this publication may be registered trademarks and may thus fall under copyright restrictions and trade protection laws. In no way do the authors make claim to any such names.</para>
    <para>THIS DOCUMENTATION IS PROVIDED BY THE AUTHORS "AS IS" AND ANY EXPRESS OR
        IMPLIED WARRANTIES, INCLUDING, BUT NOT LIMITED TO, THE IMPLIED WARRANTIES OF MERCHANTABILITY
        AND FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE ARE DISCLAIMED. IN NO EVENT SHALL THE AUTHORS BE LIABLE
        FOR ANY DIRECT, INDIRECT, INCIDENTAL, SPECIAL, EXEMPLARY, OR CONSEQUENTIAL DAMAGES
        (INCLUDING, BUT NOT LIMITED TO, PROCUREMENT OF SUBSTITUTE GOODS OR SERVICES; LOSS OF USE,
        DATA, OR PROFITS; OR BUSINESS INTERRUPTION) HOWEVER CAUSED AND ON ANY THEORY OF LIABILITY,
        WHETHER IN CONTRACT, STRICT LIABILITY, OR TORT (INCLUDING NEGLIGENCE OR OTHERWISE) ARISING
        IN ANY WAY OUT OF THE USE OF THIS SOFTWARE, EVEN IF ADVISED OF THE POSSIBILITY OF SUCH DAMAGE.</para>
</legalnotice>

        
<publisher>
    <publishername>The Ubuntu Documentation Project</publishername>
</publisher>

</bookinfo>

