<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.3//EN" 
        "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.3/docbookx.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % globalent SYSTEM "../../../libs/global.ent">
%globalent;
<!ENTITY % cdo-C SYSTEM "../../../libs/cdo-C.ent">
%cdo-C;
<!ENTITY language "&EnglishAmerican;">
]>
<article lang="&language;" id="x01">
    <title>Edubuntu School Advocacy</title>
    <subtitle>Edubuntu &distro-rev; &quot;&distro-version;&quot;</subtitle>
    <articleinfo>
        &copyright; 
		<legalnotice id="Credits-And-License">
			<title>Credits and License</title>
			<para>The following Ubuntu Documentation Team authors maintain
				this document:</para>
			<itemizedlist>
					<listitem>
						<para>Jerome Gotangco</para>
					</listitem>
					<listitem>
						<para>Corey Burger</para>
					</listitem>
					<listitem>
						<para>Jordan Mantha</para>
					</listitem>
			</itemizedlist>
			
			<para>The following people have contributed to this
				document:</para>
			<itemizedlist>
				<listitem>
					<para>Pete Savage</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>Andrea Veri</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>Jonathan Carter</para>
				</listitem>
			</itemizedlist>	
            <para>This document is made available under Creative Commons 2.5
				License (CC-BY).</para>
            <para>You are free to modify, extend, and improve the Ubuntu documentation source code under the
               terms of this license. Copies of this license are available at
			   <ulink
				   url="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.5/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.5/</ulink></para>
            <para>This documentation is distributed in the hope that it will be useful, but WITHOUT ANY
                WARRANTY; without even the implied warranty of MERCHANTABILITY or FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR
                PURPOSE AS DESCRIBED IN THE DISCLAIMER.</para>
		</legalnotice>	
		<authorgroup>
                &author-ubuntu-documentation-project;
        </authorgroup>
		<abstract>
            <para>This is a School Advocacy pamphlet for &distro-rev;</para>
        </abstract>
        &disclaimer; 
		&publisher;
	</articleinfo>
<sect1 id="welcome"><title>Welcome to Edubuntu</title>
        <para><inlinemediaobject>
            <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref="../../images/C/edubuntu_logo_png.png" format="PNG"/>
            </imageobject>
  <textobject>
    <phrase>OpenOffice</phrase>
  </textobject>
        </inlinemediaobject></para>
<para>Welcome to the world of Edubuntu, a Linux distribution designed for 
  schools and other educational environments.  Built on the popular 
  Ubuntu, it is a complete operating system that includes an office 
  suite, web browser, many educational applications, and much more. 
  Edubuntu is designed to allow a teacher or network administrator to be 
  able to set up a complete classroom quickly and easily.  Edubuntu is 
  committed to the principles of free and open source software, which means it 
  is free of charge and will always remain that way. Open Source software 
  aims to preserve the freedom to use, copy and change the software and to distribute those 
  changes. This means Edubuntu can offer higher quality software at no cost, 
  while allowing everyone to modify Edubuntu to fit the exact 
  needs of their particular environment. </para>

<para>Edubuntu is comprised of several key technologies, one of which 
  is the Linux Terminal Server Project (LTSP), which allows you to boot 
  thin clients from an Edubuntu LTSP server. For educational environments, 
  LTSP lowers hardware costs by enabling the use of older machines as thin clients, 
  as well as reduced administration overhead by having only to install and 
  maintain the software on the server. When a workstation fails, it can simply 
  be replaced without data loss or reinstallation of the operating 
  system. </para>

<para>Any good educational platform should provide applications specifically for its 
  target audience, and Edubuntu is no exception. For the younger crowd, just starting 
  out with computers, Gcompris offers a fantastic early learning environment. For 
  slightly older pupils, there is a number of games and activities from the 
  Tux4Kids and KDEEdu projects, and for those in high school and older, there is 
  a full office suite as well as applications for instant messaging, graphics, sound and video.
  And that is just by default! Edubuntu also includes access to thousands of other high 
  quality open source programs at no cost. </para>
</sect1>

<sect1 id="difference"><title>The Edubuntu Difference</title>
<itemizedlist>

<listitem>
<para><emphasis role='strong'>Compatible</emphasis> - Most 
  educational computing uses a mix of Microsoft Windows, Apple OS X 
  and Linux. In this setting, you need an operating system that plays 
  well with others. Edubuntu does that.  Edubuntu servers can happily 
  coexist on the same network as other operating systems; OpenOffice.org 
  can open and save Microsoft Office formats, such as Powerpoint, Word 
  and Excel documents, and you can even install Edubuntu and another operating 
  system on the same machine. Need to share files between Edubuntu and 
  other operating system or connect to a remote server? Edubuntu does 
  that too. </para>
</listitem>

<listitem>
<para><emphasis role='strong'>Secure</emphasis> - Security has become 
  a key challenge for educators, and the team behind Edubuntu recognize 
  this. Often, schools lack the specialized IT staff or time to lock down and 
  clean up computers. Edubuntu, being a Linux-based operating system, 
  enjoys the security advantages of its Unix and open source 
  heritages. This translates into higher quality code and fewer threats from spyware 
  and viruses that plague other operating systems. In addition, Edubuntu 
  has a strict, proactive security policy, meaning many common problems 
  such as open ports or misconfigured software are much less of an issue. 
  Finally, Edubuntu is a true multi-user operating system, making it easy to 
  allow users to complete their tasks without compromising the system.</para>
</listitem>

<listitem>
<para><emphasis role='strong'>Managable</emphasis> - With teachers and school 
  IT departments deploying and administering an increasingly large number of 
  computers, time to manage individual computers is scarce to non-existant. 
  Edubuntu, by using LTSP thin client technology, makes deployment and management 
  simple and easy. A single server is all that is needed to set up, manage and 
  administrate an entire classroom full of computers. The Edubuntu team also recognizes 
  that not every school's setup is the same. As such, Edubuntu is easy to customize 
  for your unique needs, whether it be a simple rebranding or the addition or 
  removal of programs. Hence Edubuntu can reduce the amount of time you 
  spend administrating your computers. </para>
</listitem>

<listitem>
<para><emphasis role='strong'>Cost Effective</emphasis> - With ever-increasing 
  demands on budgets, it seems expensive technology is often last on the list. 
  Edubuntu can help you offer what your students increasingly require from computer technology, 
  without breaking the bank. Edubuntu is and always will be free to acquire, 
  use and modify. Need to set up another machine? Or another hundred? Just install them! 
  No more expensive OS upgrades and licenses, or only having specific programs on 
  some computers. Since Edubuntu is built on Open Source software, schools are welcome to 
  seek whomever they wish to help them support their computers and are not locked 
  into getting help from the vendor. Edubuntu can also help you save hardware costs 
  by allowing you to redeploy older machines as thin clients using LTSP technology.
</para>
</listitem>

<listitem>
<para><emphasis role='strong'>Well Supported</emphasis> - Edubuntu
  support is available from both the Edubuntu community and the larger Ubuntu
  community. Many of the authors of the software included in
  Edubuntu can be contacted directly via mailing lists and IRC
  channels, including the Edubuntu developers themselves. There are
  many forms of support available on mailing lists, wiki websites,
  IRC channels and bug trackers.  There is also a special support
  group for using Edubuntu in schools. Should you want paid support, 
  Canonical, who funds Edubuntu and Ubuntu development, can offer 
  assistance, or you could find a local company who offer similar services. 
  With Edubuntu, the choice is yours. </para>
</listitem>

<listitem>
<para><emphasis role='strong'>Built for Education</emphasis>
  - Above all, what sets Edubuntu apart from other operating systems
  is its unwavering focus on the educational needs of children all
  over the world. Edubuntu's motto is "Linux for Young Human Beings",
  and every development decision and application has that goal in
  mind. Edubuntu comes with translations for many languages and
  localization features that allow people from all over the world to
  enjoy their computing experience, as well as acessibility features 
  to help disabled users. The Live CD allows pupils to boot
  their home computers into Edubuntu and use exactly the
  same applications that they are using at school. The LTSP server
  software allows teachers and administrators to create a low-cost
  computer lab so that students can have access to the best educational
  opportunities that Edubuntu and the Internet can provide. </para>
</listitem>

</itemizedlist>
</sect1>

<sect1 id="applications">
<title>Applications</title>
<para>Edubuntu aims to be a complete and ready-to-use educational 
  environment. As such, Edubuntu comes pre-installed with a complete 
  office suite, teaching and learning programs, pre-school resources 
  and much more, across a range of categories. Here is a brief summary 
  and some screenshots for the most popular Edubuntu packages, and 
  if you need more, Edubuntu has thousands of additional applications ready
  for you to install. </para>

<sect2 id="office-suite">
<title>Office Suite</title>
<para>OpenOffice.org is a complete office suite similar to the Microsoft
  Office suite. It features a word processor, as well as spreadsheet,
  presentation, drawing, database, and mathematical formula
  applications. OpenOffice.org can open and convert most Microsoft Office
  documents and has support for many different languages. </para>
        <para><inlinemediaobject>
            <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref="../../images/C/openoffice.png" format="PNG"/>
            </imageobject>
  <textobject>
    <phrase>OpenOffice</phrase>
  </textobject>
        </inlinemediaobject></para>
</sect2>

<sect2 id="firefox">
<title>Web Browser</title>
<para>Firefox is the incredible successor to the hugely popular Mozilla
  browser.  Among its many features are tabbed browsing, which makes
  viewing multiple sites a breeze, 
  pop-up blocking, live bookmarks and great accessibility support.  
  Combine these with its fantastic customisation engine and you have 
  the most powerful web browsing at your fingertips.
  </para>
</sect2>

<sect2 id="internet"> <title>Email, IM and VoIP</title> 

<para>Moving beyond the simple web browser, Edubuntu also comes with an email
client and personal information manager, <application>Evolution</application>. Video conferencing with
<application>Ekiga</application> and instant messaging and chat with <application>Gaim</application> provide communication
tools that teachers and students need in an Internet age.</para> 

<para><inlinemediaobject> <imageobject> <imagedata
fileref="../../images/C/internet.png" format="PNG"/> </imageobject>
<textobject> <phrase>Internet</phrase> </textobject>
</inlinemediaobject></para> </sect2>

<sect2 id="graphics">
<title>Graphics</title>

<para>In the graphics department, diagrams and flowcharts are a breeze with <application>Dia</application>. <application>Xsane</application> provides an easy to use scanner interface. 3D modeling and animation are <application>Blender's</application> specialty. Image editing similar to Adobe Photoshop is accomplished using <application>the GIMP</application>. <application>Scribus</application> provides layout and publishing capabilites similar to Adobe Illustrator.</para>

        <para><inlinemediaobject>
            <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref="../../images/C/graphics.png" format="PNG"/>
            </imageobject>
  <textobject>
    <phrase>Graphics</phrase>
  </textobject>
        </inlinemediaobject></para>
</sect2>

<sect2 id="sound-and-video">
<title>Sound and Video</title>

<para>For all your video and audio playback and editing needs, Edubuntu provides several programs including
<application>Rhythmbox</application> for playing music and <application>Serpentine</application> for burning audio CDs. <application>Sound Juicer</application> rips audio CD tracks to your computer. <application>Totem</application> is an excelent video and movie player, and you can use <application>Kino</application> to edit video clips. <application>Sound Recorder</application> can be used to record audio clips to your computer.</para>

        <para><inlinemediaobject>
            <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref="../../images/C/soundandvideo.png" format="PNG"/>
            </imageobject>
  <textobject>
    <phrase>Sound and Video</phrase>
  </textobject>
        </inlinemediaobject></para>
</sect2>

<sect2 id="science">
<title>Science</title>

<itemizedlist>
<listitem>
<para><emphasis role='strong'>Explore the stars</emphasis> - <application>KStars</application> is a Desktop
  Planetarium that provides an accurate graphical
  simulation of the night sky. The program includes details for 130000 stars, 13000 deep-sky
  objects and all of the planets. <application>KStars</application> has an easy to use
  interface, so it can be used by everyone, from amateurs to astronomy experts.  
  You will also find a great deal of general
  information regarding telescopes and other astronomy-related
  matter. </para>
</listitem>

<listitem><para><emphasis role='strong'>Research the periodic table</emphasis> - <application>Kalzium</application>
	is a package for discovering and researching information about the
	periodic table and the elements.  It includes pictures for most of the 111 elements
	present, along with more detailed information including atomic
	models, spectrum analysis, chemical data and energies. </para>
</listitem>

<listitem><para><emphasis role='strong'>Test your chemistry skills</emphasis> - <application>Atomix</application> is
	a puzzle game, the purpose of which is to make
	up the molecule displayed from the atomic pieces scattered throughout the level.
	</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
        <para><inlinemediaobject>
            <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref="../../images/C/science.png" format="PNG"/>
            </imageobject>
  <textobject>
    <phrase>Science</phrase>
  </textobject>
        </inlinemediaobject></para>
</sect2>

<sect2 id="mathematics">
<title>Mathematics</title>
<itemizedlist>

<listitem><para><emphasis role='strong'>Program in Logo</emphasis> - <application>KTurtle</application>
	is a Logo programming language interpreter. The Logo
	programming language is very easy to learn and thus it can be used
	by young children.  A unique quality of Logo is that the commands
	or instructions can be translated, so the 'programmer' can program
	in his or her native language. This makes Logo ideal for teaching
	kids the basics of programming, mathematics and geometry.  One of
	the reasons many children warm to Logo is that the
	programmable icon is a small turtle, which can be moved around the
	screen with simple commands and can be programmed to draw
	objects. </para>
</listitem>

<listitem><para><emphasis role='strong'>Create geometric constructions</emphasis> - <application><application>Kig</application></application>
	allows teachers and students to create high-precision 
	geometrical constructions.  These can be built on and
	used to explain concepts like perpendicular bisectors, tangents
	and arcs. </para>
</listitem>

<listitem><para><emphasis role='strong'>Plot mathematical equations</emphasis> - <application>KmPlot</application> is
	a mathematical function graphing and plotting package.  <application>KmPlot</application> has a powerful
	built-in expression parser, and
	you can plot different functions simultaneously and combine their
	terms to build more complex mathematical functions. It
	supports functions with parameters and functions in polar
	coordinates. Plots may also be printed with high precision.</para>
</listitem>

<listitem><para><emphasis role='strong'>Calculate percentages</emphasis> -
	<application>KPercentage</application> is a mathematical application that helps
	pupils improve their skills in calculating percentages.
	Percentages are split into three types, and <application>KPercentage</application> tests
	pupils on these in three training modes.  In addition to this,
	there is a random mode which will pick questions from
	each of the three percentage question variations. </para>
</listitem>

<listitem><para><emphasis role='strong'>Practice Fractions</emphasis> - <application>KBruch</application> is
	a small program to help pupils practice calculations involving
	fractions. There are four different types of fraction
	exercise: </para>
<itemizedlist>

	<listitem><para>Exercise Fraction Task, where pupils have to solve a given
			fraction task </para></listitem>

	<listitem><para>Exercise Comparison, where pupils have to compare two given
			fractions' sizes </para></listitem>

	<listitem><para>Exercise Conversion, where pupils have to convert an already-given 
			number into a fraction </para></listitem>

	<listitem><para>Exercise Factorization, where pupils have to factor a
			given number into its prime factors</para></listitem>

</itemizedlist>
</listitem>

<listitem><para><emphasis role='strong'>Play at Math</emphasis> - <application>TuxMath</application>
	is an educational arcade game starring Tux, the Linux mascot!
	Based on the classic arcade game &quot;Missile Command,&quot; Tux
	must defend his cities by solving arithmetic problems.</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
        <para><inlinemediaobject>
            <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref="../../images/C/maths.png" format="PNG"/>
            </imageobject>
  <textobject>
    <phrase>Maths</phrase>
  </textobject>
        </inlinemediaobject></para>
</sect2>

<sect2 id="drawing">
<title>Drawing</title><itemizedlist>

<listitem><para><emphasis role='strong'>Tux Paint</emphasis> - <application>Tux
	Paint</application> is a free drawing program designed for young children. 
	The program provides an easy to use interface with
	fun sound effects and an encouraging cartoon mascot that gives
	help to children while they are painting.</para>
</listitem>

<listitem><para><emphasis role='strong'>Generate Fractals</emphasis> - <application>Xaos</application> is a 
	fractal generator with a whole host of extra features for 
	teaching pupils about fractal patterns.</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
        <para><inlinemediaobject>
            <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref="../../images/C/drawing.png" format="PNG"/>
            </imageobject>
  <textobject>
    <phrase>Drawing</phrase>
  </textobject>
        </inlinemediaobject></para>
</sect2>

<sect2 id="language">
<title>Language</title>
<itemizedlist>

<listitem><para><emphasis role='strong'>Practice Spanish verbs</emphasis> - With
	<application>KVerbos</application> you can practice Spanish verb conjugation. The program
	comes with a set of over 9,000 Spanish verbs that you can
	choose from to begin your verb training.  The package also keeps
	track of previous scores so that pupils can identify where their
	strengths and weaknesses are.  Some exercises also have a time
	limit, to raise the level of difficulty for more advanced
	users. </para>
</listitem>

<listitem><para><emphasis role='strong'>Play Hangman</emphasis> - <application>KHangman</application>
	is the classic hangman game, where pupils try to guess a word letter by 
	letter.</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
        <para><inlinemediaobject>
            <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref="../../images/C/language.png" format="PNG"/>
            </imageobject>
  <textobject>
    <phrase>Language</phrase>
  </textobject>
        </inlinemediaobject></para>
</sect2>

<sect2 id="basic-skills">
<title>Basic Skills</title>
<itemizedlist>

<listitem><para><emphasis role='strong'>Generate and give tests</emphasis> - <application>KEduca</application> is
	an educational testing package, allowing teachers to create tests
	for pupils to take. <application>KEduca</application> includes a module for constructing and
	saving new tests, as well as a separate module for loading and
	running the exams. Questions can be enhanced with images, multiple
	choice answers with varying weights, and time limits.</para>
</listitem>

<listitem><para><emphasis role='strong'>Learn touch typing</emphasis> - <application>KTouch</application>
	helps pupils learn to type quickly and correctly. With many different 
	modes and detailed reporting, <application>KTouch</application> truly makes learning touch-typing 
	easy.</para>
</listitem>
<!--</itemizedlist>

<itemizedlist>
<listitem><para><emphasis role='strong'>Play with touch typing</emphasis> - TuxType
	is an educational tutorial game that will help pupils to learn how
	to type on a keyboard whose the main star is Tux, the Linux Penguin.
	The player guides Tux to eat the fish that are falling
	from the sky, each fish has a letter or word written on it. The player
	needs only to press the correct key, and Tux will move to position
	himself under the fish. The game has a variety of difficulty
	settings which even experienced typists may find
	challenging. </para>
</listitem>-->

<listitem><para><emphasis role='strong'>Gcompris</emphasis> - <application>Gcompris</application>
	is a suite of over 80 educational games and activities for kids 
	age 4 to 10 to learn with. These include:</para>
<itemizedlist>

	<listitem><para>computer discovery: keyboard, mouse</para></listitem>
	<listitem><para>algebra: table memory, enumeration, double entry table,
			mirror image </para></listitem>
	<listitem><para>science: the canal lock, the water cycle, the submarine,
			electric simulation</para></listitem>
	<listitem><para>geography: place the country on the map</para></listitem>
	<listitem><para>games: chess, memory, connect 4, oware, sudoku</para></listitem>
	<listitem><para>reading: reading practice</para></listitem>
	<listitem><para>other: learn to tell time, puzzle of famous paintings,
			vector drawing</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>

        <para><inlinemediaobject>
            <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref="../../images/C/skills.png" format="PNG"/>
            </imageobject>
  <textobject>
    <phrase>Skills</phrase>
  </textobject>
        </inlinemediaobject></para>
</sect2>
</sect1>

<sect1 id="common-questions">
<title>Common Questions</title>
<sect2 id="obtaining-edubuntu">
<title>How Can I Get Edubuntu?</title>
<para>Edubuntu (both the Install and Live CDs) are available for
  download at <ulink
  url='http://www.edubuntu.org/'>http://www.edubuntu.org/</ulink>.</para>
</sect2>

<sect2 id="involved"><title>How Can Get Involved?</title>
<para>Edubuntu is built by a community of people, most of whom are
  volunteers. Edubuntu welcomes advice and feedback from as many
  different people as possible.  It's what makes this project work.
  There is a need for help in every area - documentation, developing,
  testing, advocacy, and support, so if you want to get involved please
  do.  Just email the
  Edubuntu <ulink url='http://lists.ubuntu.com/edubuntu-devel'>mailing
	list</ulink> or join
  the <emphasis role='strong'>#edubuntu</emphasis> IRC channel on
  &irc-server;. </para>
</sect2>

<sect2 id="ubuntu">
<title>How is Edubuntu related to Ubuntu?</title>
<para>Edubuntu is based on, and is indeed dependant on Ubuntu.  As
  packages are updated in Ubuntu, they are also updated in Edubuntu,
  as they share the same package repository.  This also means that they both
  have the same release cycle, which occurs roughly every six months.
  You will also find that many Edubuntu developers are also developers
  for Ubuntu.</para>
</sect2>

<sect2 id="language-help">
<title>I don't know much English. Can I also get help in my
  language?</title>
<para>Of course you can! As well as this document being translated
  into several other languages, there are a few Edubuntu localization
  teams around the world and a huge number of Ubuntu 
  localization teams.  If you think you can help, why not join
  your local team?</para>
</sect2>
</sect1>
</article>
