<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.3//EN" 
 "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.3/docbookx.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % globalent SYSTEM "../../../libs/global.ent">
%globalent;
<!ENTITY % cdo-C SYSTEM "../../../libs/cdo-C.ent">
%cdo-C;
<!ENTITY % kde SYSTEM "../../libs/kde.ent">
%kde;
<!ENTITY % kde-menus-C SYSTEM "../../libs/kde-menus-C.ent">
%kde-menus-C;
<!ENTITY language "&EnglishAmerican;">
]>
<article id="art-about-kubuntu" status="review" lang="&language;">

 <title>About Kubuntu</title>
 
 <para>Welcome to Kubuntu &kdistro-rev;: the &kdistro-version;
  	Release.</para>
  	
 <para>The Kubuntu project aims to be to KDE what Ubuntu is to GNOME: a great
  integrated distribution with all the great features of Ubuntu, but based
  on the KDE desktop.</para>
  
 <para>The team behind Kubuntu makes the following commitment to its users:</para>
 
 <itemizedlist>
 
  <listitem>
  
   <para>Kubuntu uses the solid base of Ubuntu plus the latest KDE. We
    are part of the Ubuntu community and use their infrastructure
    and support. Our mission is to be the best KDE distribution
    available. </para>
    
  </listitem>
  
  <listitem>
  
   <para>Kubuntu will always be free of charge, and there is no extra
    fee for the <quote>enterprise edition</quote>, we make our very
    best work available to everyone on the same free terms. </para>
    
  </listitem>
  
  <listitem>
  
   <para>Kubuntu includes the very best translations and accessibility
    infrastructure that the Free Software community has to offer, to
    make Kubuntu usable by as many people as possible. </para>
    
  </listitem>
  
  <listitem>
  
   <para>Kubuntu is entirely committed to the principles of free
    software and open source development; we encourage people to use
    free and open source software, improve it and pass it on.
   </para>
   
  </listitem>
  
 </itemizedlist>
 
 <para id="aboutkubuntu03">Kubuntu includes more than 1,000 pieces of software, starting with Linux
  version 2.6 and KDE 3.4, and covering every standard desktop application from word processing and
  spreadsheet to Internet access applications, web server software, email software, programming
  languages and tools, and of course, several games. </para>
  
 <sect1 id="wonderful-linux" status="review">
 
  <title>The Wonderful World of Linux</title>
  
  <para>Kubuntu uses the <quote>Linux</quote> kernel, the software which
   has come to define the worldwide movement to embrace open source
   software. Find out about Linux at <ulink url="&linuxorg;"
    >Linux.org</ulink>
  </para>
  
  <sect2 id="sect-kubuntu-difference" status="review">
  
   <title>The Difference</title>
   
   <para>There are many GNU/Linux distributions (e.g., Redhat, SuSE,
    Debian, Mandriva) but Kubuntu distinguishes itself as a
    different kind of distribution. </para>
    
   <para>Built on the solid and advanced base of Ubuntu, the Kubuntu
    team aims to create a distribution that provides an up-to-date and
    coherent GNU/Linux system for desktop and server computing.
    Kubuntu includes a number of selected packages from Ubuntu and
    is based on Debian's powerful <quote>APT</quote> package
    management system. APT allows easy installation and clean
    removal of programs, as well as automatic download of extra
    packages to satisfy dependencies. Unlike most distributions that
    ship a wide range of software packages that may or may not be of
    quality, Kubuntu's core list of packages is reduced only to the
    most important applications. (Although for maximum choice, you
    may choose from the full list, rather than being limited to the
    high quality core.) </para>
    
   <para>By focusing on quality, Kubuntu provides a robust and feature
    rich computing environment that is flexible for use in home and
    commercial environments. The project has more time to spend on
    the finer details and is able to release a version featuring the
    latest and greatest of today's software, every 6 months. Kubuntu
    ships with versions for i386 (Pentium CPUs / IBM-compatible
    PCs), AMD-64 (Hammer) and PowerPC (iBook/Powerbook, G4 and G5)
    architectures. </para>
    
  </sect2>
  
  <sect2 id="sect-about-KDE" status="review">
  
   <title>About KDE</title>
   
   <para>The default desktop environment for Kubuntu is KDE, a powerful Free Software graphical
    desktop environment for Linux and Unix workstations. It combines ease of use, contemporary
    functionality, and outstanding graphical design with the technological superiority of the Unix
    operating system. KDE is one of the two leading graphical desktop environments for GNU/Linux
    users. KDE sports an impressive array of easy to use, but powerful, graphical interface
    applications for users of all ages in both home and work environments. For developers, KDE
    provides a robust application development framework that enables rapid creation of first rate
    applications implementing cutting-edge technology. </para>
   
   <para>KDE is in many ways similar to GNOME, but there are a few distinct differences, which
    distinguish KDE as a desktop environment. KDE uses C++ at its base, with Qt (the Q-toolkit),
    whereas GNOME, using GTK, is written in C. KDE is typically the older and most widely used
    desktop environment, and is known to stress more the importance of features, and more recently
    -- usability. GNOME more notoriously attempts to prize itself on simplicity and easy-of-use.
    Popular criticisms of GNOME are that it's lacking in features and applications, while it's often
    commented that KDE has too many features which may themselves be hard to locate.</para>
   
    <para>Nevertheless, KDE and GNOME respectively target different audiences,
    and are fundamentally different in some respects, and the question of which
    desktop environment is superior is inherently a subjective opinion in many 
    ways. Because of this, to at least form a proper decision upon which is 
    more suited to yourself, it is advised that you try them both out. 
    Thus, it is very easy to install GNOME from a Kubuntu distribution, and 
    equally as easy to install KDE from an Ubuntu setup. </para>
  </sect2>
  
  <sect2 id="sect-switching-desktops" status="review">
  
   <title>Switching Desktops</title>
   
   <para>As an Ubuntu user, you may be concerned that your favorite
    GNOME applications will not run under Kubuntu. That
    is not the case. In recent times, much work has been done to
    increase compatibility between GNOME and KDE. Today, virtually
    all GNOME applications will run under KDE and vice-versa. </para>
    
   <para>While the KDE desktop is very different to that of GNOME, all
    your favorite GNOME applications will be integrated with your
    KDE menu system. </para>
    
   <para>Another concern for users wanting to try Kubuntu, may be that
    KDE will become their only desktop once it is installed. While
    we do indeed hope you will make KDE your desktop of choice, this
    is not the case, both desktop session types can be run after
    installing Kubuntu. Furthermore, during installation you will be
    given the choice of using either the GNOME Display Manager (GDM)
    or the K Display Manager (KDM). </para>
    
   <para>Either display manager will suffice and after installation you
    will be able to run both GNOME and KDE session types. Both GDM
    and KDM are replacements to the X Window Display Manager (XDM)
    that comprises the default display manager for the X Window
    System. Display managers are the <quote>windowing
    systems</quote> that generate the windows used to contain and
    control application interfaces. </para>
    
   <para>Feel free to try KDM, you can always switch back to GDM later
    if you like. </para>
    
  </sect2>
  
 </sect1>
 
</article>