<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.3//EN" 
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.3/docbookx.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % globalent SYSTEM "../../../libs/global.ent">
%globalent;
<!ENTITY % cdo-C SYSTEM "../../../libs/cdo-C.ent">
%cdo-C;
<!ENTITY % kde SYSTEM "../../libs/kde.ent">
%kde;
<!ENTITY % kde-general SYSTEM "/usr/share/apps/ksgmltools2/customization/obsolete/general.entities">
%kde-general;
<!ENTITY % xinclude SYSTEM "../../../libs/xinclude.mod">
%xinclude;
<!ENTITY language "en">
]>
<chapter id="add-applications" status="review">
    <title>Adding, Removing and Updating Applications</title>
    <para>This chapter is a complete guide to adding, removing and updating applications on a Kubuntu system.</para>
    <sect1 id="introduction-to-add-applications" status="writing">
        <title>Introduction</title>
        <para>There are several ways to manage your applications in Kubuntu. In order to add or remove applications you need to use a <emphasis>package manager</emphasis>. The following package managers are described in this chapter:</para>
        <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
                <para><application>Add/Remove Programs</application> - this is the simplest way to manage programs.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para><application>Adept</application> - this graphical program provides an advanced way of managing programs;</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para><application>APT</application> - this is a powerful command line program to manage programs.</para>
            </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
        <para>You may also wish to increase the number of programs available to install through your package managers. Not all the programs that exist for Kubuntu are available by default. You may have to add extra repositories in order to make them available: that is also described in this chapter.</para>
        <para>Finally, this chapter explains how to update your system.</para>
			<note>
                <para>You can only have one package management application running at a time. For example, if you are running <application>Add/Remove Programs</application> and try to launch <application>Adept</application>, it will fail with an error. Close the running application before you relaunch the new one.</para>
			</note>

    </sect1>
	    <sect1 id="kde-app-install" status="review">
		<title>Add/Remove Programs</title>
			<para><application>Add/Remove Programs</application> is a simple graphical way of installing and removing applications in Kubuntu. To launch <application>Add/Remove Programs</application>, choose <menuchoice><guimenu>K Menu</guimenu>
					<guimenuitem>Add/Remove Programs</guimenuitem></menuchoice> from the desktop menu system.</para>
			<note>
			<para>Running <application>Add/Remove Programs</application> requires administrative privileges (see <xref linkend="root-and-sudo"/>).</para>
			</note>
			<para>To install new applications select the category on the left, then tick the box of the applications you want to install. Click <guimenu>Apply</guimenu> and your chosen programs will be downloaded and installed automatically, as well as installing any additional applications that are required. The default selection is restricted to the KDE suite, but GNOME applications can be installed by selecting them from the dropdown menu at the top.</para>

            <para>Alternatively, if you know the name of the program you want, use the <guibutton>Search</guibutton> tool at the top.</para>
            <para>Software from additional repositories may be installed by enabling the Show: <emphasis>unsupported</emphasis> and Show: <emphasis>proprietary software</emphasis> tickboxes <emphasis role="bold"> if they are enabled</emphasis> in your repository list. For more information, see see <xref linkend="extra-repositories"/>check</para>
		</sect1>
    <sect1 id="adept" status="complete">
        <title>Adept Package Manager</title>
        <para>&appshort; is a graphical frontend to the <application>APT</application> package management system for the K Desktop Environment (KDE). &appshort; provides an easy-to-use interface with which users can perform software management operations.</para>
        <para>&appshort; can be started from the K menu system or the command line. In order to start &appshort;, you will be required to provide your password.</para>
        <para>To start &appshort; from the menu system select <menuchoice><guimenu>K Menu</guimenu>
                <guisubmenu>System</guisubmenu>
                <guimenuitem>Adept (Package Manager)</guimenuitem></menuchoice>.</para>
        <para>To start &appshort; from the command line:</para>
        <programlisting>kdesu adept </programlisting>
        <para>Both methods require that you enter your password. This will run &appshort; with root privileges which will be required in order to perform the requested operations. It is therefore advised that you use &appshort; with caution since improper usage could lead to the removal, deletion, or corruption of software packages that are required to preserve system integrity.</para>
        <para>For more help with using &appshort;, please refer to the <ulink url="help:/adept/index.html">Adept Handbook</ulink>.</para>
    </sect1>
    <sect1 id="apt-get" status="complete">
        <title>APT</title>
        <para><application>APT</application> (Advanced Packaging Tool) is a powerful package management system, on which the graphical programs <application>Add/Remove Programs</application> and <application>Adept</application> are based. <application>APT</application> automatically handles dependencies and performs other operations on system packages to allow the installation of the desired packages.</para>
        <note>
            <para>Running <application>APT</application> requires administrative privileges (see <xref linkend="root-and-sudo"/>).</para>
        </note>

        <para>Some common commands that can be used with <application>APT</application>:</para>
        <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
                <para>Install packages: <screen>sudo apt-get install <emphasis>packagename</emphasis></screen></para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Remove packages: <screen>sudo apt-get remove <emphasis>packagename</emphasis></screen></para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Search for packages: <screen>apt-cache search <emphasis>keyword</emphasis></screen></para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Retrieve new lists of available packages: <screen>sudo apt-get update</screen></para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Upgrade system with available updates: <screen>sudo apt-get dist-upgrade</screen></para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>List further commands and options: <screen>apt-get help</screen></para>
            </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
        <tip>
            <para>For further information about the use of <application>APT</application>, you can read the comprehensive <ulink url="&debian-apt;">Debian APT User Manual</ulink>.</para>
        </tip>
    </sect1>
	<sect1 id="manual-install" status="complete">
        <title>Manual Installation</title>
        <para>Although the preferred method of installing programs is via the package managers described in <xref linkend="add-applications"/>, you can also download and install individual package files containing software. There are many different kinds of Linux package files. Most of these are associated with the package managers of specific Linux distributions.</para>

        <para>If you find a packaged application that you wish to install, it is recommended that you check if there is a native Kubuntu package of the application available through a package manager, and that you install that version instead. This guarantees that the program is completely compatible with your system. If there is no package available through the package manager, you can install it manually. The installation procedure depends on the type of package file.</para>
        <sect2 id="install-deb" status="complete">
            <title>Install/Uninstall .deb files</title>
            <para>The package files associated with Kubuntu have the <emphasis>.deb</emphasis> suffix because of Kubuntu's close relation to the Debian GNU/Linux distribution. You can download and install individual <emphasis>.deb</emphasis> files. You will need administrative privileges to do this (see <xref linkend="root-and-sudo"/>).</para>
            <procedure>
                <step>
                    <para>To install a .deb file, simply <mousebutton>Right</mousebutton> click on the .deb file, and choose <menuchoice><guimenu>Kubuntu Package Menu</guimenu>
                            <guimenuitem>Install Package</guimenuitem></menuchoice>.</para>
                </step>
                <step>
                    <para>Alternatively, you can also install a .deb file by opening a terminal and typing:</para>
                    <screen>sudo dpkg -i package_file.deb</screen>
                </step>
                <step>
                    <para>To uninstall a .deb file, remove it using <application>Adept</application>, or type:</para>
                    <screen>sudo apt-get remove package_name</screen>
                </step>
            </procedure>
        </sect2>
        <sect2 id="alien" status="complete">
            <title>Convert .rpm files to .deb files</title>
            <para>Another type of package files is Red Hat Package Manager Files which have the <emphasis>.rpm</emphasis> suffix. It is not recommended to install these on an Kubuntu system. In almost all cases, a native Kubuntu <emphasis>.deb</emphasis> package is available. However, if absolutely necessary, an <emphasis>.rpm</emphasis> file can be converted to a <emphasis>.deb</emphasis> package using the program <application>alien</application>.</para>
            <procedure>
                <step>
                    <para>Install the <application>alien</application> program (<xref linkend="add-applications"/>).</para>
                </step>
                <step>
                    <para>Run the following command in a terminal, with administrative privileges:</para>
                    <screen>sudo alien package_file.rpm</screen>
                </step>
            </procedure>
        </sect2>
        <sect2 id="tarballs" status="complete">
            <title>Install from Source</title>
            <para>Files with the <emphasis>.tar.gz</emphasis> or <emphasis>.tar.bz2</emphasis> suffix are package files known as <emphasis>tarballs</emphasis> or <emphasis>source</emphasis> packages which are widely used in Linux. If there is no native Kubuntu package available in any of the Kubuntu repositories, you can try to compile the package from source. For tips on compiling software, look at the <ulink url="https://wiki.ubuntu.com/CompilingSoftware">Compiling Software</ulink> page on the Ubuntu Wiki.</para>
        </sect2>
	</sect1>
    <sect1 id="extra-repositories" status="complete">
        <title>Managing Repositories</title>
        <sect2 status="complete"><title>What are Repositories?</title>
            <para>There are thousands of programs freely available to install on Kubuntu. These programs are stored in software archives (<emphasis>repositories</emphasis>) and are made available for installation over the Internet. This makes it very easy to install new programs in Linux, and it is also very secure, because each program you install is built specially for Kubuntu and checked before it is installed. To organise the software, Kubuntu repositories are categorised into four groups: <emphasis>Main</emphasis>, <emphasis>Restricted</emphasis>, <emphasis>Universe</emphasis>, and <emphasis>Multiverse</emphasis>.</para> 
            <para>The rationale used to determine which software goes into which category is based on two factors:</para>
            <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para>The level of support software development teams provide for a program</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>The level of compliance the program has to the <ulink url="&ubuntu-philosophy;">Free Software Philosophy</ulink></para>
                </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
            <para>You can find more information about the Repositories available on the <ulink url="http://www.ubuntu.com/ubuntu/components"> Ubuntu website</ulink>.</para>
            <para>The standard Kubuntu Install CD contains some software from the <emphasis>Main</emphasis> and <emphasis>Restricted</emphasis> categories. Once your system is made aware of the Internet-based locations for these repositories, many more programs are made available for installation. Using the software package management tools already installed on your system, you can search for, install and update any piece of software directly over the Internet, without the need for the CD.</para>
        </sect2>
        <sect2 status="complete"><title>Removing the CD-ROM Repository</title>
            <para>The Kubuntu Install CD-ROM is included in the repositories after installation. This can cause &appshort; to ask for the CD-ROM when installing packages. It is possible to disable this repository so that &appshort; relies solely on the Internet repositories.</para> 
            <para>To disable the CD-ROM repository:</para>
            <procedure>
                <step>
                    <para>Start &appshort; by choosing <menuchoice><guimenu>K Menu</guimenu>
                            <guisubmenu>System</guisubmenu>
                            <guimenuitem>Adept (Package Manager)</guimenuitem></menuchoice> from the Desktop menu system.</para>
                </step>
                <step>
                    <para>Select <menuchoice><guimenu>View</guimenu>
                            <guimenuitem>Manage Repositories</guimenuitem></menuchoice> in the <application>Adept</application> package manager window.</para>
                </step>
                <step>
                    <para>Find the repository line that starts with "cdrom:", <mousebutton>right</mousebutton> click the line, and select <guimenuitem>Disable</guimenuitem>.</para>
                </step>
                <step>
                    <para>Click <guibutton>Apply</guibutton> to save your changes, and then exit using <guibutton>Close</guibutton>.</para>
                </step>
            </procedure>
        </sect2>
        <sect2 status="complete">
            <title>Adding Extra Repositories</title>
            <para>To enable the extra repositories:</para>
            <procedure>
                <step>
                    <para>Start &appshort; by choosing <menuchoice><guimenu>K Menu</guimenu>
                            <guisubmenu>System</guisubmenu>
                            <guimenuitem>Adept (Package Manager)</guimenuitem></menuchoice> from the Desktop menu system.</para>
                </step>
                <step>
                    <para>Select <menuchoice><guimenu>View</guimenu>
                            <guimenuitem>Manage Repositories</guimenuitem></menuchoice> in the <application>Adept</application> package manager window.</para>
                </step>
                <step>
                    <para>To enable the <emphasis>Universe</emphasis> repository, find the repository line with the Universe Component, and <mousebutton>right</mousebutton> click the line and select <guimenuitem>Enable</guimenuitem>.</para>
                    <note>
                        <para>Adding this repository will mean that the majority of the Free Software universe will be available to install on your system. This software is supported by a carefully selected group of volunteers within the Kubuntu Community, but is not supported by the core Kubuntu development team and may not include security updates.</para>
                    </note>
                </step>
                <step>
                    <para>To enable the <emphasis>Multiverse</emphasis> repository, find the repository lines (two of them) with the Universe Component, and click the word "universe". Edit the entry so that it reads "universe multiverse". <mousebutton>Right</mousebutton> click the line and select <guimenuitem>Enable</guimenuitem> to enable it if it is not already enabled.</para>
                    <warning>
                        <para>Adding this repository will mean that software which has been classified as <emphasis>non-free</emphasis> will be available to install on your system. This software may not be permitted in some jurisdictions. When installing each package from this repository, you should verify that the laws of your country permit you to use it. Again, this software may not include security updates.</para>
                    </warning>
                </step>
                <step><para>Click <guibutton>Apply</guibutton> to save your changes, and then exit using <guibutton>Close</guibutton>.</para>
                </step>
            </procedure>
        </sect2>
    </sect1>
    <sect1 id="updates" status="complete">
        <title>Updates</title>
        <para>Sometimes the Kubuntu developers release feature and security updates for applications and packages within the Kubuntu system.</para>
        <para>When these updates are available, Kubuntu will inform you with a red warning icon in the system tray. To update your system, click the red button, enter your password and click <guibutton>Fetch List of Updates</guibutton>.</para>
        <para>The <application>Adept Updater</application> program will list the available updates: to download and install these updates click <guibutton>Apply Updates</guibutton>. Kubuntu will then download and install the available updates from the Internet.</para>
        <para>When <application>Adept Updater</application> has finished updating your system, close the pop-up window by clicking the <guibutton>Quit</guibutton> button.</para>
        <note>
            <para>After installing some important updates, it may be necessary to restart your computer. If so, Kubuntu will inform you with a pop up and an icon in your system tray.</para>
        </note>
    </sect1>
</chapter>

