<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD Docbook XML V.4.3//EN"
	  "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.3/docbookx.dtd" [
	  <!ENTITY % globalent SYSTEM "../../../libs/global.ent">
	  %globalent;
	  <!ENTITY % cdo-C SYSTEM "../../../libs/cdo-C.ent">
	  %cdo-C;
	  <!ENTITY % gnome-menus-C SYSTEM "../../../ubuntu/libs/gnome-menus-C.ent">
	  %gnome-menus-C;
	  <!ENTITY % xinclude SYSTEM "../../../libs/xinclude.mod">
	  %xinclude;
	  <!ENTITY language "en">
	  <!ENTITY ubuntu '<phrase>Ubuntu</phrase>'>
	  ]>

<chapter id="applications" status="not started">	
	<title>Applications in &ubuntu;</title>
	<para>&ubuntu; has a wide selection of applications.</para>
	<sect1 id="applications-installing">
		<title>Using and Installing applications</title>
		<para>&ubuntu; includes a selection of useful applications which are installed by default. You can start an application by pressing <guibutton>Applications</guibutton> and then selecting an application from one of the categories displayed.</para>
		<para>If you would like to install additional applications, press <menuchoice><guimenuitem>Applications</guimenuitem><guimenuitem>Add/Remove...</guimenuitem></menuchoice>. Then, browse the selection of packages available and check the ones which you would like to install. When you have finished selecting packages, press <guibutton>Apply</guibutton> and wait for the installation process to finish.</para>
		<tip>
			<title>Additional, unsupported software</title>
			<para>By default, you can only install software which is fully supported in &ubuntu;. To gain access to the collection of unsupported software which is available for &ubuntu;, you can check the <guilabel>Show unsupported applications</guilabel> check box in the <application>Add/Remove...</application> application.</para>
		</tip>
	</sect1>
	<sect1 id="applications-games">
		<title>Games</title>
		<para>&ubuntu; ships with a modest selection of games to keep you entertained.</para>
		<sect2 id="applications-games-aisleriot">
			<title>AisleRiot Solitaire</title>
			<para><application>AisleRiot</application> is a collection of solitaire card games. Press <menuchoice><guimenuitem>Game</guimenuitem><guimenuitem>Select Game...</guimenuitem></menuchoice> to choose which type of solitaire you would like to play - there are over 80 different games to keep you occupied!</para>
			<para>To start <application>AisleRiot</application>, press <menuchoice><guimenuitem>Applications</guimenuitem><guimenuitem>Games</guimenuitem><guimenuitem>AisleRiot Solitaire</guimenuitem></menuchoice>.</para>
		</sect2>
		<sect2 id="applications-games-fom">
			<title>Five or More</title>
			<para>In <application>Five or More</application>, you must make a line of five (or more) marbles of the same color - the marbles will then disappear from the board. Click a marble to select it (it will start spinning) and then click an empty square to move the marble into that square. After each turn, three new marbles are added to the board. The object of the game is to prevent the board from filling with marbles for as long as possible.</para>
			<para>To start <application>Five or More</application>, press <menuchoice><guimenuitem>Applications</guimenuitem><guimenuitem>Games</guimenuitem><guimenuitem>Five or More</guimenuitem></menuchoice>.</para>
		</sect2>
		<sect2 id="applications-games-mahjongg">
			<title>Mahjongg</title>
			<para><application>Mahjongg</application> is a tile-matching game. You must select pairs of tiles which are at the edge of the pile - if you pick a pair which match, the tiles will disappear. The object of the game is to make all of the tiles disappear without getting stuck.</para>
			<para>To start <application>Mahjongg</application>, press <menuchoice><guimenuitem>Applications</guimenuitem><guimenuitem>Games</guimenuitem><guimenuitem>Mahjongg</guimenuitem></menuchoice>.</para>
		</sect2>
		<sect2 id="applications-games-others">
			<title>Optional applications</title>
			<para>As well as the default games which come pre-installed with &ubuntu;, there are many hundreds of games which you can optionally install. Below are just a few which are available to you:</para>
			<itemizedlist>
				<listitem><para><application>LXDoom</application> - classic first person shooting game</para></listitem>
				<listitem><para><application>GNOME Sudoku</application> - traditional number logic game</para></listitem>
				<listitem><para><application>Monkey Bubble</application> - explode bubbles of different colours</para></listitem>
				<listitem><para><application>Atomix</application> - make up molecules by pushing atoms around</para></listitem>
				<listitem><para><application>Chromium</application> - arcade-style space-shooter</para></listitem>
				<listitem><para><application>GCompris</application> - activities and games for kids</para></listitem>
			</itemizedlist>
			<para>For more information on games available in &ubuntu;, please see the <ulink url="https://help.ubuntu.com/community/Games">&ubuntu; community pages</ulink>.</para>
		</sect2>
	</sect1>
	<sect1 id="applications-graphics">
		<title>Graphics applications</title>
		<para>&ubuntu; ships with several graphics applications, which you can use to manage and edit your photos and pictures.</para>
		<sect2 id="applications-graphics-gimp">
			<title>GIMP Image Editor</title>
			<para>The <application>GIMP Image Editor</application> allows you to edit your photos quickly and easily, whether you want to remove a speck of dust or erase an entire building from the picture! With its large collection of filters, you can also apply fun and artistic effects to your images.</para>
			<para>To start the <application>GIMP Image Editor</application>, press <menuchoice><guimenuitem>Applications</guimenuitem><guimenuitem>Graphics</guimenuitem><guimenuitem>GIMP Image Editor</guimenuitem></menuchoice>.</para>
		</sect2>
		<sect2 id="applications-graphics-fspot">
			<title>F-Spot Photo Manager</title>
			<para>The <application>F-Spot Photo Manager</application> makes organizing your photos easy. You can tag, categorise and sort your photos with the minimum of effort. Whether you want to show your photos in a slideshow or publish them online, <application>F-Spot</application> makes it easy.</para>
			<para>To start the <application>F-Spot Photo Manager</application>, press <menuchoice><guimenuitem>Applications</guimenuitem><guimenuitem>Graphics</guimenuitem><guimenuitem>F-Spot Photo Manager</guimenuitem></menuchoice>.</para>
		</sect2>
		<sect2 id="applications-graphics-others">
			<title>Optional applications</title>
			<para>&ubuntu; has a wide selection of graphics applications available for you to use. Here are just a few:</para>
			<itemizedlist>
				<listitem><para><application>Inkscape Vector Illustrator</application> - powerful drawing application for creating graphics and artwork</para></listitem>
				<listitem><para><application>Scribus</application> - desktop-publishing (DTP) package, which you can use to produce professional-looking publications</para></listitem>
			</itemizedlist>
			<para>For more information on graphics software available in &ubuntu;, please see the <ulink url="https://help.ubuntu.com/community/GraphicsApplications">&ubuntu; community pages</ulink>.</para>
		</sect2>
	</sect1>
	<sect1 id="applications-internet">
		<title>Internet applications</title>
		<para>&ubuntu; includes a collection of world-class Internet applications to make your on-line experience as effortless as possible.</para>
		
		<sect2 id="applications-internet-ff">
			<title>Firefox Web Browser</title>
			<para><application>Firefox</application> is an award-winning browser which allows you to enjoy the web comfortably and securely. With many novel features, such as live bookmarks, integrated search and tabbed-browsing, <application>Firefox</application> offers one of the best browsing experiences available.</para>
			<para>To start the <application>Firefox Web Browser</application>, press <menuchoice><guimenuitem>Applications</guimenuitem><guimenuitem>Internet</guimenuitem><guimenuitem>Firefox Web Browser</guimenuitem></menuchoice>, or press the blue globe icon at the top of your screen.</para>
		</sect2>
		<sect2 id="applications-internet-evo">
			<title>Evolution Mail</title>
			<para><application>Evolution</application> is an easy-to-use personal organizer, which is the default email application in &ubuntu;. It offers a pleasing mix of advanced features and ease of use, designed to keep yourself and your emails organized. Whether you want to keep track of your tasks and appointments or just send and receive email, <application>Evolution</application> is a great choice.</para>
			<para>To start <application>Evolution Mail</application>, press <menuchoice><guimenuitem>Applications</guimenuitem><guimenuitem>Internet</guimenuitem><guimenuitem>Evolution Mail</guimenuitem></menuchoice>.</para>
		</sect2>
		<sect2 id="applications-internet-gaim">
			<title>Gaim Internet Messenger</title>
			<para><application>Gaim</application> is an instant messaging application with a twist - it allows you to talk to your friends and contacts on <emphasis>all</emphasis> of the major instant messaging networks, such as AIM and MSN, at the same time. While advanced features are not available for some networks, <application>Gaim</application> does a great job of allowing you to chat with your buddies.</para>
			<para>To start the <application>Gaim Instant Messenger</application>, press <menuchoice><guimenuitem>Applications</guimenuitem><guimenuitem>Internet</guimenuitem><guimenuitem>Gaim Instant Messenger</guimenuitem></menuchoice>.</para>
		</sect2>
		<sect2 id="applications-internet-others">
			<title>Optional applications</title>
			<para>A wide range of excellent Internet software is available for use with &ubuntu;, including these examples:</para>
			<itemizedlist>
				<listitem><para><application>Liferea Feed Reader</application> - allows you to collect and read Internet news feeds</para></listitem>
				<listitem><para><application>Ekiga Softphone</application> - make free phone calls over the Internet</para></listitem>
				<listitem><para><application>Drivel Journal Editor</application> - publish your very own online diary (blog)</para></listitem>
			</itemizedlist>
		</sect2>
		
	</sect1>
	<sect1 id="applications-office">
		<title>Office applications</title>
		<para>&ubuntu; includes a full office suite by default, the popular <application>OpenOffice.org</application> suite.</para>
		<sect2 id="applications-office-oow">
			<title>OpenOffice.org Word Processor</title>
			<para>The <application>Word Processor</application> allows you to create written documents of any type. Whether you want to send a letter to a relative or type up your lecture notes, <application>Word processor</application> has all of the tools you need to produce a high-quality document.</para>
			<para>To start the <application>Word Processor</application>, press <menuchoice><guimenuitem>Applications</guimenuitem><guimenuitem>Office</guimenuitem><guimenuitem>OpenOffice.org Word Processor</guimenuitem></menuchoice>.</para>
		</sect2>
		<sect2 id="applications-office-oos">
			<title>OpenOffice.org Spreadsheet</title>
			<para>The <application>Spreadsheet</application> allows you to collect and analyse sets of numbers. These could be anything from your household finances to local football scores - whatever you like. You can perform complex calculations on the numbers and produce illustrative graphs too.</para>
			<para>To start the <application>Spreadsheet</application>, press <menuchoice><guimenuitem>Applications</guimenuitem><guimenuitem>Office</guimenuitem><guimenuitem>OpenOffice.org Spreadsheet</guimenuitem></menuchoice>.</para>
		</sect2>
		<sect2 id="applications-office-oop">
			<title>OpenOffice.org Presentation</title>
			<para>Do you have a slideshow or presentation to make? <application>OpenOffice.org Presentation</application> allows you to create and show high-impact presentations quickly and easily. A collection of animation effects is available and you can even publish your slideshow on the web.</para>
			<para>To start <application>OpenOffice.org Presentation</application>, press <menuchoice><guimenuitem>Applications</guimenuitem><guimenuitem>Office</guimenuitem><guimenuitem>OpenOffice.org Presentation</guimenuitem></menuchoice>.</para>
		</sect2>
		<sect2 id="applications-office-others">
			<title>Optional applications</title>
			<para>&ubuntu; has a great collection of software designed to make office-type work simple. The following are some examples:</para>
			<itemizedlist>
				<listitem><para><application>gLabels</application> - design your own labels and business cards</para></listitem>
				<listitem><para><application>GnuCash</application> - keep track of your finances with this personal accounting package</para></listitem>
				<listitem><para><application>Dia</application> - draw professional diagrams and flowcharts</para></listitem>
			</itemizedlist>
			<para>For more information on office software available in &ubuntu;, please see the <ulink url="https://help.ubuntu.com/community/OfficeApplications">&ubuntu; community pages</ulink>.</para>
		</sect2>
	</sect1>
	<sect1 id="applications-sv">
		<title>Sound and Video applications</title>
		<para>You can enjoy music and movies in &ubuntu; using its collection of high-quality multimedia software.</para>
		<sect2 id="applications-sv-totem">
			<title>Movie Player</title>
			<para>You can use <application>Movie Player</application> to watch movies and video clips, or even to play music. DVD support is optional due to legal issues (see the <ulink url="https://help.ubuntu.com/community/RestrictedFormats">Restricted Formats</ulink> page on the &ubuntu; website for more information).</para>
			<para>To start <application>Movie Player</application>, press <menuchoice><guimenuitem>Applications</guimenuitem><guimenuitem>Sound &amp; Video</guimenuitem><guimenuitem>Movie Player</guimenuitem></menuchoice>, or simply double-click a movie file.</para>
		</sect2>
		<sect2 id="applications-sv-rb">
			<title>Rhythmbox Music Player</title>
			<para><application>Rhythmbox</application> is much more than just a music player. Not only does it boast features such as automatic playlists, instant music search and drag-and-drop queuing, but it can even handle podcasts, share music over a network and integrate with the online <emphasis>Last.fm</emphasis> service. What more could you ask for?</para>
			<para>To start <application>Rhythmbox</application>, press <menuchoice><guimenuitem>Applications</guimenuitem><guimenuitem>Sound &amp; Video</guimenuitem><guimenuitem>Rhythmbox Music Player</guimenuitem></menuchoice>.</para>
		</sect2>
		<sect2 id="applications-sv-sj">
			<title>Sound Juicer CD Extractor</title>
			<para><application>Sound Juicer</application> can be used to both play and extract audio CDs. If you have an Internet connection, it will even fetch the names of the songs on your CD for you.</para>
			<para>To start <application>Sound Juicer</application>, press <menuchoice><guimenuitem>Applications</guimenuitem><guimenuitem>Sound &amp; Video</guimenuitem><guimenuitem>Sound Juicer CD Extractor</guimenuitem></menuchoice>, or simply insert an audio CD.</para>
		</sect2>
		<sect2 id="applications-sv-serp">
			<title>Serpentine Audio CD Creator</title>
			<para><application>Serpentine</application> allows you to make your own compilation CDs. Simply drag and drop songs from <application>Rhythmbox</application> into <application>Serpentine</application>, insert a blank CD and then press <guibutton>Write to Disc</guibutton>. Your new CD will be ready in no time!</para>
			<para>To start <application>Serpentine</application>, press <menuchoice><guimenuitem>Applications</guimenuitem><guimenuitem>Sound &amp; Video</guimenuitem><guimenuitem>Serpentine Audio CD Creator</guimenuitem></menuchoice>, or insert a blank CD and press <guibutton>Make Audio CD</guibutton> on the screen which should appear.</para>
		</sect2>
		<sect2 id="applications-sv-others" status="jono-ified">
			<title>Optional applications</title>
			<para>&ubuntu; has a <emphasis>massive</emphasis> collection of multimedia applications at your disposal - below are a few examples:</para>
			<itemizedlist>
				<listitem><para><application>Jokosher</application> and <application>Audacity</application> - record, edit and mix your own music</para></listitem>
				<listitem><para><application>Pitivi</application> - record and edit your video footage</para></listitem>
				<listitem><para><application>Banshee</application> - organize and play your music, then sync it with your digital audio player</para></listitem>
			</itemizedlist>
			<para>For more information on office software available in &ubuntu;, please see the <ulink url="https://help.ubuntu.com/community/OfficeApplications">&ubuntu; community pages</ulink>.</para>
		</sect2>
	</sect1>
</chapter>
