<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD Docbook XML V.4.3//EN"
	  "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.3/docbookx.dtd" [
	  <!ENTITY % globalent SYSTEM "../../../libs/global.ent">
	  %globalent;
	  <!ENTITY % cdo-C SYSTEM "../../../libs/cdo-C.ent">
	  %cdo-C;
	  <!ENTITY % gnome-menus-C SYSTEM "../../../ubuntu/libs/gnome-menus-C.ent">
	  %gnome-menus-C;
	  <!ENTITY % xinclude SYSTEM "../../../libs/xinclude.mod">
	  %xinclude;
	  <!ENTITY language "en">
	  <!ENTITY ubuntu '<phrase>Ubuntu</phrase>'>
	  ]>

<chapter id="installing" status="review" xreflabel="Installing Ubuntu">	
	<title>Installing Ubuntu</title>
	<para>This chapter provides a step-by-step guide to installing Ubuntu onto your computer.</para>
	<sect1 id="installing-get" xreflabel="Obtaining an Ubuntu installation disc" status="review">
		<title>Obtaining an Ubuntu installation disc</title>
		<para>In order to install Ubuntu, you must obtain an installation CD. There are numerous ways of doing this, and the method you use will depend on what is available to you.</para>
		<sect2 id="installing-get-iso" status="review">
			<title>Download a CD image</title>
			<para>The Ubuntu installation CD is available to download from the Ubuntu website as a <emphasis>CD image (.iso)</emphasis>. Visit <ulink url="http://www.ubuntu.com/download">the Ubuntu website</ulink> to download a copy. Select your country (or a country which is close to you) and click to download the <emphasis>PC (Intel x86) desktop CD</emphasis>. The instructions in this chapter assume that you are installing Ubuntu using the <emphasis>Desktop CD</emphasis>, although some users may wish to use the <emphasis>alternate install CD</emphasis>, a copy of which is available from the same download page.</para>
			<para> The CD image is a very large file and may take several hours to download even with a fast Internet connection. If you have a slow Internet connection (such as dial-up), it is recommended that you obtain a CD by some other means (see the following sections).</para>
			<para>Once you have downloaded the ISO file, you must burn it onto a CD. In order to do this, you will need suitable CD-writing software. Full instructions on burning the ISO file to disc are provided on the <ulink url="https://help.ubuntu.com/community/BurningIsoHowto">Ubuntu support website</ulink>.</para>
		</sect2>
		<sect2 id="installing-get-shipit" status="review">
			<title>Order a CD from ShipIt</title>
			<para>Ubuntu offers the <emphasis>ShipIt</emphasis> service, which will deliver a small set of Ubuntu CDs to you at no cost. Follow the instructions on the <ulink url="http://shipit.ubuntu.com">ShipIt website</ulink> to place an order - delivery will typically take 6-10 weeks.</para>
		</sect2>
		<sect2 id="installing-get-borrow" status="review">
			<title>Borrow a copy</title>
			<para>Ubuntu is freely available <emphasis>software libre</emphasis>. You are encouraged and legally entitled to copy, reinstall and redistribute your copy of Ubuntu, and so if you know someone who will allow you to borrow their Ubuntu CD, then by all means do so! If you have a local <emphasis>Linux user group</emphasis>, they may also be able to provide an Ubuntu disc for you.</para>
		</sect2>
		<sect2 id="installing-get-buy" status="review">
			<title>Buy a CD</title>
			<para>It is possible to buy an Ubuntu CD from a third party, for a (typically) small charge. While these third parties are likely to be selling Ubuntu CDs for their own profit, you may find that buying a CD is the most convenient option for you.</para>
		</sect2>
	</sect1>
	<sect1 id="installing-booting" status="review">
		<title>Booting from the install CD</title>
		<para>In order to install Ubuntu, you must start your computer using the installation CD. While most computers will start from the installation CD if you simply insert the CD and then restart the computer, some computers may require additional steps to allow this.</para>
		<para>If your computer does not start from the installation CD if you insert it and then restart the computer, use the following steps:</para>
		<orderedlist>
			<listitem><para>Restart your computer with the CD still inserted in the drive</para></listitem>
			<listitem><para>When the computer restarts, look very carefully at the initial screen it shows. Look for an option such as <guilabel>&lt;F10&gt; Boot Order</guilabel> or <guilabel>Press DEL to enter setup</guilabel> and press the key which is noted (e.g. the <keycap>Delete</keycap> key). There are many different variations, so please see your computer manual if you are unsure which button you need to press.</para></listitem>
			<listitem><para>Find the options relating to <emphasis>Boot Order</emphasis>, <emphasis>Boot Sequence</emphasis> or similar. Ensure that your CD drive is <emphasis>first</emphasis> in the boot order by following the instructions on-screen.</para></listitem>
			<listitem><para>Once satisfied that your CD is first in the boot order, save your changes and restart the computer. It should now start from the Ubuntu installation CD.</para></listitem>
		</orderedlist>
		<para>If you are still unable to boot from CD, please seek support from one of the <ulink url="http://www.ubuntu.com/support">Ubuntu support channels</ulink>.</para>
		<para>If it has booted from the CD successfully, Ubuntu will load. This may take a while, as a cut-down copy of Ubuntu must be started from the CD.</para>
	</sect1>
	<sect1 id="installing-info" status="review">
		<title>Entering basic information</title>
		<para>Once the Ubuntu installation CD has booted successfully, you will be presented with a desktop, with an icon labelled <guilabel>Install</guilabel>. Double-click this icon to start the <application>Ubuntu installer</application>. Then, follow the instructions below:</para>
		<orderedlist>
			<listitem><para>Select your language from the list provided and then press <guibutton>Forward</guibutton>.</para></listitem>
			<listitem><para>Select a city from your country and timezone by either clicking the map or selecting a city from the drop-down menu labelled <guilabel>Selected city</guilabel>. Press <guibutton>Set Time...</guibutton> if the time is set incorrectly. Once you are satisfied that the time is correct for your location, press <guibutton>Forward</guibutton>.</para></listitem>
			<listitem><para>Select your keyboard layout from the list provided. You can type in the box provided to test that your keyboard is working correctly. Press <guibutton>Forward</guibutton> once you are satisfied that you have chosen the correct keyboard layout.</para></listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para>Enter the details requested. Pay particular attention to the password section - by choosing a more complicated password, you can help to make your computer more secure. You must also ensure that you can remember your password correctly, including the case of the letters you use (&apos;ABC&apos; is different to &apos;abc&apos;). Once satisfied that all of the information you entered is correct, press <guibutton>Forward</guibutton>.</para>
				<caution>
					<para>When choosing a password, try to use a combination of letters, numbers and punctuation symbols which spell out a random word (e.g. <emphasis>p0tato!</emphasis>). This will make your password harder to guess if someone tries to access your computer without your permission.</para>
				</caution>
			</listitem>
			<listitem><para>The <guilabel>Prepare disk space</guilabel> screen will load. This will allow you to partition your hard disk. Partitioning is covered in the next section, <xref linkend="installing-partitioning"/>.</para></listitem>
		</orderedlist>
	</sect1>
	<sect1 id="installing-partitioning" xreflabel="Partitioning your disks" status="draft">
		<title>Partitioning your disks</title>
		<note>
			<title>Installing both Ubuntu and Windows</title>
			<para>If you would like to install both Ubuntu and Windows on the same computer, please see the appendix <xref linkend="dualboot"/> for instructions.</para>
		</note>
		<para>If you do not intend to keep your copy of Windows installed on the computer, and you have made a backup of all of your important files, choose the <guilabel>Erase entire disk</guilabel> option from the <guilabel>Prepare disk space</guilabel> screen and then press <guibutton>Forward</guibutton>. The installer will automatically partition your hard disk in a suitable manner.</para>
		<para>Partitioning does not occur until you finalize the installation, so you can decide to abort the installation at the very last minute if you require. After finalizing the installation, however, the hard disk will be re-partitioned and all existing data stored on it will be lost. <emphasis role="strong">Ensure that you have made and tested a backup copy of all important data.</emphasis></para>
		<para>For more complicated partitioning requirements, select <guilabel>Manually edit partition table</guilabel> from the <guilabel>Prepare disk space</guilabel> screen, and then press <guibutton>Forward</guibutton>. This will start a partitioning tool which you can use to partition your disk yourself. If you are unfamiliar with partitioning, please seek support through an Ubuntu <ulink url="http://www.ubuntu.com/support">support channel</ulink> for advice on partitioning your hard disk safely and correctly.</para>
	</sect1>
	<sect1 id="installing-final" status="review">
		<title>Finalizing the installation</title>
		<para>After you have completed the partitioning stage, you will be presented with the <guilabel>Ready to install</guilabel> screen. This will provide a summary of the installation settings you have chosen. If you would like to change any of these settings, this is your last chance to do so. Press <guibutton>Back</guibutton> to change your settings.</para>
		<para>Once you are sure that you would like to proceed with installation, press <guibutton>Install</guibutton>. The installation process will then start, and may take a while to complete.</para>
		<warning>
			<para>Once you press <guibutton>Install</guibutton>, the changes you specified on the partitioning screen will be applied. <emphasis role="strong">These changes cannot be undone.</emphasis> Please make sure that the changes you have specified are correct and that you have a back-up copy of any valuable data stored safely.</para>
		</warning>
	</sect1>
	<sect1 id="installing-restarting" status="review">
		<title>Restarting into Ubuntu</title>
		<para>Once the installation process is complete, your computer will restart. After a short while, Ubuntu will start up for the first time. Type in your user name and password, which you entered earlier on in the installation process. After another short period, your Ubuntu desktop will load completely. <emphasis role="strong">Congratulations - you are now using Ubuntu!</emphasis></para>
	</sect1>
</chapter>
