<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.3//EN" 
	  "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.3/docbookx.dtd" [
	  <!ENTITY % globalent SYSTEM "../../../libs/global.ent">
	  %globalent;
	  <!ENTITY % cdo-C SYSTEM "../../../libs/cdo-C.ent">
	  %cdo-C;
	  <!ENTITY % kde SYSTEM "../../libs/kde.ent">
	  %kde;
	  <!ENTITY % kde-menus-C SYSTEM "../../libs/kde-menus-C.ent">
	  %kde-menus-C;
	  <!ENTITY language "&EnglishAmerican;">
	  ]>
	  <article id="art-kubuntu-releasenotes" status="help" lang="&language;">
		  <title>Kubuntu 5.10 Release Notes</title>
		  <subtitle>Kubuntu &kdistro-version; &kdistro-rev;</subtitle>
		  <articleinfo>
			  <abstract>
				  <para>This document contains the release notes for Kubuntu
					  &kdistro-version; &kdistro-rev;.</para>
			  </abstract>
			  <authorgroup>&author-sean-wheller; &author-troy-williams; 
				  <author>
					  <firstname>Jonathan</firstname>
					  <surname>Jesse</surname> 
				  </author> </authorgroup>
			 
		  </articleinfo>
		  <sect1 id="document" status="review">
		  <sect2 id="releasenotes-introduction" status="review">
			  <title>Introduction</title>
			  <para>
				  Kubuntu is a GNU/Linux distribution for your desktop or server, with a fast and easy install, regular releases,
				  a tight selection of excellent packages installed by default, and every other package you can imagine available
				  from the network.  Kubuntu also provieds security updates for 18 months after each releasea, and professional
				  technical support is available from many companies around the world.
			  </para>
			  <para>
				  These Release Notes cover new features in Kubuntu 5.10, download and installation notes, known issues, and
				  frequently asked questions.  Please read these notes before, during and after installation and configuration
				  before reporting bugs
			  </para>
			  <para>
				  We hope you enjoy the release of Kubuntu 5.10
			  </para>
		  </sect2>
		  <sect2 id="releasenotes-new" status="help">
			  <title>What's New</title>
			  <para>Here's what's new with Kubuntu 5.10</para>
			  <sect3 status="review">
				  <title>On the Desktop </title>
				  <variablelist>
					  <varlistentry>
						  <term>Adept and Adept-Updater</term>
						  <listitem>
							  <para>Adept is a new package manager for KDE.  With advanced search facilities using debtags, hunting for packages is now easier than ever.
							  </para>
							  <para>To help keep your system current, adept-updater checks to see which packages
								  have changed and makes it easy to download and install the latest fixes.
							  </para>
						  </listitem>
					  </varlistentry>
					  <varlistentry>
						  <term>KDE System Settings</term>
						  <listitem>
							  <para>Kawabunga! The traditional KDE Control Center has been replaced with
								  KDE System Settings. This change is not part of KDE, but is unique to
								  Kubuntu. The new interface is cleaner, faster, simpler and comes with
								  improved usability features such as quick search.</para>
						  </listitem>
					  </varlistentry>
					  <varlistentry>
						  <term>KDE Language Packs</term>
						  <listitem>
							  <para>Kubuntu now includes KDE translations on the CD for the most popular languages, over 50 languages are supported.</para>
						  </listitem>
					  </varlistentry>
					  <varlistentry>
						  <term>KDE Bluetooth Framework</term>
						  <listitem>
							  <para>The KDE Bluetooth tools aim to provide easy access to Bluetooth
								  profiles and facilitate the communication between Bluetooth enabled
								  devices such as cell phones and PDAs.</para>
						  </listitem>
					  </varlistentry>
					  <varlistentry>
						  <term>OpenOffice.org 2</term>
						  <listitem>
							  <para> The OpenOffice.org 2 is installed by default and now comes with KDE integration.
							  </para>
						  </listitem>
					  </varlistentry>
					  <varlistentry>
						  <term>GStreamer for Kaffine and AmaroK</term>
						  <listitem>
							  <para>Our Kaffine video player and AmaroK music player now use the GStreamer media framework, a large range of GStreamer plugins are available for many different media file formats.</para>
						  </listitem>
					  </varlistentry>
					  <varlistentry>
						  <term>Krita</term>
						  <listitem>
							  <para> A new advanced image editor program that is has been added to the
								  mix by default</para>
						  </listitem>
					  </varlistentry>
					  <varlistentry>
						  <term>KLaptopDaemon</term>
						  <listitem>
							  <para>To help out our laptop users, KLaptopDaemon now works for hibernation and uses acpi.</para>
						  </listitem>
					  </varlistentry>
					  <varlistentry>
						  <term>Locate File Search</term>
						  <listitem>
							  <para>Having problems finding that file?  In Konqueror just type locate:/ followed by what you
								  are looking for.  Konqueror will search for it.</para>
							  <para>Searching for something on the web?  Use Konqueror's search bar and Google suggest to help find exactly
								  what you are looking for.</para>
						  </listitem>
					  </varlistentry>
					  <varlistentry>
						  <term>Automounting</term>
						  <listitem>
							  <para>If you are sick of hunting for where your CD-ROM and Memory stick are setup, in Kubuntu 5.10, these are
								  automounted for ease of use.
							  </para>
						  </listitem>
					  </varlistentry>
					  <varlistentry>
						  <term>KOffice 1.4 and Kexi</term>
						  <listitem>
							  <para>KOffice 1.4 is now included in the main repository.  This lightweight but powerful office suite includes
								  Kexi, a powerful database frontend.
							  </para>
						  </listitem>
					  </varlistentry>
					  <varlistentry>
						  <term>X.org 6.8.2</term>
						  <listitem>
							  <para>For better hardware support Kubuntu 5.10 has updated X.org to version 6.8.2</para>
						  </listitem>
					  </varlistentry>
					  <varlistentry>
						  <term>Katapult</term>
						  <listitem>
							  <para>Katapult is used to start applications and bookmarks. Just press Alt+Space then type the name of the program you are interested in, it will quickly become the most useful tool on your desktop.</para>
						  </listitem>
					  </varlistentry>
				  </variablelist>
			  </sect3>
			  <sect3>
				  <title>On the Server</title>
				  <variablelist>
					  <varlistentry>
						  <term> PHP5 </term>
					  </varlistentry>
					  <varlistentry>
						  <term>LVM Volumes</term>
					  </varlistentry>
					  <varlistentry>
						  <term>Support for thin client devices</term>
					  </varlistentry>
					  <varlistentry>
						  <term>Support for 4 GB of RAM</term>
					  </varlistentry>
				  </variablelist>
			  </sect3>
			  <sect3>
				  <title>Hardware Support Improvements</title>
				  <variablelist>
					  <varlistentry>
						  <term>Linux 2.6.12.6</term>
					  </varlistentry>
					  <varlistentry>
						  <term>Changes for laptop users</term>
						  <listitem>
						  <para>
							  To help out our laptop users, a lot of enhancements have been made to improve their
							  experience (hot keys, working supsend/resume on many models)
						  </para>
						  </listitem>
					  </varlistentry>
					  <varlistentry>
						  <term>HP All-in-one devices</term>
						  <listitem>
						  <para>
							  Out of the box support is enabled for many HP all-in-one printer/scanner 
						  </para>
						  </listitem>
					  </varlistentry>
					  <varlistentry>
						  <term>Bluetooth</term>
						  <listitem>
						  <para>
							  Using a Bluetooth enabled devices?  Input devices such as a keyboards and mice
							  are also supported out of the box
						  </para>
						  </listitem>
					  </varlistentry>
					  <varlistentry>
						  <term>64-bit PowerPC</term>
						  <listitem>
						  <para>
							  Do you have a 64-bit PowerPC?  Use the kernel for that architecture
						  </para>
						  </listitem>
					  </varlistentry>
				  </variablelist>
			  </sect3>
			  
		  </sect2>
		  <sect2>
			  <title>Downloading and Installing</title>
			  <sect3>
				  <title>Where do I download Kubuntu 5.10?</title>
				  <para>
					  Kubuntu 5.10 can be download from http://releases.ubuntu.com/kubuntu/5.10 and
					  then burned onto a writable CD
				  </para>
			  </sect3>
			  <sect3>
				  <title> How do I install Kubuntu 5.10?</title>
				  <para>
					  It is extremly easy to install Kubuntu 5.10.  Make sure your computer can boot
					  from a CD-ROM, insert the CD-ROM and then follow the screens.
				  </para>
			  </sect3>
		  </sect2>
		  <sect2 id="releasenotes-upgradenotes" status="writing">
			  <!-- Jonathan Jesse: Writing this Part -->
			  <title>Upgrade Notes</title>
			  <sect3 id="upgradenotes-pre" status="writing">
				  <title>Pre-Upgrade</title>
				  <para>The easiest way to make the switch between Hoary HedgeHog and Breezy
					  Badger is to simply change the source list that is currently being used.
					  From the K Menu go to run and type kdesu kate /etc/apt/sources.list.  This
					  will bring up the list and then it is a simple apt-get update to fetch the
					  new package information.
				  </para>
				  <para>
					  Before starting the actual upgrade login to failsafe
					  mode, this will prevent problems with chances to X and the easy installation
					  of the latest version of KDE.  Replace each instance of Hoary with Breezy and close
					  the file, saving changes.  After doing this, a simple sudo apt-get dist-upgrade from
					  the command prompt.  The system will check for the updated packages and will prompt 
					  for a response on whether or not these need to be installed.  Answer yes to the 
					  question and sit back while Brezy Badger is installed.
				  </para>
			  </sect3>
			  <sect3 id="upgradenotes-post" status="help">
				  <title>Post-Upgrade</title>
				  <para>After the upgrade is finished, logout to restart your session
					  with the new version of KDE and everything else upgraded.  No reboot
					  necessary.</para>
				  
			  </sect3>
		  </sect2>
		  
		  <sect2 id="releasenotes-credits" status="help">
			  <title>Credits</title>
			  <itemizedlist>
				  <listitem>
					  <para>
						  <emphasis role="bold">Kubuntu Documentation</emphasis>: Greg Taylor,
						  Jerome Gotangco, Jonathan Jesse, Sean Wheller, Troy
						  Williams</para>
				  </listitem>
			  </itemizedlist>
		  </sect2>
		  </sect1>
	  </article>
