<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.3//EN" 
	"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.3/docbookx.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % xinclude SYSTEM "../../libs/xinclude.mod">
%xinclude;
<!ENTITY % globalent SYSTEM "../../libs/global.ent">
%globalent;
]>
<chapter id="software-updates">
	<title>Keeping your System up-to-date and beyond</title>
	<sect1 id="sect-soft-update">
		<title>Keeping the System up-to-date</title>
		<para>
			Computers are supposed to be used, people need them for work and play, you should not have to spend all your time fixing and updating it. At the same time is keeping your system up-to-date a must. You cannot just leave your computer as it is. Especially if you are connected to the internet then you need to install at least security updates. Ubuntu makes this really simple.
    		</para>
	</sect1>
	<sect1 id="sect-soft-uptodate">
		<title>Keeping the System up-to-date</title>
		<para>
			Beginning with Hoary, Ubuntu has a smart update tool running in your panel. It will check every once in a while if your system is up-to-date and if it finds updates it will show the following:
		</para>
		<figure>
			<title>Panel thingie</title>
			<screenshot> 
				<mediaobject> 
					<imageobject>
						<imagedata fileref="../images/synaptic-toolbar.png" 
							format="PNG"/> 
					</imageobject>
					<textobject> 
						<phrase>
							Shows available updates
						</phrase>
					</textobject> 
				</mediaobject> 
			</screenshot> 
		</figure>
</sect1>
	<sect1 id="sect-soft-upgrade">
		<title>Upgrading your system to the next version of Ubuntu</title>
		<para>
			Imagene that you are completely satisfied with the way you have setup your computer. You spent considarable time making it look just like you want. You added wallpapers and made folders, you installed programs and configured them, basically you're finally satisfied. And now all of a sudden comes this new version of Ubuntu. What to do? Stay with your old system or start from scratch? Don't worry there is hope. It's called Dist-upgrade.
		</para>
		<para>
			It is possible to install from one version of Ubuntu to the next. For this to work you need to be able to get all the new packages, usually from internet, and you need o do some configuring. What do you need to change?
		</para>
		<para>
			Open synaptic (&synaptic;)
		</para>
		<para>
			Open the repository editor with <menuchoice><guimenu>Preferences</guimenu>
			<guimenuitem>Repositories</guimenuitem></menuchoice> from the menu.
		</para>
		<figure>
			<title>Repository Preferences</title>
			<screenshot> 
				<mediaobject> 
					<imageobject>
						<imagedata fileref="../images/synaptic-repositories.png" 
							format="PNG"/> 
					</imageobject>
					<textobject> 
						<phrase>
							Shows the repository preferences
						</phrase>
					</textobject> 
				</mediaobject> 
			</screenshot> 
		</figure>
		<para>
			Choose your main Ubuntu repository (like in the screenshot). In the screenshot you see "Warty", this you change to the next version of Ubuntu, for example Hoary. Do the same with all the other repository entries.
		</para>
		<para>
			Press <guibutton>Ok</guibutton> and update your package-list (Click on <guibutton>Reload</guibutton> in the toolbar). When you now press <guibutton>applicationly</guibutton>, your system will be updated to the next version of Ubuntu. This will take a while.
		</para>
		<note>
			<para>
				Synaptic might ask several questions, read those carefully.
			</para>
		</note>
	</sect1>
    <!--<para>Security updates, blah, blah, dist-upgrades to Hoary, blah... </para>-->
</chapter>
