<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.3//EN" 
	"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.3/docbookx.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % xinclude SYSTEM "../../libs/xinclude.mod">
%xinclude;
<!ENTITY % globalent SYSTEM "../../libs/global.ent">
%globalent;
]>

<!--
  https://www.ubuntulinux.org/wiki/SynapticHowto is a possible source for contents
-->
<chapter id="software-installremove">
    <title id="title-software-installremove">Install Software</title>
    <!-- FIX ME:  Alexander: I do not have hoary yet so I can not really write a description of the new package installer, this is just a draft. -->
    <para>Ubuntu is based on Debian which has the most advanced package management system written
        to date. Installing software with Ubuntu is quite different from what you might be used to,
        usually you don't have to search for programs (or packages as it is usually called on
        Linux), all you need is just a few mouse-clicks away. Here we will explain three ways to
        install software. This might look overly complicated but, as always, people have different
        tastes and needs. The first method is the new installer. It is called . Many people will
        only use this tool. It is the easiest way to install all your basic software. If you do a
        lot with packages (the term that we will use from now on), then Synaptic will be the next
        step. Synaptic has it's own manual so we will only shortly describe it here. And then the
        third way, the command-line tools. Now you might object that you don't want to type
        anything! That's ok, you don't have to, you can do all you need with synaptic, but if you
        like to make things really complicated, or do really complicated things (all depends on your
        point of view), or just don't like using the mouse, then there are the command-line tools,
        apt, dpkg and friends. </para>
    <para>All the tools described above use the same underlying system, so you do not have to
        worried that over time your system will become unstable, just because you install or remove
        packages. Actually you'll notice that you might start to install and remove packages just to
        check them out. It's just that easy. </para>
    <sect1>
        <title>Fast and Easy</title>
        <para>NAME can be found here: </para>
        <para>&gnome-app-install; </para>
        <para>The icons and short descriptions help you to quickly find the requested package. By
            pressing ... you select it and by pressing ..., it will get installed. You'll see a
            window popping telling you what it is doing but you can safely ignore this. In a couple
            of seconds (depending on what you just installed and how fast your network connection
            is), you'll be able to start your application from the menu. The most difficult part is
            actually finding it in your menu. For the rest: easy as pie. </para>
    </sect1>
    <sect1>
        <title>Installing Packages</title>
        <para>text</para>
    </sect1>
    <sect1>
        <title>Removing Packages</title>
        <para>... </para>
    </sect1>
    <sect1>
        <title>Purging Packages</title>
        <para>... </para>
    </sect1>
    <sect1>
        <title>Using advanced tools</title>
        <para>Don't let the title scare you off. Using the advanced tools for pakage management is
            not that hard. Actually if you are used to using the simpler tools then you have a basic
            understanding already of what is going on. The following tools will give you more power
            to have more fine-grained control over what you are doing: </para>
        <para>The <application>Synaptic package manager</application> is a powerfull tool for
            package-management. Documentation to it you can find <ulink type="help"
            url="ghelp:synaptic">here</ulink>. </para>
        <para>And then there are the command line tools. These are the most powerfull but to use
            these you have to understand wht is going on. Documentation can be found here. </para>
    </sect1>
</chapter>
