<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.3//EN" 
	"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.3/docbookx.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % xinclude SYSTEM "../../libs/xinclude.mod">
%xinclude;
<!ENTITY % globalent SYSTEM "../../libs/global.ent">
%globalent;
]>
<chapter id="about-linux">
	<title>Defining Linux</title>
	<para>Contrary to what you may have heard from the media, from friends, or from the Internet, Linux is not an operating system.
	No, really.
	It isn't an OS.
	What is commonly referred to as "Linux" is actually a combination of <ulink url="http://www.gnu.org">GNU</ulink>, pronounced "guh-noo", software and the Linux kernel.</para>
	
	<para>Linux was brought to life in 1991 by a Finnish student named Linus Torvalds.
	At the time, it would run only on i386 systems, and was essentially an independently created clone of the UNIX kernel, intended to take advantage of the then-new i386 architecture.
	Around the same time, the GNU project, launched in 1984, was making progress on their UNIX OS clone, lacking, for all practical purposes, only a kernel.
	Linux, unlike the GNU project's ideal kernel, Hurd, was, at the time, limited to the i386 platform, so it took some time before the two projects joined forces, so to speak.</para>
	
	<para>Following a substantial amount of development effort, Linux runs on virtually every modern architecture, and GNU software provides the necessary tools to make it useful.
	Conceptually, Linux is the heart of the GNU/Linux operating system model, and GNU is the body.
	Distributions, such as Ubuntu, which provide GNU/Linux as well as a number of useful programs, are operating systems.</para>
	
	<para>To summarize that, Ubuntu is an operating system based on the GNU/Linux model, with Linux being but a kernel.</para>

	<para>However, beyond the technical definition of Linux, there exists an entire community of people who believe in the ideals of free software and spend their time helping to make open source technology as good as it can be.</para>
	
	<para>People in this community gave rise to initiatives such as Ubuntu, standards commitees that shape the development of the Internet, organizations like the Mozilla Foundation, responsible for creating Mozilla Firefox, and countless other software projects from which you've certainly benefitted in the past.</para>
	
	<para>The spirit of open source, commonly attributed to Linux, is influencing software developers and users everywhere, making it the kernel driving a community.</para>
</chapter>
