<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.3//EN" 
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.3/docbookx.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % globalent SYSTEM "../../../libs/global.ent">
%globalent;
<!ENTITY % cdo-C SYSTEM "../../../libs/cdo-C.ent">
%cdo-C;
<!ENTITY % kde SYSTEM "../../libs/kde.ent">
%kde;
<!ENTITY % kde-menus-C SYSTEM "../../libs/kde-menus-C.ent">
%kde-menus-C;
<!ENTITY % kde-general SYSTEM
"/usr/share/apps/ksgmltools2/customization/obsolete/general.entities">
%kde-general;
<!ENTITY % xinclude SYSTEM "../../../libs/xinclude.mod">
%xinclude;
<!ENTITY language "en">
]>
<article id="keep-safe" status="complete">
<articleinfo>
<title>Keeping Your Computer Safe</title>
&legalnotice;
<abstract>
<para>
This section describes how to keep your computer safe from security threats.
</para>
</abstract>
</articleinfo>

<sect1 id="keep-safe-updates" status="complete">
<title>Keeping your computer updated</title>

<para>
Refer to <ulink type="help"
url="help:/kubuntu/add-applications">Updates</ulink> under the <emphasis>Adding
Applications</emphasis> documentation.
</para>

</sect1>


<sect1 id="keep-safelock-screen" status="complete">
<title>Lock your screen while away</title>

<para>
Locking your screen prevents other people from accessing your computer while you
are away from it. All of your applications and work remain open while the screen
is locked, and the screensaver is displayed.
</para>

<para>
You can lock your screen in one of the following ways:
<itemizedlist>
<listitem>
<para>
Press &menulock;.
</para>
</listitem>

<listitem>
<para>
Press 
<keycombo>
<keycap>Alt</keycap>
<keycap>Ctrl</keycap>
<keycap>L</keycap>
</keycombo>
 to lock the screen. This keyboard shortcut can be changed in
<application>System Settings</application> under the <guilabel>Keyboard &amp;
Mouse</guilabel>. To access this go to &menukbandmouse; and under the
<guilabel>Keyboard Shortcuts</guilabel> section, <guilabel>Global
Shortcuts</guilabel> tab, locate the <guilabel>Lock Session</guilabel> under
<guilabel>Desktop</guilabel>.
</para>
</listitem>

</itemizedlist>
</para>

<note>
<para>
You can add a <guibutton>Lock Screen</guibutton>
button to the <application>Kicker</application> for easy access. Right-click
the <application>Kicker</application>, select <guibutton>Add Applet
to Panel...</guibutton> and select the <guibutton>Lock/Logout
Buttons</guibutton> item, and then press the <guibutton>Add to
Panel</guibutton> button.
</para>
</note>

<para>
To unlock the screen, move the mouse or press a key. Then, type your password
and either press the <keycap>Return</keycap> key or press the
<guibutton>Unlock</guibutton> button.
</para>

<para>
If more than one person has a user account on your computer and the screen is
locked, other users can press the <guibutton>Switch user...</guibutton> button
to use the computer, even while the screen is locked. They will be unable to
access your currently-open work, and you will be able to switch back to your
locked session when they have finished using the computer.
</para>

</sect1>

<sect1 id="keep-safe-firewall" status="complete">
<title>Set up a firewall</title>

<para>
<application>Guarddog</application> is the firewall of choice for KDE. Please
review the <ulink type="help" url="help:/kubuntu/network/">Networking</ulink>
documentation and locate the <application>Guarddog</application> section.
</para>

</sect1>

<sect1 id="keep-safe-avoid-internet-crime" status="complete">
<title>Avoid Internet nuisances and crime</title>

<para>From time to time, you may be sent an email which carries a
virus or links to a fraudulent website. This type of email is very common, and
it is important to learn how to deal with it, in order to prevent your computer
or your personal details from being compromised or misused.
</para>

<para>
Such messages are often received from total strangers. However, sometimes an
email may appear to be from someone you know, when really it is not. This is
because it is possible to include a fake sender email address in emails.
</para>

<para>
Unwanted (unsolicited) mail tends to fall in to one of several categories:
</para>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem>
<para>
Spam (junk) email, where people offer unwanted services and products
</para>
</listitem>

<listitem>
<para>
Scam emails, where people pretend to ask for help in exchange for large sums of
money
</para>
</listitem>

<listitem>
<para>
Phishing email, where the message appears to be from a bank or other online
service, asking you to enter your personal and financial details, or passwords.
</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>

<para>Below are some tips for keeping safe online:</para>

<itemizedlist>
<listitem>
<para>
You should never reply to unsolicited mail, or even click on the links in the
mail. Doing so usually results in more junk mail being sent to you.
</para>
</listitem>

<listitem>
<para>
Never click on links in emails which lead to websites asking for your password
or similar. It is possible for the text of the link to give one address, when
really it opens up another (possibly dangerous) address. Instead, type the link
into your web browser yourself and proceed from there.
</para>
</listitem>

<listitem>
<para>
When visiting a website that asks for your financial information, ensure that
it is secure. In <application>Konqueror</application> and in
<application>Firefox</application> there are two areas that will provide
notification if the current page is secure. The first area is the address bar.
If the page is a secure page, the address bar will have a yellow background as
well as a lock to the right of the address. The second area is the status bar
which is located at the bottom right of each browsers window. If the page is a
secure page, a lock will appear in this area. Clicking on either of the locks
will provide you with a dialog that will explain in detail the type of licensing
and security for that page.
</para>
</listitem>

<listitem>
<para>
Only download and run software from sources that you trust. By default, you can
only download software directly from Ubuntu.
</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>

</sect1>

<sect1 id="keep-safe-backup-files" status="complete">
<title>Make backup copies of your files</title>

<para>
A problem which you may occasionally encounter is the unexpected loss of some of
your work and settings for one reason or another. The causes of such
<emphasis>data loss</emphasis> are many and varied; it could be anything from a
power cut to accidentally deleting a file. It is highly recommended that you
make regular back-up copies of your important files so that, if you do encounter
a problem, you will not have lost those files.
</para>

<para>
It is wise to store back-up copies of files separately from
your computer; that is, you should make use of some form of file storage which
is not permanently attached to your computer. Options include:
</para>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem><para>Writable CDs and DVDs</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>External hard disks and flash memory devices</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Another computer on the network</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist>

<para>
A simple way of backing-up your files is to manually copy them to a safe
location (see above) by using <application>Konqueror</application>.
</para>

<para>
Alternatively and the preferred way, is that you can use
<application>Keep</application>, the dedicated KDE backup solution. Access
<application>Keep</application> by going to &menukeep;.
</para>

</sect1>

</article>
