<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.3//EN" 
	"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.3/docbookx.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % globalent SYSTEM "../../../libs/global.ent">
%globalent;
<!ENTITY % cdo-C SYSTEM "../../../libs/cdo-C.ent">
%cdo-C;
<!ENTITY % xubuntu-ent SYSTEM "../../../xubuntu/libs/xubuntu.ent">
%xubuntu-ent;
<!ENTITY % xinclude SYSTEM "../../../libs/xinclude.mod">
%xinclude;
<!ENTITY language "en">
<!ENTITY ubuntu '<phrase>Ubuntu</phrase>'>
]>
<?db.chunk.max_depth 2?>
<?yelp:chunk-depth 2?>
	<article id="internet" status="complete">
	<articleinfo>
		<title>Internet</title>
    	&legalnotice;
	</articleinfo>
		<para>This section describes a number of tasks related to the Internet, including how to connect to the Internet, configure and use a web browser, and use other types of Internet programs.</para>
	<sect1 id="connect-to-internet" status="complete">
		<title>Connecting to the Internet</title>
		<sect2 id="internet-basic-procedure" status="review">
			<title>Basic Procedure</title>
			<para>This section describes the basic procedure for connecting to the Internet.</para>
                        <note>
                        	<para>If you have a wireless connection or connect to the Internet through a modem (including an ADSL modem), and this section does not work, you should read <xref linkend="wireless"/> or <xref linkend="modems"/>.</para>
                        </note>
   	                 <para>To connect to the Internet:</para>
			<procedure>
				<step>
					<para>Open &networking;.</para>
	                        </step>
				<step>
					<para>Go to the <guilabel>Connections</guilabel> tab and click the connection you wish to use to select it.</para>
				</step>
				<step>
					<para>Press <guibutton>Properties</guibutton> to change any settings.</para>
				</step>
				<step>
					<para>If your ISP or network administrator has given you an <emphasis>IP address</emphasis>, set <guilabel>Configuration</guilabel> to <guilabel>Static IP address</guilabel>, then enter the address in the <guilabel>IP address</guilabel> field and click <guibutton>OK</guibutton>. Otherwise, set <guilabel>Configuration</guilabel> to <guilabel>Automatic configuration (DHCP)</guilabel> and click <guibutton>OK</guibutton>.</para>
				</step>
				<step>
					<para>Tick the box next to your connection to enable it.</para>
				</step>
			</procedure>
		</sect2>
			
	<sect2 id="wireless" status="review">
		<title>Wireless Cards</title>
		<para>Many wireless cards are automatically detected by Xubuntu during installation. To see if your card is supported, open &networking;. If your wireless card is listed, you can follow <xref linkend="internet-basic-procedure"/> to connect to the Internet. You need to enter a valid <guilabel>ESSID</guilabel> value. If in doubt, type <userinput>any</userinput>.  A complete listing of wireless cards which work with Xubuntu can be found online at the <ulink url="https://help.ubuntu.com/community/WifiDocs/WirelessCardsSupported">Ubuntu Wiki</ulink>. Please add your wireless card to the list if it works with Xubuntu.</para>
		
			<para>If your wireless network is protected by WEP encryption, ensure that you specify your network password when configuring your connection.</para>
			<procedure><step><para> Press &networking; and click the wireless connection you wish to use.</para> </step>
			<step><para>Press <guibutton>Properties</guibutton>, choose <guilabel>Password Type</guilabel> and enter your <guilabel>WEP</guilabel> password in <guilabel>Network Password</guilabel> form below. </para></step>
			<step><para>Press <guibutton>Ok</guibutton> and <guibutton>Close</guibutton> to apply changes.</para></step>
			
			</procedure>
		
		<sect3 id="wireless-unsupported" status="review">
			<title>Unsupported wireless cards</title>
			<para>Some cards may not work automatically with Xubuntu. If this is the case, please look at the <ulink url="https://wiki.ubuntu.com/WirelessTroubleshootingGuide">Wireless Troubleshooting Guide</ulink> on the Ubuntu Wiki which is an excellent resource for troubleshooting wireless cards.</para>
			<para>If your wireless card does not work with Xubuntu, you may have to do some research in order to activate it. A relatively reliable way of getting a wireless card to work is to use the <application>ndiswrapper</application> tool which allows Xubuntu to use the Microsoft Windows driver for the wireless card. To do this, follow the instructions below in <xref linkend="wireless-ndiswrapper"/>.
			</para>
			<para>All other information regarding wireless networking on Xubuntu is collected at <ulink url="https://help.ubuntu.com/community/WifiDocs">Wireless Networking Central</ulink> on the Ubuntu Wiki.</para>
		</sect3>
	
	<sect3 id="troubleshooting" status="review">
		<title>Troubleshooting</title>
		<para>Check for device recognition</para>
			<orderedlist>
				<listitem><para>Open a <application>Terminal</application> (&terminal;) and type the command: <code>sudo lshw -C network</code></para></listitem>
				<listitem><para>If there is a driver listed then see <xref linkend="troubleshooting-disabled"/>.</para></listitem>
				<listitem><para>Set up NDISWrapper (<xref linkend="wireless-ndiswrapper"/>).</para></listitem>
			</orderedlist>
		</sect3>
		<sect3 id="troubleshooting-disabled" status="writing">
			<title>Check device is on</title>
			<orderedlist>
				<listitem><para>Many wireless network devices can be turned on or off. Check to see if the device is turned on by opening a <application>Terminal</application> (&terminal;) and type the command: <code>sudo lshw -C network</code>.</para></listitem>
				<listitem><para>If it is turned on then see <xref linkend="troubleshooting-connection"/>.</para></listitem>
			</orderedlist>
		</sect3>
		<sect3 id="troubleshooting-connection" status="writing">
			<title>Check for a connection to the router</title>
			<orderedlist>
				<listitem><para>Open a <application>Terminal</application> (&terminal;) and type the command: <code>iwconfig</code>.</para></listitem>
				<listitem><para>If there is an entry that says <code>ESSID=""</code> then see Setting Up WPA (<xref linkend="security-wpa"/></para></listitem>
				<listitem><para>If the ESSID for our router is shown there may be a problem with ACPI support. Boot the kernel with the <code>pci=noacpi</code> option.</para></listitem>
			</orderedlist>
		</sect3>	
		<sect3 id="troubleshooting-ip" status="writing">
			<title>Check IP assignment</title>
			<orderedlist>
				<listitem><para>Open a <application>Terminal</application> (&terminal;) and type the command: <code>ifconfig</code>.</para></listitem>
				<listitem><para>If there is an IP address shown see <xref linkend="troubleshooting-dns"/>.</para></listitem>
				<listitem><para>From the <application>Terminal</application> enter the command: <code>dhclient if_name</code> where if_name is the connection listed earlier.</para></listitem>
				<listitem><para>If you receive a message that says <code>bound to xxx.xxx.xxx.xxx</code> then see <xref linkend="troubleshooting-dns"/></para></listitem>
				<listitem><para>If not then reboot the system.</para></listitem>
			</orderedlist>
		</sect3>
		<sect3 id="troubleshooting-dns" status="writing">
			<title>Check DNS</title>
			<orderedlist>
				<listitem><para>Open a <application>Terminal</application> (&terminal;) and type the command: <code>ping 82.211.81.158</code>.</para></listitem>
				<listitem><para>Now type the command: <code>ping www.ubuntu.com</code>.</para></listitem>
				<listitem><para>Type the command: <code>cat /etc/resolv.conf</code>. If there is no nameserver listed then contact your ISP and find out your primary and secondary domain name servers. Once you have this information see <xref linkend="wireless"/>.</para></listitem>
			</orderedlist>
		</sect3>
	
		
		<sect3 id="wireless-ndiswrapper" status="review">
			<title>Using Windows wireless drivers</title>
			<para>Even if your wireless network card does not have a native Linux driver, you may still be able to get it working with <application>ndiswrapper</application>. <application>Ndiswrapper</application> is a Linux module which allows Xubuntu to use Microsoft Windows driver for wireless cards (in most cases).</para>
			<note>
				<para>These instructions apply only to the x86 and AMD64 versions of Xubuntu, and not to Xubuntu for Power PC (PPC).</para>
			</note>
			<tip>
				<para>If you have access to the Internet, you can see if your wireless cards is in the list of cards supported by <application>ndiswrapper</application> <ulink url="http://ndiswrapper.sourceforge.net/mediawiki/index.php/List">on the ndiswrapper website</ulink>.</para>
			</tip>
			<para>To install ndiswrapper, install the package <application>ndiswrapper-utils</application> (see <ulink type="help" url="ghelp:add-applications">Add Applications</ulink>). This package is provided on the Xubuntu CD. If you have access to the Internet, you can also optionally install a graphical tool, <application>ndisgtk</application> from the <emphasis>Universe</emphasis> repository (see <ulink type="help" url="ghelp:add-applications#extra-repositories"/>).</para>
			<para>In order to set up <application>ndiswrapper</application>, it is necessary to obtain the Windows driver for your wireless card. Generally, the best way to do this is from the CD supplied with your wireless card. You should copy two files to the same place on your computer, one ending in .SYS and one ending in .INF. If you find any files which end in .BIN, also copy those. If you are not able to find the right files, and have alternative access to the Internet, you may be able to obtain help from the <ulink url="http://ndiswrapper.sourceforge.net/mediawiki/index.php/list">ndiswrapper website</ulink>.</para>
			<para>If you have installed the graphical tool <application>ndisgtk</application>, to set up ndiswrapper, simply select &ndisgtk; from the menu, and follow the instructions given.</para>
			<para>If you have not installed the graphical tool, use this procedure:</para>
			<procedure>
				<step>
					<para>Open &terminal; and type: <screen>sudo ndiswrapper -i ~/Desktop/drivername.inf</screen></para>
					<note>
						<para>The above command assumes that your .INF file is named <filename>drivername.inf</filename> and was copied to your Desktop. Replace these values if necessary.</para>
					</note> 
				</step>
				<step>
					<para>To check if it is working correctly, type: <screen>ndiswrapper -l</screen>If it is working correctly, you should see:
					<screen>Installed ndis drivers:
{name of driver}  driver present, hardware present</screen>
		</para>
				</step>
				<step>
					<para>For ndiswrapper to function, you need to load a module. To do this, type:<screen>sudo depmod -a
sudo modprobe ndiswrapper</screen></para>
				</step>
				<step>
					<para>To ensure that the module is loaded each time you boot the computer, type:<screen>sudo ndiswrapper -m</screen>
		</para>
				</step>
			</procedure>
			<para>You should now be able to connect to the Internet by following the instructions at <xref linkend="internet-basic-procedure"/>.</para>
		</sect3> 
		
		<sect3 id="security" status="writing">
		<title>Wireless network security</title>
		<para></para>
		<sect4 id="security-wpa" status="writing">
			<title>Configuring WPA support.</title>
			<para>WiFi Protected Access (WPA) is an based on WEP and provides stronger security.</para>
			<para>WPA is integrated with <application>Network Manager</application>. You must also have the <application>wpasupplicant</application> package installed.</para>
			<para>If you need to manually configure WPA support, see the <ulink url="https://help.ubuntu.com/community/WifiDocs/WPAHowTo?highlight=%28wpa%29">Wiki Entry</ulink>.</para>
		</sect4>
	</sect3>
		
        </sect2>
        
	<sect2 id="modems" status="complete">
		<title>ADSL Connections</title>
		<para>All PPPoE and router-style ADSL modems that use an Ethernet connection are supported by Xubuntu, and some USB ADSL modems are supported too.</para>
		<para>For a router-style ADSL modem, simply follow <xref linkend="internet-basic-procedure"/></para>
		<para>For information on setting up a PPPoE ADSL modem see <xref linkend="modems-adsl-pppoe"/>.</para>
		<para>For information on setting up a USB ADSL modem see <xref linkend="modems-adsl-usb"/>.</para>

		<sect3 id="modems-adsl-pppoe" status="review">
			<title>PPPoE Modems</title>
			<para>This section is about setting up an ADSL Internet connection using an ethernet PPPoE modem.</para>
			<para>You will need to have subscribed to an <emphasis>Internet Service Provider</emphasis>, and your Internet connection must be installed and functional. A "DSL" light on your modem usually shows that the line is synchronized.</para>
			<para>You will need your username and password for the account. You must also have an ethernet card connected to your PPPoE modem with the correct type of cable.</para>
			<para>Finally, you need the PPPoE package to be installed in order for the following command to work. This package is installed by default, but can be missing if the configuration has been changed. If the following command does not work, you will need to install this package, which can be found on the Xubuntu CD.</para>
			<para>To set up the modem:</para>
			<procedure>
				<step><para>Open &terminal;</para></step>
				<step><para>In the terminal type:<screen>sudo pppoeconf</screen></para></step>
				<step><para>A text-based menu program will guide you through the next steps, which are:
					<orderedlist numeration='arabic'>
						<listitem><para>Confirm that your Ethernet card is detected. </para></listitem>
						<listitem><para>Enter your username. </para></listitem>
						<listitem><para>Enter your password. </para></listitem>
						<listitem><para>If you already have a PPPoE Connection configured, you will be asked if it may be modified. </para></listitem>
						<listitem><para>Popular options: you are asked if you want the <quote>noauth</quote> and <quote>defaultroute</quote> options and to remove <quote>nodetach</quote> - choose <guibutton>Yes</guibutton>. </para></listitem>
						<listitem><para>Use peer DNS - choose <guibutton>Yes</guibutton>. </para></listitem>
						<listitem><para>Limited MSS problem - choose <guibutton>Yes</guibutton>. </para></listitem>
						<listitem><para>When you are asked if you want to connect at start up, you will probably want to say yes. </para></listitem>
						<listitem><para>Finally you are asked if you want to establish the connection immediately. </para></listitem>
					</orderedlist></para>
				</step>
				<step><para>Once you have finished these steps, your connection should be working. </para></step>
			</procedure>
			<para>To start your ADSL connection on demand, in a terminal type:</para>
				<screen>sudo pon dsl-provider</screen>
			<para>To stop your ADSL connection, in a terminal type:</para>
				<screen>sudo poff dsl-provider</screen>
		</sect3>

		<sect3 id="modems-adsl-usb" status="review">
			<title>USB ADSL Modems</title>				
			<para>Often parts of ADSL USB modem drivers are proprietary, closed source software, with a restrictive licence, and so the whole driver cannot be supplied with Xubuntu. To get a modem to work with these drivers, you will need to download files from Internet with a computer having a working connection, then transfer the downloaded files to you Xubuntu installation.</para>
			<warning>
				<para> USB is far from the ideal medium for network access. If you have a modem that can connect both via USB and ethernet, or an ethernet router, you should use the ethernet connection instead of the USB modem.</para>
			</warning>
			<para>Since any USB modem installation will require Internet access to download the necessary proprietary drivers, as well as extensive configuration which is beyond the scope of this guide, all we can do here is to list the USB Modem models known to work with Xubuntu with links to the relevant installation instructions on the Xubuntu community help site.</para>
			<para>The installation procedure of USB modems differs depending on the specific make and model of your modem. To identify model of your modem, note the name and number on the front. Occasionaly you may have to look for a label to discover the exact model. Consult the list below to see which driver your modem requires and note the link.</para>
			<para>When you go online to download the necessary drivers, you can access the relevant driver download links from the page with the installation instructions relevant to that model of USB modem.</para>

			<orderedlist numeration='arabic'>
				<listitem><para>Speedtouch modems:</para>
				<para><ulink url="https://help.ubuntu.com/community/UsbAdslModem/SpeedTouch">https://help.ubuntu.com/community/UsbAdslModem/SpeedTouch</ulink></para></listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>Modems using the Analog Devices Inc. eagle-usb I, II or III chipset (such as Sagem Fast 800, Comtrend ct 350 etc.):</para>
					<para><ulink url="https://help.ubuntu.com/community/UsbAdslModem/ueagle-atm">https://help.ubuntu.com/community/UsbAdslModem/ueagle-atm</ulink></para>
					<para><ulink url="https://help.ubuntu.com/community/UsbAdslModem/EagleUsb">https://help.ubuntu.com/community/UsbAdslModem/EagleUsb</ulink></para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>Connexant AccessRunner based modems:</para>
					<para><ulink url="https://help.ubuntu.com/community/UsbAdslModem/EciAdsl">https://help.ubuntu.com/community/UsbAdslModem/EciAdsl</ulink></para>
					<para><ulink url="https://help.ubuntu.com/community/UsbAdslModem/AccessRunner">https://help.ubuntu.com/community/UsbAdslModem/AccessRunner</ulink></para>
					<para><ulink url="https://help.ubuntu.com/community/UsbAdslModem/e-techV2">https://help.ubuntu.com/community/UsbAdslModem/e-techV2</ulink></para>
				</listitem>
			</orderedlist>
		</sect3>
		
	</sect2>

	<sect2 id="dialup" status="review">		
		<title>Dialup Modems</title>
		<para>Most dialup modems are not supported by Xubuntu, but drivers can be found that will enable the use of such modems. You need a working internet connection to proceed. First you need to identify what chipset your dialup modem is using. Open &terminal; and type:</para>
		
			<screen>
wget -c <ulink url="&scanmodem-url;">&scanmodem-url;</ulink> 
gunzip -c &scanmodem-gz; &gt; scanModem 
chmod +x scanModem
sudo ./scanModem 
</screen>
      <para>Read carefully instructions on the screen and follow them if necessary. Once the script obtains the relevant information, type:</para>
      <screen>mousepad Modem/ModemData.txt</screen>
		<para>Read this file, it should list what modem chipset you have. Once you are aware of the chipset you have, see <ulink url="&linmodem;">&linmodem;</ulink> and follow the directions for your modem. More infomation can be found at <ulink url="https://wiki.ubuntu.com/SettingUpModems">SettingUpModems</ulink> on the Ubuntu Wiki.</para>
		<para>Network Manager provides graphical tools to configure a modem connection.</para>
	<important>
		<para>You will need to know the following information:</para>
		<para>ISP Phone Number; Username; Password.</para>
	</important>
	<procedure>
		<step><para>Open Network Manager(&networking;)</para></step>
		<step><para>Select <guilabel>Modem Connection</guilabel></para></step>
		<step><para>Choose <guilabel>Properties</guilabel> and fill out the fields.</para></step>
		<step><para>Click OK</para></step>
	</procedure>
	</sect2>
	
	<sect2 id="network-troubleshooting" status="review">
		<title>Tools to help with network connection problems</title>
		<para>If you have a network connection which is not working properly, you can use a few tools to help diagnose what the problem is.</para>
		<para>Most of the tools in this section require use of the Terminal, which you can open by pressing &terminal;.</para>
		
		<sect3 id="network-troubleshooting-iwconfig" status="review">
			<title>Identify wireless connections</title>
			<para><application>iwconfig</application> allows you to change certain settings of your wireless hardware. However, it is also very useful for identifying wireless connections.</para>
			<para>To identify a wireless connection:</para>
			<orderedlist>
				<listitem><para>Press &terminal; to open a Terminal</para></listitem>
				<listitem><para>Type <userinput>iwconfig</userinput> in the Terminal and press <keycap>Return</keycap></para></listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>You should get output similar to the following:</para>
					<screen>lo        no wireless extensions.

eth0      no wireless extensions.

eth1      IEEE 802.11g  ESSID:"WLAN Name"  
        Mode:Managed  Frequency:2.432 GHz  Access Point: 00:12:CF:02:6F:EC   
        Bit Rate:54 Mb/s   Tx-Power=20 dBm   Sensitivity=8/0  
        Retry limit:7   RTS thr:off   Fragment thr:off
        Power Management:off
        Link Quality=75/100  Signal level=-54 dBm  Noise level=-89 dBm
        Rx invalid nwid:0  Rx invalid crypt:0  Rx invalid frag:0
        Tx excessive retries:0  Invalid misc:0   Missed beacon:1</screen>
				</listitem>
				<listitem><para>The column on the left gives the name of the connection, such as <quote>eth0</quote> or <quote>wlan0</quote></para></listitem>
				<listitem><para>If the column on the right says <quote>no wireless extensions</quote>, that connection has not been recognized as a wireless connection and is probably a wired network connection</para></listitem>
				<listitem><para>If the connection <emphasis>has</emphasis> been recognized as a wireless connection, details of the wireless connection will be shown in the column on the right</para>
				<itemizedlist>
					<listitem><para><emphasis>ESSID</emphasis> gives the name of the wireless network that you are connected to, if any</para></listitem>
					<listitem><para><emphasis>Link Quality</emphasis> gives a measure of the strength of the wireless signal</para></listitem>
				</itemizedlist>
				</listitem>
			</orderedlist>
		</sect3>
		
		<sect3 id="network-troubleshooting-iwlist" status="review">
			<title>Find information about wireless connections</title>
			<para><application>iwlist</application> is able to display information about your wireless connection.</para>
			<orderedlist>
				<listitem><para>Press &terminal; to open a Terminal</para></listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>Type the following commands in the Terminal and press <keycap>Return</keycap> to run them. Make sure that you replace <emphasis>eth1</emphasis> with the name of your wireless interface, if it is different.</para>
					<itemizedlist>
						<listitem><para><userinput>iwlist eth1 accesspoints</userinput> - Show a list of available wireless access points</para></listitem>
						<listitem><para><userinput>iwlist eth1 rate</userinput> - Show a list of all possible transmission rates for your wireless connection, including the current rate</para></listitem>
						<listitem><para><userinput>iwlist eth1 key</userinput> - Show information about wireless encryption</para></listitem>
					</itemizedlist>
				</listitem>
			</orderedlist>
		</sect3>
		
		<sect3 id="network-troubleshooting-ifconfig" status="iwconfig">
			<title>Get information about the current connection</title>
			<para><application>ifconfig</application> is intended to allow you to change the settings of your network connections, but can also be used to list information about the current connection.</para>
			<orderedlist>
				<listitem><para>Press &terminal; to open a Terminal</para></listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>Type <userinput>ifconfig eth1</userinput> in the Terminal and press <keycap>Return</keycap>, replacing <emphasis>eth1</emphasis> with the name of your network interface if it is different.</para>
					<itemizedlist>
						<listitem><para><emphasis>inet addr</emphasis> gives the current <emphasis>IP address</emphasis> of the connection</para></listitem>
						<listitem><para><emphasis>HWaddr</emphasis> gives the <emphasis>MAC address</emphasis> of your network device</para></listitem>
					</itemizedlist>
				</listitem>
			</orderedlist>
		</sect3>
		
		<sect3 id="network-troubleshooting-ping" status="review">
			<title>Check if a connection is working correctly</title>
			<para>A good way of checking if a connection is working correctly is to <emphasis>ping</emphasis> another computer on the network or the Internet.</para>
			<para>To check if you are connected to the Internet press &terminal; and type:</para>
			<screen>ping -c 8 xubuntu.com</screen>
			<para>Afer a while, <emphasis>xubuntu.com ping statistics</emphasis> should appear. Look at the <emphasis>% packet loss</emphasis>. </para>
					<itemizedlist>
						<listitem><para><emphasis>0% packet loss</emphasis> - Your computer should have a good connection to the Internet</para></listitem>
						<listitem><para><emphasis>More than 0% packet loss</emphasis> - Your computer probably has a poor connection to the Internet or a poor wireless signal</para></listitem>
						<listitem><para><emphasis>100% packet loss</emphasis> - Your connection is set improperly, or your computer is connected to an access point or router which is not connected to the Internet</para></listitem>
					</itemizedlist>			
			
			<para>If you get an error message which says <emphasis>ping: unknown host &apos;xubuntu.com&apos; </emphasis>, then your computer is probably not connected to the Internet or cannot reach a <emphasis>DNS server</emphasis>.</para>
		</sect3>
	</sect2>
</sect1>

<sect1 id="networking" status="review">
	<title>Configuring a network</title>
	<para>There are many ways of configuring and customizing the way your computer behaves on a network.</para>
	
	<sect2 id="networking-enable" status="review">
		<title>Connect to a network</title>
		<para>If you change the settings of your network connection or connect to a different network than usual, you may have to enable the connection yourself.</para>

		<sect3 id="networking-enable-nm" status="review">
			<title>Use Network Manager to connect to a network</title>
			<para>If your network connection is managed by <application>Network Manager</application> (as most are), the connection should be enabled automatically.</para>
			<para>If the connection is not enabled automatically:</para>
			<orderedlist>
				<listitem><para>Find the Network Manager icon in the notification area. It should look like a small signal strength indicator or a computer monitor and will probably be close to the clock</para></listitem>
				<listitem><para>Right-click the icon and ensure that <guilabel>Enable Networking</guilabel> is ticked</para></listitem>
				<listitem><para>If you have a wireless network connection, also ensure that <guilabel>Enable Wireless</guilabel> is ticked</para></listitem>
				<listitem><para>Left-click once on the Network Manager icon and then click on the network you want to connect to</para></listitem>
				<listitem><para>After a short period you should receive a message which says <guilabel>Connection Established</guilabel></para></listitem>
				<listitem><para>You should now be connected to a network.</para></listitem>
			</orderedlist>
			<para>If you are not connected to a network after following the procedure above:</para>
			<orderedlist>
				<listitem><para>Left-click the Network Manager icon again and press <guibutton>Manual configuration...</guibutton></para></listitem>
				<listitem><para>Select the <guilabel>Connections</guilabel> tab</para></listitem>
				<listitem><para>Tick the box next to your network connection to enable the connection</para></listitem>
				<listitem><para>The connection process make take a short while</para></listitem>
				<listitem><para>Press <guibutton>Close</guibutton></para></listitem>
			</orderedlist>
		</sect3>
		
		<sect3 id="networking-enable-ifup" status="writing">
			<title>Use the ifup command to connect to a network</title>
			<para><application>ifup</application> is a command-line tool for enabling network connections.</para>
			<para>To enable a network connection:</para>
			<orderedlist>
				<listitem><para>Press &terminal; to open a Terminal</para></listitem>
				<listitem><para>Type <userinput>sudo ifdown eth1</userinput> in the Terminal and press <keycap>Return</keycap>, replacing <emphasis>eth1</emphasis> with the name of your network interface if it is different</para></listitem>
				<listitem><para>Enter your password if prompted</para></listitem>
				<listitem><para>Type <userinput>sudo ifup eth1</userinput> in the Terminal and press <keycap>Return</keycap>, again replacing <emphasis>eth1</emphasis> with the name of your network interface</para></listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>If you have connected successfully, you should see a message similar to the following (the numbers may be different):</para>
					<screen>DHCPACK from 192.168.2.1
	bound to 192.168.2.4 -- renewal in 536349522 seconds.</screen>
				</listitem>
			</orderedlist>
		</sect3>
	</sect2>
		
	<sect2 id="networking-disable" status="review">
		<title>Disable a network connection</title>
		<para>Sometimes you may want to disable a network connection. There are several different ways of achieving this.</para>
		
		<sect3 id="networking-disable-nm" status="review">
			<title>Disconnecting using Network Manager</title>
			<para>It is likely that <application>Network Manager</application> is running your network connections. If so, you must disconnect from the network by disabling your network connection in Network Manager:</para>
			<orderedlist>
				<listitem><para>Find the Network Manager icon in the notification area. It should look like a small signal strength indicator or a computer monitor and will probably be close to the clock</para></listitem>
				<listitem><para>Right-click the icon and untick <guilabel>Enable Networking</guilabel></para></listitem>
				<listitem><para>You should be disconnected from the network</para></listitem>
			</orderedlist>
		</sect3>
		
		<sect3 id="networking-disable-networksettings" status="review">
			<title>Disconnecting using Network Settings</title>
			<para>If Network Manager is not running, use the <application>Network Settings</application> tool to disconnect your network connection:</para>
			<orderedlist>
				<listitem><para>Press &networking;</para></listitem>
				<listitem><para>Select the <guilabel>Connections</guilabel> tab</para></listitem>
				<listitem><para>Untick your network connection to disconnect it</para></listitem>
				<listitem><para>Press <guibutton>Close</guibutton></para></listitem>
			</orderedlist>
		</sect3>
		
		<sect3 id="networking-disable-ifdown" status="review">
			<title>Disconnecting using the ifdown command</title>
			<para><application>ifdown</application> is a command-line tool for disabling network connections.</para>
			<para>To disable a network connection using ifdown:</para>
			<orderedlist>
				<listitem><para>Press &terminal; to open a Terminal</para></listitem>
				<listitem><para>Type <userinput>sudo ifdown eth1</userinput> in the Terminal and press <keycap>Return</keycap>, replacing <emphasis>eth1</emphasis> with the name of your network interface if it is different</para></listitem>
				<listitem><para>Enter your password if prompted</para></listitem>
				<listitem><para>Your network connection should be disconnected</para></listitem>
			</orderedlist>
		</sect3>
	</sect2>
	
	
        <sect2 id="networking-changecompname" status="review">
        	<title>Change the Computer Name</title>
        	<para>When connected to a network, your computer can be referred to by its <emphasis>host name</emphasis>. It is possible to change the host name of your computer.</para>
                <procedure>
                <step>
                        <para>Open &networking;.</para>
                </step>
                <step>
                        <para>Click <guilabel>General</guilabel>, and enter the name of the computer in the <guilabel>Host name</guilabel> field.</para>
                </step>
                </procedure>
                <para>Restart the computer for the change to take effect.</para>
        </sect2>
		
	<sect2 id="networking-shares" status="review">
        	<title>Share files and folders with other computers</title>
        	<para>You can share files and folders with other people on your network.</para>
                <procedure>
	                <step>
	                <para>Press &shared-folders;</para>
	                </step>
	                <step>
	                        <para>You may receive a message which says <guilabel>Sharing services are not installed</guilabel>. If this is the case, ensure that the two checkboxes in the message box are checked and press <guibutton>Install services</guibutton>. Sharing service support will then be downloaded and installed; this may take a while.</para>
	                </step>
	                <step>
	                <para>Select the <guilabel>Shared Folders</guilabel> tab and press <guibutton>Add</guibutton></para>
	                </step>
	                <step>
	                <para>Select the location of the folder you wish to share by changing the <guilabel>Path</guilabel> option</para>
	                </step>
	                <step>
	                <para>Choose <guilabel>Windows networks (SMB)</guilabel> from the <guilabel>Share through</guilabel> option</para>
	                </step>
	                <step>
	                <para>Enter a name and comment for the shared folder</para>
	                </step>
	                <step>
	                <para>If you would like people accessing the shared folder to be able to add, change and remove files in the folder, uncheck <guilabel>Read only</guilabel>. If you leave <guilabel>Read only</guilabel> checked, people will only be able to view files in the folder</para>
	                </step>
	                <step>
	                        <para>Press <guibutton>OK</guibutton> to make the shared folder available. Other people on the same network (LAN) as you should now be able to access the folder</para>
	                </step>
                </procedure>
                <para>See the <ulink type='help' url='ghelp:shares-admin'>Shared Folders Administration Tool manual</ulink> for more information on managing network shares.</para> </sect2>		
                
                <sect2 id="networking-shares-windows" status="review">
                	<title>Accessing shared folders on Microsoft Windows</title>
                	<para>If you would like to access a shared folder hosted on an Xubuntu computer by using computers running Windows, you may have to perform some additional steps:</para>
                	<procedure>
                		<step>
                			<para>Press &terminal; to open a Terminal</para>
                		</step>
                		<step>
                			<para>Type <userinput>sudo smbpasswd -a username</userinput>, replacing <quote>username</quote> with your own username. Press <keycap>Return</keycap> to run the command.</para>
                			<note>
                				<para>You can find out what your username is by typing <userinput>whoami</userinput> into the Terminal and then pressing <keycap>Return</keycap></para>
                			</note>
                		</step>
                		<step>
                			<para>Enter your password when prompted with <quote>[sudo] password for username:</quote> and press <keycap>Return</keycap> again.</para>
                		</step>
                		<step>
                			<para>When prompted with <quote>New SMB password:</quote>, enter the password that you would like to use to access the shared folder and then press <keycap>Return</keycap>. You can leave the password blank if you like, which will allow anyone to access the shared folder.</para>
                		</step>
                		<step>
                			<para>When prompted with <quote>Retype new SMB password:</quote>, enter the password that you just entered and then press <keycap>Return</keycap></para>
                		</step>
                		<step>
                			<para>You should now be able to connect to the shared folders on the Xubuntu computer</para>
                		</step>
                	</procedure>
        	</sect2>
        	
        	<sect2 id="networking-shares-troubleshooting" status="review">
        		<title>Problems connecting to shared folders in Microsoft Windows</title>
                	<para>If you are unable to connect to a shared folder using Microsoft Windows, try using the <emphasis>IP address</emphasis> of the Xubuntu computer rather than its <emphasis>host name</emphasis> to access the share:</para>
                	<para></para>
                	<procedure>
                		<step>
                			<para>Press &network-tools; and select the <guilabel>Devices</guilabel> tab</para>
                		</step>
                		<step>
                			<para>Select the name of your network connection from the <guilabel>Network device</guilabel> option list (for example, <quote>eth0</quote>). If you have several network connections, you may have to try this several times.</para>
                		</step>
                		<step>
                			<para>Make a note of the number in the <guilabel>IP address</guilabel> column. It should consist of four numbers separated by dots (for example, <quote>192.168.2.10</quote>)</para>
                		</step>
                		<step>
                			<para>On the Microsoft Windows computer, select <menuchoice><guimenuitem>Start</guimenuitem><guimenuitem>Run</guimenuitem></menuchoice> and type <userinput>\\ipaddress</userinput> in the text box, replacing <quote>ipaddress</quote> with the IP address of the Xubuntu computer</para>
                		</step>
                		<step>
                			<para>Press <guibutton>OK</guibutton> to connect to the shared folder</para>
                		</step>
                	</procedure>
                	
                	<para>If you are still unable to access the shared folder, check that the folder sharing service is running on the Xubuntu computer:</para>
                	<procedure>
                		<step>
                			<para>Press &services;</para>
                		</step>
                		<step>
                			<para>Find the <guilabel>Folder sharing service (samba)</guilabel> and ensure that the checkbox next to it is checked</para>
                		</step>
                		<step>
                			<para>Press <guibutton>Close</guibutton></para>
                		</step>
                	</procedure>
                	<para>More information can be found on the Ubuntu <ulink url='https://help.ubuntu.com/community/SettingUpSamba'>community help pages</ulink>.</para>
                </sect2>

		
	<sect2 id="networking-firestarter" status="review">
		<title>Install a firewall</title>
		<para>A firewall protects a computer system from unauthorized access. It is not normally necessary to install a firewall on an Xubuntu system, because access to the system is closed by default. However, if you run any services that let other computers access yours (for example, the Apache web server), it is advisable to install a firewall. <application>Firestarter</application> is a program that lets you control a firewall through a graphical interface.
		</para>
		<procedure>
			<step>
				<para>Install the <application>Firestarter</application> package from the <quote>Universe</quote> repository (see <ulink type="help" url="ghelp:add-applications">Add Applications</ulink>).
				</para>
			</step>
			<step>
				<para>After it is installed, run &firestarter-firewall-tool; to configure your firewall. The firewall will now start in the background when your computer starts.
				</para>
			</step>
		</procedure>
	</sect2>
			
	<sect2 id="networking-networkmonitor" status="review">
		<title>Monitor network traffic</title>
		<para>Etherape displays network activity among different hosts using circles of varying size.</para>
		<procedure>
			<step>
				<para>Install the <application>etherape</application> package from the <quote>Universe</quote> repository (see <ulink type="help" url="ghelp:add-applications">Add Applications</ulink>).</para>
			</step>
			<step>
				<para>Press &etherape;.</para>
			</step>
		</procedure>
	</sect2>
		
	<sect2 id="networking-trafficanalyzer" status="review">
		<title>Analyze network traffic</title>
		<para>Wireshark is a network traffic analyzer/sniffer that captures packets off the network in real time and displays their contents.</para>
		<procedure>
			<step>
				<para>Install the <application>wireshark</application> package from the <quote>Universe</quote> repository (see <ulink type="help" url="ghelp:add-applications">Add Applications</ulink>).</para>
			</step>
			<step>
				<para>Press &wireshark;</para>
			</step>
		</procedure>
	</sect2>
</sect1>

<sect1 id="web-browsing" status="review">
	<title>Web browsing with Firefox</title>
	<para>The powerful and secure <application>Mozilla Firefox</application> web browser is included in Xubuntu. <application>Firefox</application> features tabbed browsing, pop-up blocking, built-in search, and live bookmarks. Also supported are popular plug-ins such as Java, Flash, and RealPlayer.</para>
	<para><application>Firefox</application> can be launched by clicking &firefox;.</para>
	
	<sect2 id="web-browsing-altbrowsers" status="review">
		<title>Alternative web browsers</title>
		<para>As well as the default <application>Firefox Web Browser</application>, Xubuntu also provides a large selection of alternative browsers. A list of some of these is given below:</para>
		<itemizedlist>
			<listitem><para><application>Epiphany Web Browser</application></para></listitem>
			<listitem><para><application>Konqueror</application></para></listitem>
			<listitem><para><application>Mozilla Web Browser</application></para></listitem>
			<listitem><para><application>Opera</application></para></listitem>
		</itemizedlist>
		<para>See <ulink type="help" url="ghelp:add-applications">Add Applications</ulink> for help on installing new software.</para>
	</sect2>
		
<sect2 id="web-plugins" status="review">
	<title>Get plugins for your web browser</title>
	<para>A plugin is a small program which extends the capabilities of another program. In the case of web browsers, plugins typically allow the browser to play different types of multimedia or to run small, web-based programs.</para>
	<para>To view a list of currently-installed plugins in the <application>Firefox Web Browser</application>, type <quote>about:plugins</quote> into the address bar and press <keycap>Return</keycap>.</para>
	
	<sect3 id="web-plugins-commonrestricted" status="review">
		<title>Quickly install common plugins</title>
		<para>It is possible to install a whole set of commonly-used restricted plugins at once, by installing the <application>Ubuntu restricted extras</application> package.</para>
		<para><emphasis>Restricted plugins</emphasis> are those which cannot be distributed with Xubuntu because of legal issues surrounding their use in some countries. Check that you are allowed to use this software before installing it. See the <ulink url='http://www.ubuntu.com/ubuntu/licensing'>Ubuntu website</ulink> for more information on restricted software.</para>
		<procedure>
			<step>
				<para>Install the <application>Ubuntu restricted extras</application> package from the <quote>Multiverse</quote> repository (see <ulink type="help" url="ghelp:add-applications">Add Applications</ulink>).</para>
			</step>
			<step>
				<para>Restart the <application>Firefox Web Browser</application> to make the included browser plugins available.</para>
			</step>
		</procedure>
		<para>As well as plugins and multimedia codecs, <application>Java</application> and a set of Windows fonts will be installed.</para>
		<para>The following plugins and codecs are installed by the <application>Ubuntu restricted extras</application> package:</para>
		<itemizedlist>
			<listitem><para><application>flashplugin-nonfree</application></para></listitem>
			<listitem><para><application>gstreamer0.10-plugins-ugly</application></para></listitem>
			<listitem><para><application>gstreamer0.10-plugins-ugly-multiverse</application></para></listitem>
			<listitem><para><application>msttcorefonts</application></para></listitem>
			<listitem><para><application>sun-java5-jre</application></para></listitem>
			<listitem><para><application>sun-java5-plugin</application></para></listitem>
		</itemizedlist>
	</sect3>
	
	<sect3 id="web-plugins-audiovideo" status="review">
		<title>Audio and video plugins</title>
		<para>Many different multimedia formats are used on the Internet, and so you may find that you are unable to play some audio and video files without first installing an appropriate plugin.</para>
		<para>See the following articles for information on installing and using multimedia plugins with the <application>Firefox Web Browser</application>:</para>
		<itemizedlist>
			<listitem><para><ulink type="help" url='ghelp:musicvideophotos#onlinemedia-plugins'>Watch videos in a web browser</ulink></para></listitem>
			<listitem><para><ulink type="help" url="ghelp:musicvideophotos#video">Play movies and videos</ulink></para></listitem>
			<listitem><para><ulink url='https://help.ubuntu.com/community/FirefoxPlugins'>Firefox Plugins</ulink> (Ubuntu Community support pages)</para></listitem>
			<listitem><para><ulink type="help" url='ghelp:internet#web-plugins-flash'>Flash multimedia plugin</ulink></para></listitem>
			<listitem><para><ulink type="help" url="ghelp:musicvideophotos#onlinemedia-audiostreams">Listen to online audio streams</ulink> (instructions for installing <application>RealPlayer</application>)</para></listitem>
			<listitem><para><ulink type="help" url="ghelp:musicvideophotos#codecs">Multimedia codecs</ulink></para></listitem>
		</itemizedlist>
	</sect3>
	
	<sect3 id="web-plugins-flash" status="review">
		<title>Flash multimedia plugin</title>
		<para>Flash is a proprietary plugin which allows you to watch videos and animations on the Internet.</para>
		<para>To view Flash graphics from the <application>Firefox Web Browser</application>:</para>
		<procedure>
			<step>
				<para>Install the <application>flashplugin-nonfree</application> package from the <quote>Multiverse</quote> repository (see <ulink type="help" url="ghelp:add-applications">Add Applications</ulink>).</para>
			</step>
			<step>
				<para>Restart <application>Firefox</application> to make the plugin available.</para>
			</step>
		</procedure>
		<para>Installing the package as described above will download and install the plugin. You need an Internet connection for this to work. If, after installing the application, you need to download and install the plugin at a later time, enter the following command in a terminal:<screen>sudo dpkg-reconfigure flashplugin-nonfree</screen></para>
	</sect3>
	
	<sect3 id="web-plugins-java" status="review">
		<title>Java browser plugin</title>
		<para>Some websites use small <application>Java</application> programs, which require a Java plugin to be installed in order to run.</para>
		<para>These instructions are for <emphasis>i386</emphasis> and <emphasis>AMD64</emphasis> computers only. The plugin is not currently available for other computers.</para>
		<itemizedlist>
			<listitem>
			<para>If you are using an <emphasis>i386</emphasis> computer install the <application>sun-java5-plugin</application> package from the <quote>Multiverse</quote> repository.</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
			<para>If you are using an <emphasis>AMD64</emphasis> computer install the <application>j2re1.4-mozilla.plugin</application> package from the <quote>Multiverse</quote> repository.</para>
			</listitem>
		</itemizedlist>
		<para>See <ulink type="help" url="ghelp:add-applications">Add Applications</ulink> for help on installing new software.</para>
		<para>For a more complete Java installation, see <ulink type="help" url="ghelp:programming#java">Java</ulink>.</para>
	</sect3>
	
</sect2>

<sect2 id="internet-firefox-customizing" status="review">
	<title>Customizing Firefox</title>

<para>The <application>Firefox Web Browser</application> is highly customizable - you can change the way it looks and works to suit your needs, with very little effort.</para>

<sect3 id="internet-firefox-customizing-toolbar" status="review">
	<title>Adding and removing toolbar buttons</title>

	<para>By default, Firefox has a <emphasis>toolbar</emphasis> consisting of five large buttons at the top of its screen, which you can use to navigate the web. These are in a particularly convenient location because you will often find yourself using these buttons, so it makes sense to put them where they are easy-to-reach. But what if there are certain other actions which you often perform which you'd like to make just as easy to reach?</para>

	<para><emphasis role='strong'>To add new buttons to the toolbar:</emphasis></para>
	<orderedlist>
		<listitem><para>Right-click any of the (active) buttons on the toolbar and select <guibutton>Customize...</guibutton> to open the <guilabel>Customize Toolbar</guilabel> window</para></listitem>
		<listitem><para>Look for a button which you would like to add to the toolbar. The <guibutton>New Tab</guibutton> button is particularly useful</para></listitem>
		<listitem><para>Drag the button onto the desired location on the toolbar</para></listitem>
		<listitem><para>Press <guibutton>Done</guibutton></para></listitem>
	</orderedlist>

	<para>You can remove items from the toolbar in a similar way. Instead of dragging a button from the <guilabel>Customize Toolbar</guilabel> window to the toolbar, drag it from the toolbar into the <guilabel>Customize Toolbar</guilabel> window.</para>

	<para>If you would like to change the way that the toolbar buttons are displayed, select a different option from the drop-down list labelled <guilabel>Show</guilabel>.</para>
</sect3>

<sect3 id="internet-firefox-customizing-theme" status="review">
	<title>Changing the theme</title>

	<para>Firefox looks like any other application on your computer. However, you can completely change the way it looks by changing the theme. There are many different themes available - most of these have been made by members of the Firefox community and are available for free.</para>
	<note>
		<para>Only install themes from websites you trust. It is best to only use the official website, <ulink url='http://addons.mozilla.org'>addons.mozilla.org</ulink></para>
	</note>
	<caution>
		<para>Some themes may be poorly designed, and can occasionally cause Firefox to experience problems. If this happens, just remove the theme.</para>
	</caution>

	<sect4 id="internet-firefox-customizing-theme-apply" status="review">
		<title>To apply a new theme</title>
		<orderedlist>
			<listitem><para>Press <menuchoice><guimenuitem>Tools</guimenuitem><guimenuitem>Add-ons</guimenuitem></menuchoice> and select the <guilabel>Themes</guilabel> tab</para></listitem>
			<listitem><para>Press <guibutton>Get Themes</guibutton>. You will be taken to a website with a large collection of themes to choose from</para></listitem>
			<listitem><para>Choose a theme you like and press the <guibutton>Install Now</guibutton> button on that theme's page</para></listitem>
			<listitem><para>A window will appear, asking if you would like to install the theme. Press <guibutton>Install Now</guibutton></para></listitem>
			<listitem><para>Go back to the <guilabel>Add-ons</guilabel> window and wait for the theme to be downloaded. The progress of the download is shown in the <guilabel>Installation</guilabel> tab</para></listitem>
			<listitem><para>Once the download and installation has finished, go to the <guilabel>Themes</guilabel> tab</para></listitem>
			<listitem><para>Select the newly-installed theme and press <guibutton>Use Theme</guibutton></para></listitem>
			<listitem><para>Go back to the <guilabel>Installation</guilabel> tab and press <guibutton>Restart Firefox</guibutton> to apply the new theme</para></listitem>
		</orderedlist>
	</sect4>

	<sect4 id="internet-firefox-customizing-theme-apply-change" status="review">
		<title>To switch to another theme, which is already installed</title>
		<orderedlist>
			<listitem><para>Press <menuchoice><guimenuitem>Tools</guimenuitem><guimenuitem>Add-ons</guimenuitem></menuchoice> and select the <guilabel>Themes</guilabel> tab</para></listitem>
			<listitem><para>Select the theme you want to use and press <guibutton>Use Theme</guibutton></para></listitem>
			<listitem><para>Restart Firefox to apply the new theme</para></listitem>
		</orderedlist>
	</sect4>

	<sect4 id="internet-firefox-customizing-theme-remove" status="review">
		<title>To remove a theme</title>
		<orderedlist>
			<listitem><para>Press <menuchoice><guimenuitem>Tools</guimenuitem><guimenuitem>Add-ons</guimenuitem></menuchoice> and select the <guilabel>Themes</guilabel> tab</para></listitem>
			<listitem><para>Select the theme you want to remove and press <guibutton>Uninstall</guibutton></para></listitem>
			<listitem><para>You will be asked for confirmation. Press <guibutton>Uninstall</guibutton></para></listitem>
			<listitem><para>The theme will be uninstalled when you close Firefox</para></listitem>
		</orderedlist>
	</sect4>
</sect3>

<sect3 id="internet-firefox-customizing-fontsize" status="review">
	<title>Changing the default font size</title>

	<para>If you find that the size of text in Firefox is too small to read comfortably, you can increase the default font size.</para>

	<orderedlist>
		<listitem><para>Press <menuchoice><guimenuitem>Edit</guimenuitem><guimenuitem>Preferences</guimenuitem></menuchoice> and select the <guilabel>Content</guilabel> tab</para></listitem>
		<listitem><para>Under <guilabel>Fonts &amp; Colors</guilabel>, change the <guilabel>Size</guilabel> to a larger number (around 20 tends to be quite comfortable to read)</para></listitem>
		<listitem><para>Text on web pages should immediately look larger. Press <guibutton>Close</guibutton></para></listitem>
	</orderedlist>

	<para>To temporarily increase the size of text on a web page, press <menuchoice><guimenuitem>View</guimenuitem><guimenuitem>Text Size</guimenuitem><guimenuitem>Increase</guimenuitem></menuchoice>. Alternatively, hold down the <keycap>Ctrl</keycap> key and scroll down with your mouse's scroll wheel, or press <keycombo><keycap>Ctrl</keycap><keycap>+</keycap></keycombo>.</para>

	<para>To return the text to its normal size, press <menuchoice><guimenuitem>View</guimenuitem><guimenuitem>Text Size</guimenuitem><guimenuitem>Normal</guimenuitem></menuchoice>.</para>
</sect3>

<sect3 id="internet-firefox-customizing-homepage" status="review">
	<title>Changing the home page</title>
	<para>When you open Firefox, the first web page which is displayed is your <emphasis>home page</emphasis>. This is usually a web page which you want to view every time you use the web, such as a news site, search engine or online email account.</para>
	<para>To change your home page:</para>
	<orderedlist>
		<listitem><para>Open the page which you want to use as your home page</para></listitem>
		<listitem><para>Press <menuchoice><guimenuitem>Edit</guimenuitem><guimenuitem>Preferences</guimenuitem></menuchoice> and select the <guilabel>Main</guilabel> tab</para></listitem>
		<listitem><para>Under <guilabel>Startup</guilabel>, press <guibutton>Use Current Page</guibutton> and then press <guibutton>Close</guibutton></para></listitem>
	</orderedlist>
	<para>When you start Firefox or press the <guibutton>Home</guibutton> button, you will be taken to your new home page.</para>
	<para>If you want to have more than one home page, open all of the pages that you would like to use as home pages in separate tabs. Then, follow the procedure above.</para>
</sect3>

<sect3 id="internet-firefox-extending" status="review">
	<title>Extending Firefox</title>
	
	<para>You can add all sorts of useful extras to Firefox by installing <emphasis>Extensions</emphasis>. These provide features such as advert-blocking, news readers and a download manager. There are literally thousands of extensions to choose from.</para>

	<sect4 id="internet-firefox-extending-install" status="review">
		<title>To install a new extension</title>
		<orderedlist>
			<listitem><para>Press <menuchoice><guimenuitem>Tools</guimenuitem><guimenuitem>Add-ons</guimenuitem></menuchoice> and select the <guilabel>Extensions</guilabel> tab</para></listitem>
			<listitem><para>Press <guibutton>Get Extensions</guibutton>. A web page will open with a collection of extensions that you can install</para></listitem>
			<listitem><para>Find an extension you like and press the <guibutton>Install Now</guibutton> button on the page for that extension</para></listitem>
			<listitem><para>You will be asked to confirm that you want to install the extension. Press <guibutton>Install Now</guibutton></para></listitem>
			<listitem><para>Go back to the <guilabel>Add-ons</guilabel> window and select the <guilabel>Installation</guilabel> tab to watch the progress of the installation</para></listitem>
			<listitem><para>Once installation is complete, press <guibutton>Restart Firefox</guibutton> to enable the extension</para></listitem>
		</orderedlist>
	</sect4>
			
	<sect4 id="internet-firefox-extending-settings" status="review">
		<title>To change the settings of an extension</title>
		<para>Many extensions have a number of settings that you can change.</para>
		<orderedlist>
			<listitem><para>Press <menuchoice><guimenuitem>Tools</guimenuitem><guimenuitem>Add-ons</guimenuitem></menuchoice> and select the <guilabel>Extensions</guilabel> tab</para></listitem>
			<listitem><para>Select the extension that you want to change the settings of</para></listitem>
			<listitem><para>Press <guibutton>Preferences</guibutton> and change settings as appropriate</para></listitem>
		</orderedlist>

		<para>Some extensions may not have any settings for you to change, and so will not have a <guibutton>Preferences</guibutton> button.</para>
	</sect4>

	<sect4 id="internet-firefox-extending-remove" status="review">
		<title>To remove an extension</title>
		<orderedlist>
			<listitem><para>Press <menuchoice><guimenuitem>Tools</guimenuitem><guimenuitem>Add-ons</guimenuitem></menuchoice> and select the <guilabel>Extensions</guilabel> tab</para></listitem>
			<listitem><para>Select the extension you want to remove and press <guibutton>Uninstall</guibutton></para></listitem>
			<listitem><para>You will be asked to confirm that you want to uninstall the extension. Press <guibutton>Uninstall</guibutton></para></listitem>
			<listitem><para>Restart Firefox to fully remove the extension</para></listitem>
		</orderedlist>
	</sect4>

</sect3>
</sect2>

<sect2 id="internet-firefox-privacy" status="review">
	<title>Handling private information in Firefox</title>

	<para>Protecting your privacy online is important, and Firefox offers many ways for you to protect or remove private information such as your passwords, which websites you have been looking at and so on.</para>

<sect3 id="internet-firefox-privacy-history" status="review">
	<title>Clearing your browsing history and other data</title>

	<para>When you browse the web, a list of the pages that you have recently visited is stored by Firefox. This is called the <emphasis>browsing history</emphasis>, and is useful if you want to go back to a site that you recently visited, but can't remember the web address.</para>

	<para>However, if someone else has access to your user account, they can look at the browsing history and see which websites you have been visiting.</para>

	<para>As well as the browsing history, Firefox stores other information about how you use the web. This information is intended to make browsing websites faster and more convenient for you, but you may wish to remove it every so often to help protect your privacy.</para>

	<sect4 id="internet-firefox-privacy-history-clear" status="review">
		<title>To clear the browsing history list and other information</title>
		<orderedlist>
			<listitem><para>Press <menuchoice><guimenuitem>Tools</guimenuitem><guimenuitem>Clear Private Data...</guimenuitem></menuchoice></para></listitem>
			<listitem><para>Tick the items that you want to clear and press <guibutton>Clear Private Data Now</guibutton></para></listitem>
			<listitem><para>The items you selected will be cleared</para></listitem>
		</orderedlist>
	</sect4>
</sect3>
</sect2>

<sect2 id="internet-firefox-searching" status="review">
	<title>Searching for things on the web</title>

	<para>The easiest way to find something on the Internet is to search for it using a search engine such as Google. Firefox has a handy search box feature which makes searching for information quick and easy.</para>
	<para>The search box can be found in the top right of the Firefox window.</para>
	<para>To search for something</para>
	<orderedlist>
		<listitem><para>Click the search box and type what you want to search for, e.g. 'weather report'</para></listitem>
		<listitem><para>Press the <keycap>Return</keycap> key. The search will be carried out in the current tab</para></listitem>
	</orderedlist>
	<para>The default search engine in Firefox is Google. However, there are several other types of search that you may find useful, including Wikipedia (which searches an online encyclopedia) and Last.fm (which searches for music-related information).</para>
	<para>To change which search engine is being used:</para>
	<orderedlist>
		<listitem><para>Press the button immediately to the left of the search box (it has a small icon and a down-arrow)</para></listitem>
		<listitem><para>Select the search engine that you want to use from the list</para></listitem>
		<listitem><para>Click the search box and type what you want to search for</para></listitem>
		<listitem><para>Press the <keycap>Return</keycap> key to carry out the search</para></listitem>
	</orderedlist>
</sect2>

<sect2 id="internet-firefox-bookmarking" status="review">
	<title>Bookmarking pages for viewing later</title>
	<para>If you visit a particular website often, or just want to remember a page for viewing later, why not create a bookmark for that page?</para>
	<para>To create a bookmark:</para>
	<orderedlist>
		<listitem><para>Visit the page you want to bookmark</para></listitem>
		<listitem><para>Press <menuchoice><guimenuitem>Bookmarks</guimenuitem><guimenuitem>Bookmark This Page...</guimenuitem></menuchoice></para></listitem>
		<listitem><para>If you like, change the name of the bookmark</para></listitem>
		<listitem><para>Under <guilabel>Create in</guilabel>, choose which bookmarks folder you would like to put the bookmark in</para></listitem>
		<listitem><para>Press <guibutton>Add</guibutton> to create the bookmark</para></listitem>
	</orderedlist>

	<para>Bookmarks can be organized into different folders and locations. All of you bookmarks can be accessed by using the <guilabel>Bookmarks</guilabel> menu or by pressing <menuchoice><guimenuitem>View</guimenuitem><guimenuitem>Sidebar</guimenuitem><guimenuitem>Bookmarks</guimenuitem></menuchoice>.</para>
	<para>Add sites which you use particularly often to the <guilabel>Bookmarks Toolbar Folder</guilabel>. The <guilabel>Bookmarks Toolbar</guilabel> is shown immediately below the <guilabel>Address Bar</guilabel>, so it is very easy to access.</para>
	<para>For a quick way of adding a bookmark to the Bookmarks Toolbar, go to the Address Bar and drag the small icon immediately to the left of the web address onto the toolbar.</para>
	<para>If you have a very large collection of bookmarks, press <menuchoice><guimenuitem>Bookmarks</guimenuitem><guimenuitem>Organize Bookmarks...</guimenuitem></menuchoice> for a tool to help you organize them.</para>
</sect2>
</sect1>

<sect1 id="email" status="working">
	<title>Send and receive emails</title>
	<para>Email is one of the most popular ways to communicate over the Internet. Xubuntu includes all of the tools that you need to send, receive and organize email messages.</para>
	
	<sect2 id="email-mozilla-thunderbird" status="review">
		<title>Mozilla Thunderbird</title>
		<para><application>Mozilla Thunderbird</application> is an application for sending, receiving and managing email messages. To install it, install the <application>mozilla-thunderbird</application> package (see <ulink type="help" url="ghelp:add-applications">Add Applications</ulink>).</para>
		<para>To start <application>Thunderbird</application>, choose &thunderbird;.</para>
		<para>The first time you run Mozilla Thunderbird you will be presented with a wizard which will guide you through the configuration process of your email accounts.</para>
	</sect2>
	
</sect1>


<sect1 id="internet-instant-messaging" status="review">
	<title>Instant Messaging</title>
	<para>Instant messaging (IM) is a way of communicating with friends and family by sending messages to one another over the Internet. Instant messaging happens in real-time, and there is no delay between you typing a message and the other person receiving it.</para>
	
	<sect2 id="internet-instant-messaging-pidgin" status="review">
		<title>Pidgin Internet Messenger</title>
		<para><application>Pidgin</application> is an instant messenger client in Xubuntu, and was formerly known as <application>Gaim</application>. With Pidgin you can talk to people who use AIM/ICQ, Gadu-Gadu, GroupWise, IRC, Jabber, MSN, Napster and Yahoo, and list all your buddies in a single window.</para>
		<para>To start <application>Pidgin</application>, choose &pidgin;.</para>
	</sect2>
	
	<sect2 id="internet-instant-messaging-irc" status="review">
		<title>IRC instant messaging</title>
		<para>For users of IRC instant messaging services, an alternative to <application>Pidgin</application> is <application>XChat</application>. Its features include advanced scripting support (perl and python) and a clean, easy to use interface.</para>
		<procedure>
			<step>
				<para>Install the <application>xchat</application> package from the <quote>Universe</quote> repository (see <ulink type="help" url="ghelp:add-applications">Add Applications</ulink>).</para>
			</step>
			<step>
				<para>To start <application>XChat</application>, choose &xchat;.</para>
			</step>
		</procedure>
	</sect2>
	
	<sect2 id="internet-instant-messaging-irchelp" status="review">
		<title>Getting help using IRC instant messaging</title>
		<para>One excellent way to get help with Xubuntu or to introduce yourself to IRC is to join Xubuntu's official support channel on &irc-network;.</para> 
		<procedure>
			<step>
				<para>Start <application>XChat</application> as above.</para>
			</step>
			<step>
				<para>When you start <application>XChat</application> for the first time, it will ask you for an IRC Nickname &amp; your real name. Pick anything you want for your nick (first initial &amp; your last name is good, or be more creative), put your real name or part of it, and press <guibutton>OK</guibutton>.</para>
			</step>
			<step>
				<para>In the Server Window that opens next, select <emphasis>Ubuntu Servers</emphasis>, and press <guibutton>Connect</guibutton>.</para>
			</step>
		</procedure>
	</sect2>
	
</sect1>

<sect1 id="internet-otherapps" status="review">
	<title>Other Internet applications</title>
	<para>The Internet has much more to offer besides web browsing, email and instant messaging. Xubuntu provides a selection of other applications to help you get the most out of the Internet.</para>
	
	<sect2 id="internet-otherapps-p2p" status="review">
		<title>Peer-to-Peer networks</title>
		<para>Peer-to-peer (P2P) networks are a way of sharing files, music and videos between people from all around the world.</para>
		<para>A popular P2P service is <application>aMule File Sharing Client</application>.</para>
		<procedure>
			<step>
				<para>Install the <application>amule</application> package from the <quote>Universe</quote> repository (see <ulink type="help" url="ghelp:add-applications">Add Applications</ulink>).</para>
			</step>
			<step>
				<para>To open <application>aMule</application>, choose &amule;.</para>
			</step>
		</procedure>
	</sect2>

	<sect2 id="internet-otherapps-newsreaders" status="review">
		<title>News Readers</title>
		<para>You can automatically receive news updates from the Internet. There are several different types of news service to choose from:</para>
		<itemizedlist>
			<listitem>
				<para><emphasis>Usenet</emphasis> is one of the oldest and allows you to discuss news and other topics with people from all around the world. <application>Pan Newsreader</application> is a news reader which works with Usenet.</para>
				<para>Install the <application>pan</application> package and then choose &pan; to start using <application>Pan</application>.
				</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para><emphasis>RSS feeds</emphasis> are a popular way of automatically receiving regular news updates and articles. <application>Liferea Feed Reader</application> is an RSS feed reader with many useful features.</para>
				<para>Install the <application>liferea</application> package and then choose &liferea; to start using <application>Liferea</application>.</para>
			</listitem>
		</itemizedlist>
	</sect2>
	
</sect1>

<sect1 id="web-design" status="review">
	<title>Design web pages</title>
	<para>Xubuntu includes a wide selection of tools to help you design and develop web pages.</para>
	<itemizedlist>
		<listitem>
			<para><emphasis role='strong'><application>Geany</application></emphasis> is a powerful editor for web designers and programmers.</para>
			<para><application>Geany</application> supports many programming and markup languages, and includes many utilities for designers and programmers.</para>
			<itemizedlist>
				<listitem><para>For more information, see the <ulink url="http://geany.uvena.de/">Geany website</ulink>.</para></listitem>
				<listitem><para>Install the <application>geany</application> package from the <quote>Universe</quote> repository (see <ulink type="help" url="ghelp:add-applications">Add Applications</ulink>).</para></listitem>
				<listitem><para>To start <application>Geany</application>, press &geany;.</para></listitem>
			</itemizedlist>
		</listitem>
	</itemizedlist>
</sect1>

</article>
