<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.3//EN" 
 "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.3/docbookx.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % globalent SYSTEM "../../../libs/global.ent">
%globalent;
<!ENTITY % cdo-C SYSTEM "../../../libs/cdo-C.ent">
%cdo-C;
<!ENTITY % kde SYSTEM "../../libs/kde.ent">
%kde;
<!ENTITY % kde-menus-C SYSTEM "../../libs/kde-menus-C.ent">
%kde-menus-C;
<!ENTITY language "&EnglishAmerican;">
]>
<article id="art-about-kubuntu" status="review" lang="th">
	<articleinfo>
	<title>เกี่ยวกับ Kubuntu</title>
	<legalnotice>
	<title>ผู้จัดทำและลิขสิทธิ์</title>
	<para>ผู้เขียนของทีมงานเอกสารของอูบันตูต่อไปนี้ดูแลเอกสารนี้:</para>
		<itemizedlist>
			<listitem>
				<para>Jonathan Jesse</para>
			</listitem>
		</itemizedlist>
	<para>บุคคลต่างๆ ตามรายชื่อต่อไปนี้ได้มีส่วนร่วมในการเขียนเอกสารนี้:</para>
		<itemizedlist>
			<listitem>
				<para>Matthew East</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para>Jerome Gotangco</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para>Jonathan Riddell</para>
			</listitem>
		</itemizedlist>
		<para>เอกสารนี้อยู่ภายใต้สัญญาอนุญาตสองแบบ คือ GNU Free Documentation License (GFDL)  และ Creative Commons ShareAlike 2.0 License (CC-BY-SA)</para>
		<para>คุณสามารถแก้ไขปรับปรุงเอกสารของ Ubuntu ตามเงื่อนไขของสัญญาอนุญาตข้างต้นได้อย่างอิสระ ผลงานที่พัฒนาต่อจำเป็นต้องใช้สัญญาอนุญาตอย่างใดอย่างหนึ่ง หรือทั้งสองแบบก็ได้</para>
		<para>คุณสามารถแก้ไขปรับปรุงเอกสารของ Ubuntu ตามเงื่อนไขของสัญญาอนุญาตข้างต้นได้อย่างอิสระ ผลงานที่พัฒนาต่อจำเป็นต้องใช้สัญญาอนุญาตอย่างใดอย่างหนึ่ง หรือทั้งสองแบบก็ได้</para>
		<para>เอกสารนี้แจกจ่ายด้วยความหวังที่ว่าจะเป็นประโยชน์แต่ไมีมีการรับรอง (WARRANTY) ไม่มีแม้แต่ที่บอกเป็นนัยว่ารับรองขายได้ (MERCHANTABILITY) หรือเหมาะสมสำหรับจุดประสงค์ใดโดยเฉพาะดังที่ได้บรรยายในเอกสารปฏิเสธความรับผิดชอบ(DISCLAIMER)</para>
		<para>สำเนาของใบอนุญาติต่างๆอยู่ในภาคผนวกข้างหลังของหนังสือนี้,หรือฉบับออนไลน์(Online versions )สามารถหาอ่านได้ที่ URLs:</para>
		<itemizedlist>
			<listitem>
				<para>&fdl-url;</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para>&cc-attrib;</para>
			</listitem>
		</itemizedlist>
	</legalnotice>
	&copyright;
	<authorgroup>
		&author-ubuntu-documentation-project;
	</authorgroup>
	<abstract>
		<para>เอกสารนี้เป็นการแนะนำคูบันตูโดยจะอธิบายแนวคิดและความเป็นมา และแนะนำคูบันตูเด็สก์ท็อป</para>
	</abstract>
	&disclaimer;
	&publisher;
  </articleinfo>
 
 <para>Welcome to Kubuntu &distro-rev;: the &distro-version;
  	Release.</para>

 <para>Kubuntu is a user-friendly operating system based on KDE, the K
 Desktop Environment. With a predictable 6 month release cycle as part of
 the Ubuntu project, Kubuntu is the Linux distribution for
 everyone.</para>
  
 <para>ทีมงานเบื้องหลังคูบันตูได้ให้คำมั่นสัญญาต่อไปนี้ให้กับผู้ใช้:</para>
 <itemizedlist>
 
  <listitem>
  
   <para>คูบันตูใช้พื้นฐานที่มั่นคงของอูบันตูบวกกับรุ่นล่าสุดของ KDE เราเป็นส่วนหนึ่งของชุมชนอูบันตูและใช้โครงสร้างและบริการสนับสนุนเดียวกัน จุดมุ่งหมายของเราคือเป็นชุดเผยแพร่ที่ดีที่สุดของ KDE</para>
    
  </listitem>
  
  <listitem>
  
   <para>คุณสามารถใช้งานคูบันตูโดยไม่เสียค่าใช้จ่าย และรับประกันว่าไม่มีค่าใช้จ่ายเพิ่มเติมสำหรับรุ่นที่ใช้ในระดับองค์กร เราพยายามอย่างเต็มที่ในการพัฒนาซอฟต์แวร์ที่ทุกคนสามารถใช้ได้อย่างเสรี</para>
    
  </listitem>
  
  <listitem>
  
   <para>คูบันตูได้รับการแปลเป็นภาษาต่างๆ และสนับสนุนการใช้งานโดยผู้พิการและด้อยความสามารถเป็นอย่างดี เพื่อส่งเสริมให้ทุกคนสามารถใช้งาน Ubuntu ได้</para>
    
  </listitem>
  
  <listitem>
  
   <para>โครงการคูบันตูทั้งโครงการนั้นยึดถือแนวคิดการพัฒนาซอฟต์แวร์แบบโอเพนซอร์สอย่างจริงจัง เราส่งเสริมการใช้งานโอเพนซอร์ส และต่อยอดพัฒนาซอฟต์แวร์ให้ดียิ่งขึ้น</para>
   
  </listitem>
  
 </itemizedlist>
 
 <para id="aboutkubuntu03">Kubuntu includes more than 1,000 pieces of software, starting with Linux
  version &linux-kernel-version; and KDE &kde-version;, and covering every standard desktop application from word processing and
  spreadsheet to Internet access applications, web server software, email software, programming
  languages and tools, and of course, several games. </para>
  
 <sect1 id="wonderful-linux" status="review">
 
  <title>โลกที่สวยงามของลีนุกซ์</title>
  
  <para>Kubuntu uses the <quote>Linux</quote> kernel, the software which
   has come to define the worldwide movement to embrace open source
   software. Find out about Linux at <ulink url="&linuxorg;">Linux.org</ulink>
  </para>
  
  <sect2 id="sect-kubuntu-difference" status="review">
  
   <title>สิ่งที่แตกต่างกับระบบอื่น</title>
   
   <para>There are many Linux distributions (e.g., Redhat, SuSE,
    Debian, Mandriva) but Kubuntu distinguishes itself as a
    different kind of distribution. </para>
    
   <para>Built on the solid and advanced base of Ubuntu, the Kubuntu
    team aims to create a distribution that provides an up-to-date and
    coherent Linux system for desktop and server computing.
    Kubuntu includes a number of selected packages from Ubuntu and is
    based on Debian's powerful <quote>Adept</quote> package management
    system. Adept allows easy installation and clean removal of
    programs, as well as automatic download of extra packages to
    satisfy dependencies. Unlike most distributions that ship a wide
    range of software packages that may or may not be of quality,
    Kubuntu's core list of packages is reduced only to the most
    important applications. (Although for maximum choice, you may
    choose from over 10,000 packages ready to download, rather than
    being limited to the selected core.) </para>
    
   <para>โดยเน้นที่คุณภาพ คูบันตูให้ระบบคอมพิวเตอร์ที่ทนทานและคุณสมบัติพร้อมที่สามารถใช้ในบ้านหรือธุรกิจ โครงการนี้ใช้เวลาส่วนใหญ่ดูอย่างละเอียดละออและสามารถให้รุ่นที่ทันสมัยที่สุดทุก 6 เดือน คูบันตูมาพร้อมกับรุ่นสำหรับ  PCs (Intel Pentium / AMD Athlon), 64-bit PCs (AMD64) และ Mac (PowerPC) architectures.</para>
    
  </sect2>
  
  <sect2 id="sect-about-KDE" status="review">
  
   <title>KDE สำหรับผู้ใช้อูบันตู</title>
   
   <para>The default desktop environment for Kubuntu is KDE, a powerful Free Software graphical
    desktop environment for Linux and Unix workstations. It combines ease of use, contemporary
    functionality, and outstanding graphical design with the technological superiority of the Unix
    operating system. KDE is one of the two leading graphical desktop environments for Linux
    users. KDE sports an impressive array of easy to use, but powerful, graphical interface
    applications for users of all ages in both home and work environments. For developers, KDE
    provides a robust application development framework that enables rapid creation of first rate
    applications implementing cutting-edge technology. </para>
   
   <para>KDE is in many ways similar to GNOME, but there are a few distinct differences which
    distinguish KDE as a desktop environment. KDE uses C++ at its base, with Qt (the Q-toolkit),
    whereas GNOME, using GTK, is written in C. KDE is the older and most widely used
    desktop environment, and is known to stress more the importance of features, and more recently,
    usability. GNOME more notoriously prides itself on simplicity and ease of use.
    Popular criticisms of GNOME are that it's lacking in features and applications, while it's often
    commented that KDE has too many features which may themselves be hard to locate.</para>
   
    <para>อย่างไรก็ตาม KDE และ GNOME มีเป้าหมายของผู้ใช้ที่แตกต่างกัน และแตกต่างกันในบางมุมมองเบื้องต้น และคำถามที่ว่าเดสก์ท็อปไหนดีกว่าขึ้นอยู่กับความคิดเห็นในหลายๆทาง เพราะเป็นอย่างนี้ถ้าจะตัดสินใจให้ถูกต้องว่าอันไหนเหมาะสมกับคุณ คำแนะนำคือทดลองทั้งสองอย่าง ด้วยเหตุนี้จึงเป็นเรื่องที่ง่ยมากที่จะติดตั้ง GNOME จากชุดเผยแพร่คูบันตูและเหมือนกันเป็นการง่ายมากที่จะติดตั้ง KDE จากอูบันตู</para>
  </sect2>
  
  <sect2 id="sect-switching-desktops" status="review">
  
   <title>เปลี่ยนเดสก์ท็อป</title>
   
   <para>ในสถานะผู้ใช้อูบันตู คุณอาจจะกังวลว่าโปรแกรมโปรด GNOME แอพพิลเคชันจะไม่สามารถใช้ได้กับคูบันตู มันไม่เป็นเช่นนั้น ในเวลาที่ผ่านไปได้มีการปรับปรุงมากมายเพื่อที่จะทำให้ GNOME และ KDE ใช้ร่วมกันได้ ในวันนี้เกือบจะทุกแอพพิลเคชันของ GNOME สามารถใช้กับ KDE และในทางกลับกัน</para>
    
   <para>ในขณะที่ KDE เดสก์ท็อปแตกต่างมากจากของ GNOME แอพพิลเคชันของ GNOME ที่คุณชอบจะถูกรวมเข้ากับระบบเมนูของ KDE</para>
    
   <para>Another concern for users wanting to try Kubuntu may be that
    KDE will become their only desktop once it is installed. While
    we do indeed hope you will make KDE your desktop of choice, this
    is not the case; both desktop session types can be run after
    installing Kubuntu. Furthermore, during installation you will be
    given the choice of using either the GNOME Display Manager (GDM)
    or the K Display Manager (KDM) as your login manager. </para>
    
   <para>Either display manager will suffice, and after installation
    you will be able to run both GNOME and KDE session types.  Feel
    free to try KDM.  You can always switch back to GDM later if you
    like.  The only noticeable difference will be the artwork used 
	before you log in.</para>

    <para>ติดตั้งคูบันตู คุณเพียงแค่ติดตั้งแพ็กเกจ <emphasis>kubuntu-desktop</emphasis></para>
    
  </sect2>
  
 </sect1>
 
</article>

