<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.3//EN" 
 "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.3/docbookx.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % globalent SYSTEM "../../../libs/global.ent">
%globalent;
<!ENTITY % cdo-C SYSTEM "../../../libs/cdo-C.ent">
%cdo-C;
<!ENTITY % kde SYSTEM "../../libs/kde.ent">
%kde;
<!ENTITY % kde-menus-C SYSTEM "../../libs/kde-menus-C.ent">
%kde-menus-C;
<!ENTITY language "&EnglishAmerican;">
]>
<article id="art-about-kubuntu" status="review" lang="ja">
	<articleinfo>
	<title>Kubuntuについて</title>
	<legalnotice>
	<title>謝辞とライセンス</title>
	<para>以下のUbuntu文書化チーム員がこの文書を管理しています：</para>
		<itemizedlist>
			<listitem>
				<para>Jonathan Jesse</para>
			</listitem>
		</itemizedlist>
	<para>以下の方々がこの文書に貢献しました：</para>
		<itemizedlist>
			<listitem>
				<para>Matthew East</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para>Jerome Gotangco</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para>Jonathan Riddell</para>
			</listitem>
		</itemizedlist>
		<para>この文書はGNU Free Documentation License (GFDL)とCreative Commons ShareAlike 2.0 License (CC-BY-SA)の二重ライセンスの下でリリースされています。</para>
		<para>Ubuntuの文書をこれらのライセンスに基づき、変更・加筆・改善することができます。これらはどちらかのライセンスか両方のライセンスでリリースしなければなりません。</para>
		<para>Ubuntuの文書をこれらのライセンスに基づき、変更・加筆・改善することができます。これらはどちらかのライセンスか両方のライセンスでリリースしなければなりません。
Used elsewhere: 		

このUbuntuドキュメントのソースコードは、これらのライセンス条項のもと、自由に改変・拡張・改良することができます。すべての派生物は、これらのライセンスのうち一方、もしくは両方のもとでリリースされなければなりません。</para>
		<para>この文書は利用者の便宜になることを期待して配布しますが、何らの保証をするものではなく、また、免責条項に記載のある通り、商品性や特定用途に対する適合性を暗黙に保証するものでもありません。</para>
		<para>これらのライセンスの内容はこの本の附録にあります。オンライン版は以下のＵＲＬで入手できます：</para>
		<itemizedlist>
			<listitem>
				<para>&fdl-url;</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para>&cc-attrib;</para>
			</listitem>
		</itemizedlist>
	</legalnotice>
	&copyright;
	<authorgroup>
		&author-ubuntu-documentation-project;
	</authorgroup>
	<abstract>
		<para>この文書はKubuntuの紹介についてです。Kubuntuの方針と歴史、そしてKubuntuデスクトップを紹介します。</para>
	</abstract>
	&disclaimer;
	&publisher;
  </articleinfo>
 
 <para>ようこそ Kubuntu &distro-rev;: the &distro-version; リリースへ.</para>

 <para>Kubuntu は KDE こと K Desktop Environment をベースにしたユーザにやさしいオペレーティングシステムです。
Ubuntu プロジェクトの一部として6ヶ月のリリースサイクルを予定しています。
Kubuntu は皆のための Linux ディストリビューションです。</para>
  
 <para>Kubuntuに携わるチームはユーザのために以下を公約致します：</para>
 <itemizedlist>
 
  <listitem>
  
   <para>KubutnuはUbuntuの基礎の上に最新のKDEを乗せたものです。我々はUbuntuコミュニティーの一部でUbuntuの基盤のサポートを使用します。我々の使命は最高のKDEディストロビューションになることです。</para>
    
  </listitem>
  
  <listitem>
  
   <para>Kubuntuは無料で提供するものであり、いわゆる<quote>エンタープライズ版</quote>が有料になることはありません。また、我々は最高傑作も同じ無料の条件の下で提供します。</para>
    
  </listitem>
  
  <listitem>
  
   <para>Kubutnuがより多くの方にとって使えるよう、Kubuntuはフリーソフトウェアのコミュニティーが提供している最高の翻訳とアクセシビリティのインフラを盛込んでいます。</para>
    
  </listitem>
  
  <listitem>
  
   <para>Kubuntu is entirely committed to the principles of free
    software and open source development; we encourage people to use
    free and open source software, improve it, and pass it on.
   </para>
   
  </listitem>
  
 </itemizedlist>
 
 <para id="aboutkubuntu03">Kubuntu includes more than 1,000 pieces of software, starting with Linux
  version &linux-kernel-version; and KDE &kde-version;, and covering every standard desktop application from word processing and
  spreadsheet to Internet access applications, web server software, email software, programming
  languages and tools, and of course, several games. </para>
  
 <sect1 id="wonderful-linux" status="review">
 
  <title>Linuxの素晴らしき世界</title>
  
  <para>Kubuntu uses the <quote>Linux</quote> kernel, the software which
   has come to define the worldwide movement to embrace open source
   software. Find out about Linux at <ulink url="&linuxorg;">Linux.org</ulink>
  </para>
  
  <sect2 id="sect-kubuntu-difference" status="review">
  
   <title>他との違い</title>
   
   <para>There are many Linux distributions (e.g., Redhat, SuSE,
    Debian, Mandriva) but Kubuntu distinguishes itself as a
    different kind of distribution. </para>
    
   <para>Built on the solid and advanced base of Ubuntu, the Kubuntu
    team aims to create a distribution that provides an up-to-date and
    coherent Linux system for desktop and server computing.
    Kubuntu includes a number of selected packages from Ubuntu and is
    based on Debian's powerful <quote>Adept</quote> package management
    system. Adept allows easy installation and clean removal of
    programs, as well as automatic download of extra packages to
    satisfy dependencies. Unlike most distributions that ship a wide
    range of software packages that may or may not be of quality,
    Kubuntu's core list of packages is reduced only to the most
    important applications. (Although for maximum choice, you may
    choose from over 10,000 packages ready to download, rather than
    being limited to the selected core.) </para>
    
   <para>By focusing on quality, Kubuntu provides a robust and feature
    rich computing environment that is flexible for use in home and
    commercial environments. The project has more time to spend on the
    finer details and is able to release a version featuring the
    latest and greatest of today's software, every 6 months. Kubuntu
    ships with versions for PCs (Intel Pentium / AMD Athlon), 64-bit
    PCs (AMD64) and Mac (PowerPC) architectures. </para>
    
  </sect2>
  
  <sect2 id="sect-about-KDE" status="review">
  
   <title>Ubuntu使用者のためのKDE</title>
   
   <para>The default desktop environment for Kubuntu is KDE, a powerful Free Software graphical
    desktop environment for Linux and Unix workstations. It combines ease of use, contemporary
    functionality, and outstanding graphical design with the technological superiority of the Unix
    operating system. KDE is one of the two leading graphical desktop environments for Linux
    users. KDE sports an impressive array of easy to use, but powerful, graphical interface
    applications for users of all ages in both home and work environments. For developers, KDE
    provides a robust application development framework that enables rapid creation of first rate
    applications implementing cutting-edge technology. </para>
   
   <para>KDE is in many ways similar to GNOME, but there are a few distinct differences which
    distinguish KDE as a desktop environment. KDE uses C++ at its base, with Qt (the Q-toolkit),
    whereas GNOME, using GTK, is written in C. KDE is the older and most widely used
    desktop environment, and is known to stress more the importance of features, and more recently,
    usability. GNOME more notoriously prides itself on simplicity and ease of use.
    Popular criticisms of GNOME are that it's lacking in features and applications, while it's often
    commented that KDE has too many features which may themselves be hard to locate.</para>
   
    <para>Nevertheless, KDE and GNOME respectively target different audiences,
    and are fundamentally different in some respects, and the question of which
    desktop environment is superior is inherently a subjective opinion in many 
    ways. Because of this, to at least make a proper decision about which is 
    more suited to yourself, it is advised that you try them both out. 
    Thus, it is very easy to install GNOME from a Kubuntu distribution, and 
    equally easy to install KDE from an Ubuntu setup. </para>
  </sect2>
  
  <sect2 id="sect-switching-desktops" status="review">
  
   <title>デスクトップを変更する</title>
   
   <para>Ubuntu使用者にとっては、お好みのGNOMEアプリケーションがKubuntuでは作動しないことを心配しているかもしれません。心配要りません。最近GNOMEとKDEの間で互角性を高めるように努力が施されています。現在殆どのGNOMEアプリケーションはKDEで作動し、逆もしかりです。</para>
    
   <para>KDEデスクトップはGNOMEとはかなり違いますが、お好みのGNOMEアプリケーションは全てKDEメニューシステムに統合されます。</para>
    
   <para>Another concern for users wanting to try Kubuntu may be that
    KDE will become their only desktop once it is installed. While
    we do indeed hope you will make KDE your desktop of choice, this
    is not the case; both desktop session types can be run after
    installing Kubuntu. Furthermore, during installation you will be
    given the choice of using either the GNOME Display Manager (GDM)
    or the K Display Manager (KDM) as your login manager. </para>
    
   <para>Either display manager will suffice, and after installation
    you will be able to run both GNOME and KDE session types.  Feel
    free to try KDM.  You can always switch back to GDM later if you
    like.  The only noticeable difference will be the artwork used 
	before you log in.</para>

    <para>Kubuntuをインストールするには、<emphasis>kubuntu-desktop</emphasis>パッケージをインストールする必要があります。</para>
    
  </sect2>
  
 </sect1>
 
</article>

