<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.1.2//EN" 
	"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.1.2/docbookx.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % globalent SYSTEM "../../../libs/global.ent">
%globalent;
<!ENTITY % cdo-C SYSTEM "../../../libs/cdo-C.ent">
%cdo-C;
<!ENTITY % gnome SYSTEM "../../libs/gnome.ent">
%gnome;
<!ENTITY % gnome-menus-C SYSTEM "../../libs/gnome-menus-C.ent">
%gnome-menus-C;
<!ENTITY language "&EnglishAmerican;">
]>
<article id="art-about-ubuntu" status="complete" lang="&language;">
<articleinfo>
  <title>Welcome to Ubuntu &distro-rev;, &distro-version;!</title>
  </articleinfo>
<para>
        <inlinemediaobject>
            <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref="../../images/&language;/ubuntuheader.png" format="PNG"/>
            </imageobject>
  <textobject>
    <phrase>Ubuntu Logo</phrase>
  </textobject>
        </inlinemediaobject>
</para>
	   <para>The Ubuntu Project is built on the ideas enshrined in the <ulink url="&ubuntu-philosophy;">Ubuntu Philosophy</ulink>: that software should be available free of charge, that software tools should be usable by people in their local language, and that people should have the freedom to customize and alter their software in whatever way they need.</para>
<sect1><title>Getting Help with Ubuntu</title>
	<para>There are many ways to get help with Ubuntu. You can obtain <ulink url="&ubuntu-paidsupport;">paid support</ulink>. However there are also many free support options, listed <ulink url="&ubuntu-freesupport;">on this web page</ulink>. Access Ubuntu's local help by clicking the help icon on the top panel of your desktop or from the System menu. You can also find help from <ulink url="&ubuntu-documentation;">Official Ubuntu Documentation Project</ulink> and <ulink url="&wiki-UserDocumentation;">Community Contributed Documentation</ulink> on the Ubuntu Wiki. If you prefer some human contact, you can use the <ulink url="&ubuntu-lists;">Mailing Lists</ulink>, <ulink url="&ubuntu-forums;">Web Forums</ulink>, or chat with the community on Freenode IRC Channel: #ubuntu.</para>
</sect1>
<sect1><title>Participate in Ubuntu</title>
        <para>The Ubuntu community is made up of software developers, documentation writers, translators, graphic artists, and most importantly, the people who are using Ubuntu in their everyday life. We invite you to join this community and help shape Ubuntu into an operating system that better meets your needs.</para>
 	<para>To find out how to participate, visit <ulink url="&ubuntu-participate;">this webpage</ulink>!</para>
</sect1>
</article>
