<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.3//EN" 
 "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.3/docbookx.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % globalent SYSTEM "../../../libs/global.ent">
%globalent;
<!ENTITY % cdo-C SYSTEM "../../../libs/cdo-C.ent">
%cdo-C;
<!ENTITY % kde SYSTEM "../../libs/kde.ent">
%kde;
<!ENTITY % kde-menus-C SYSTEM "../../libs/kde-menus-C.ent">
%kde-menus-C;
<!ENTITY language "&EnglishAmerican;">
]>
<article id="art-about-kubuntu" status="review" lang="zh_CN">
	<articleinfo>
	<title>关于 Kubuntu</title>
	<legalnotice>
	<title>贡献者与授权许可</title>
	<para>本文档由下列 Ubuntu 文档组作者维护：</para>
		<itemizedlist>
			<listitem>
				<para>Jonathan Jesse</para>
			</listitem>
		</itemizedlist>
	<para>下列人员对本文档亦有贡献</para>
		<itemizedlist>
			<listitem>
				<para>Matthew East</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para>Jerome Gotangco</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para>Jonathan Riddell</para>
			</listitem>
		</itemizedlist>
		<para>本文档采用双重许可政策：GNU Free Documentation License (GFDL) 以及 Creative Commons ShareAlike 2.0 License (CC-BY-SA)。</para>
		<para>您可以在这些授权的许可下自由的修改、扩充和改进 Ubuntu 文档的源代码。所有派生作品必须在上述任一或双重许可下发布。</para>
		<para>只要遵照上述两份授权许可的条款，您可以自由的修改、扩充和完善 Ubuntu 文档源代码。所有派生作品必须在上述任一或双重许可下发布。</para>
		<para>本文档发布的目的是期望它有所用途，但不提供任何担保；甚至如免责声明中所说那样对特定目标的适销性或适用性也不提供任何隐性的担保。</para>
		<para>本文档的附录部分提供了上述两份授权许可的副本，此外您可以通过下列网址获取其在线版本：</para>
		<itemizedlist>
			<listitem>
				<para>&fdl-url;</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para>&cc-attrib;</para>
			</listitem>
		</itemizedlist>
	</legalnotice>
	&copyright;<copyright><year>2006</year><holder>Linxiao Li (linxiao.li@gmail.com)</holder></copyright>
	<authorgroup>
		&author-ubuntu-documentation-project;
	</authorgroup>
	<abstract>
		<para>本文档是份 Kubuntu 简介，说明了 Kubuntu 的理念和起源，并且介绍了 Kubuntu 桌面。</para>
	</abstract>
	&disclaimer;
	&publisher;
  </articleinfo>
 
 <para>Welcome to Kubuntu &distro-rev;: the &distro-version;
  	Release.</para>

 <para>Kubuntu is a user-friendly operating system based on KDE, the K
 Desktop Environment. With a predictable 6 month release cycle as part of
 the Ubuntu project, Kubuntu is the Linux distribution for
 everyone.</para>
  
 <para>Kubuntu 团队为用户提供如下承诺：</para>
 <itemizedlist>
 
  <listitem>
  
   <para>Kubuntu 使用坚实的 Ubuntu 加上最新的 KDE。我们是 Ubuntu 社区的一部分，分享他们的基础组织和支持。我们的任务是成为基于 KDE 的最好发行版。</para>
    
  </listitem>
  
  <listitem>
  
   <para>Kubuntu 永远免费，即便是“企业版本”也毋需额外费用, 我们要把最好的工作成果免费提供给所有人，一视同仁。</para>
    
  </listitem>
  
  <listitem>
  
   <para>Kubuntu 包含了自由软件社区所能提供的最优质的翻译和易用的架构，以期更多的人能享用Kubuntu的易用性。</para>
    
  </listitem>
  
  <listitem>
  
   <para>Kubuntu 完全遵从自由/开源软件开发的原则；我们鼓励人们使用、完善并传播开源软件。</para>
   
  </listitem>
  
 </itemizedlist>
 
 <para id="aboutkubuntu03">Kubuntu includes more than 1,000 pieces of software, starting with Linux
  version &linux-kernel-version; and KDE &kde-version;, and covering every standard desktop application from word processing and
  spreadsheet to Internet access applications, web server software, email software, programming
  languages and tools, and of course, several games. </para>
  
 <sect1 id="wonderful-linux" status="review">
 
  <title>Linux 的精彩世界</title>
  
  <para>Kubuntu uses the <quote>Linux</quote> kernel, the software which
   has come to define the worldwide movement to embrace open source
   software. Find out about Linux at <ulink url="&linuxorg;">Linux.org</ulink>
  </para>
  
  <sect2 id="sect-kubuntu-difference" status="review">
  
   <title>不同之处</title>
   
   <para>There are many Linux distributions (e.g., Redhat, SuSE,
    Debian, Mandriva) but Kubuntu distinguishes itself as a
    different kind of distribution. </para>
    
   <para>Built on the solid and advanced base of Ubuntu, the Kubuntu
    team aims to create a distribution that provides an up-to-date and
    coherent Linux system for desktop and server computing.
    Kubuntu includes a number of selected packages from Ubuntu and is
    based on Debian's powerful <quote>Adept</quote> package management
    system. Adept allows easy installation and clean removal of
    programs, as well as automatic download of extra packages to
    satisfy dependencies. Unlike most distributions that ship a wide
    range of software packages that may or may not be of quality,
    Kubuntu's core list of packages is reduced only to the most
    important applications. (Although for maximum choice, you may
    choose from over 10,000 packages ready to download, rather than
    being limited to the selected core.) </para>
    
   <para>注重质量，Kubuntu 提供了一个健壮、功能丰富的计算环境，既适合家用又适用于商业环境。本项目花费了大量必要的时间，努力精益求精，每6个月就会发布一个版本，以提供最新最强大的流行软件。Kubuntu 支持各种形形色色的架构，包括 PC(Intel Pentium / AMD Athlon), 64-bit PC (AMD64) 和 Mac (PowerPC) 等。</para>
    
  </sect2>
  
  <sect2 id="sect-about-KDE" status="review">
  
   <title>Ubuntu 用户的 KDE</title>
   
   <para>The default desktop environment for Kubuntu is KDE, a powerful Free Software graphical
    desktop environment for Linux and Unix workstations. It combines ease of use, contemporary
    functionality, and outstanding graphical design with the technological superiority of the Unix
    operating system. KDE is one of the two leading graphical desktop environments for Linux
    users. KDE sports an impressive array of easy to use, but powerful, graphical interface
    applications for users of all ages in both home and work environments. For developers, KDE
    provides a robust application development framework that enables rapid creation of first rate
    applications implementing cutting-edge technology. </para>
   
   <para>KDE is in many ways similar to GNOME, but there are a few distinct differences which
    distinguish KDE as a desktop environment. KDE uses C++ at its base, with Qt (the Q-toolkit),
    whereas GNOME, using GTK, is written in C. KDE is the older and most widely used
    desktop environment, and is known to stress more the importance of features, and more recently,
    usability. GNOME more notoriously prides itself on simplicity and ease of use.
    Popular criticisms of GNOME are that it's lacking in features and applications, while it's often
    commented that KDE has too many features which may themselves be hard to locate.</para>
   
    <para>尽管如此，KDE 和 GNOME 还是各有各的支持者，并且某些方面有着根本的差异；至于哪个桌面环境更强，答案显然由各自的主观意志而定。也正因如此，为了能够作出正确选择，确定哪个更适合自己，这两个桌面环境您都应该试试。毕竟，在 Kubuntu 发行版上安装 GNOME 轻而易举，而在 Ubuntu 系统上安装 KDE 也是小菜一碟。</para>
  </sect2>
  
  <sect2 id="sect-switching-desktops" status="review">
  
   <title>切换桌面</title>
   
   <para>作为一名 Ubuntu 用户，您或许会担心自己喜欢的 GNOME 程序能否在 Kubuntu 上运行。不必担心，近来已开展了大量工作来提高 GNOME 和 KDE 之间的兼容性。现在，几乎所有 GNOME 程序都能在 KDE 上运行，反之亦然。</para>
    
   <para>尽管 KDE 桌面和 GNOME 桌面有很大不同，不过您喜欢的所有 GNOME 程序都会集成到您的 KDE 菜单系统中。</para>
    
   <para>Another concern for users wanting to try Kubuntu may be that
    KDE will become their only desktop once it is installed. While
    we do indeed hope you will make KDE your desktop of choice, this
    is not the case; both desktop session types can be run after
    installing Kubuntu. Furthermore, during installation you will be
    given the choice of using either the GNOME Display Manager (GDM)
    or the K Display Manager (KDM) as your login manager. </para>
    
   <para>Either display manager will suffice, and after installation
    you will be able to run both GNOME and KDE session types.  Feel
    free to try KDM.  You can always switch back to GDM later if you
    like.  The only noticeable difference will be the artwork used 
	before you log in.</para>

    <para>欲使用 Kubuntu，您只需安装 <emphasis>kubuntu-desktop</emphasis> 软件包。</para>
    
  </sect2>
  
 </sect1>
 
</article>

