<chapter id="contribfaq">
		<title>Participating</title>
	<highlights>
		<para>
			Everybody can participate in the Ubuntu community. Here we discuss
			how you can work in the wiki, how it is going with the forums and
			what kind of non-technical work there is, so you can also take part
			in the creation of this great distribution.
		</para>
	</highlights>


<!--
	SECTION: CONTRIBUTING
-->

	<sect1 id="sect-contributing">
		<title>Contributing</title>

		<sect2>
			<title>Where do I start if I want to help with Ubuntu?</title>
			<para>
				Ubuntu is a real community project. Here is a list of web-links that will get you started in no time:</para>
			<itemizedlist>
				<listitem>
					The first place to go is <ulink url="http://www.ubuntulinux.com/wiki">the wiki</ulink>.	
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					Subscribe to <ulink url="http://www.ubuntulinux.org/community/lists">the mailinglists</ulink>. Ubuntu is high-traffic, ubuntu-devel is for development related items only.	
				</listitem>
			</itemizedlist>
		</sect2>

		
				
		<sect2>
			<title>How do I get an account and contribute to this wiki?</title>
			<para>
				If you wish to contribute to Ubuntu by adding items to this wiki, you
				must first create an account. To get an account, click on
				<emphasis>join</emphasis> in the upper right hand corner of the
				webpage, and follow the directions on that page. If you are returning
				and wish to log back in, click <emphasis>log in</emphasis>. To edit a
				page, click on <emphasis>edit.</emphasis>	
			</para>
		</sect2>

		<sect2>
			<title>What international user resources are available?</title>
			<para>
				Please check the local languages page page which is kept
				updated.
			</para>
		</sect2>
		
		<sect2>
			<title>Can I edit the wiki?</title>
			<para>
				Yes - you just have to log in first. Register on the site and
				log in, or make a new account. There are some areas, such as
				the seed lists, that should not be changed without confirmation
				from Matt Zimmerman or Jeff Waugh on the sounder mailing list.
				We'll put a note on special pages such as these.
			</para>
			<para>
				The wiki and the web site have the same account information.
				You are able to add and edit most pages on the website and all
				in the wiki. Thank you for contributing.
			</para>
		</sect2>

		<sect2>
			<title>Where are the Ubuntu forums?</title>
			<para>
				We are currently researching different software to run the
				Ubuntu forums that can also integrate with our mailing lists.
				We have had some great input from our community with
				suggestions and we are working on this facet of our community
				support. As soon as we have them available, we will announce
				it.
			</para>
			<para>
				Until then you are invited to join the mailing lists. See the
				<ulink url="http://lists.ubuntu.com/mailman/listinfo/">mailing
					list page</ulink>.
			</para>
		</sect2>

		<sect2>
			<title>What non-technical work is there that volunteers can do for Ubuntu?</title>
			<para>
				If you don't code, there's still plenty of ways to get involved
				with Ubuntu.
			</para>
			<para>
				You can:
			</para>
			<itemizedlist>

	<!--
		SECTION: TODO error in the next <para>
	-->

				<listitem>Use Ubuntu.</listitem>
				<para>
					It's always surprising what you can find during a normal
					usage of a pre-release distro that, while nowhere being
					major bugs, are still worth reporting in the bugzilla for
					this or future releases. That's the whole point of beta and
					pre-releases: so that things are tested in thousands of
					different ways by many different users. What at first
					applicationear to be a simple bug can turn into a major
					vulnerability/problem worth patching as soon as possible.
				</para>
				<listitem>Answer questions on mailing lists, forums and IRC</listitem>
				<listitem>Maintain and tidy up the wiki</listitem>
				<listitem>Write documentation</listitem>
				<listitem>
					Spread the word. Order cds from Shipit - the Ubuntu CD
					Distribution System and give them away to friends, family,
					complete strangers.
				</listitem>
			</itemizedlist>
		</sect2>

		<sect2>
			<title>How do I activate the non-plone zwiki skin?</title>
			<para>
				If you are using the wiki a lot, try the non-plone zwiki skin;
				it is faster out of the box. Press alt - (or your browser's
				equivalent) or select it in preferences.
			</para>
			<para>
				If you still see the plone skin, do shift-reload or ctrl-f5.
			</para>
		</sect2>

	</sect1>

</chapter>

