<chapter id="installfaq">
    <title>Installation Issues</title>
    <highlights>
        <para>This chapter covers issues and questions you might have concerning Ubuntu
            installation. We will also cover installing Ubuntu inside a virtual machine and
            installing non-free software.</para>
    </highlights>
    <!-- SECTION: INSTALLING -->
    <sect1 id="sect-hardware">
        <title>Hardware</title>
        <sect2>
            <!-- Will Ubuntu support my hardware? -->
            <title>Will Ubuntu support my hardware?</title>
            <para> Ubuntu mainly provides the software packages and uses Debian's package management
                system. The hardware is controlled by the Linux kernel. So you may want to check
                your favorite web search engine for the keywords 'linux' and 'hardware'. There are
                already a few well-known resources where you can check if your hardware is
                supported. </para>
        </sect2>
        <sect2>
            <title>I have an applicationle system with only one mouse button. How can I perform actions
                which require right-clicking or middle-clicking?</title>
            <para> The F11 and F12 keys can be used to simulate these actions. </para>
        </sect2>
        <sect2>
            <title>I have more than 900 megabytes of RAM, but the system only sees the first 900.
                Why is that?</title>
            <para> The default generic i386 kernel only has support for 900 megabytes of RAM. After
                installation, you can select a different kernel as applicationropriate for your hardware. If
                you are running on a P4, for example, you might type: </para>
            <screen>sudo apt-get install linux-686</screen>
            <para> Otherwise, if you are on a dual-processor workstation, you might type: </para>
            <screen>sudo apt-get install linux-686-smp</screen>
            <para> Choose from the list of linux packages the one that best suits your hardware. </para>
        </sect2>
        <sect2>
            <title>What is the recommended RAM and how much hard drive space does Ubuntu need?</title>
            <para> To install Ubuntu you should have at least 32MB of RAM. </para>
            <para> You should have space on your hard disk to create a new disk partition of at
                least 1.8 GB for a standard Ubuntu desktop system, or at least 350 MB for a minimal
                custom installation. </para>
        </sect2>
    </sect1>
    <sect1 id="sect-vm">
        <title>Virtual Machines</title>
        <sect2>
            <!--Does Ubuntu work in Microsoft Virtual PC 2004?-->
            <title>Does Ubuntu work in Microsoft Virtual PC 2004?</title>
            <para> Yes, with a quick manual hack. Ubuntu currently auto-configures XFree86? during
                the installation process, asking the user only what resolutions they'd like to
                enable. The default color depth is automatically set to 24-bpp, and Microsoft
                Virtual PC 2004 does not support 24-bpp color depth. In practice, this results in
                garbled graphics output when the X Server starts and the login screen is displayed.
                To fix this problem, you may manually change the default color depth setting in the
                XFree86? config file. </para>
            <para> These directions assume that you have installed Ubuntu as your guest operating
                system normally, have rebooted, and have seen the garbled graphics output. </para>
            <itemizedlist>
                <listitem> In Microsoft Virtual PC, select Action-&gt;Reset to reboot the virtual
                    machine. </listitem>
                <listitem> Watch for the GNU GRUB prompt (don't blink or you'll miss it) and hit ESC
                    when you see it. </listitem>
                <listitem> Select the option in GRUB for recovery mode, and wait for Ubuntu to boot
                    into the shell. Then type: </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <emphasis>su root</emphasis> (you may have to type your password at this point,
                    I'm not sure) </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <emphasis>cd /etc/X11</emphasis>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <emphasis>nano XF86Config-4</emphasis>
                </listitem>
                <listitem> Now, scroll down in emacs to Section "Screen" and find the entry named
                    "DefaultDepth?". Change the setting you find there from 24 to 16. </listitem>
                <listitem> Hit F10, f, s to save your changes </listitem>
                <listitem> Hit F10, f, e to exit emacs </listitem>
                <listitem> Reboot the virtual machine again as described in step 1. </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
            <para> That's it - the virtual machine should now boot successfully into the beautiful
                minimalist Ubuntu login screen. </para>
        </sect2>
        <sect2>
            <!--  How do I get VMware to work after reboots?  -->
            <title>How do I get VMware to work after reboots?</title>
            <para> Using VMware under Ubuntu causes some problems because of Ubuntu's use of udev.
                Until the VMware developers have created a patch for this, here is a quick way to
                hack in 'support' for udev :) </para>
            <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para> First clear VMware's "Not Configured"-flag so that the next time, when
                        you try to start VMware, you won't have to reconfigure VMware first. If it
                        exists: </para>
                    <screen>rm /etc/vmware/not_configured</screen>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para> Next we need to edit <emphasis>/etc/init.d/vmware</emphasis>. Find the
                        following text (around line 800):
                        <screen>
case "$1" in
start)
						</screen> And insert the following text
                        right under those two lines: <screen>
for a in `seq 0 9`; do
mknod /dev/vmnet$a c 119 $a &gt; /dev/null 2&gt;&amp;1
done
mknod /dev/vmmon c 10 165 &gt; /dev/null 2&gt;&amp;1
						</screen>
                    </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para> Now run /etc/init.d/vmware start and the program should work again. </para>
                </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
        </sect2>
    </sect1>
    <sect1 id="sect-installationapplications">
        <title>Non-Free</title>
        <sect2>
            <!-- Where are Flash / Java / mp3 support? -->
            <title>Where are Flash / Java / mp3 support? Is there a Free and working DVD player or
                video player?</title>
            <para> There are a number of commonly used formats and tools that we are unable to
                support because they have restrictive distribution rights, require special licenses,
                or are patent encumbered. We may be able to provide support for some of these in
                restricted, but in general, we would prefer to support Free software and Free
                formats. </para>
            <para> If you add the debian-marillat repository to your Ubuntu sources.list (use
                testing/main), you can use Synaptic or apt-get to install MPlayer, lame, and other
                tools to deal with non-free formats like DVD and MP3. </para>
            <para> A relatively clean way of getting Totem to work with all the proprietary file
                formats is to install totem-xine rather than totem-gstreamer. Then you can download
                the win32 codecs from elsewhere and install them in ~/.gnome2/totem-addons/ and
                everything works fine. Of course, this isn't as cool and integrated as using
                GStreamer for handling all the media, but it works well. </para>
            <para> If you wish to use the Java SDK/RE, see Java on Debian for an installation guide
                (it's also valid for Ubuntu). </para>
            <para> As an alternative to the above mentioned Java on Debian tutorial, you may wish to
                install some pre-packaged packages. The website http://z42.de/debian/ lists an apt
                source that lets you install for example Sun Java2 v1.5 with a single
                command:apt-get install sun-j2sdk1.5 sun-j2sdk1.5debian </para>
        </sect2>
        <sect2>
            <!-- How do I install Java? -->
            <title>How do I install Java?</title>
            <para> Because Java is not open-source software, it is not installed by default.
                However, Ubuntu users can choose to install Java quite easily, if they wish. All
                that is needed is to follow these instructions. </para>
            <para>
                <emphasis>Note: These instructions are for 32 bit systems (e.g., Celerons, Pentium,
                    Pentium2, Pentium3, Pentium4, Durons, Semprons, Athlons, AthlonsXP). If you are
                    running a 64 bit system (e.g., Athlon64 or AMD Opteron), then it is recommended
                    to download Java from <ulink url="http://www.blackdown.org">BlackDown</ulink>
                    and follow their instructions.</emphasis>
            </para>
            <para>
                <itemizedlist>
                    <listitem> Download Java: <ulink url="http://java.sun.com/webapplications/download/AutoDL?BundleId=9718">JAVA</ulink>
                    </listitem>
                </itemizedlist>
            </para>
            <para>
                <emphasis> Note: Enter the commands shown in the box below in a terminal/console
                    screen. Be sure to change to the directory where the
                    j2re-1_4_2_05-linux-i586.bin is stored before entering the first command below. </emphasis>
            </para>
            <screen>
chmod a+x j2re-1_4_2_05-linux-i586.bin
./j2re-1_4_2_05-linux-i586.bin
sudo mv j2re1.4.2_05 /usr/local/
sudo mkdir /usr/bin/java
sudo ln -sf /usr/local/j2re1.4.2_05/bin/java /usr/bin/java
sudo ln -sf /usr/local/j2re1.4.2_05/bin/java_vm /usr/bin/java_vm
cd /home/username/.mozilla/plugins
			</screen>
            <para>
                <emphasis>Note: In line 3 above, the character '1' is the numeral one, not the
                    letter 'l' (pronounced 'el').</emphasis>
            </para>
            <para>
                <itemizedlist>
                    <listitem> If you do not have a plugins directory you can create one. </listitem>
                </itemizedlist>
                <screen>
mkdir -p /home/username/.mozilla/plugins
			</screen>
            </para>
            <para>
                <itemizedlist>
                    <listitem> Just a few remaining steps: </listitem>
                </itemizedlist>
                <screen>
ln -s /usr/local/j2re1.4.2_05/plugin/i386/ns610-gcc32/libjavaplugin_oji.so libjavaplugin_oji.so
sudo ln -s /usr/local/j2re1.4.2_05/plugin/i386/ns610-gcc32/libjavaplugin_oji.so /usr/lib/mozilla-firefox/plugins/
			</screen>
            </para>
            <para> That should give you working firefox java and systemwide java support. </para>
            <para>
                <emphasis>Note: These instructions first applicationeared in the Ubuntu FAQs and HOWTOs
                    Forum posted by UbuntuGeek.</emphasis>
            </para>
        </sect2>
    </sect1>
    <sect1 id="sect-packageManagement">
        <title>Package Management</title>
        <sect2>
            <!-- Which packages are available in Ubuntu? -->
            <title>Which packages are available in Ubuntu?</title>
            <para> Ubuntu contains essentially all of the packages available in the Debian
                repositories, as well as many packages from third-party sources. Many packages are
                customised to integrate smoothly with the Ubuntu system, to fix bugs, and to provide
                newer versions of software. In the future, a website will be provided which lists
                all of the available software. </para>
        </sect2>
        <sect2>
            <!-- Do you provide packages compiled with processor- -->
            <title>Do you provide packages compiled with processor-specific optimisations? Where can
                I find them?</title>
            <itemizedlist>
                <listitem> Optimised kernels can be obtained by installing the "linux-686",
                    "linux-k7", etc. packages. Search for "linux" with Synaptic, aptitude or
                    apt-cache. </listitem>
                <listitem> An optimised C library is installed by default, in the libc6-i686
                    packages. </listitem>
                <listitem> Optimised cryptography routines for i586- and i686-class systems are
                    included with the OpenSSL library and used automatically </listitem>
                <listitem> All Ubuntu packages are compiled using the i486 instruction set, with
                    instruction choices based on the Pentium 4 processor. This combination provides
                    benefits for modern processors without sacrificing compatibility with older and
                    embedded devices. </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
            <para> A comprehensive experiment to evaluate the effectiveness of more aggressive
                processor optimisations for all Ubuntu packages is planned after the Warty release. </para>
        </sect2>
        <sect2>
            <!-- I need newer versions of some Ubuntu packages, -->
            <title>I need newer versions of some Ubuntu packages, such as I am accustomed to
                receiving in Debian unstable. Where can I find them?</title>
            <para> Soon after the Warty release, updated packages will be available in our
                development branch on an ongoing basis, similar to the pace of Debian unstable. </para>
        </sect2>
        <sect2>
            <!-- multiverse repository -->
            <title>What kind of software does the multiverse repository contain?</title>
            <para> Software in the "multiverse" component has not been determined to be Free
                Software. </para>
            <para> Please make certain that you verify your rights to use this software and comply
                with the licensing terms of the copyright holder. This software receives no support
                and usually cannot be fixed or updated. Use it at your own risk. </para>
        </sect2>
        <sect2>
            <!-- an I use both Ubuntu and Debian packages together -->
            <title>Can I use both Ubuntu and Debian packages together, in the same sources.list?</title>
            <para> In general, it's not a very good idea. While Debian and Ubuntu are compatible to
                a large degree, and share many of the same source packages, the binary packages are
                not identical due to having been built independently. This causes unexpected effects
                in the package management system. </para>
            <para> However, in general, this is not an issue, for one simple reason: essentially all
                of the software in Debian is also available in Ubuntu repositories, so there is no
                reason to mix the two. </para>
        </sect2>
        <sect2>
            <title>Is it possible to upgrade from Debian Sarge to Ubuntu Warty Warthog simply by
                adding the "deb http://archive.ubuntu.com/ubuntu warty main restricted universe"
                lines to /etc/apt/sources.list? </title>
            <para> This is not supported, though a few brave souls have done it and reported mixed
                results. Sarge and Warty froze at similar times, so some of the code in Warty is
                newer than code in Sarge, and vice-versa. For example, Warty includes Gnome 2.8,
                while Sarge is Gnome 2.6. Just trying to switch sources in sources.list will have
                interesting and undefined results. Please feel free, if you are also feeling brave,
                to try it and update this answer or the wiki with your results. </para>
        </sect2>
        <sect2>
            <title>Can I upgrade directly from Debian Woody to Ubuntu?</title>
            <para> Yes, you can upgrade directly from Debian Woody to Ubuntu 4.10 (Warty Warthog).
                Notes and caveats about the upgrade process can be found <ulink
                url="http://wiki.ubuntu.com/WartyWarthog/UpgradeNote">here</ulink>. </para>
        </sect2>
    </sect1>
    <sect1 id="sect-packages">
        <title>Package Questions</title>
        <sect2>
            <title>Do you include XFree86 or X.org?</title>
            <para> Warty Warthog includes XFree86 4.3.99 packages with much improved hardware
                support. The next Ubuntu release, codenamed Hoary Hedgehog will use the X.org server
                instead. </para>
        </sect2>
        <sect2>
            <title>Does Ubuntu come with a firewall installed?</title>
            <para> Since Ubuntu doesn't run any daemons that listen to the outside world by default
                (the postfix install only listens on localhost) there's no need for a default
                firewall. </para>
            <para> The rationale is that if a user's got a need for installing a world-facing
                daemon, they'll be aware that they should configure a firewall/ACL for it too. </para>
        </sect2>
        <sect2>
            <title>Where is gpdf?</title>
            <para> GNOME 2.8's version of gpdf is available in universe. We decided to ship xpdf for
                WartyWarthog instead, as gpdf doesn't support text searching and Type3 fonts. It
                should do, by the time we release HoaryHedgehog with GNOME 2.10. </para>
        </sect2>
        <sect2>
            <title>Does Warty Warthog / Ubuntu include complete multimedia support?</title>
            <para> We're still working out some of the difficult legal / policy issues involved with
                multimedia support. Warty Warthog includes some basic multimedia support, but
                limited by what we can safely and freely do. Specific information is available for
                some multimedia issues in the RestrictedFormats wiki page. </para>
        </sect2>
        <sect2>
            <title>How do I get Firefox to open a new tab when I click a link?</title>
            <para> Edit the file /etc/mozilla-firefox/mozilla-firefoxrc and change the line that
                reads FIREFOX_OPEN_IN="window" to be FIREFOX_OPEN_IN="tab". There is a comment about
                this on the line above. </para>
        </sect2>
        <sect2>
            <title>Does Ubuntu include Mono and applications based on Mono?</title>
            <para> Mono is not included in our Warty Warthog release, but may be included in future
                releases. </para>
        </sect2>
    </sect1>
    <sect1 id="sect-graphics">
        <title>Graphics Questions</title>
        <sect2>
            <title>Where are the icons on the desktop? I want my Trashcan, Computer and Home icons
                on the desktop!</title>
            <para> In Warty Warthog, we decided to try out a new way of getting to all the important
                locations on your computer and across the network, which complements the spatial
                design behind Nautilus very nicely. </para>
            <para> Icons on the desktop are almost always obscured by windows when you're getting
                work done, and it's often a pain to move them out of the way or switch to a
                different workspace to get at them. So, we've turned all of the special desktop
                icons off, and provided access to them in the Computer menu. No more window tidying
                when you just want to open your file manager! </para>
            <para> We've included trashapplicationlet, which provides a working trash icon on your panel, so
                it's always accessible. In the future, we'd like to make it so that you can delete
                anything - not just files - by dragging to the trash. </para>
            <para> If you want to turn some of the special desktop icons back on, run applications
                &gt; System Tools &gt; Configuration Editor, navigate to /applications/nautilus/general, and
                choose the icons you want to applicationear. </para>
        </sect2>
        <sect2>
            <!-- What background images are available for widescreen laptop -->
            <title>What background images are available for widescreen laptops and displays?</title>
            <para> The Ubuntu Default Desktop and Ubuntu Monthly Calendar images are also available
                in a 16:9 aspect ratio for those with widescreen laptops and displays. </para>
        </sect2>
    </sect1>
    <sect1 id="sect-networking">
        <title>Networking Questions</title>
        <sect2>
            <title>When I browse my network using the "Windows Network" method I can see all of the
                machines, but only connect to XP workstations. When I try to connect to Windows 2003
                Servers, I get a permissions error. Now, when I try "Connect to Server" method, I
                fill out the details and enter my password when asked, it responds by asking for the
                password again. I have also added a computer account to Windows server for my
                Unbuntu machine then repeated these steps with the same results.</title>
            <para> It seems entering 'servername' in the server field and 'sharename' in the share
                field is not sufficient. Try putting 'servername/sharename' in the server field and
                leaving the share field blank. We understand this is very counter-intuitive, but it
                works, we're working to improve this user interface. </para>
        </sect2>
        <sect2>
            <title>My wireless network uses WEP encryption for better security. How can I set up
                Ubuntu to connect to it?</title>
            <para> Ubuntu's Network Settings dialog has support for wireless network cards. Network
                configuration is in 'Computer -&gt; System Configuration -&gt; Networking' </para>
        </sect2>
    </sect1>
    <sect1 id="sect-other">
        <title>Miscelenious Questions</title>
        <sect2>
            <title>What's the root password after I install? How do I use the root account?</title>
            <para> The root account is disabled when you first install Ubuntu. The first user
                created during the installation has administrative rights on the system, and can run
                programs as root with sudo, using only their normal user password. For example: sudo
                apt-get update. </para>
            <para> All uses of sudo will require the user's password.Note that the root account does
                not have a password at all after the initial install. You can set the root password
                by typing sudo passwd root.If you need a shell with root privileges, run sudo -s.
                The benefits of this are mentioned in the wiki here. </para>
            <para> Please keep in mind that booting into recovery mode only works if you have a root
                password set. Otherwise the only way to access your system in case of problems is to
                use a Live CD and mount your filesystem. </para>
        </sect2>
        <sect2>
            <title>The default installation is for a graphical desktop environment, but I'd like to
                install a server or other minimal system. How can I do this?</title>
            <para> Type "custom" at the initial CD-ROM boot prompt. This will install only the base
                packages, after which you can install only what you need, using 'aptitude' or
                'apt-get'. </para>
        </sect2>
        <sect2>
            <title>How can I boot Ubuntu with different options using grub?</title>
            <para> You can have grub boot the kernel using different options for just the one boot
                by changing the boot command line using grub's interactive mode: </para>
            <itemizedlist>
                <listitem> When you see the GRUB Loading message, press ESC to get to the grub menu.
                    Here, you will see several lines with kernel descriptions in them: select the
                    one that does not say '''recovery''' using the arrow keys. </listitem>
                <listitem> Press e to edit the commands associated with that kernel. This will bring
                    up another screen with various options, the one you are looking for has kernel
                    in it. Using the arrow keys, select the line with kernel in it and press e to
                    edit the line. </listitem>
                <listitem> This will take you to a screen with the contents of the line in it, just
                    add your new command at the end, then press enter. </listitem>
                <listitem> You will be returned to the previous menu and you should be able to see
                    your altered boot options added to the line you edited (unless the boor command
                    line is too long). Press b to boot using the edited boot command. </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
            <para> Ubuntu will now load with your new option enabled. </para>
        </sect2>
        <sect2>
            <title>How do I permanently change the options grub uses to boot Ubuntu?</title>
            <para> Ok, so you have used the above technique and found that you need to permanently
                make a change to the grub parameters, here is what you need to do. </para>
            <itemizedlist>
                <listitem> Edit /boot/grub/menu.lst (e.g., sudo gedit /boot/grub/menu.lst) </listitem>
                <listitem> Find the line which looks like: <screen>kopt root=/dev/hda1 ro</screen>
                </listitem>
                <listitem> Add your parameters to the end of the line </listitem>
                <listitem> Save your changesRun sudo update-grub </listitem>
                <listitem> Run sudo update-grub </listitem>
                <listitem> Reboot </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
        </sect2>
        <sect2>
            <title>How do I change the Login Screen image?</title>
            <itemizedlist>
                <listitem> Computer -&gt; System Configuration -&gt; Login Screen Setup </listitem>
                <listitem> Enter your password if prompted </listitem>
                <listitem> Choose the Graphical greeter tab </listitem>
                <listitem> Select an alternate theme </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
        </sect2>
        <sect2>
            <title>How do I change the Splash Screen image?</title>
            <itemizedlist>
                <listitem> applications -&gt; System Tools -&gt; Configuration Editor </listitem>
                <listitem> Choose /applications/gnome-session/options from the tree on the left </listitem>
                <listitem> Change the splash_image key to (e.g.) splash/ubuntu-logo-508x340.png </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
            <warning>
                <title>Careful</title>
                <para> The above does not work for me on a post-RC Warty system. It says pairs and
                    schemes cannot be edited, and refuses to change anything. What does work IME is
                    disabling the splash by way of Computer / Desktop Preferences / Sessions,
                    unchecking the show splash item. MartinManey </para>
            </warning>
        </sect2>
    </sect1>
</chapter>
