<chapter id="nonclassfaq">
		<title>Don't know</title>
	<highlights>
		<para>These questions are not classified. E.g. the rest.</para>
	</highlights>


	<!--
	    Don't know
	-->

	<sect1 id="sec-Don't know">
		<title>Don't know</title>
		<sect2>
			<title>Is the Warty artwork final?</title>
			<para>
				During the Preview Release we are using placeholder artwork and
				icons while the art team finishes the theme for the Warty
				release. The final artwork will be dropped into the final few
				release candidate CD's for Warty Warthog, and then shipped with
				the Final build.
			</para>
		</sect2>
	
		<sect2>
			<title>What is the Ubuntu Monthly Calendar background?</title>
			<para>
				It's an image in the Human theme that will be changed once a
				month to give you a fresh desktop background.
			</para>
			<para>
				All months seen so far are also selectable so you can go back
				and select an older background that you liked without it
				changing at the end of the month.
			</para>
		</sect2>

		<sect2>
			<title>Does the Ubuntu Live CD include everything in the normal installed version?</title>
			<para>
				Yes, it does. The packages installed on the Live CD are
				identical to those installed in the normal default installation
				of Ubuntu. During the preview release, there might be a
				difference in the version of the packages, as we build new
				releases of the Live CD and Install CD at different times so
				the packages might be slightly different versions, but once we
				release they will be the same.
			</para>
			<para>
				One difference we can't improve at this stage is the way the
				Live CD and Install CD handle their auto-detection. Because
				they use slightly different systems for auto-detection, things
				that work perfectly on one might not work on the other, like
				sound or X resolution guessing. In general, the installation
				system gives you more room to tweak your config to work exactly
				the way you want it.
			</para>
		</sect2>
	</sect1>
</chapter>	
