<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.3//EN" 
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.3/docbookx.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % globalent SYSTEM "../../../libs/global.ent">
%globalent;
<!ENTITY % cdo-C SYSTEM "../../../libs/cdo-C.ent">
%cdo-C;
<!ENTITY % kde SYSTEM "../../libs/kde.ent">
%kde;
<!ENTITY % kde-menus-C SYSTEM "../../libs/kde-menus-C.ent">
%kde-menus-C;
<!ENTITY % kde-general SYSTEM "/usr/share/apps/ksgmltools2/customization/obsolete/general.entities">
%kde-general;
<!ENTITY % xinclude SYSTEM "../../../libs/xinclude.mod">
%xinclude;
<!ENTITY language "en">
]>
<article id="office" status="complete">
<articleinfo>
<title>Office</title>
&klegalnotice;
<abstract>
<para>
This chapter contains information on the installed and available Office Suites
for Kubuntu.
</para>
</abstract>
</articleinfo>

<!-- OPENOFFIC.ORG -->
<sect1 id="openoffice-suite" status="complete">
<title>OpenOffice.org Suite</title>

<para>
The default office application is OpenOffice.org 2.  This is the second major
release of the popular office suite that includes Writer, Calc, Draw, Impress,
and Math.  This suite is the open source equivalent of the Microsoft Office
suite and each application corresponds to a similar product in that line.  Calc
is very similar to Excel, Writer is the same for Word, Impress is PowerPoint,
and Base functions similarly to Access.  OpenOffice.org can handle all but
Microsoft Access files without problems.
</para>

<para>
While all of these applications are installed by default, Kubuntu has chosen to
rename the titles that are listed in the <application>KMenu</application> to
better reflect how these applications are used and in some cases have removed
them from the <application>KMenu</application> entirely.  For more details about
the OpenOffice.org suite, visit <ulink
url="http://www.openoffice.org">OpenOffice.org homepage</ulink>.
</para>

<orderedlist>
<listitem>
<para>
OpenOffice.org Impress, or Presentation, provides the capability to create slide
presentations. Most PowerPoint files may be opened and edited in Impress.
OpenOffice.org Impress can be launched by going to &menuooimpress;.
</para>
</listitem>

<listitem>
<para>
OpenOffice.org Calc, Spreadsheets, is a fully featured spreadsheet program. The
module supports multiple spreadsheets, built-in functions and can read most
Microsoft Excel documents. OpenOffice.org Calc can be launched by going to
&menuoocalc;.
</para>
</listitem>

<listitem>
<para>
Open Office Writer, or Word Processor, is a fully featured word processor that
can create simple or complex documents. Writer can open most Microsoft Word
documents and can save in the .doc format. OpenOffice.org Writer can be launched
by going to &menuoowriter;.
</para>
</listitem>

<listitem>
<para>
OpenOffice.org Draw provides complex functionality to allow the creation of
drawings, diagrams, charts, and other business presentations. The program is
object oriented and allows for layering of various panes of work. OpenOffice.org
Draw can be launched from within any other OpenOffice application or by pressing
<keycombo><keycap>Alt</keycap><keycap>F2</keycap></keycombo> and typing
<userinput>oodraw</userinput> and pressing the <guibutton>OK</guibutton> button.
</para>
</listitem>

<listitem>
<para>
OpenOffice.org Math allows the user to create and assemble math-oriented
documents. There are special functions here that allow the creation of
mathematical formulas and table nomenclature not easily assembled in the
standard Writer application. OpenOffice.org Math can be launched from within any
other OpenOffice application or by pressing
<keycombo><keycap>Alt</keycap><keycap>F2</keycap></keycombo> and typing
<userinput>oomath</userinput> and pressing the <guibutton>OK</guibutton> button.
</para>
</listitem>
</orderedlist>
</sect1>

<!-- KEXI (DATABASE) -->
<sect1 id="database" status="draft">
<title>Database Application</title>

<para>
Kubuntu no longer ships with a default database application, however you have
to options in which to choose from.
<itemizedlist>
<listitem>
<para>
<application>OpenOffice.org Base</application> is the database application
created by the same group that creates the OpenOffice.org suite.
<application>OpenOffice.org Base</application> is in the
<emphasis>Main</emphasis> repository. Please refer to the <ulink type="help"
url="help:/kubuntu/add-applications">Adding Applications</ulink> documentation
for help on installation.
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
<application>Kexi</application> is your choice for a database application. Kexi
is part of the KDE <application>KOffice</application> suite and tends to
integrate better within KDE. <application>Kexi</application> is in the
<emphasis>Main</emphasis> repository. Please refer to the <ulink type="help"
url="help:/kubuntu/add-applications">Adding Applications</ulink> documentation
for help on installation.
</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
It is recommended you try both applications in order to see which one works
best in your situation.
</para>
</sect1>

<!-- KMYMONEY2 -->
<sect1 id="kmymoney2" status="complete">
<title>KMyMoney2 Personal Finance</title>

<para>
<application>KMyMoney2</application> is an excellent personal and/or business
cash management application similar to Quicken or Microsoft Money. Quicken QIF
import and export is supported within accounts so KMyMoney2 can read files
exported from other programs or downloaded from online banking institutions.
</para>

<procedure>
<step>
<para>
Install the <application>kmymoney2</application> package. Please refer to the
<ulink type="help" url="help:/kubuntu/add-applications/">Adding
Applications</ulink> documentation for help on installation.
</para>
</step>
<step>
<para>
Open <application>KMyMoney2</application> by going to &menukmymoney;
</para>
</step>
</procedure>
</sect1>

<sect1 id="kivio" status="complete">
<title>Kivio Flowchart and Diagram Editor</title>

<para>
<application>Kivio</application> is a flowchart and diagram editor for creating
and editing organizational charts, flowcharts, ERDs, or other kinds of diagrams.
It is analagous to Gnome <application>Dia</application> and Microsoft Visio.
</para>

<procedure>
<step>
<para>
Install the <application>kivio</application> package. Please refer to the
<ulink type="help" url="help:/kubuntu/add-applications">Adding
Applications</ulink> documentation for help on installation.
</para>
</step>

<step>
<para>
Open <application>Kivio</application> by going to &menukivio;.
</para>
</step>
</procedure>
</sect1>

<sect1 id="scribus" status="draft">
<title>Scribus Desktop Publisher</title>

<para>
<application>Scribus</application> is an open-source desktop publisher similar
in idea to that of Microsoft Publisher. Currently there is no import filter
available that will allow you to open Publisher, Quark, Indesign, or other
desktop top publishing files. There are some work arounds for doing so, however
the outcome may not be what you are expecting.
<application>Scribus</application> is available in the
<emphasis>Main</emphasis> repository. Please refer to the <ulink type="help"
url="help:/kubuntu/add-applications">Adding Applications</ulink> documentation
for help on installation.
</para>

<para>
Further information on <application>Scribus</application> is available at
<ulink type="http" url="http://www.scribus.net" />.
</para>
</sect1>
</article>
