<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.3//EN" 
	"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.3/docbookx.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % globalent SYSTEM "../../../libs/global.ent">
%globalent;
<!ENTITY % genericent SYSTEM "../../libs/generic.ent">
%genericent;
<!ENTITY % cdo-C SYSTEM "../../../libs/cdo-C.ent">
%cdo-C;
<!ENTITY % gnome-menus-C SYSTEM "../../../ubuntu/libs/gnome-menus-C.ent">
%gnome-menus-C;
<!ENTITY % xinclude SYSTEM "../../../libs/xinclude.mod">
%xinclude;
<!ENTITY language "&EnglishAmerican;">
<!ENTITY ubuntu '<phrase>Ubuntu</phrase>'>
]>
<chapter id="installation" status="review">
	<title>Installation</title>
  <para>The quick overview of the Ubuntu Server &distro-rev; is explained in
  this chapter. For detailed instructions, please refer to the Ubuntu Linux
  Installation Guide.</para>
	<sect1 id="preparing-to-install" status="review">
		<title>Preparing to Install</title>
    <para>
      This section explains various aspects to consider before starting the
      installation. </para>
    		<sect2 id="system-requirements" status="review">
    			<title>System Requirements</title>
    			<para>Ubuntu Server &distro-rev; supports three (3) major architectures: Intel x86, AMD64, and PowerPC. Depending on your needs, you might manage with less than some of the recommended hardware listed in the table below. However, most users risk being frustrated if they ignore these suggestions.</para>
				<table>
				<title>Recommended Minimum Requirements</title>
					<tgroup cols="2">
						<colspec colname="1"/>
						<colspec colname="2"/>
						<colspec colname="3"/>
						<thead>
							<row>
								<entry><para>Install Type</para></entry>
								<entry><para>RAM</para></entry>
								<entry><para>Hard Drive Space</para></entry>
							</row>
						</thead>
						<tbody>
							<row>
								<entry><para>Server</para></entry>
								<entry><para>64 megabytes</para></entry>
								<entry><para>500 megabytes</para></entry>
							</row>
						</tbody>
					</tgroup>
				</table>
				<para>Here are some common Ubuntu &distro-rev; system configurations.
        Once again, the size of the installation will greatly depend on
        the services you install during setup. For most administrators,
        the default services are suitable enough for general server
        use.</para>
				<variablelist>
					<varlistentry>
						<term><emphasis role="bold">Server</emphasis></term>
						<listitem><para>This is a small server profile, which provides a common base for all sorts of server applications. It's minimal and designed to have the desired services added on top, such as file/print services, web hosting, email hosting, etc. For these services at least 500MB of disk space would suffice, but consider adding more space depending on the services you'd like to host with your server.</para></listitem>
					</varlistentry>
				</variablelist>
				<para>Remember that these sizes don't include all the other materials which are usually to be found, such as user files, mail, and data. It is always best to be generous when considering the space for your own files and data.</para>
    		</sect2>
      <sect2 id="backing-up" status="review">
        <title>Backing Up</title>
          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>
              Before you start, make sure to back up every file that is
              now on your system. If this is the first time a
              non-native operating system has been installed on your
              computer, it's quite likely you will need to re-partition
              your disk to make room for Ubuntu Server &distro-rev;.  
			  Anytime you partition your disk, you should be prepared to 
			  lose everything on the disk should you make a mistake, or 
			  something goes wrong during partitioning such as power 
			  loss to the system.  The programs used in installation are 
			  quite reliable, and most have seen years of use, but they 
			  also perform destructive actions, and one mistake in use 
			  can result in loss of your valuable data.
              </para>
              <para>

                If you are creating a multi-boot system, make sure that
                you have the distribution media of any other present
                operating systems on hand. Especially if you
                repartition your boot drive, you might find that you
                have to reinstall your operating system's boot loader,
                or in many cases the whole operating system itself and
                all files on the affected partitions. 
              </para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>
      </sect2>
    </sect1>
	<sect1 id="installing-from-cd" status="review">
		<title>Installing from CD</title>
          <para>
          Insert your installation CD into your CD-ROM drive and reboot
          the computer. The installation system is started immediately
          when booting from the CD-ROM. Once initialized, your first
          screen will appear.
          </para>
          <para>
          At this point, read the text on the screen. You may want to
          read the help screen provided by the installation system. To
          do this, press F1.
          </para>
          <para>
            We will be performing a server installation, so just enter
            <quote>server</quote> and press Enter. The installation process
            will be started. During the initial phase, hardware and
            configuration information will be detected and collected.
            Running messages will be displayed. Next, the installation
            process will be continued. 
          </para>
    </sect1>
	</chapter>
