<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE preface PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.3//EN" 
	"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.3/docbookx.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % globalent SYSTEM "../../../libs/global.ent">
%globalent;
<!ENTITY % cdo-C SYSTEM "../../../libs/cdo-C.ent">
%cdo-C;
<!ENTITY % gnome-menus-C SYSTEM "../../../ubuntu/libs/gnome-menus-C.ent">
%gnome-menus-C;
<!ENTITY % xinclude SYSTEM "../../../libs/xinclude.mod">
%xinclude;
<!ENTITY language "&EnglishAmerican;">
<!ENTITY ubuntu '<phrase>Ubuntu</phrase>'>
]>
<preface id="serverguide" status="review">
        	<title>Preface</title>
		<sect1 id="conventions" status="review">
			<title>Conventions</title>
			<para>
				<emphasis role="bold">The following admonitions will be found
					throughout the book:
				</emphasis>
			</para>
			<note>
				<para>A note presents interesting, sometimes technical, pieces
					of information related to the surrounding discussion.
				</para>
			</note>
			<tip>
				<para>A tip offers advice or an easier way of doing
					something.
				</para>
			</tip>
			<caution>
				<para>A caution alerts the reader to potential problems and
					helps avoid them.
				</para>
				<!-- Direct referencing in a non-instructional context is bad. -->
			</caution>
			<warning>
				<para>A warning advises the reader of a hazard condition that
					may arise in a given scenario.
				</para>
			</warning>
			<para>
				<emphasis role="bold">Cross-reference conventions for print will
					be displayed as follows:
				</emphasis>
			</para>
			<itemizedlist>
				<listitem>
					<para>
						Internal references will look like this:
						The numeral contained within square braces is the [page number].
					</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>External references, such as those pointing to a Web
						site, will look like <ulink url="http://www.ubuntulinux.org">this</ulink>.
					</para>
				</listitem>
			</itemizedlist>
			<note>
				<para>PDF, HTML, and XHTML versions of this document will use
					hyperlinks to handle cross-referencing.
				</para>
			</note>
			<para>
				<emphasis role="bold">Type conventions will be displayed as
					follows:
				</emphasis>
			</para>
			<itemizedlist>
				<listitem>
					<para>File names or paths to directories will be shown in
						<filename>monospace</filename> type.
					</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>Packages that need to be installed will be shown as:</para>
					<para>Category &gt; PackageName</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>
						Commands that you type at a <application>Terminal</application>
						prompt will
						be shown as:
					</para>
					<para>
						<!-- NOTE: the spaces before </screen> are significant, and will be in the html output. -->
						<screen>command to type                                 </screen>
					</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>When variables, parameters, SGML tags, etc. are
						contained within a paragraph of text, they will be shown
						in <filename>monospace</filename> type. Otherwise, they
						will use the normal type.
					</para>
				</listitem>
			</itemizedlist>
			<para>
				<emphasis role="bold">Code conventions:</emphasis>
			</para>
			<itemizedlist>
				<listitem>
					<para>Code and mark-up samples will be formatted in a grey
						block.
					</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>Sometimes, lines of code or mark-up examples will be
						longer than the page width. To avoid having them run off
						the page, the slash character &quot;\&quot; is
						used to denote a soft line break. This means that the
						line of code is meant to be on one line, but for print
						formatting, it has been broken across two or more
						lines.
					</para>
				</listitem>
			</itemizedlist>
			<para>
				<emphasis role="bold">Text editing:</emphasis>
			</para>
			<itemizedlist>
				<listitem>
					<para>You can use the editor of your choice to edit the
          configuration files mentioned in appropriate sections.</para>
				</listitem>
			</itemizedlist>
		</sect1>
		<sect1 id="contributing" status="review">
			<title>Contributing and Feedback</title>
			<para>
				This book is developed by the <ulink
					url="&ubuntu-doc-team;">Ubuntu Documentation
					Team
				</ulink>. The source code for this book is written using
				Docbook XML and is kept in a Subversion code revision control
				repository. Everyone is able to checkout a copy of the source
				code and provide updates in the form of patches. Another way of
				contributing is by sending ideas or comments to the Ubuntu
				Documentation Team mailing list. Information about the team, its
				mailing lists, projects, etc. can be found on the <ulink
					url="&ubuntu-doc-team;">Ubuntu Documentation Team
					Website
				</ulink>.
			</para>
 		       <para>As the reader of this publication, you are our most important critic. We welcome your input
                       and ask that you let us know what we are doing right and what we are doing wrong.</para>
                       <para>We have tried to compile this publication with the utmost attention to detail. However,
                       this does not mean it is error-free. For this reason, we would like to solicit your
		       assistance in improving the quality of this publication by asking you to report all problems
		       you may encounter, regardless of nature. To report a problem or make a suggestion, please file
		       a bug report at the <ulink url="&ubuntu-bugzilla;">Ubuntu Bugzilla</ulink>, under the
		       &apos;Documentation&apos; category.</para>
		       <para>Many thanks,</para>
		       <para>-Your Ubuntu Documentation Team</para>
		</sect1>
</preface>
