<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.3//EN" 
	"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.3/docbookx.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % globalent SYSTEM "../../../libs/global.ent">
%globalent;
<!ENTITY % cdo-C SYSTEM "../../../libs/cdo-C.ent">
%cdo-C;
<!ENTITY language "&EnglishAmerican;">
]>
<article lang="&language;" id="x01">
    <title>Release Notes</title>
    <subtitle>EdEdubuntu &distro-rev; &quot;&distro-version;&quot;</subtitle>
    <articleinfo>
        <revhistory>
            <revision>
                <revnumber>1.1</revnumber>
                <date>Feb 18, 2006</date>
                <authorinitials>JSG</authorinitials>
                <revdescription>
                    <para>Version &distro-rev;</para>
                </revdescription>
            </revision>
        </revhistory>
        &copyright; 
        &disclaimer; 
        &legalnotice;
        &publisher; 
        <authorgroup>
        		<author>
        			<firstname>Oliver</firstname>
        			<surname>Grawert</surname>
        			<email>ogra@ubuntu.com</email>	
        		</author>
            <author>
                <firstname>Jerome</firstname>
                <surname>Gotangco</surname>
                <email>jgotangco@ubuntu.com</email>
            </author>
        </authorgroup>
        <abstract>
            <para>These are the Release Notes for EdEdubuntu &distro-rev;</para>
        </abstract>
    </articleinfo>
    		<mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
                <imagedata
                    fileref="../../images/&language;/edubuntu_logo_png.png"
                    format="PNG"/>
            </imageobject>
        	</mediaobject>
    <para>Edubuntu is a Linux distribution for your desktop or server, with a fast and easy install, regular releases, a tight selection of excellent applications installed by default, and every other software you can imagine available from the Internet. Edubuntu provides security updates for 18 months after each release, and professional technical support is available from many companies around the world.</para>
<para>These Release Notes cover new features in Edubuntu &distro-rev;, download and installation notes, known issues, and frequently asked questions. Please read these notes before, during, and after installation and configuration of Edubuntu &distro-rev; before reporting bugs in <ulink url="http://launchpad.net/malone">Launchpad</ulink>.</para>
<para>We hope you enjoy Edubuntu &distro-rev;.</para>
    <sect1 id="sect1-whatsnew" status="review">
        <title>What's New</title>
        <para>Edubuntu is released <emphasis>regulary and predictably</emphasis>. Since our October 2005 debut release (Edubuntu 5.10), we've made a lot of improvements to give you the best educational environment with free software, the biggest of which is that Edubuntu &distro-rev; is now available on the PowerPC platform! Much of what Ubuntu offers is also available to Edubuntu with some additional software:</para>
        <sect2 id="desktop" status="review">
            <title>On The Desktop</title>
            <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para>A set of <emphasis role="bold">selected educational</emphasis> apps containing:</para>
                    <orderedlist>
                    		<listitem><para>most of the <emphasis>kdeedu</emphasis> suite</para></listitem>
                    		<listitem><para>Gcompris</para></listitem>
                    		<listitem><para>Scribus desktop publishing</para></listitem>
                    		<listitem><para>Blender 3D Modeller</para></listitem>
                    		<listitem><para>Dia Diagram Editor</para></listitem>
                    		<listitem><para>Kino Video Editor</para></listitem>
                    		<listitem><para>and lots more!</para></listitem>
                    </orderedlist>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Fresh, colorful artwork for the desktop with support for three themes for three age groups</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Full LTSP client functionality by default</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                		<para>New documentation (<emphasis>Edubuntu &distro-rev; Quick Guide</emphasis> and <emphasis>Edubuntu &distro-rev; Cookbook</emphasis>)</para>
                </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
            </sect2>
            <sect2 id="server" status="review">
            	<title>On the Server</title>
            	<itemizedlist>
            			<listitem>
            					<para>Standalone Classroom server installed by default, based on the brand-new Ubuntu thin-client infrastructure developed in cooperation with the LTSP project</para>
            			</listitem>
            			<listitem>
            					<para>Simple NFS root setup with automatic hardware detection through initramfs-tools</para>
            			</listitem>
            			<listitem>
            					<para>Support for up to 4 gigabytes of RAM by default on 32-bit architectures</para>
            			</listitem>
            			<listitem>
            					<para>Kernel support for cluster filesystems (OCFS2 and GFS)</para>
            			</listitem>
            	</itemizedlist>
            </sect2>
            <sect2 id="hardware-support" status="review">
            	<title>Hardware Support Improvements</title>
            	<itemizedlist>
            			<listitem>
            					<para>Linux &linux-kernel-version; with many updated drivers from third parties</para>
            			</listitem>
            			<listitem>
            					<para>HP all-in-one printer/scanner devices are supported out of the box</para>
            			</listitem>
            			<listitem>
            					<para>Bluetooth input devices (such as keyboards and mice) are supported out of the box</para>
            			</listitem>
            			<listitem>
            					<para>Multiple audio devices are handled more gracefully (and one can easily select the default device)</para>
            			</listitem>
            	</itemizedlist>		
            </sect2>
            <sect2 id="installation" status="review">
            	<title>Installation</title>
            	<itemizedlist>
            			<listitem>
            					<para>Automated installation of the thin-client environment by default</para>
            			</listitem>
            			<listitem>
            					<para>Easy installation of the ltsp server by default with as few questions as possible</para>
            			</listitem>
            			<listitem>
            					<para>Optional workstation install for standalone workstations (just type <emphasis role="bold">workstation</emphasis> at the CD boot prompt)</para>
            			</listitem>
            	</itemizedlist>
            </sect2>
            <sect2 id="under-the-hood" status="review">
            	<title>&quot;Under the Hood&quot;</title>
            	<itemizedlist> 
            	<listitem> 
            			<para>gcc &gcc-version;</para>
            	</listitem> 
            	<listitem> 
            			<para>glibc &glibc-version;</para>
            	</listitem> 
            	<listitem> 
            			<para>New early userspace infrastructure based on <emphasis>initramfs-tools</emphasis></para>
            	</listitem> 
            	<listitem> 
            			<para>More modular X.org packaging</para>
            	</listitem>
            	</itemizedlist>
            	 <para>As always, Edubuntu includes the very best of the <emphasis role="bold">100% free/libre</emphasis> application software world, and each new release incorporates countless new features and bugfixes from the global development community.</para>
            </sect2>
    </sect1>
    <sect1 id="sect1-downlading-installing" status="review">
    		<title>Downlading and Installing</title>
    		<sect2 id="system-requirements" status="review">
    			<title>System Requirements</title>
    			<para>Edubuntu &distro-rev; supports three (3) major architectures: Intel x86, AMD64, and PowerPC. Depending on your needs, you might manage with less than some of the recommended hardware listed in the table below. However, most users risk being frustrated if they ignore these suggestions.</para>
				<table>
				<title>Recommended Minimum Requirements</title>
					<tgroup cols="3">
						<colspec colname="1"/>
						<colspec colname="2"/>
						<colspec colname="3"/>
						<thead>
							<row>
								<entry><para>Install Type</para></entry>
								<entry><para>RAM</para></entry>
								<entry><para>Hard Drive Space</para></entry>
							</row>
						</thead>
						<tbody>
							<row>
								<entry><para>Desktop</para></entry>
								<entry><para>128 megabytes</para></entry>
								<entry><para>2 gigabytes</para></entry>
							</row>
							<row>
								<entry><para>Server</para></entry>
								<entry><para>64 megabytes</para></entry>
								<entry><para>500 megabytes</para></entry>
							</row>
						</tbody>
					</tgroup>
				</table>
				<para>Here are some common Edubuntu &distro-rev; system configurations. Once again, the size of the installation will greatly depend on the software you install during setup. For most users, the default applications are suitable for general use.</para>
				<variablelist>
					<varlistentry>
						<term><emphasis role="bold">Desktop</emphasis></term>
						<listitem><para>A standard desktop machine, including the X window system, full desktop environment, sound, office suite, email clients, etc. You'll need about 2 gigabytes of hard drive space using the standard desktop task.</para></listitem>
					</varlistentry>
					<varlistentry>
						<term><emphasis role="bold">Server</emphasis></term>
						<listitem><para>This is a small server profile, which provides a common base for all sorts of server applications. It's minimal and designed to have the desired services added on top, such as file/print services, web hosting, email hosting, etc. For these services as little as 500MB of disk space would suffice, but consider adding more space depending on the services you'd like to host with your server.</para></listitem>
					</varlistentry>
				</variablelist>
				<para>Remember that these sizes don't include all the other materials which are usually to be found, such as user files, mail, and data. It is always best to be generous when considering the space for your own files and data.</para>
    		</sect2>
    		<sect2 id="downloading-Edubuntu" status="review">
    			<title>Downloading EdEdubuntu &distro-rev;</title>
    			<para>You can download EdEdubuntu &distro-rev; from the following mirrors located worldwide:</para>
    			<itemizedlist>
    				<listitem>
    					<para>United States: <ulink url="http://us.releases.ubuntu.com/edubuntu/&distro-rev;/">http://us.releases.ubuntu.com/edubuntu/&distro-rev;</ulink>
</para>
    				</listitem>
    				<listitem>
    					<para>Europe: <ulink url="http://se.releases.ubuntu.com/edubuntu/&distro-rev;">http://se.releases.ubuntu.com/edubuntu/&distro-rev;</ulink></para>
    				</listitem>
    				<listitem>
    					<para>United Kingdom: <ulink url="http://releases.ubuntu.com/edubuntu/&distro-rev;">http://releases.ubuntu.com/edubuntu/&distro-rev;</ulink></para>
    				</listitem>
    				<listitem>
    					<para>Rest of the World: <ulink url="http://releases.ubuntu.com/edubuntu/&distro-rev;">http://releases.ubuntu.com/edubuntu/&distro-rev;</ulink>
</para>
    				</listitem>
    			</itemizedlist>
    			<para>You can also download all architecture types of Edubuntu &distro-rev; using Bittorrent or Jigdo.</para>
    		</sect2>
    		<sect2 id="installing-Edubuntu" status="review">
    			<title>Installing EdEdubuntu &distro-rev;</title>
    			<para>Once you have a copy of Edubuntu &distro-rev;, follow these instructions to install:</para>
    			<sect3 id="default-mode">
    				<title>Default Mode</title>
    				<para>The default installation mode provides the best computing experience with Edubuntu &distro-rev;. You'll have a fully functioning desktop with the default settings. Make sure your computer meets the recommended minimum requirements when installing in Default Mode.</para>
    				<orderedlist>
						<listitem>
    						<para>Place the Edubuntu &distro-rev; Install CD in the CD-ROM Drive and power on the computer.</para>
    					</listitem>
    					<listitem>
    						<para>At <emphasis role="bold">boot:</emphasis>, press Enter.</para>
    					</listitem>
    					<listitem>
    						<para>The Edubuntu &distro-rev; installer will run. Follow the on-screen instructions to start the installation.</para>
    					</listitem>
    					<listitem>
    						<para>Once the installation is complete, the login screen will appear and you are ready to use Edubuntu &distro-rev;</para>
    					</listitem>
    				</orderedlist>
    			</sect3>
    			<sect3 id="server-mode">
    				<title>Server Mode</title>
    				<para>The Server Mode provides a base system suitable for installing server applications. You can add more services as needed after installation. Make sure your computer meets the recommended minimum specifications when installing in Default Mode.</para>
    				<orderedlist>
						<listitem>
    						<para>Place the Edubuntu &distro-rev; Install CD in the CD-ROM Drive and power on the computer.</para>
    					</listitem>
    					<listitem>
    						<para>At <emphasis role="bold">boot:</emphasis>, type <emphasis>server</emphasis>, and press Enter.</para>
    					</listitem>
    					<listitem>
    						<para>The Edubuntu &distro-rev; installer will run. Follow the on-screen instructions to start the installation.</para>
    					</listitem>
    					<listitem>
    						<para>Once the installation is complete, you will be informed that your Edubuntu &distro-rev; is ready for use.</para>
    					</listitem>
    				</orderedlist>
    			</sect3>
    			<sect3 id="oem-mode">
    				<title>OEM Mode</title>
    				<para>Edubuntu &distro-rev; can be pre-installed to computers for resale and redistribution. Make sure the computer meets the recommended minimum specifications when installing in OEM Mode.</para>
    				<orderedlist>
    					<listitem>
    						<para>Place the Edubuntu &distro-rev; Install CD in the CD-ROM Drive and power on the computer.</para>
    					</listitem>
    					<listitem>
    						<para>At <emphasis role="bold">boot:</emphasis>, type <emphasis>oem</emphasis> and press Enter.</para>
    					</listitem>
    					<listitem>
    						<para>The Edubuntu &distro-rev; installer will run. Follow the on-screen instructions to start the installation.</para>
    					</listitem>
    					<listitem>
    						<para>Once the installation is complete, you will be informed that Edubuntu &distro-rev; has been fully installed and the computer is ready for shipping.</para>
    					</listitem>
    					<listitem>
    						<para>You can also run a system test to check if the installation of Edubuntu &distro-rev; OEM mode went smoothly. The system test will run the Edubuntu Hardware Database and will check that your hardware is configured correctly.</para>
    					</listitem>
    					<listitem>
    						<para>On the first boot after installation, you will be asked to select your language, keyboard layout, and time zone configuration, and create your first user account. The first user account created has administrative rights via <emphasis>sudo</emphasis>. Since Edubuntu &distro-rev; is a multi-user system, you can create more user accounts as needed.</para>
    					</listitem>
    				</orderedlist>
    			</sect3>
    		</sect2>
    </sect1>
	<!--
    <sect1 id="sect1-known-issues" status="review">
        <title>Known Issues</title>
        <para>XXX To add known issues here</para>
    </sect1>
	-->
    <sect1 id="sect1-FAQ" status="review">
    		<title>Frequently Asked Questions</title>
    		<para></para>
    		<note><para>You can read more in-depth FAQs in the <ulink url="///usr/share/Edubuntu-docs/generic/faqguide/C/faqguide.xml">Edubuntu &distro-rev; FAQ Guide</ulink>
.</para></note>

    </sect1>
    <sect1 id="sect1-feedback" status="review">
    		<title>Getting Help and Technical Support</title>
    		<para>Edubuntu &distro-rev; gives users an easy way to get help in most applications installed by default. Once you have an active Internet connection, from an open application, just click on
    		<menuchoice>
    			<guimenu>Help</guimenu>
    			<guimenuitem>Get Help Online</guimenuitem>
    		</menuchoice>
    		and you'll be connected to a web page that gives you help and support options for the application.
    		</para>
    		<para>Technical Support for Edubuntu &distro-rev; is available from a variety of sources: from the community, from Canonical Ltd, from recognized organizations, and from developers directly through open web forums, mailing lists, and IRC channels:</para>
    		<itemizedlist>
    			<listitem>
    				<para><ulink url="http://www.ubuntu.com/support">http://www.ubuntu.com/support</ulink>
</para>
    			</listitem>
    		</itemizedlist>
    		<para>If you have a question, or if you think you may have found a bug but aren&apos;t sure, first try asking on the #edubuntu IRC channel on &irc-network;, or on the Edubuntu Users mailing list:</para>
    		<itemizedlist>
    			<listitem>
    				<para><ulink url="http://lists.ubuntu.com/mailman/listinfo/edubuntu-devel">http://lists.ubuntu.com/mailman/listinfo/edubuntu-devel</ulink>
</para>
    			</listitem>
    		</itemizedlist>
    </sect1>
    <sect1 id="sect-bugs">
    		<title>Reporting Bugs</title>
    		<para>Your comments, bug reports, patches and suggestions will help fix bugs and improve future Edubuntu releases. Please report bugs through <emphasis>Launchpad</emphasis>:</para>
    		<itemizedlist>
    			<listitem>
    				<para><ulink url="http://launchpad.net/malone">http://launchpad.net/malone</ulink>
</para>
    			</listitem>
    		</itemizedlist>
    </sect1>
    <sect1 id="sect-participate">
    		<title>Participate in Edubuntu</title>
    		<para>If you would like to help shape Edubuntu, take a look at the list of ways you can participate at:</para>
    		<itemizedlist>
    			<listitem>
    				<para><ulink url="http://wiki.edubuntu.org/EdubuntuCommunity">http://wiki.edubuntu.org/EdubuntuCommunity</ulink></para>
    			</listitem>
    		</itemizedlist>
    </sect1>
    <sect1 id="sect-moreinfo" status="review">
    		<title>More Information</title>
    		<para>You can find out more about Edubuntu and about the &distro-rev; release on our website, IRC channel, and wiki. If you're new to Edubuntu, please visit <ulink url="http://www.edubuntu.org">http://www.edubuntu.org</ulink>.</para>
			<para>To sign up for future Edubuntu announcements, please subscribe to Ubuntu's announcement list at <ulink url="http://lists.ubuntu.com/mailman/listinfo/ubuntu-announce">http://lists.ubuntu.com/mailman/listinfo/ubuntu-announce</ulink>.</para>
    </sect1>
</article>
