<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE part PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.3//EN" 
	"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.3/docbookx.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % xinclude SYSTEM "../../libs/xinclude.mod">
%xinclude;
<!ENTITY % globalent SYSTEM "../../libs/global.ent">
%globalent;
]>
<preface id="pref-userguide">
	<title>Preface</title>
	<para>This handbook is intended for users with little, if any, prior GNU/Linux-related experience.
	That said, its intent is not to exclude experienced users.</para>
	<para>Newcomers will be guided through the entire process of setting up an Ubuntu system for personal use, while experienced users will benefit from having a reference for learning to do things the "Ubuntu way".</para>
	
	<!-- Include common Ubuntu sections -->
	&conventions;
	&feedback;
	
	<sect1 id="sect-organization">
		<title>Book Organization</title>
		<para>This guide is divided into seven major sections:<itemizedlist>
			<listitem><link linkend="chIntroduction">Introducing Ubuntu and GNU/Linux</link></listitem>
			<listitem><link linkend="chInstalling">Installing the Ubuntu Operating System</link></listitem>
			<listitem><link linkend="chSettling">Getting Settled in Your New Ubuntu Environment</link></listitem>
			<listitem><link linkend="chCaring">Caring for Your Ubuntu System</link></listitem>
			<listitem><link linkend="chAdvanced">Advanced Ubuntu Usage</link></listitem>
			<listitem><link linkend="chServices">Using Ubuntu as a Network Server</link></listitem>
			<listitem><link linkend="chTroubleshooting">Troubleshooting - Help is Always Available</link></listitem>
		</itemizedlist></para>
		<para>Readers following this guide will begin by learning what GNU/Linux is, what Ubuntu is, and how to think about computing from a Linux user's point of view.
		Of course, this section is entirely for personal information and is not required to begin using Ubuntu.</para>
		<para>Next, readers will be prepared for the process of installing Ubuntu, then walked through the entire installation process, leaving no surprises.</para>
		<para>After that, readers will become acquainted with their new desktop environment, and be introduced to software likely to be part of their daily work and entertainment.</para>
		<para>Readers will then be informed about how to maintain their Ubuntu system, protecting it from attacks and keeping all their favourite software up to date.</para>
		<para>An introduction to the command line follows, teaching readers the basics of non-graphical system usage.</para>
		<para>Finally, readers will be provided with the information needed to begin serving web pages, sharing printers, administering their system remotely, and other like tasks.</para>
	</sect1>
	<sect1 id="sect-acknowledge">
		<title>Acknowledgements</title>
		<para>This handbook represents the efforts of everyone who has contributed to the Ubuntu community.
		Much of the information contained within these pages was found on mailing lists, in the Ubuntu Wiki, and gathered by listening to user requests.</para>
		<para>Credit for this book belongs to no one person, and like the Ubuntu project itself, it will continue to grow and evolve.</para>
		<para><emphasis role="bold"><emphasis role="italic">"This is a community project"</emphasis></emphasis></para>
	</sect1>
</preface>
