<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.3//EN"
	"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.3/docbookx.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % globalent SYSTEM "../../../libs/global.ent">
%globalent;
<!ENTITY % cdo-C SYSTEM "../../../libs/cdo-C.ent">
%cdo-C;
<!ENTITY % gnome-menus-C SYSTEM "../../../ubuntu/libs/gnome-menus-C.ent">
%gnome-menus-C;
<!ENTITY % xinclude SYSTEM "../../../libs/xinclude.mod">
%xinclude;
<!ENTITY language "en">
]>
<chapter id="bugs-chap" status="review">
	<title>Bugs</title>
	
	<para>One thing that you will almost certainly face as a packager is a bug, either in
		the software itself or in your packaging. Packaging bugs are often fairly easy and
		straightforward to fix.  However, as packagers often act as the initial contact
		for software bugs for the users of their distribution they also many time
		implement temporary fixes and are responsible for forwarding software bugs and
		fixes to the original (upstream) authors.</para>

	<sect1 status="review">
	  <title>Bug Tracking Systems</title>

	  <para> In order to track bugs (both software and packaging) many distributions have
		  developed bug tracking systems to manage the bug reports and notify the package
		  maintainers and reporters of changes. The table below shows some of the Debian
		  and &ubuntu; tools for tracking bugs.</para>

	<para><emphasis role="bold">Bug Tracking System</emphasis></para>
	<para>Debian : <ulink url="http://bugs.debian.org">http://bugs.debian.org</ulink></para>
	<para>&ubuntu; : <ulink url="http://launchpad.net/malone/distros/ubuntu">http://launchpad.net/malone/distros/ubuntu</ulink>				
	</para>
	<para><emphasis role="bold">Bugs For Specific Packages</emphasis></para>
	<para>Debian : http://bugs.debian.org/<emphasis>&lt;packagename&gt;</emphasis></para>
	<para>&ubuntu; : use search at &ubuntu; BTS </para>
	<para><emphasis role="bold">Bugs For Source Packages</emphasis></para>
	<para>Debian : http://bugs.debian.org/src:<emphasis>&lt;packagename&gt;</emphasis></para>
	<para>&ubuntu; : https://launchpad.net/distros/ubuntu/+source/<emphasis>&lt;packagename&gt;</emphasis>/+bugs</para>
	<para><emphasis role="bold">Package Information</emphasis></para>
	<para>Debian : <ulink url="http://packages.debian.org">http://packages.debian.org</ulink> or http://packages.qa.ubuntu.org/<emphasis>&lt;packagename&gt;</emphasis>
	</para>
	<para>&ubuntu; : <ulink	url="http://packages.ubuntu.com">http://package.ubuntu.com</ulink> or
	https://launchpad.net/distros/ubuntu/+source/<emphasis>&lt;packagename&gt;</emphasis>
	for source packages
	</para>
			
	</sect1>

	<sect1 status="review">
		<title>Bug Tips</title>

		<sect2>
			<title>Proper source package</title>
			
			<para>Assigning bugs to packages helps direct bug reports to the developer(s)
				most likely to be able to help. By ensuring that this information is
				accurate, you can increase the chances of the bug being fixed promptly.
				Often, it is unclear which package contains the bug, and in these cases it
				is appropriate to file the bug in Ubuntu. If a bug is assigned to a
				package which is clearly not correct, and you don't know the correct
				package, change it to Ubuntu.</para>

			<para>The correct package for bugs in the Linux kernel is linux, regardless of
				which particular package is in use (there are many packages which contain
				Linux kernels).</para>
		</sect2>
		
		<sect2>
			<title>Confirming problems</title> 

			<para>If a bug is marked as Unconfirmed, it is helpful for you to try to
				reproduce the problem, and record the results in Malone. If you are able
				to confirm the problem, you may change the status to Confirmed. If you are
				unable to confirm the problem, that is also useful information which
				should be recorded in a comment.  Forwarding bugs upstream</para>

			<para>You can forward bugs to the authors of the software (upstream), if</para>

			<itemizedlist>
				
				<listitem>
						<para>you made sure that the bug doesn't occur because of Ubuntu
							related changes,</para> </listitem>
				
				
				<listitem>
						<para>the change is too hard to be fixed by yourself or anyone
							else in the team.</para> </listitem>
			</itemizedlist>
				
			<para>If you do this, be sure to include all the necessary information, such
				as</para>
			
			<itemizedlist> 
				
				<listitem> <para>how to reproduce the bug</para> </listitem>

				<listitem> <para>which version is used (which version of dependent
						libraries, if the bug indicates problems there)</para> </listitem>

				<listitem><para>who reported it</para> </listitem> 

				<listitem> <para>where the whole conversation can be found</para>
				</listitem>

			</itemizedlist>
			
			<para>Make sure to also create a bug watch in Malone for this bug.</para>

		</sect2>

		<sect2>
			<title>How to Deal with Feature Requests</title>
			
			<para>If you feel that the bug reported is a feature request disguised as a
				bug report, please introduce the reporter gently to the Specification
				Process we have. Be sure to mention the following specification resources;
				FeatureSpecifications, SpecSpec, SpecTemplate and <ulink
					url="http://launchpad.net/specs"> http://launchpad.net/specs</ulink>
			</para>
		</sect2>

		<sect2>
			<title>How to deal with Support Requests</title>

			<para>If you feel that the bug reported is a support request disguised as a
				bug report, please introduce the reporter gently to the Support Tracker we
				have. Be sure to mention <ulink url="http://launchpad.net/support">
					http://launchpad.net/support</ulink> </para>
		</sect2>

		<sect2>
			<title>How to deal with suggestions for changing defaults</title>

			<para>If you feel that the bug reported is a suggestions for changing defaults
				disguised as a bug report, please kindly reroute the discussion to an
				appropriate mailing list or a discussion forum. If this has already been
				discussed and rejected, explain the reasons to the user and direct them to
				the corresponding discussion for further suggestions/comments.</para>
		</sect2>
		
		<sect2>
			<title>Finding Duplicates</title>

			<para>Finding duplicates of bugs is a very valuable contribution in the Bug
				community. Users sometimes don't know how to check if the same bug has
				already been filed, and sometimes they don't care. Weeding out simple ME
				TOO messages and aggregating information in one place is crucial to the
				process of fixing a bug.</para>

			<para>There are quite a few measures you can take to assist with this aspect,
				one way is to search for bugs filed for the same component, also try to
				rephrase your search, and concentrate on actions and words that describe
				the items involved to reproduce this crash.</para>

			<para><emphasis role="bold">Examples:</emphasis></para>

			<itemizedlist>
				<listitem><para>Easy ones: <ulink
							url="https://launchpad.net/malone/bugs/24932">DAAP
							support</ulink> is a duplicate of <ulink
							url="https://launchpad.net/malone/bugs/24860">please enable
							daap</ulink>.</para></listitem>
				<listitem><para>More difficult ones: <ulink
							url="https://launchpad.net/malone/bugs/24011">plug:spdif on
							emu10k1 gone after breezy upgrade</ulink> is a duplicate of
						<ulink url="https://launchpad.net/malone/bugs/21804"> Muted sound
							after dist-upgrade from Hoary to
							Breezy</ulink>.</para></listitem>
			</itemizedlist>

			<para>If you can't find it in the list of open bugs, you could try to find it
				in the list of closed ones. Don't feel discouraged, if you don't find
				duplicates fast in the beginning, after some time you will get to know the
				usual suspects, and learn how to more easily identify them.</para>

			<note><para>If you encounter a bug that has a terrible / unintelligible title,
					rephrase it, so people find it more easily.</para></note>

		</sect2>

		<sect2>
			<title>	Reminder of the Code of Conduct</title>
			
			<para>Note that the Code of Conduct applies to conversations in bug reports
				too. So if you observe people being disrespectful, please direct them to
				the <ulink
					url="http://www.ubuntu.com/community/conduct">Ubuntu Code
					of Conduct</ulink>.</para>

		</sect2>

		<sect2>
			<title>Managing Status</title>

			<para>As a reporter you usually don't have to take care of statuses. As a bug
				triager or developer it's an important tool to categorize bugs and have a
				good overview over the state of packages and software.</para>

			<para>Here's a brief list and explanation of the various statuses:</para>

			<itemizedlist>
				
				<listitem><para><emphasis role="bold">Unconfirmed:</emphasis> Bugs start
						with this status. Bugs marked Unconfirmed sometimes lack
						information, are not ready and are not confirmed yet, most of them
						are have not been triaged yet.</para></listitem>
				
				<listitem><para><emphasis role="bold">Needs Info:</emphasis> If you have
						to ask the reporter questions, please set this bug to "Needs
						Info". A regular task for Needs Info bugs is to ask back, if there
						are no answers and after a reasonable stage, close them saying "If
						you have more information on this bug, please
						reopen."</para></listitem>

				<listitem><para><emphasis role="bold">Rejected:</emphasis> Bugs marked as
						Rejected are closed. Be sure to triple-check a bug before you
						reject it.</para></listitem>

				<listitem><para><emphasis role="bold">Confirmed:</emphasis> Confirmed bugs
						require somebody else to confirm. Please don't confirm your own
						bugs.</para></listitem>

				<listitem><para><emphasis role="bold">In Progress:</emphasis> If you start
						working on a bug, set it to In Progress so people know someone is
						working on the bug.</para></listitem>
				  
				<listitem><para><emphasis role="bold">Fix Committed:</emphasis> For
						upstream projects this means the fix is in CVS/SVN/bzr or committed
						somewhere. For package maintainers it means that the changes are
						pending and to be uploaded soon (it is what PENDINGUPLOAD was in
						Bugzilla)</para></listitem>
    
				<listitem><para><emphasis role="bold">Fix Released:</emphasis> For
						upstream projects this means that a release tarball was announced
						and is publicly available. For package maintainers this means
						that a fix was uploaded. Please don't be hesitant to add a
						changelog as a comment, so people know what to look out
						for.</para></listitem>

			</itemizedlist>
		</sect2>

		<sect2>
			<title>Managing Severity</title>

			<para>Ubuntu uses the following guidelines for assigning severity:</para>

			<itemizedlist>

				<listitem><para><emphasis role="bold">Wishlist:</emphasis> a request to
						add a new feature to one of the programs in Ubuntu. Use this for
						bugs which aren't really bugs, but ideas for new features which do
						not yet exist.</para></listitem>

				<listitem><para><emphasis role="bold">Minor:</emphasis> bugs which affect
						functionality, but to a lesser extent than most
						bugs</para></listitem>
 
				<listitem><para><emphasis role="bold">Normal:</emphasis> a functionality
						bug of the standard variety. Most bugs are of "Normal"
						severity.</para></listitem>

				<listitem><para><emphasis role="bold">Major:</emphasis> a bug which has a
						severe impact on a small portion of Ubuntu users (estimated) or
						has a moderate impact on a large portion of Ubuntu users
						(estimated)</para></listitem>
	  
				<listitem><para><emphasis role="bold">Critical:</emphasis> a bug which has
						a severe impact on a large portion of Ubuntu
						users</para></listitem>

			</itemizedlist>
				
		</sect2>
		
		<sect2>
			<title>Target Milestone</title>

			<para>Don't change this field unless specifically instructed by a developer.
				In particular, do NOT use this field to record the release of Ubuntu in
				which the bug was observed: that is not its purpose! It is used by the
				release team when there is a reason to address the bug in a specific
				milestone release.</para> 
		</sect2>

	</sect1>
			
</chapter>
