<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.1.2//EN" 
	"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.1.2/docbookx.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % globalent SYSTEM "../../../libs/global.ent">
%globalent;
<!ENTITY % cdo-C SYSTEM "../../../libs/cdo-C.ent">
%cdo-C;
<!ENTITY % xubuntu-ent SYSTEM "../../../xubuntu/libs/xubuntu.ent">
%xubuntu-ent;
<!ENTITY language "&EnglishAmerican;">
<!ENTITY language "en">
]>
<?db.chunk.max_depth 0?>
<?yelp:chunk-depth 0?>
<article>
	<articleinfo>
		<title>Xubuntu - Linux for Human Beings!</title>
			&legalnotice;
	</articleinfo>
       		<para>This section is an introduction to Xubuntu. It explains the Xubuntu philosophy and roots, as
       		well as introduces the Xubuntu desktop.
       			</para>
    		<para>
        <inlinemediaobject>
            	<imageobject>
                	<imagedata fileref="../../libs/img/headerlogo.png" format="PNG"/>
            		</imageobject>
  				<textobject>
    				<phrase>Xubuntu Logo</phrase>
  					</textobject>
        </inlinemediaobject>
    			</para>
            <para>Thank you for your interest in Xubuntu &distro-rev;
                - the <emphasis>&distro-version;</emphasis> - released in &distro-release-date;.
				</para> 
			<para>Xubuntu is an entirely open source operating system built around the <emphasis>Linux</emphasis>
			kernel. The Xubuntu community is built around the ideals enshrined in the <ulink url=
			"&ubuntu-philosophy;">Ubuntu Philosophy</ulink>: that software should be available free 
			of charge, that software tools should be usable by people in their local language and 
			despite any disabilities, and that people should have the freedom to customize and alter 
			their software in whatever way they see fit. For those reasons: 
                <itemizedlist>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Xubuntu will always be free of charge, and there is
                            no extra fee for the &quot;enterprise
                            edition,&quot; we make our very best work
                            available to everyone on the same Free terms.
								</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Xubuntu includes the very best in translations and
                            accessibility infrastructure that the free software
                            community has to offer, making Xubuntu usable for as
                            many people as possible.
								</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Xubuntu is released regularly and predictably; a
                            new release is made every six months. You can use
                            the current stable release or the current
                            development release. Each release is supported for
                            at least 18 months.
								</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Xubuntu is entirely committed to the principles of
                            open source software development; we encourage
                            people to use open source software, improve it and
                            pass it on.
								</para>
                    </listitem>
                </itemizedlist>
            </para>
		<para>Find out more at <ulink url="&xubuntu-web;">the Xubuntu website</ulink>.
			</para>

            <sect1 id="about-xubuntu-name" status="draft">
                    <title>About the Name</title>
							<para>The "X" in Xubuntu stands for the Xfce graphical desktop environment, but the word "Ubuntu" represents both the technical and philosophical core of the operating system.  "Ubuntu" is a South African ethical ideology focusing on people&apos;s allegiances and relations with each other. The word comes from the Zulu and Xhosa languages. Ubuntu (pronounced &quot;oo-BOON-too&quot;) is seen as a traditional African concept, is regarded as one of the founding principles of the new republic of South Africa and is connected to the idea of an African Renaissance.
								</para>
							<para>A rough translation of the principle of Ubuntu is &quot;humanity towards others&quot;. Another translation could be: &quot;the belief in a universal bond of sharing that connects all humanity&quot;.
								</para>
			<blockquote><attribution>Archbishop Desmond Tutu</attribution>
				<para>&quot;A person with ubuntu is open and available to others, affirming of others, does not feel threatened that others are able and good, for he or she has a proper self-assurance that comes from knowing that he or she belongs in a greater whole and is diminished when others are humiliated or diminished, when others are tortured or oppressed.&quot;
				</para>
			</blockquote>
                <para>As a part of the Ubuntu family of Linux-based distributions, the Xubuntu operating system brings the spirit of ubuntu to the software world.
					</para>
		</sect1>
                <sect1 id="free-software" status="draft">
                    <title>Free Software</title>
                    		<para>The Xubuntu project is entirely committed to the
                        principles of free software development; people
                        are encouraged to use free software, improve it,
                        and pass it on.
								</para>
                    <para>&quot;Free software&quot; doesn&apos;t mean that you shouldn&apos;t have to pay for it (although Xubuntu is committed to being free of charge as well); it means that you should be able to use the software in any way you wish: the code that makes up free software is available for anyone to download, change, fix, and use in any way. Alongside ideological benefits, this freedom also has technical advantages: when programs are developed, the hard work of others can be used and built upon. With non-free software, this cannot happen and when programs are developed, they have to start from scratch. For this reason the development of free software is fast, efficient and exciting!
                    </para>
			<para>You can find out more about free software and the ideological and technical philosophy behind it at the <ulink url="&gnu-philosophy;">GNU website</ulink>.
			</para>
                </sect1>
                <sect1 id="xubuntu-difference" status="draft">
                    <title>The Difference</title>
                    	<para>There are many different operating systems based on Linux:
 	                 	Debian, SuSE, Gentoo, Red Hat, and Mandriva are examples. 
			   			Xubuntu is yet another contender in what
                        is already a highly competitive world. So what makes
                        Xubuntu different?
							</para>
                    	<para>Xubuntu is part of the Ubuntu family of Linux distributions, and is based on
                    	Debian, one of the most widely acclaimed,
                        technologically advanced, and well-supported
                        distributions, Xubuntu
                        aims to create a distribution that provides
                        an up-to-date and coherent Linux system for desktop and
                        server computing. Xubuntu includes a number of carefully
                        selected packages from the Debian distribution and
                        retains its powerful package management system which
                        allows easy installation and clean removal of programs. Unlike most
                        distributions that ship with a large amount of software
                        that may or may not be of use, Xubuntu&apos;s list of packages
                        is reduced to a number of important applications of high
                        quality.
							</para>
                    	<para>By focusing on quality, Xubuntu produces a robust and
                        feature-rich computing environment that is suitable for
                        use in both home, commercial, and educational environments. The
                        project takes the time required to focus on finer
                        details and is able to release a version featuring the
                        latest and greatest of today&apos;s software once every 6
                        months. Xubuntu is available in flavours for the i386
                        (386/486/Pentium(II/III/IV) and Athlon/Duron/Sempron
                        processors), AMD64 (Athlon64, Opteron, and new 64-bit
                        Intel processors).  A community-supported PowerPC (iBook/Powerbook, G4 and
                        G5) architecture architecture is also available.
							</para>
                </sect1>
                <sect1 id="xubuntu-desktop" status="draft">
                    <title>The Desktop</title>
                    	<para>As mentioned above, the default desktop environment for Xubuntu is <ulink
                            url="&xfce;">Xfce</ulink>, one of the top three Unix and Linux desktop suite and
                            development platforms.  In the words of Olivier Fourdan, the creator of the Xfce
                            desktop environment, "Xfce is a lightweight desktop environment for various *NIX
                            systems. Designed for productivity, it loads and executes applications fast, while
                            conserving system resources."
							</para>
						<para>Because of this emphasis on conserving system resources, Xubuntu is an ideal
							candidate for old or low-end machines, thin-client networks, or for
							those who would like to get more performance out of their hardware.  
							</para>
						<para>Another leading UNIX and Linux desktop is <ulink
                            url="&gnome;">GNOME</ulink>. Gnome is the default desktop 
                            environment of the <ulink url="&ubuntu-main;">Ubuntu</ulink> project.
                    	Xubuntu users are able to easily install and use the Gnome desktop on their
                        system. To get a working install of Ubuntu on a Xubuntu system, 
                        install the <application>ubuntu-desktop</application> package. 
						Once ubuntu-desktop is installed, you can choose to use either 
						an Xfce or Gnome desktop environment.
							</para>	
                    	<para>A third leading UNIX and Linux desktop is <ulink
                            url="&kde;">KDE</ulink>. The <ulink
                            url="&kubuntu-main;">Kubuntu</ulink> project
                        offers Ubuntu users an alternative choice
                        to the Xfce or Gnome desktop environments. Thanks
                        to the efforts of the Kubuntu team, users can also 
                        install and use the KDE desktop on their system. 
                        To get a working installation of Kubuntu, just install 
                        the <application>kubuntu-desktop</application> package. 
                        Once kubuntu-desktop is installed, you can also choose to use 
                        the KDE desktop environment when logging in to your computer.
							</para>
				</sect1>			
                <sect1 id="version-numbers" status="complete">
                    <title>Version and Release Numbers</title>
                    	<para>The Xubuntu version numbering scheme is based on the
                        date we release a version of the distribution. The
                        version number comes from the year and month of the
                        release rather than reflecting the actual version of the
                        software. The first official release of Xubuntu (Dapper Drake) was in
                        June of 2006 so its version was 6.06. This version of Xubuntu (&distro-version;) was
                        released in &distro-release-date; so its version number is &distro-rev;.
							</para>
                </sect1>
                <sect1 id="xubuntu-backing-support" status="draft">
                    <title>Backing and Support</title>
                    	<para>Xubuntu is developed and supported by a quickly growing community.
                        The project is sponsored by <ulink
                            url="&canonical-url;">Canonical Ltd.</ulink>, a
                        holding company founded by Mark Shuttleworth. Canonical
                        employs the core Ubuntu developers and offers support and consulting services
                        for Ubuntu.  More information about Canonical's support offerings can be found on the 
                        <ulink url="&canonical-url;">Canonical website</ulink>.
                        	</para>
                        <para>Although Canonical does not provide professional consulting services support 
                        for Xubuntu at this time, Xubuntu user support is available through the Xubuntu 
                        community.  Information regarding community support can be found at the 
                        <ulink url="&xubuntu-web-help;">Help &amp; Support</ulink> page of the Xubuntu website.
							</para>
                </sect1>
            	<sect1 id="about-linux" status="complete">
            		<title>What is Linux?</title>
            			<para>The <ulink url="&kernel;">Linux kernel</ulink>, pronounced
            			&apos;linnuks&apos; is the heart of the Xubuntu operating system.  
            			A kernel is an important part of any operating system, providing the 
            			communication bridge between hardware and software.
							</para>
            			<para>Linux was brought to life in 1991 by a Finnish student named
                		Linus Torvalds. At the time, it would run only on i386 systems,
                		and was essentially an independently created clone of the UNIX
                		kernel, intended to take advantage of the then-new i386
                		architecture.
							</para>
            			<para>Nowadays, thanks to a substantial amount of development
            			effort by people all around the world, Linux runs on virtually 
            			every modern architecture.
		  					</para>
            			<para>The Linux kernel has gained an ideological importance as well as a technical one.
            			There is an entire community of people who believe in the ideals
            			of free software and spend their time helping to make open
            			source technology as good as it can be.
							</para>
            			<para>People in this community gave rise to initiatives such as
            			Ubuntu, standards committees that shape the development of the
            			Internet, organizations like the Mozilla Foundation, responsible
            			for creating Mozilla Firefox, and countless other software
            			projects from which you&apos;ve certainly benefited in the past.
							</para>
						<para>The spirit of open source, commonly attributed to Linux, is
						influencing software developers and users everywhere to drive
						communities with common goals.
							</para>
        		</sect1>
        		<sect1 id="about-gnu" status="complete">
            		<title>What is GNU?</title>
            			<para>The <emphasis>GNU Project</emphasis>, pronounced “guh-noo”, was
            			launched in 1984 to develop a complete UNIX style operating system which 
            			is comprised of free software: the GNU system. Variants of the GNU operating 
            			system, which use the Linux kernel, are now widely used.
							</para>
						<para>The GNU project is closely linked to the philosophy of free
						software, which is central to the projects that derive from it, 
						such as Ubuntu. The concept of free software is explained at <xref 
						linkend="free-software"/>.
							</para>
				</sect1>
</article>
