<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.3//EN" 
	"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.3/docbookx.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % globalent SYSTEM "../../../libs/global.ent">
%globalent;
<!ENTITY % cdo-C SYSTEM "../../../libs/cdo-C.ent">
%cdo-C;
<!ENTITY % gnome-menus-C SYSTEM "../../../ubuntu/libs/gnome-menus-C.ent">
%gnome-menus-C;
<!ENTITY % xinclude SYSTEM "../../../libs/xinclude.mod">
%xinclude;
<!ENTITY language "en">
<!ENTITY ubuntu '<phrase>Ubuntu</phrase>'>
]>
	<article id="music-video-photos" status="complete">
	<articleinfo>
	<title>Music and Video</title>
    	&legalnotice;
	</articleinfo>
				<para>This section describes how to import, organise and use music, video and photos with Ubuntu.</para>
	<sect1 id="music" status="complete">
		<title>Music</title>
			<sect2 id="music-files" status="complete">
					<title>Playing and Organising Music Files</title>
				<para>To play and organize your music, Ubuntu comes with		    <application>Rhythmbox Music Player</application>, which looks similar to <application>iTunes</application>. When you first start <application>Rhythmbox</application>, it will scan your home directory for any supported music files you have and add it to the database. To start <application>Rhythmbox</application>, choose &rhythmbox;.</para>
					<para>Ubuntu does not directly support the <emphasis role="strong">MP3</emphasis> format, because it is restricted by patents and proprietary rights. Instead Ubuntu supports the <emphasis role="strong">Ogg Vorbis</emphasis> format out of the box, a completely free, open and non-patented format. Ogg Vorbis files also sound better then MP3 files of the same file size and are supported by many portable music players.</para>
					<itemizedlist>
						<listitem><para><ulink url="http://wiki.xiph.org/index.php/PortablePlayers">Players that work with Vorbis</ulink></para></listitem>
					</itemizedlist>
					<para>You can still play your old MP3 files by installing MP3 support (see <xref linkend="codecs"/>). Instructions for other formats, such as Windows Media Audio (wma/wmv) and other patent-encumbered formats can be found <ulink url="http://wiki.ubuntu.com/RestrictedFormats">on the Ubuntu Wiki</ulink>.</para>
				<para>The <application>Cowbell</application> ID3 tag editor can edit the metadata on your
					MP3 and other music files. To use <application>Cowbell</application>:</para>
				<procedure>
						<step>
							<para>Install the <application>cowbell</application> package from the <quote>Universe</quote> repository (see <ulink url="../add-applications/add-applications.xml">Add Applications</ulink>);
							</para>
						</step>
						<step>
							<para>To run <application>Cowbell</application>, choose
								<menuchoice>
									<guimenu>Applications</guimenu>
									<guisubmenu>Sound &amp; Video</guisubmenu>
									<guimenuitem>Cowbell Music Organizer</guimenuitem>
								</menuchoice>.</para>
						</step>
				</procedure>
			</sect2>
			<sect2 id="audio-cds" status="complete">
				<title>Playing and Extracting Audio CDs</title>
				<para>When you insert an audio CD, the <application>Sound Juicer</application> CD player and ripper opens automatically. To play the CD, click the <guibutton>Play</guibutton> button or press <keycombo><keycap>Ctrl</keycap><keycap>P</keycap></keycombo>. To play a particular track, double-click on the track or select the track and click <guibutton>Play</guibutton>.</para>
				<para>To extract (rip) your audio CD, make sure the tracks that you want to rip are selected, then click the <guibutton>Extract</guibutton> button or press <keycombo><keycap>Ctrl</keycap><keycap>Enter</keycap></keycombo>.
				</para>
					<note>
						<para>If you are connected to the internet, <application>Sound Juicer</application> will retrieve the CD artist, title, and track data from <ulink url="http://musicbrainz.org">MusicBrainz.org</ulink>, a community-maintained database of over 360,000 albums.
						</para>
					</note>
				<para>To start <application>Sound Juicer</application> manually, choose 
				<menuchoice>
					<guimenu>Applications</guimenu>
					<guimenuitem>Sound &amp; Video</guimenuitem>
					<guimenuitem>Sound Juicer CD Extractor</guimenuitem>
				</menuchoice>.
				</para>
				<para>You can use the preferences window to control where the extracted audio files are stored on your computer, the filename of extracted audio files, and the file format and codec used for the files. In the main window, choose 
				<menuchoice>
					<guimenu>Edit</guimenu>
					<guimenuitem>Preferences</guimenuitem>
				</menuchoice>.
				</para>
				<para><application>Sound Juicer</application> can extract audio files to these formats:
					<itemizedlist>
						<listitem>
							<para><emphasis role="strong">Ogg Vorbis</emphasis> - A patent-free lossy audio compression format, which typically produces higher quality and greater compression than MP3.</para>
							<itemizedlist>
								<listitem><para><ulink url="http://vorbis.com/faq/">More about Vorbis from vorbis.com</ulink></para></listitem>
							</itemizedlist>
						</listitem>
						<listitem>
							<para><emphasis role="strong">FLAC</emphasis> - The Free Lossless Audio Codec. It can compress audio files up to 50% without removing any information from the audio stream.</para>
							<itemizedlist>
								<listitem><para><ulink url="http://flac.sourceforge.net/">FLAC Web site</ulink></para></listitem>
							</itemizedlist>
						</listitem>
						<listitem>
							<para><emphasis role="strong">WAV</emphasis> - Typically used for voice recordings. <application>Sound Juicer</application> uses this format for low quality mono audio files. 
							</para>
						</listitem>
					</itemizedlist>
				</para>
				<para>You can also extract CD audio files to the proprietary non-free <emphasis role="strong">MP3</emphasis> format. Instructions on how to rip to the MP3 format are in the help for <application>Sound Juicer</application>. Choose 
				<menuchoice>
					<guimenu>Help</guimenu>
					<guisubmenu>Contents</guisubmenu>
				</menuchoice> and navigate to the <emphasis>Preferences</emphasis> section.
				</para>
			</sect2>
			<sect2 id="burning-cds" status="complete">
					<title>Burning CDs</title>
					<para>When you put a blank CD in the drive Ubuntu will ask if you want to burn an audio or data CD. Clicking on <guibutton>Burn Audio CD</guibutton> will launch <application>Serpentine</application> . To add music to your audio CD, either drag music from your File Browser or use the <guibutton>Add</guibutton> button. You will also need to select the size of your CD (21, 74, 80 or 90 minutes). Serpentine will warn you if you exceed the set limit.
					</para>
					<para>To make a photo or data CD, click <guibutton>Burn Data CD</guibutton>. Ubuntu will open a CD/DVD Creator window. The CD Creator is built into the File Browser, and it allows you to add any file or folder you have permission to access. When you are ready to burn the CD, click <guibutton>Write to Disc</guibutton>. Ubuntu will then prompt you to select the drive containing the blank CD, and give you the opportunity to name the CD and select the write speed. Finally, click <guibutton>Write</guibutton> to create the new photo or data CD.
					</para>
			</sect2>

			<sect2 id="ipod" status="complete">
			        <title>Using an iPod</title>
				<para>You can play music directly off an iPod with <application>Rhythmbox Music Player</application>. Plug the iPod into the computer, and open <application>Rhythmbox</application>.</para>
				<para>To transfer music files to and from an iPod, you can use <application>gtkpod</application>:</para>
					<procedure>
					<step>
						<para>Install the <application>gtkpod</application> package from the <quote>Universe</quote> repository (see <ulink url="../add-applications/add-applications.xml">Add Applications</ulink>).
						</para>
					</step>
					<step>
						<para>To run <application>gtkpod</application>, choose
								<menuchoice>
									<guimenu>Applications</guimenu>
									<guisubmenu>Sound &amp; Video</guisubmenu>
									<guimenuitem>gtkpod</guimenuitem>
								</menuchoice>.
						</para>
					</step>
					</procedure>
			</sect2>
			<sect2 id="edit-audio-files" status="complete">
				<title>Editing Audio Files</title>
					<para>Audacity is free, open source software for recording and editing sounds. To use Audacity:</para>
					<procedure>
						<step>
							<para>Install the audacity package from the <quote>Universe</quote> repository (see <ulink url="../add-applications/add-applications.xml">Add Applications</ulink>).
							</para>
						</step>
						<step>
							<para>To run <application>Audacity</application>, choose
								<menuchoice>
									<guimenu>Applications</guimenu>
									<guisubmenu>Sound &amp; Video</guisubmenu>
									<guimenuitem>Audacity</guimenuitem>
								</menuchoice>.
							</para>
						</step>
						<step>
							<para>For further help with Audacity, use Audacity&#8217;s <guimenu>Help</guimenu> menu.</para>
						</step>							
					</procedure>
			</sect2>
		</sect1>

		<sect1 id="video">
		<title>Video Playback</title>
		<para>To play video, Ubuntu comes with <application>Totem Movie Player</application>, which looks and functions similar to Windows Media Player. Features of
		<application>Totem</application> include custom playlists and DVD playback. 
	        You can start <application>Totem</application> by clicking: &totem; from the desktop menu system.
		</para>
		<para>To read video files, <application>Totem</application> uses the <application>Gstreamer</application> framework. To play some video formats, you may need to add further codec support (see <xref linkend="codecs"/>).</para>
		<para>There are also other multimedia applications available. Examples include <application>Mplayer</application>, <application>Xine</application> and <application>Totem-xine</application> (which uses the <application>Xine</application> framework, instead of the <application>Gstreamer</application> framework). You may benefit from trying alternative video players.</para>

		<sect2 id="dvdplayback" status="complete">
			<title>DVD Playback</title>
				<para>The movie players provided in Ubuntu are capable of reading DVDs that are not encrypted. However, most commercial DVDs are encrypted with CSS (the Content Scrambling System) and currently for legal reasons it is not possible to include support for these DVDs in Ubuntu. However, it is possible to enable support as follows:</para>
				<warning><para>The legal status of this library is not fully clear. In some countries it is possible that the use of this library to play or copy DVDs is not permitted by law. Verify that you are within your rights in using it.</para></warning>
				<procedure>
					<step>
						<para>Install the <application>libdvdread3</application> package from the <quote>Multiverse</quote> repository (see <ulink url="../add-applications/add-applications.xml">Add Applications</ulink>).
						</para>
					<note><para>You will need to use <application>Synaptic Package Manager</application> to install this package</para></note>
					</step>
					<step>
						<para>To activate DVD decryption, type the following line into a terminal prompt:<screen>sudo /usr/share/doc/libdvdread3/install-css.sh</screen>
						</para>
					</step>
					<step>
						<para>To play DVDs with <application>Totem</application>, you will need to install some extra codecs (see <xref linkend="codecs"/>).</para>
					</step>
					<step>
						<para>However, the <application>Gstreamer</application> framework (used by <application>Totem</application>) does not support menus or subtitles for DVD playback. For this reason, you can install a separate DVD player, <application>Xine</application>, which supports these. To install <application>Xine</application>, install the <application>gxine</application> package from the <quote>Universe</quote> repository (see <ulink url="../add-applications/add-applications.xml">Add Applications</ulink>).</para>
					</step>
					<step>
						<para>You can then open <application>gxine</application> from the Sound &amp; Video menu.</para>
					</step>
				</procedure>
		</sect2>

			<sect2 status="complete">
				<title>Backing Up DVDs</title>
					<para>You can back up your DVDs to files or onto blank +/- DVD discs with <application>dvd::rip</application>. To install
<application>dvd::rip</application>:</para>
					<warning><para>Before backing up a DVD, you must ensure that you are legally permitted to make copies of it.</para></warning>
					<procedure>
						<step>
							<para>Install the Multimedia Codecs (see <xref linkend="codecs"/>).
							</para>
						</step>
						<step>
							<para>Enable DVD video playback (see <xref linkend="dvdplayback"/>).
							</para>
						</step>
						<step>
							<para>Install <application>dvdrip</application> and <application>transcode</application> from the <quote>Multiverse</quote> repository (see <ulink url="../add-applications/add-applications.xml">Add Applications</ulink>).
							</para>
						</step>
						<step>
							<para>You can run the program using the command <application>dvdrip</application> (see <ulink type="help" url="ghelp:user-guide#tools-run-app">the run application manual</ulink> for help on how to run an application without using the menu). If you wish, you can add a menu entry for the program <application>dvdrip</application> (see <ulink type="help" url="ghelp:user-guide#menu-editor">the menu editor manual</ulink> for help on how to add menu entries). We recommend you enter it in the Sound &amp; Video menu, and that you use the file <filename>/usr/share/perl5/Video/DVDRip/icon.xpm</filename> for the icon.
							</para>
						</step>
						<step>
							<para>To start  <application>dvd::rip</application>, choose
								<menuchoice>
									<guimenu>Applications</guimenu>
									<guisubmenu>Sound &amp; Video</guisubmenu>
									<guimenuitem>dvd::rip</guimenuitem>
								</menuchoice>.
							</para>
						</step>
					</procedure>
			</sect2>

		<sect2 status="complete">
			<title>RealPlayer</title>
					<procedure>
						<step>
							<para>Install the <application>realplay</application> package from the <emphasis>Commercial</emphasis> repository (see <ulink url="../add-applications/add-applications.xml">Add Applications</ulink>).</para>
						</step>
						<step>
							<para>To run <application>RealPlayer</application>, choose
								<menuchoice>
									<guimenu>Applications</guimenu>
									<guisubmenu>Sound &amp; Video</guisubmenu>
									<guimenuitem>RealPlayer 10</guimenuitem>
								</menuchoice>.
							</para>
						</step>
					</procedure>
			</sect2>
			<sect2 status="complete">
					<title>Video Editing</title>
					<para><application>Kino</application> is an advanced video editor. It features excellent integration with IEEE-1394 (Firewire) for capture, VTR control, and recording back to the camera. It captures video to disk in Raw DV and AVI format, in both type-1 DV and type-2 DV (separate audio stream) encodings. For more information, see <ulink url="http://www.kinodv.org/article/static/2">the Kino website</ulink>. To use it:</para>
					<procedure>
						<step>
							<para>Install the <application>kino</application> package (see <ulink url="../add-applications/add-applications.xml">Add Applications</ulink>).</para>
						</step>
						<step>
							<para>To run <application>Kino</application>, choose
								<menuchoice>
									<guimenu>Applications</guimenu>
									<guisubmenu>Sound &amp; Video</guisubmenu>
									<guimenuitem>Kino Video Editor</guimenuitem>
								</menuchoice>.
							</para>
						</step>
					</procedure>
					<para>You can also try the <application>PiTiVi</application> video editor by installing the <application>pitivi</application> package from the <quote>Universe</quote> repository (see <ulink url="../add-applications/add-applications.xml">Add Applications</ulink>). <application>PiTiVi</application> is a video editor for the GNOME desktop. It is still in fairly early development, but worth a try.</para>
			</sect2>

		</sect1>

		<sect1 id="codecs" status="complete">
		<title>Multimedia Codecs</title>
			<para>Many applications in Ubuntu use the <application>GStreamer</application> open source multimedia framework. The codec plugins for <application>GStreamer</application> are organised in different packages depending on the licensing that applies to the various codecs. You can see which codecs are contained in which plugin on the <ulink url="http://gstreamer.freedesktop.org/documentation/plugins.html">GStreamer website</ulink>.</para>
			<para>Other applications, such as <application>Mplayer</application> and <application>Xine</application>, do not use the <application>Gstreamer</application> framework. Due to patent and copyright restrictions, codecs for these programs are not included at all in Ubuntu. For more information on these read the <ulink url="&restricted-formats;">Restricted Formats</ulink> wiki page.</para>
			<para>To install extra codecs for <application>Gstreamer</application>:</para>
				<procedure>
					<step>
							<para>Install the following packages from the <quote>Universe</quote> and <quote>Multiverse</quote> repositories (see <ulink url="../add-applications/add-applications.xml">Add Applications</ulink>):
								<literallayout>gstreamer0.10-plugins-ugly
gstreamer0.10-plugins-ugly-multiverse
gstreamer0.10-plugins-bad
gstreamer0.10-plugins-bad-multiverse
gstreamer0.10-ffmpeg
								</literallayout>
							</para>
							<note>
								<para>You will need to use <application>Synaptic Package Manager</application> to install these packages.
								</para>
							</note>
							<warning>
								<para>Some of these packages may not be permitted in some countries: you should verify that you are permitted to use them before installing them.
								</para>
							</warning>
					</step>
				</procedure>
	</sect1>

	<sect1 id="photos" status="complete">
		<title>Pictures &amp; Photos</title>
			<para>This section describes the photo management and graphic design applications available to use with Ubuntu.</para>
		<sect2 id="digital-cameras" status="complete">
			<title>Digital Cameras</title>
				<para>Ubuntu detects most USB digital cameras automatically. Plug in and switch on the camera by placing it in review mode, and Ubuntu will then ask you if you would like to import the photos it contains. Click on <guibutton>Import</guibutton>, and Ubuntu will show you a preview of the photos. Choose a location to save your photos to, then click on <guibutton>Import</guibutton>, and Ubuntu will save your photos to your hard drive.</para>
				<tip>
					<para>
					The majority of digital cameras are just USB devices, and you can access the photos like any other USB device from within the file manager.
					</para>
				</tip>
				<para>If Ubuntu does not ask you if it can import the photos:</para>
				<procedure>
					<step><para>Open &gthumb;.</para></step>
					<step>
						<para>Choose
					<menuchoice>
						<guimenu>File</guimenu>
						<guimenuitem>Import Photos</guimenuitem>
					</menuchoice>.</para>
					</step>
				</procedure>
				<para>See the next section for more information on <application>gThumb</application>.</para>
		</sect2>

		<sect2 id="gthumb" status="complete">
			<title>gThumb Image Viewer</title>
				<para><application>gThumb</application> is an advanced image viewer and browser. It has many useful features, such as filesystem browsing, slide show, image catalogs, web album creation, camera import, image CD burning, batch file operations and quick image editing features like transformation and color manipulation.</para>
				<para><application>gThumb</application> is included in Ubuntu by default. To start it, choose &gthumb;.
				</para>
				<para>For help with <application>gThumb</application>, use <ulink type="help" url="ghelp:gthumb#intro">gThumb's help</ulink>.</para>
				<para>For more advanced photo &amp; image editing, see <application>The GIMP</application>.
				</para>
		</sect2>
		<sect2 id="f-spot" status="review">
			<title>F-Spot</title>
				<para><application>F-Spot</application> provides a complete solution for managing your photo collection. With it you can import photos from your digital camera or USB stick, tag them with familiar terms, do touch ups, and edit them in different ways. In addition to this, <application>F-Spot</application> can upload photos easily to your Flickr, PicasaWeb album and other online photo galleries.
				</para>
				<para><application>F-Spot</application> is included in Ubuntu by default. To start it, choose &f-spot;
				</para>
				<para>For help with <application>F-Spot Photo Manager</application>, go to the online <ulink url="http://f-spot.org/User_Guide">F-Spot User Guide</ulink>.
				</para>
 				<para>For more advanced photo &amp; image editing, see <application>The GIMP</application>.
 			<itemizedlist>
				<listitem>
					<para><ulink url="http://f-spot.org/">F-Spot Web site</ulink></para>
				</listitem>
			</itemizedlist>
 				</para>
 		</sect2>
		<sect2 id="gimp" status="complete">
			<title>The GIMP (Gnu Image Manipulation Program)</title>
			<para><application>The GIMP</application> lets you draw, paint, edit images, and much more. GIMP includes the functionality and plug-ins of other famous image editing and processing programs. <application>The GIMP</application> provides a comprehensive range of functionality for creating different types of graphics. It includes tools for selections, drawing, creating paths, masks, filters, effects, and more. 
				</para>
				<para><application>The GIMP</application> is installed in Ubuntu by default, and can be started by choosing &gimp;.
				</para>
			<itemizedlist>
				<listitem><para><ulink url="http://gimp.org/">GIMP Web site</ulink></para></listitem>
			</itemizedlist>
		</sect2>
		<sect2 id="inkscape" status="complete">
			<title>Inkscape Vector Graphics Editor</title>
				<para><application>Inkscape</application> is a drawing package for creating Scalable Vector Graphics (SVG). Ever since the SVG format was introduced, it has taken the design world by storm and allows the creation of graphics that can scale to any size. Inkscape is a hugely flexible tool for creating such graphics, and a huge range of icons and artwork in Open Source projects are made in Inkscape.
 				</para>
				<procedure>
					<step>
						<para>Install the <application>inkscape</application> package (see <ulink url="../add-applications/add-applications.xml">Add Applications</ulink>).
						</para>
					</step>
					<step>
						<para>To start <application>Inkscape</application> choose &inkscape;.
						</para>
					</step>
				</procedure>
			<itemizedlist>
				<listitem><para><ulink url="http://www.inkscape.org/">Inkscape Web site</ulink></para></listitem>
			</itemizedlist>
		</sect2>
		<sect2 id="blender" status="complete">
			<title>Blender 3d Modeller</title>
				<para><application>Blender</application> is an incredibly powerful 3D modeling, animation, rendering, and production studio. Blender amasses an impressive range of functionality for creating photorealistic scenes, animations, and real-time virtual walkthroughs.
 				</para>
				<procedure>
					<step>
						<para>Install the <application>blender</application> package from the <quote>Universe</quote> repository (see <ulink url="../add-applications/add-applications.xml">Add Applications</ulink>).
						</para>
					</step>
					<step>
						<para>To start <application>Blender</application> choose &blender3d;.
						</para>
					</step>
				</procedure>
			<itemizedlist>
				<listitem><para><ulink url="http://www.blender.org/">Blender Web site</ulink></para></listitem>
			</itemizedlist>
		</sect2>
	</sect1>

</article>
