<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.3//EN" 
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.3/docbookx.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % globalent SYSTEM "../../../libs/global.ent">
%globalent;
<!ENTITY % cdo-C SYSTEM "../../../libs/cdo-C.ent">
%cdo-C;
<!ENTITY % kde SYSTEM "../../libs/kde.ent">
%kde;
<!ENTITY % kde-general SYSTEM "/usr/share/apps/ksgmltools2/customization/obsolete/general.entities">
%kde-general;
<!ENTITY % xinclude SYSTEM "../../../libs/xinclude.mod">
%xinclude;
<!ENTITY language "en">
]>
<chapter id="introduction" status="review">
    <title>Introduktion</title>
    <para>
    This chapter provides some background information about Kubuntu, obtaining
    Kubuntu and finding help with Kubuntu.
    </para>
    <sect1 id="about-kubuntu" status="complete">
        <title>Om Kubuntu</title>
        <para>Thank you for your interest in Kubuntu &distro-rev;
            - the <emphasis>&distro-version;</emphasis> release.</para> 
        <para>Kubuntu is an entirely open source operating system built around the 
            Linux kernel. The Kubuntu community is built around the ideals
            enshrined in the <ulink url="&ubuntu-philosophy;">Ubuntu 
                Philosophy</ulink>: that software should be
            available free of charge, that software tools should be usable
            by people in their local language and despite any disabilities,
            and that people should have the freedom to customize and alter
            their software in whatever way they see fit. For those reasons: 
            <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Kubuntu will always be free of charge, and there is
                        no extra fee for the "enterprise
                        edition," we make our very best work
                        available to everyone on the same Free terms.
                    </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Kubuntu includes the very best in translations and
                        accessibility infrastructure that the Free Software
                        community has to offer, to make Kubuntu usable for as
                        many people as possible.
                    </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Kubuntu is released regularly and predictably; a
                        new release is made every six months. You can use
                        the current stable release or explore the current
                        development release. Each release is supported for
                        at least 18 months.
                    </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Kubuntu is entirely committed to the principles of
                        open source software development; we encourage
                        people to use open source software, improve it, and
                        pass it on.
                    </para>
                </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
        </para>
        <para>
            The Kubuntu community is comprised of developers, programmers,
            testers, tech-writers, documentation testers, translators, and
            most importantly, the people who use Kubuntu every day. We
            invite you to join this community and help make Kubuntu the
            operating system you, your family, your friends, and your
            colleagues will love to use. Help us translate Kubuntu into your
            language, try it on new and unusual hardware, improve the
            experience of other users with hints, tips, and FAQs, or help
            to shape the direction Kubuntu is headed by providing feedback
            about the software you love most.</para>
        <para>
            Find out more at <ulink url="&kubuntu-web;">the Kubuntu website</ulink>.
        </para>
        <sect2 id="about-kubuntu-name" status="complete">
            <title>Om navnet</title>
            <para>Kubuntu is based on the Ubuntu system, but with the latest KDE packages. Kubuntu
                means "towards humanity" in Bemba. Kubuntu is pronounced
                "koo-boon-too". </para> 
            <!-- Needs some word foo -->
            <para>Ubuntu is a South African ethical ideology focusing on
                people's allegiances and relations with each other. The
                word comes from the Zulu and Xhosa languages. Ubuntu
                (pronounced "oo-BOON-too") is seen as a
                traditional African concept, is regarded as one of the
                founding principles of the new republic of South Africa
                and is connected to the idea of an African Renaissance.</para>
            <para>A rough translation of the principle of Ubuntu is
                "humanity towards others". Another
                translation could be: "the belief in a
                universal bond of sharing that connects all
                humanity".</para>
            <blockquote><attribution>Ærkebiskop Desmond Tutu</attribution>
                <para>
                    A person with ubuntu is open and available to others,
                    affirming of others, does not feel threatened that others
                    are able and good, for he or she has a proper
                    self-assurance that comes from knowing that he or she
                    belongs in a greater whole and is diminished when others
                    are humiliated or diminished, when others are tortured or
                    oppressed.</para>
            </blockquote>
            <para>
                As a platform based on Linux, the Kubuntu
                operating system brings the spirit of ubuntu to the software
                world.
            </para>
        </sect2>
        <sect2 id="free-software" status="complete">
            <title>Free Software</title>
            <para>The Kubuntu project is entirely committed to the
                principles of open source software development; people
                are encouraged to use open source software, improve it,
                and pass it on. This means that Kubuntu is and will
                always be free of charge.</para>
            <para>
                However, this means more than just being available at
                zero cost. The philosophy of Free Software is that
                people should be free to use software in all the ways
                that are "socially useful". "Free
                software" not only means that you shouldn't have
                to pay for it, it also means that you should be able to
                use the software in any way you wish.  The code that
                makes up Free Software is available for anyone to
                download, change, fix, and use in any way. So apart
                from the fact that Free Software is often available
                without charge, this freedom also has technical
                advantages: when programs are developed, the hard work
                of others can be used and built upon. This cannot
                happen with non-free Software, and when programs are
                developed, they have to start from scratch. For this
                reason the development of Free Software is fast,
                efficient and exciting!
            </para>
            <para>You can find out more about the philosophy of Free Software
                <ulink url="&gnu-philosophy;">here</ulink>.</para>
        </sect2>
        <sect2 id="kubuntu-difference" status="complete">
            <title>The Difference</title>
            <para>
                There are many different operating systems based on Linux:
                Debian, SUSE, Gentoo, RedHat, and Mandriva for example. 
                Kubuntu is yet another contender in what
                is already a highly competitive world. So what makes
                Kubuntu different?</para>
            <para>
                Based on Debian, one of the most widely acclaimed,
                technologically advanced, and well-supported
                distributions, Kubuntu
                aims to create a distribution that provides
                an up-to-date and coherent Linux system for desktop and
                server computing. Kubuntu includes a number of carefully
                selected packages from the Debian distribution and
                retains its powerful package management system, which
                allows easy installation and clean removal of programs. Unlike most
                distributions that ship with a large amount of software
                that may or may not be of use, Kubuntu's list of packages
                is reduced to a number of important applications of high
                quality.
            </para>
            <para>
                By focusing on quality, Kubuntu produces a robust and
                feature-rich computing environment that is suitable for
                use in both home and commercial environments. The
                project takes the time required to focus on finer
                details and is able to release a version featuring the
                latest and greatest of today's software once every 6
                months. Kubuntu is available in flavors for the i386
                (386/486/Pentium(II/III/IV) and Athlon/Duron/Sempron
                processors), x86_64 (Athlon64, Opteron, and new 64-bit
                Intel processors), and PowerPC (iBook/Powerbook, G4 and
                G5) architectures.</para>
        </sect2>
        <sect2 id="sect-kubuntu-desktop" status="complete">
            <title>The Desktop</title>
            <para>The default desktop environment for Kubuntu is <ulink url="&kde;">KDE</ulink>, a leading UNIX and
                Linux desktop suite and development platform.</para>
            <para>Another leading UNIX and Linux desktop is <ulink url="&gnome;">Gnome</ulink>. Kubuntu does not 
                make use of the Gnome desktop by default. However, the
                <ulink url="&ubuntu-main;">Ubuntu</ulink> project offers
                Kubuntu users a choice between these two excellent desktop
                environments. Thanks to the efforts of the Ubuntu team,
                Kubuntu users are able to install and use the Gnome
                desktop easily on their system. The Gnome desktop can 
                be found in and downloaded from the main Ubuntu archive.
                The easiest way to get a working install of Ubuntu is
                <command>sudo apt-get install ubuntu-desktop</command>.
                This will install the different packages required and set
                everything up correctly.</para>
            <para>After everything is installed, one can choose which 
                environment to use: either KDE or Gnome.
            </para>
        </sect2>
        <sect2 id="version-numbers" status="complete">
            <title>Version and Release Numbers</title>
            <para>
                The Kubuntu version numbering scheme is based on the date we
                release a version of the distribution. The version number comes from the year
                and month of the release rather than reflecting the actual revision of the
                software. So, our first release (Hoary Hedgehog) was in April 2005, so its
                version was 5.04. The second release (Breezy Badger) was in October 2005, so
                its version number was 5.10, and our third release (Dapper Drake) was released in June 2006
		so its version number was 6.06. This version (&distro-version;) was released in
                &distro-release-date;, so its version number is &distro-rev;.
            </para>
        </sect2>

        <sect2 id="kubuntu-backing-support" status="complete">
            <title>Backing and Support</title>
            <para>Kubuntu is maintained by a quickly growing community.
                The project is sponsored by <ulink url="&canonical-url;">Canonical Ltd.</ulink>, a
                holding company founded by Mark Shuttleworth. Canonical
                employs the core Ubuntu developers and offers support and consulting services
                for Ubuntu.</para>
            <para>Canonical Ltd also sponsors a number of other open source software projects, more information about which can be found on the <ulink url="&canonical-url;">Canonical website</ulink>.</para>
        </sect2>
        <sect2 id="about-linux" status="complete">
            <title>Hvad er Linux?</title>
            <para>The <ulink url="&kernel;">Linux kernel</ulink>, pronounced
                "lee-nucks" is the heart of the Kubuntu operating system.
                A kernel is an important part of
                any operating system, providing the communication bridge between 
                hardware and software.</para>
            <para>Linux was brought to life in 1991 by a Finnish student named
                Linus Torvalds. At the time, it would run only on i386 systems,
                and was essentially an independently created clone of the UNIX
                kernel, intended to take advantage of the then-new i386
                architecture.</para>
            <para>Nowadays, thanks to a substantial amount of development
                effort by people all around the world, Linux runs on virtually 
                every modern architecture.</para>
            <para>The Linux kernel has gained an ideological importance as well as a technical one.
                There is an entire community of people who believe in the ideals
                of Free Software and spend their time helping to make open
                source technology as good as it can be.</para>
            <para>People in this community gave rise to initiatives such as
                Ubuntu, standards committees that shape the development of the
                Internet, organizations like the Mozilla Foundation, responsible
                for creating Mozilla Firefox, and countless other software
                projects from which you've certainly benefited in the past.</para>
            <para>The spirit of open source, commonly attributed to Linux, is
                influencing software developers and users everywhere to drive
                communities with common goals.</para>
        </sect2>
        <sect2 id="about-gnu" status="complete">
            <title>Hvad er GNU?</title>
            <para>The <emphasis>GNU Project</emphasis>, pronounced "guh-noo", was
                launched in 1984 to develop a complete
                UNIX-style operating system which is comprised of Free Software: the GNU
                system. Variants of the GNU operating system,
                which use the Linux kernel, are now widely used.</para>
            <para>The GNU project is closely linked to the philosophy of free
                software, which is central to the projects that derive from it, 
                such as Ubuntu. The concept of Free Software is explained 
                at <xref linkend="free-software"/>.</para>
        </sect2>
    </sect1>
    <sect1 id="get-kubuntu" status="complete">
        <title>Getting Kubuntu</title>
        <para>There are a number of methods you may use to obtain a
            copy of Kubuntu, all of which are described on the Kubuntu
            Web site <ulink url="&kubuntu-download;">download
                page</ulink>.</para>
        <para>The first method is to download an ISO image from a
            mirror server near you and make an CD to install Kubuntu. Two types of CDs are available:</para>
				<itemizedlist>
					<listitem><para><emphasis>Desktop CD</emphasis> - the desktop CD allows you to try Kubuntu without changing your computer at all, and at your option to install it permanently later. This type of CD is what most people will want to use.</para></listitem>
					<listitem><para><emphasis>Text-mode install CD</emphasis> - the text-mode install CD allows you to perform certain specialist installations of Kubuntu. This type of CD is intended for cases such as creating pre-configured OEM systems or setting up automated deployments; it can also be used as a package source for upgrading older installations.</para></listitem>
				</itemizedlist>
        <para>If you don't have a CD burner or you have limited or expensive bandwidth,
            we can send you pressed copies of the "Desktop
            CD" free of charge. You may request CDs via
            <ulink url="&ubuntu-shipit;">Shipit</ulink>, the Ubuntu CD Distribution System.</para>
        <tip>
            <para>Ordered CDs may take several weeks to
                leave the warehouse before being shipped, and can take several months to arrive.</para>
        </tip>
        <para>Another method of obtaining Kubuntu is to join a local
            Linux Users Group (LUG) and ask if somebody with Kubuntu
            would mind making a Kubuntu CD for you. Normally, you
            will have to replace the CDs used for the duplication
            and reimburse any postage or delivery costs.</para>
        <para>If you do not know of an LUG near you, a list can be
            found at <ulink url="&lugww;">Linux Users Groups
                Worldwide</ulink>.</para>
    </sect1>
    <sect1 id="getting-help" status="review">
        <title>Getting Help</title>
        <para>There are a number of places from which you can obtain help with your Kubuntu desktop system,
            these include:
        </para>
        <sect2 id="help-system" status="writing">
            <title>KDE Help Center</title>
            <para>
                Kubuntu comes with a inbuilt help system, which can be accessed
                by choosing 
                <menuchoice>
                    <guimenu>K Menu</guimenu>
                    <guimenuitem>Help</guimenuitem>
                </menuchoice> 
                from the desktop menu system. 
                The <application>KDE Help Center</application> is the central
                location to all documentation available on your system. 
            </para>
            <para> A good place to start off learning more about KDE is the
                <ulink url="help:/khelpcenter/quickstart/index.html">KDE
                    Quickstart Guide</ulink>, which will familiarize you with
                some of the basic features of KDE.  </para>
        </sect2>
        <sect2 id="application-help" status="review">
            <title>Help with an Application</title>
            <para>
                The easiest way to find help about an application is to read
                its handbook which is accessible from the
                <emphasis>Help</emphasis> menu in the application's
                toolbar.
            </para> 
        </sect2>
        <sect2 id="online-help" status="complete">
            <title>Find Help Online</title>
            <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para>
                        <ulink url="&ubuntu-documentation;">The Ubuntu Documentation Website</ulink> contains HTML and PDF versions of this guide, and other guides produced by the Ubuntu Documentation Team for Ubuntu and Kubuntu.</para></listitem>
                <listitem> <para> You can buy this guide in book form from <ulink url="&lulu-store;">our Lulu store</ulink>. You will only pay for the price of printing and postage.  </para> </listitem> <listitem>
                    <para>
                        <ulink url="&wiki-UserDocumentation;">The Ubuntu Wiki</ulink> - this contains many other community maintained guides</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>
                        <ulink url="&kubuntu-forums2;">Kubuntu</ulink> and <ulink url="&ubuntu-forums;">Ubuntu</ulink> Community Forums - here you can ask questions on a forum and receive answers from the forum community.
                    </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para><ulink url="&kubuntu-lists;">Mailing Lists</ulink> - here you can ask questions by email, and receive answers from the mailing list community.
                    </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem><para>IRC chat: <phrase>&kubuntu-irc;</phrase> - chat in realtime with the Kubuntu community.</para></listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>
                        <ulink url="&kubuntu-web;">Kubuntu Homepage</ulink> - Get the latest news about Kubuntu. 
                    </para>
                </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
            <para>For more information, visit the <ulink url="&wiki-HowToGetHelp;">How to Get Help</ulink> wiki page.</para>
        </sect2>
    </sect1>
</chapter>

