<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.3//EN" 
	"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.3/docbookx.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % globalent SYSTEM "../../../libs/global.ent">
%globalent;
<!ENTITY % cdo-C SYSTEM "../../../libs/cdo-C.ent">
%cdo-C;
<!ENTITY % gnome-menus-ko SYSTEM "../../../ubuntu/libs/gnome-menus-ko.ent">
%gnome-menus-ko;
<!ENTITY % xinclude SYSTEM "../../../libs/xinclude.mod">
%xinclude;
<!ENTITY language "en">
<!ENTITY ubuntu '<phrase>Ubuntu</phrase>'>
]>
<chapter id="root-and-sudo" status="review">
			<title>Administrative Tasks</title>
			<para>In Ubuntu, for security reasons, administrative tasks are confined to users with special privileges. Administrative access is given to individual users, who may use the <application>sudo</application> command to perform administrative tasks. The first user account you created on your system during installation will, by default, have access to sudo. You can restrict and enable sudo access to users with the <application>Users and Groups</application> application (see <xref linkend="users-and-groups"/> for more information).
			</para>
			<para>root 권한을 필요로 하는 프로그램을 실행하였을 때, sudo 는 여러분의 일반 사용자 패스워드를 입력할 수 있도록 물어볼 것입니다. 이 것은 악의적인 프로그램이 시스템을 손상시킬 수 없도록 확인하고, 여러분이 주의가 필요한 관리적인 동작을 수행하는 것에 대하여 상기하도록 도와 줍니다.</para>
			<para>명령어 줄을 사용할 때 sudo 를 사용하려면, 실행할 명령어 앞에 "sudo" 라고 간단히 입력하십시오. sudo 는 여러분의 패스워드를 묻게 될 것입니다.</para>
			<para>Sudo will remember your password for a set amount of time, which by default is 15 minutes, but can be changed. This feature was designed to allow users to perform multiple administrative tasks without being asked for a password each time.
			</para>
				   <note>
						<para>관리적인 작업을 할 때 조심하지 않으면, 여러분은 시스템을 손상시킬 수도 있습니다!</para>
				   </note>
			<para>sudo 사용의 다른 팁:</para>
			<itemizedlist>
				<listitem>
				<para>"root" 터미널을 사용하려면 명령줄에서 "sudo -i" 를 입력하십시오.</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
				<para>우분투의 모든 기본 GUI 설정도구는 이미 sudo 를 사용하고 있어서 만약 필요하다면 패스워드를 묻게 될 것입니다.</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
				<para>For more information on the <application>sudo</application> program and the absence of a root user in Ubuntu, read the <ulink url="&wiki-RootSudo;">sudo page</ulink> on the Ubuntu wiki.
				</para>
				</listitem>

			</itemizedlist>
		</chapter>

