<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.3//EN" 
	"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.3/docbookx.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % globalent SYSTEM "../../../libs/global.ent">
%globalent;
<!ENTITY % cdo-C SYSTEM "../../../libs/cdo-C.ent">
%cdo-C;
<!ENTITY % gnome-menus-ko SYSTEM "../../../ubuntu/libs/gnome-menus-ko.ent">
%gnome-menus-ko;
<!ENTITY % xinclude SYSTEM "../../../libs/xinclude.mod">
%xinclude;
<!ENTITY language "en">
<!ENTITY ubuntu '<phrase>Ubuntu</phrase>'>
]>
<chapter id="music" status="complete">
			<title>Music and Video</title>
				<para>This section describes the music and video players available to use with Ubuntu and how to configure them to listen to different types of multimedia files.</para>
			<sect1 id="music-files" status="complete">
					<title>음악 파일을 정리하고 재생하기</title>
				<para>To play and organize your music, Ubuntu comes with		    <application>Rhythmbox Music Player</application>, which looks similar to <application>iTunes</application>. When you first start <application>Rhythmbox</application>, it will scan your home directory for any supported music files you have and add it to the database. To start <application>Rhythmbox</application>, choose &rhythmbox;.</para>
					<para>Ubuntu does not directly support the <emphasis role="strong">MP3</emphasis> format, because it is restricted by patents and proprietary rights. Instead Ubuntu supports the <emphasis role="strong">Ogg Vorbis</emphasis> format out of the box, a completely free, open and non-patented format. Ogg Vorbis files also sound better then MP3 files of the same file size and are supported by many portable music players.</para>
					<itemizedlist>
						<listitem><para><ulink url="http://wiki.xiph.org/index.php/PortablePlayers">Players that work with Vorbis</ulink></para></listitem>
					</itemizedlist>
					<para>You can still play your old MP3 files by installing MP3 support (see <xref linkend="codecs"/>). Instructions for other formats, such as Windows Media Audio (wma/wmv) and other patent-encumbered formats can be found <ulink url="http://wiki.ubuntu.com/RestrictedFormats">on the Ubuntu Wiki</ulink>.</para>
				<para><application>Cowbell</application> ID3 태그 편집기는 여러분의 mp3 와 다른 음악 파일의 메타 데이터를 편집 할 수 있습니다. <application>Cowbell</application>을 사용하려면:</para>
				<procedure>
						<step>
							<para>Install the <application>cowbell</application> package from the <quote>Universe</quote> repository (see <xref linkend="add-applications"/>);</para>
						</step>
						<step>
							<para>To run <application>Cowbell</application>, choose
								<menuchoice>
									<guimenu>Applications</guimenu>
									<guisubmenu>Sound &amp; Video</guisubmenu>
									<guimenuitem>Cowbell Music Organizer</guimenuitem>
								</menuchoice>.
							</para>
						</step>
				</procedure>
			</sect1>
			<sect1 id="audio-cds" status="complete">
				<title>오디오 CD를 연주하고, 오디오 CD에서 음원 추출하기</title>
				<para>오디오 CD를 넣었을 때, <application>Sound Juicer</application> CD 플레이어가 자동으로 실행됩니다. CD를 연주하려면 <guibutton>Play</guibutton> 버튼을 누르거나 <keycombo><keycap>Ctrl</keycap><keycap>P</keycap></keycombo>를 누르십시오. 일부 트랙을 연주하려면 트랙을 더블클릭하거나 트랙을 선택한 후<guibutton>Play</guibutton>를 누르십시오.</para>
				<para>오디오 CD에서 음원을 추출하려면 추출하길 원하는 트랙을 선택하고 <guibutton>Extract</guibutton> 버튼을 클릭하거나 <keycombo><keycap>Ctrl</keycap><keycap>Enter</keycap></keycombo>를 누르십시오.</para>
					<note>
						<para>If you are connected to the internet, <application>Sound Juicer</application> will retrieve the CD artist, title, and track data from <ulink url="http://musicbrainz.org">MusicBrainz.org</ulink>, a community-maintained database of over 360,000 albums.
						</para>
					</note>
				<para>To start <application>Sound Juicer</application> manually, choose 
				<menuchoice>
					<guimenu>Applications</guimenu>
					<guimenuitem>Sound &amp; Video</guimenuitem>
					<guimenuitem>Sound Juicer CD Extractor</guimenuitem>
				</menuchoice>.
				</para>
				<para>You can use the preferences window to control where the extracted audio files are stored on your computer, the filename of extracted audio files, and the file format and codec used for the files. In the main window, choose 
				<menuchoice>
					<guimenu>Edit</guimenu>
					<guimenuitem>Preferences</guimenuitem>
				</menuchoice>.
				</para>
				<para><application>Sound Juicer</application> can extract audio files to these formats:
					<itemizedlist>
						<listitem>
							<para><emphasis role="strong">Ogg Vorbis</emphasis> - A patent-free lossy audio compression format, which typically produces higher quality and greater compression than MP3.</para>
							<itemizedlist>
								<listitem><para><ulink url="http://vorbis.com/faq/">More about Vorbis from vorbis.com</ulink></para></listitem>
							</itemizedlist>
						</listitem>
						<listitem>
							<para><emphasis role="strong">FLAC</emphasis> - The Free Lossless Audio Codec. It can compress audio files up to 50% without removing any information from the audio stream.</para>
							<itemizedlist>
								<listitem><para><ulink url="http://flac.sourceforge.net/">FLAC Web site</ulink></para></listitem>
							</itemizedlist>
						</listitem>
						<listitem>
							<para><emphasis role="strong">WAV</emphasis> - Typically used for voice recordings. <application>Sound Juicer</application> uses this format for low quality mono audio files. 
							</para>
						</listitem>
					</itemizedlist>
				</para>
				<para>You can also extract CD audio files to the proprietary non-free <emphasis role="strong">MP3</emphasis> format. Instructions on how to rip to the MP3 format are in the help for <application>Sound Juicer</application>. Choose 
				<menuchoice>
					<guimenu>Help</guimenu>
					<guisubmenu>Contents</guisubmenu>
				</menuchoice> and navigate to the <emphasis>Preferences</emphasis> section.
				</para>
			</sect1>
			<sect1 id="burning-cds" status="complete">
					<title>CD 굽기</title>
					<para>드라이브에 빈 CD 를 넣었을 때 우분투는 음악 CD 혹은 데이터 CD 를 굽기를 원하는지 묻습니다. <guibutton>음악 CD 굽기</guibutton>를 클릭하면 <application>Serpentine</application> 을 실행할 것입니다. 음악을 여러분의 음악 CD 에 추가하기 위해서는 파일 브라우저에서 음악을 드래그하거나 <guibutton>더하기</guibutton> 버튼을 사용합니다. 또한 CD 의 크기(21, 74, 80, 90분)도 선택할 수 있습니다. Serpentine 은 지정한 제한을 넘으면 여러분에게 경고할 것입니다.</para>
					<para>To make a photo or data CD, click <guibutton>Burn Data CD</guibutton>. Ubuntu will open a CD/DVD Creator window. The CD Creator is built into the File Browser, and it allows you to add any file or folder you have permission to access. When you are ready to burn the CD, click <guibutton>Write to Disc</guibutton>. Ubuntu will then prompt you to select the drive containing the blank CD, and give you the opportunity to name the CD and select the write speed. Finally, click <guibutton>Write</guibutton> to create the new photo or data CD.
					</para>
			</sect1>

		<sect1 id="video">
		<title>Video Playback</title>
		<para>To play video, Ubuntu comes with <application>Totem Movie Player</application>, which looks and functions similar to Windows Media Player. Features of
		<application>Totem</application> include custom playlists and DVD playback. 
	        You can start <application>Totem</application> by clicking: &totem; from the desktop menu system.
		</para>
		<para>동영상 파일을 읽으려면 <application>Gstreamer</application> 프레임워크에 기반한 <application>토템</application>을 이용하면 됩니다. 몇몇 동영상 형식을 재생하기 위해서는 추가 코덱이 필요할 수도 있습니다. (<xref linkend="codecs"/>를 살펴보십시오.)</para>
		<para>There are also other multimedia applications available. Examples include <application>Mplayer</application>, <application>Xine</application> and <application>Totem-xine</application> (which uses the <application>Xine</application> framework, instead of the <application>Gstreamer</application> framework). You may benefit from trying alternative video players.</para>
		</sect1>

		<sect1 id="codecs" status="complete">
		<title>멀티미디어 코덱</title>
			<para>우분투의 많은 프로그램은 오픈 소스 멀티미디어 프레임워크 <application>GStreamer</application>를 사용합니다. <application>GStreamer</application>의 코덱 플러그인은 다양한 코덱에 적용된 라이센스에 종속되어진 다른 꾸러미에 구성되어 있습니다. 여러분은 <ulink url="http://gstreamer.freedesktop.org/documentation/plugins.html">GStreamer website</ulink>에서 플러그인에 포함된 코덱들을 볼 수 있습니다.</para>
			<para>Other applications, such as <application>Mplayer</application> and <application>Xine</application>, do not use the <application>Gstreamer</application> framework. Due to patent and copyright restrictions, codecs for these programs are not included at all in Ubuntu. For more information on these read the <ulink url="&restricted-formats;">Restricted Formats</ulink> wiki page.</para>
			<para><application>Gstreamer</application> 에 추가 코덱을 설치하려면:</para>
				<procedure>
					<step>
							<para>Install the following packages from the <quote>Universe</quote> and <quote>Multiverse</quote> repositories (see <xref linkend="add-applications"/>):
								<literallayout>gstreamer0.10-plugins-ugly
gstreamer0.10-plugins-ugly-multiverse
gstreamer0.10-plugins-bad
gstreamer0.10-plugins-bad-multiverse
gstreamer0.10-ffmpeg
								</literallayout>
							</para>
							<note>
								<para>You will need to use <application>Synaptic Package Manager</application> to install these packages.
								</para>
							</note>
							<warning>
								<para>이 꾸러미 중 몇몇은 어떤 나라에서는 허용되지 않을 것입니다: 설치전에 여러분에게 패키지의 사용이 허용되는지 먼저 확인하세요.</para>
							</warning>
					</step>
				</procedure>
	</sect1>

			<sect1 id="ipod" status="complete">
			        <title>Using an iPod</title>
				<para>You can play music directly off an iPod with <application>Rhythmbox Music Player</application>. Plug the iPod into the computer, and open <application>Rhythmbox</application>.</para>
				<para>To transfer music files to and from an iPod, you can use <application>gtkpod</application>:</para>
					<procedure>
					<step>
						<para>Install the <application>gtkpod</application> package from the <quote>Universe</quote> repository (see <xref linkend="add-applications"/>).
						</para>
					</step>
					<step>
						<para>To run <application>gtkpod</application>, choose
								<menuchoice>
									<guimenu>Applications</guimenu>
									<guisubmenu>Sound &amp; Video</guisubmenu>
									<guimenuitem>gtkpod</guimenuitem>
								</menuchoice>.
						</para>
					</step>
					</procedure>
			</sect1>
			<sect1 id="edit-audio-files" status="complete">
				<title>음악 파일 편집하기</title>
					<para>Audacity 는 소리를 편집하고 녹음하는 자유, 오픈 소스 소프트웨어입니다. Audacity를 사용하시려면:</para>
					<procedure>
						<step>
							<para>Install the audacity package from the <quote>Universe</quote> repository (see <xref linkend="add-applications"/>).
							</para>
						</step>
						<step>
							<para>To run <application>Audacity</application>, choose
								<menuchoice>
									<guimenu>Applications</guimenu>
									<guisubmenu>Sound &amp; Video</guisubmenu>
									<guimenuitem>Audacity</guimenuitem>
								</menuchoice>.
							</para>
						</step>
						<step>
							<para>For further help with Audacity, use Audacity’s <guimenu>Help</guimenu> menu.</para>
						</step>							
					</procedure>
			</sect1>

		<sect1 id="dvdplayback" status="complete">
			<title>DVD 재생기</title>
				<para>우분투에 있는 동영상 재생기는 암호화되어 있지 않은 DVD를 읽을 수 있습니다. 하지만, 대부분의 상업용 DVD는 CSS(the Content Scrambling System)으로 암호화 되어 있고, 법적인 이유로 우분투에서 지원하지 않습니다. 그러나, 다음과 같이 사용할 수 있습니다:</para>
				<warning><para>이 라이브러리가 합법적인 지에 대한 것은 완전히 명백하지 않습니다. 몇몇 나라에서는 이 라이브러리로 DVD를 재생하고 복사하는 것이 법으로 제재를 받을 수 있습니다. 이것을 사용해도 되는 지 확인하시기 바랍니다.</para></warning>
				<procedure>
					<step>
						<para><application>libdvdread3</application> 꾸러미를 설치하십시오. (<xref linkend="add-applications"/>를 살펴보십시오.)</para>
					<note><para>이 꾸러미를 설치하기 위해서 <application>시냅틱 꾸러미 관리자</application>를 사용할 필요가 있습니다.</para></note>
					</step>
					<step>
						<para>To activate DVD decryption, type the following line into a terminal prompt:<screen>sudo /usr/share/doc/libdvdread3/install-css.sh</screen>
						</para>
					</step>
					<step>
						<para>DVD 를 <application>Totem</application>으로 재생하려면 추가 코덱을 설치해야 합니다(<xref linkend="codecs"/> 참조).</para>
					</step>
					<step>
						<para>However, the <application>Gstreamer</application> framework (used by <application>Totem</application>) does not support menus or subtitles for DVD playback. For this reason, you can install a separate DVD player, <application>Xine</application>, which supports these. To install <application>Xine</application>, install the <application>gxine</application> package from the <quote>Universe</quote> repository (see <xref linkend="add-applications"/>).</para>
					</step>
					<step>
						<para>여러분은 음악과 비디오 메뉴에서 <application>gxine</application>을 실행 할 수 있습니다.</para>
					</step>
				</procedure>
		</sect1>

			<sect1 status="complete">
				<title>DVD 백업하기</title>
					<para>You can back up your DVDs to files or onto DVD+/- discs with <application>DVD::RIP</application>. To install
<application>DVD::RIP</application>:</para>
					<warning><para>DVD 를 백업하기 전에 여러분은 합법적으로 그 것의 복사본을 만드는 것이 허용되는지 보증되어야만 합니다.</para></warning>
					<procedure>
						<step>
							<para>멀티미디어 코덱을 설치하세요.(<xref linkend="codecs"/> 참조)</para>
						</step>
						<step>
							<para>DVD 동영상 재생을 활성화합니다.(<xref linkend="dvdplayback"/> 참조)</para>
						</step>
						<step>
							<para>Install <application>dvdrip</application> and <application>transcode</application> from the <quote>Multiverse</quote> repository (see <xref linkend="add-applications"/>).
							</para>
						</step>
						<step>
							<para>You can run the program using the command <application>dvdrip</application> (see <ulink type="help" url="ghelp:user-guide#tools-run-app">the run application manual</ulink> for help on how to run an application without using the menu). If you wish, you can add a menu entry for the program <application>dvdrip</application> (see <ulink type="help" url="ghelp:user-guide#menu-editor">the menu editor manual</ulink> for help on how to add menu entries). We recommend you enter it in the Sound &amp; Video menu, and that you use the file <filename>/usr/share/perl5/Video/DVDRip/icon.xpm</filename> for the icon.
							</para>
						</step>
						<step>
							<para>To start  <application>dvd::rip</application>, choose
								<menuchoice>
									<guimenu>Applications</guimenu>
									<guisubmenu>Sound &amp; Video</guisubmenu>
									<guimenuitem>dvd::rip</guimenuitem>
								</menuchoice>.
							</para>
						</step>
					</procedure>
			</sect1>
		<sect1 status="complete">
			<title>RealPlayer</title>
					<procedure>
						<step>
							<para>Install the <application>realplay</application> package from the <emphasis>Commercial</emphasis> repository (see <xref linkend="add-applications"/>).</para>
						</step>
						<step>
							<para>To run <application>RealPlayer</application>, choose
								<menuchoice>
									<guimenu>Applications</guimenu>
									<guisubmenu>Sound &amp; Video</guisubmenu>
									<guimenuitem>RealPlayer 10</guimenuitem>
								</menuchoice>.
							</para>
						</step>
					</procedure>
			</sect1>
			<sect1 status="complete">
					<title>동영상 편집하기</title>
					<para><application>Kino</application>는 고급 동영상 편집기입니다. 그 것은 캡쳐를 위한 IEEE-1394, VTR 제어, 카메라로 레코딩하는 것의 완벽한 통합이 특징입니다. 동영상을 원본 DV 와 AVI 형식, type-1 DV 과 type-2 DV (분리된 오디오 출력) 인코딩으로 캡쳐합니다. 더 많은 정보는 <ulink url="http://www.kinodv.org/article/static/2">the Kino website</ulink>를 보세요. 사용하기 위해서:</para>
					<procedure>
						<step>
							<para><application>kino</application> 꾸러미를 설치하십시오. (<xref linkend="add-applications"/>를 살펴보십시오.)</para>
						</step>
						<step>
							<para>To run <application>Kino</application>, choose
								<menuchoice>
									<guimenu>Applications</guimenu>
									<guisubmenu>Sound &amp; Video</guisubmenu>
									<guimenuitem>Kino Video Editor</guimenuitem>
								</menuchoice>.
							</para>
						</step>
					</procedure>
					<para>You can also try the <application>PiTiVi</application> video editor by installing the <application>pitivi</application> package from the <quote>Universe</quote> repository (see <xref linkend="add-applications"/>). <application>PiTiVi</application> is a video editor for the GNOME desktop. It is still in fairly early development, but worth a try.</para>
			</sect1>
	   </chapter>

