<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.3//EN" 
	"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.3/docbookx.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % xinclude SYSTEM "../../libs/xinclude.mod">
%xinclude;
<!ENTITY % globalent SYSTEM "../../libs/global.ent">
%globalent;
]>
<chapter id="installing-windowsdualboot">
    <title>Dual-booting with Windows</title>
    <para>Let’s assume you are a Windows user, and have been for a decent length of time – long
        enough that all of your computing habits are Windows based, as it’s all you have ever known.
        You have heard about Linux, free or open source programs, and it has attracted your attention
        long enough that you have decided you want to try it. You don’t want to completely abandon
        Windows for a multitude of reasons – you know how to use it, you know the shortcuts, and you
        are afraid of breaking your computing world with one fell disto sized sweep. You want to
        dual boot, and you have picked Ubuntu for its seemingly simple installation, ease of use, and
        community (Ubuntu: &quot;humanity toward others&quot;).</para>
    <para>First things first - you need to get your hands on the actual distribution that you plan
        to install. Ubuntu’s current stable release is Warty – you can download the ISO and burn the
        CD yourself, or you can place an order with Ubuntu and have the CD sent to your doorstep –
        free of charge! The latter will take a bit of time if you are in the States, as the CDs ship
        from Europe; however they are well worth the wait and come in a professional looking
        package.</para>
    <para>In this chapter we discuss the steps required for preparation and installation of Ubuntu in
        a dual boot environment.</para>
    <sect1 id="sect-dualbooting-winxp" status="writing">
        <title>Dual Booting Ubuntu with Windows 2000/XP</title>
        <authorblurb>
            <para>Sean Wheller: This writup from Kevin Mulligan who notes: These instructions were
                created using a machine running Windows 2000 Pro, not XP. The install should be
                nearly identical for XP.</para>
        </authorblurb>
        <sect2 id="sect-dualbooting-winxp-prep">
            <title>Preparation</title>
            <para>Now you need to prepare your current Windows system to accept Ubuntu in a happy
                manner. You will need a partitioning program – popular options are Partition Magic
                ($), Partimage (free), and QtParted (free available both separately and on the
                amazing System Rescue CD). I went with the System Rescue CD. </para>
            <para>You need to open up some free space on your drive for Ubuntu to install to. This
                is as simple as creating a new partition with the ext3 file system – easily
                achievable in the above programs. You may also want to consider creating a FAT32
                partition. Why? Linux cannot access NTFS partitions, but both Windows and Linux can
                access FAT32. A common option is to put programs that will be used on both operating
                systems (e-mail, browser, etc.) on the FAT32 partition to prevent installing the
                programs on the separate operating systems. This also keeps everything together at
                one point, so that e-mails or bookmarks are not left stranded on the other operating
                system. </para>
            <para>After you have created the ext3 partition (5-10GB if you intend to use Ubuntu
                frequently, considering today’s drive sizes), put your Ubuntu CD in your CD-ROM and
                reboot. If your system boots normally – back into Windows – you need to change your
                boot order settings in your BIOS (hold down F8 or Del at the beginning of the boot
                process; Google for more information) to read the CD-ROM before the hard
            drive.</para>
        </sect2>
        <sect2 id="sect-dualbooting-winxp-inst">
            <title>Installation</title>
            <para>If your boot order is correct, the installation will start. Ubuntu’s installer is
                a simple text-based guide, and is easy to follow. Following the on screen
                instructions will set up your system pretty quickly. As a Windows user, one hitch
                you must notice is that Ubuntu will attempt to install a new boot loader in your
                Master Boot Record (MBR); the default boot loader provided by Ubuntu is GRUB; LILO
                is available. </para>
            <para>You have two options. The first is to let GRUB overwrite the Windows boot manager
                in the MBR; this will severely break your installation if you ever attempt to remove
                GRUB, as Windows will become severely confused. Reinstallation of the Windows MBR is
                not difficult (Google), but may require a Windows rescue CD. If you plan to continue
                using Ubuntu, or other distros, this is not an issue. Your second option is to
                install GRUB on a separate partition, and point the Windows boot manager to its
                location so you can access GRUB and Ubuntu.</para>
            <para>Install GRUB, select your time and region settings, and point the installer toward
                the ext3 partition you created to install Ubuntu on it. The installer may ask a few
                more questions, and your Ubuntu operating system is ready for your use. Reboot,
                remove the install CD from the CD-ROM, change your BIOS settings back to boot from
                your drive first, reboot once more and your computer should load into GRUB. It
                should list Ubuntu, a safe mode for Ubuntu, a memory test, and your Windows
                installation. Make your selection, and enjoy your new operating system.</para>
        </sect2>
    </sect1>
</chapter>
