<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.3//EN" 
	"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.3/docbookx.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % xinclude SYSTEM "../../libs/xinclude.mod">
%xinclude;
<!ENTITY % globalent SYSTEM "../../libs/global.ent">
%globalent;
]>
<chapter id="installing-installation" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
    <title>Installing from CD</title>
    <sect1 id="sect-installation" status="review">
        <title>Booting the Installer</title>
        <para>Download this CD image and burn it to a CD: To boot the CD, you may need to enter your
            BIOS configuration menu and configure the list of boot devices to include the CD-ROM drive.</para>
        <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
                <para>A netboot install is also available, but for now it is outside the scope of
                    this document.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Once the installer starts, you will be greeted with an initial splash screen.
                    Press Enter to boot, or use the function keys to read the instructions for other
                    boot methods and parameters. If you have problems booting the installer, these
                    instructions document a number of workarounds that may be useful depending on
                    your hardware.</para>
            </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
    </sect1>
    <sect1 id="first-stage-inst" status="review">
        <title>First Stage of Installation</title>
        <para>After a few moments, you will be asked to select your language. </para>
        <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
                <para>Use the arrow keys to pick a language and press Enter to continue.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Next you'll be asked to select a country, with the choices including countries
                    where your language is spoken. If it's not on the short list, choose
                    &quot;other&quot; to see a list of all the countries in the world.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Now sit back while the installer detects some of your hardware, and loads the
                    rest of itself from the CD.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Next the installer will try to detect your network hardware and set up
                    networking by DHCP. If you are not on a network or do not have DHCP, you will be
                    given the opportunity to configure the network manually.</para>
            </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
    </sect1>
    <sect1 id="partition-disck" status="review">
        <title>Partition Your Disk</title>
        <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
                <para>First you will be given the opportunity to erase and automatically partition
                    an entire disk. This is recommended for new users, but if you have any valuable
                    data on the disk, be sure to back it up first, as it will be erased!</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>If you do not want to erase an entire disk, or if you want to customize the
                    partition layout, choose &quot;Manually edit partition table&quot; from
                    the menu, and the next screen will show you your partition table, how the
                    partitions will be formatted, and where they will be mounted.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Select a partition to modify or delete it. Remember to assign at least one
                    partition for swap space and to mount a partition on /. Choose &quot;Finish
                    partitioning and write changes to disk&quot; when you are finished.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>After confirmation, the installer formats your partitions and starts to
                    install the base system, which can take a while. That is followed by installing
                    a kernel, then by copying the remainder of the packages on the CD to your hard
                    disk so that you no longer need the CD.</para>
            </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
    </sect1>
    <sect1 id="inst-boot-load" status="review">
        <title>Install a Boot Loader</title>
        <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
                <para>If the installer detects other operating systems on your computer, it will add
                    them to the boot menu.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>The installer will now tell you that the first stage has finished.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Remove the CD and hit Enter to reboot your machine. It should boot up into the
                    second stage of the installation process.</para>
            </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
    </sect1>
    <sect1 id="second-stage-inst" status="review">
        <title>Second Stage of Installation</title>
        <para> After rebooting, you will be prompted to complete the configuration of your basic
            system. </para>
        <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
                <para>Following a welcome screen, you will be prompted to configure your time zone.
                    Depending on the location selected at the beginning of the installation process,
                    you will be shown either a single timezone or a list of timezones relevant for
                    that location. If a single timezone is shown, choose Yes to confirm or choose No
                    to select from the full list of timezones. If a list is shown, select your
                    timezone from the list, or select &quot;other&quot; for the full list.</para>
            </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
    </sect1>
    <sect1 id="user-acount" status="review">
        <title>User Account</title>
        <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
                <para>Enter your full name, then choose a username for the user account; generally
                    your first name or something similar will suffice and indeed will be the default.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Finally, choose a password. Note that the administrative
                    &quot;root&quot; account is disabled; you may access it using the
                    &quot;sudo&quot; program from the user account you create at this point.
                    If you wish to set the root password, run &quot;sudo passwd root&quot;
                    from a terminal.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>If your system is not connected to a network, you will be given the
                    opportunity to set up PPP, which allows you to connect to a dial-up Internet provider.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>After this, a set of packages suitable for ordinary desktop use will be
                    automatically installed. In the process, depending on your graphics card and
                    monitor, one or two questions may be asked about the kind of graphics card you
                    have and the screen resolution you would like to use.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Go and get something to drink while the messages about package installation
                    scroll by. When they finish, a graphical login screen will appear.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Type the username you selected earlier, followed by the password for the user
                    account, and the Ubuntu desktop will appear.</para>
            </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
    </sect1>
</chapter>
