<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.3//EN" 
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.3/docbookx.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % globalent SYSTEM "../../../libs/global.ent">
%globalent;
<!ENTITY % cdo-C SYSTEM "../../../libs/cdo-C.ent">
%cdo-C;
<!ENTITY % gnome-menus-C SYSTEM "../../libs/edubuntu-menus-C.ent">
%gnome-menus-C;
<!ENTITY % edubuntuent SYSTEM "../../libs/edubuntu.ent">
%edubuntuent;
<!ENTITY % xinclude SYSTEM "../../../libs/xinclude.mod">
%xinclude;
<!ENTITY language "en">
<!ENTITY ubuntu '<phrase>Ubuntu</phrase>'>
<!ENTITY edubuntu '<phrase>Edubuntu</phrase>'>
]>
<chapter id="using" status="review">
<title>Use, Configure, Support, and Contribute</title>

<!-- APPLICATIONS -->
<sect1 id="using-apps" status="draft">
<title>Introduction to available software</title>

<para>
Edubuntu builds to be a complete and ready to use educational environment. As
such, Edubuntu comes pre-installed with a complete office suite, teaching and
learning programs, pre-school resources and much more across a range of
categories. Here is a brief summary and some screenshots for the most popular
Edubuntu packages, and if you need more, Edubuntu has thousands of additional
applications ready for you to install.
</para>

<!-- OFFICE SUITE - OPENOFFICE.ORG -->
<sect2 id="using-apps-office" status="draft">
<title>Office Suite</title>

<para>
OpenOffice.org is a complete office suite similar to other, commercial
office suites. It features a word processor, as well as spreadsheet,
presentation, drawing, database, and mathematical formula applications.
OpenOffice.org can open and convert most documents from other commercial office suites and has
support for many different languages.
</para>

<informalfigure>
<mediaobject>
<imageobject>
<imagedata fileref="../../images/C/openoffice.png" format="PNG"/>
</imageobject>
</mediaobject>
</informalfigure>

</sect2>

<!-- INTERNET -->
<sect2 id="using-apps-internet" status="draft">
<title>Internet</title>

<para>
Firefox is the incredible successor to the hugely popular Mozilla browser.
Amongst its many features are tabbed browsing, which makes viewing multiple
sites a breeze, pop-up blocking, live bookmarks and great accessibility support.
Combine these with its fantastic customization engine and you have the most
powerful web browsing at your fingertips.
</para>

<para>
Moving beyond the simple web browser, Edubuntu also comes with an email client
and personal information manager, Evolution. Video conferencing with Ekiga
as well as instant messaging and chat with Gaim provide communications tools
that teachers and students need in an Internet age.
</para>

<informalfigure>
<mediaobject>
<imageobject>
<imagedata fileref="../../images/C/internet.png" format="PNG"/>
</imageobject>
</mediaobject>
</informalfigure>

</sect2>

<!-- GRAPHICS -->
<sect2 id="using-apps-graphics" status="draft">
<title>Graphics</title>

<para>
In the graphics department, diagrams and flowcharts are a breeze with Dia. Xsane
provides an easy to use scanner interface. 3D modeling and animation are
Blender's speciality. Image editing similar to other professional photo editors is done using the
GIMP. Scribus provides layout and publishing capabilites.
</para>

<informalfigure>
<mediaobject>
<imageobject>
<imagedata fileref="../../images/C/graphics.png" format="PNG"/>
</imageobject>
</mediaobject>
</informalfigure>

</sect2>

<!-- MULTIMEDIA -->
<sect2 id="using-apps-multimedia" status="draft">
<title>Sound and Video</title>

<para>
For all your video and audio play and editing needs, Edubuntu provides several
programs including Rhythmbox for music playing and Serpentine for burning audio
CDs. Sound Juicer rips audio CD tracks to your computer. Totem is an excellent
video and movie player and you can use Kino to edit video clips. Sound Recorder
can be used to record audio clips to your computer.
</para>

<informalfigure>
<mediaobject>
<imageobject>
<imagedata fileref="../../images/C/soundandvideo.png" format="PNG"/>
</imageobject>
</mediaobject>
</informalfigure>

</sect2>

<!-- SCIENCE -->
<sect2 id="using-apps-science" status="draft">
<title>Science</title>

<sect3 id="using-apps-science-stars" status="draft">
<title>Explore the stars</title>

<para>
KStars is a Desktop Planetarium that provides an accurate graphical simulation
of the night sky. The program includes details for 130000 stars, 13000 deep-sky
objects and all of the planets. KStars has an easy to use interface, so it can
be used by everyone, from amateurs through to astronomy experts. You will also
find a great deal of general information regarding telescopes and other
astronomy related matter.
</para>

</sect3>

<sect3 id="using-apps-science-table" status="draft">
<title>Research the periodic table</title>

<para>Kalzium is a package for discovering and researching information about the
periodic table and the elements. It includes pictures for most of the 111
elements present, along with more detailed information including atomic models,
spectrum analysis, chemical data and energies.
</para>

</sect3>

<sect3 id="using-apps-science-chem" status="draft">
<title>Test your chemistry skills</title>

<para>
Atomix is a puzzle game, the purpose of which is to make up the molecule
displayed from the pieces scattered throughout the level. You can only move them
up, down, left and right and they don't stop moving until they hit something.
</para>

<informalfigure>
<mediaobject>
<imageobject>
<imagedata fileref="../../images/C/science.png" format="PNG"/>
</imageobject>
</mediaobject>
</informalfigure>

</sect3>
</sect2>

<sect2 id="using-apps-math" status="draft">
<title>Mathematics</title>

<sect3 id="using-apps-math-logo" status="draft">
<title>Program in Logo</title>

<para>
KTurtle is a Logo programming language interpreter. The Logo programming
language is very easy to learn and thus it can be used by young children.
A unique quality of Logo is that the commands or instructions can be translated,
so the 'programmer' can program in his or her native language. This makes Logo
ideal for teaching kids the basics of programming, mathematics and geometry. One
of the reasons many children warm to Logo is due to fact that the programmable
icon is a small turtle, which can be moved around the screen with simple
commands and can be programmed to draw objects.
</para>

</sect3>

<sect3 id="using-apps-math-geometry" status="draft">
<title>Create geometric constructions</title>

<para>
Kig is an application that allows teachers and students to create high precision
geometrical constructions. These can be built on and used to explain concepts
like perpendicular bisectors, tangents and arcs.
</para>

</sect3>

<sect3 id="using-apps-math-plotting" status="draft">
<title>Plot mathematical equations</title>

<para>
KmPlot is a mathematical function graphing and plotting package. KmPlot has a
built in powerful expression parser and you can plot different functions
simultaneously and combine their terms to build more complex mathematical
functions. It supports functions with parameters and functions in polar
coordinates. Plots may also be printed with high precision.
</para>

</sect3>

<sect3 id="using-apps-math-percent" status="draft">
<title>Calculate percentages</title>

<para>
KPercentage is a mathematical application that helps pupils improve their skills
in calculating percentages. Percentages are split into three types and
KPercentage tests pupils on these in three training modes. In addition
to this, there is a random mode which will pick questions from each of the three
percentage question variations.
</para>

</sect3>

<sect3 id="using-apps-math-fractions" status="draft">
<title>Practice Fractions</title>

<para>
KBruch is a small program to help pupils practice calculations involving
fractions. There are four different types of fraction exercise:
<itemizedlist>
<listitem>
<para>
Exercise Fraction Task; where pupils have to solve a given fraction task.
</para>
</listitem>

<listitem>
<para>
Exercise Comparison; where pupils have to compare 2 given fractions sizes.
</para>
</listitem>

<listitem>
<para>
Exercise Conversion; where pupils have to convert an already given number into
a fraction.
</para>
</listitem>

<listitem>
<para>
Exercise Factorization; where pupils have to factorize a given number into its
prime factor.
</para>
</listitem>

</itemizedlist>
</para>

</sect3>

<sect3 id="using-apps-math-play" status="draft">
<title>Play at Math</title>

<para>
TuxMath is an educational arcade game starring Tux, the Linux mascot! Based on
the classic arcade game "Missile Command," Tux must defend his cities by solving
arithmetic problems.
</para>

<informalfigure>
<mediaobject>
<imageobject>
<imagedata fileref="../../images/C/maths.png" format="PNG"/>
</imageobject>
</mediaobject>
</informalfigure>

</sect3>
</sect2>

<!-- DRAWING -->
<sect2 id="using-apps-drawing" status="draft">
<title>Drawing</title>

<sect3 id="using-apps-drawing-tuxpaint" status="draft">
<title>Tux Paint</title>

<para>
Tux Paint is a free drawing program designed for young children. The program
provides an easy to use interface with fun sound effects and an encouraging
cartoon mascot that gives help to children while they are painting.
</para>

</sect3>

<sect3 id="usng-apps-drawing-fractals" status="draft">
<title>Generate Fractals</title>

<para>
Xaos is a fractal generator with a whole host of extra features for teaching
pupils about fractal patterns.
</para>

<informalfigure>
<mediaobject>
<imageobject>
<imagedata fileref="../../images/C/drawing.png" format="PNG"/>
</imageobject>
</mediaobject>
</informalfigure>

</sect3>
</sect2>

<!-- LANGUAGE -->
<sect2 id="using-apps-lang" status="draft">
<title>Language</title>

<sect3 id="using-apps-lang-spanish" status="draft">
<title>Practice Spanish verbs</title>

<para>
With KVerbos you can practice Spanish verb conjugation. The program comes with a
large set of over 9,000 Spanish verbs that you can choose from to begin your
verb training. The package also keeps track of previous scores so that pupils
can identify where their strengths and weaknesses are. Some exercises also
have a time limit to raise the level of difficulty for more advanced users.
</para>

</sect3>

<sect3 id="using-apps-lang-hangman" status="draft">
<title>Play Hangman</title>

<para>
KHangman is the classic hangman game with pupils try to guess a word, letter by
letter. At each miss, the picture of a hangman is added to. After 10 incorrect
tries the game is over.
</para>

<informalfigure>
<mediaobject>
<imageobject>
<imagedata fileref="../../images/C/language.png" format="PNG"/>
</imageobject>
</mediaobject>
</informalfigure>

</sect3>
</sect2>

<!-- BASIC SKILLS -->
<sect2 id="using-apps-skills" status="draft">
<title>Basic Skills</title>

<sect3 id="using-apps-skills-keduca" status="draft">
<title>Generate and give tests</title>

<para>
KEduca is an educational testing package, allowing teachers to create tests for
pupils to take. KEduca includes a module for constructing and saving new tests,
as well as a separate module for loading and running the exams. Questions can be
enhanced with images, multiple choice answers with varying grades, and time
limits.
</para>

</sect3>

<sect3 id="using-apps-skills-typing" status="draft">
<title>Learn touch typing</title>

<para>
KTouch helps pupils to learn to type quickly and correctly. With many different
modes and detailed reporting, KTouch truly makes learning touching typing
easily.
</para>

</sect3>

<sect3 id="using-apps-skills-gcompris" status="draft">
<title>Gcompris</title>

<para>
Gcompris is a suite of over 80 educational games and activities for kids age 4
to 10 to learn with. These include:
<itemizedlist>
<listitem>
<para>
Computer discovery: keyboard, mouse.
</para>
</listitem>

<listitem>
<para>
Algebra: table memory, enumeration, double entry table, mirror image.
</para>
</listitem>

<listitem>
<para>
Science: the canal lock, the water cycle, the submarine, electric simulation.
</para>
</listitem>

<listitem>
<para>
Geography: place the country on the map.
</para>
</listitem>

<listitem>
<para>
Games: chess, memory, connect 4, oware, sudoku.
</para>
</listitem>

<listitem>
<para>
Reading: reading practice.
</para>
</listitem>

<listitem>
<para>
Other: learn to tell time, puzzle of famous paintings, vector drawing.
</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</para>

</sect3>
</sect2>
</sect1>

<!-- DOCUMENTATION AND SUPPORT -->
<sect1 id="using-docandsup" status="draft">
<title>Documentation and Support</title>
<para>
This book only provides a basic introduction to Edubuntu. To learn more you
may read the extensive documentation included with the system itself, or access
the constantly expanding material that community members maintain on the
Edubuntu Web site. 
</para>

<tip>
<title>Documentation for Other Systems</title>
<para>
Documentation written for &ubuntu; also applies to the Edubuntu
system. Edubuntu shares a common layout and software with the other operating
systems in the &ubuntu; family. Material that describes the Debian system may
also apply to Edubuntu, although the &ubuntu; family differs from Debian in some
respects. 
</para>
</tip>

<para>
You may also use a range of facilities to communicate with fellow Edubuntu
and &ubuntu; users over the Internet. As a global community with a strong
commitment to sharing and cooperation, &ubuntu; has many volunteers who
contribute their time to support others. In many cases a polite query may
receive an answer in minutes.
</para>

<para>
This chapter explains the resources available to help you develop your
technical skills and overcome any difficulties that you may encounter. For
information on how to participate in the Edubuntu community yourself, refer to
<xref linkend="contribute"/>.  
</para>


<sect2 id="using-docandsup-sysdocs" status="draft">
<title>Supplied Documentation</title>

<para>
Edubuntu includes several sets of documentation by default. To
read these, select
<menuchoice>
<guimenu>System</guimenu>
<guimenuitem>Help</guimenuitem>
</menuchoice>
 and choose the relevant link in the <guilabel>Ubuntu Help Center</guilabel>.
</para>

<sect3 id="using-docandsup-sysdocs-cli" status="draft">
<title>Accessing Documentation from the Command-line</title>

<para>
You may also use command-line utilities to read the <command>man</command> and
<command>info</command> documentation in a terminal such as a text-only virtual
console, or a desktop terminal window.
</para>

<para>
Use the <command>man</command> command to read a <command>man</command> page in
a terminal. For example, to read the page for the file
<filename>sources.list</filename>, type:
</para>

<screen>
<userinput>man sources.list</userinput>
</screen>

<para>
To see the various search options available with <command>man</command>, type:
</para>

<screen>
<userinput>man man</userinput>
</screen>

<para>
To load the GNU help system in a terminal, run the
<command>info</command> command:
</para>

<screen>
<userinput>info</userinput>
</screen>

<para>
To open the manual for a specific GNU utility, add the name of the program after
<command>info</command>. For example, this command displays the manual for the
<command>chown</command> utility:
</para>

<screen>
<userinput>info chown</userinput>
</screen>

</sect3>
</sect2>

<sect2 id="using-docandsup-online" status="draft">
<title>Online Resources</title>

<para>
The &ubuntu; project and many other groups offer documentation on their Web
sites for Debian, &ubuntu;, and related Linux systems. All of the providers
listed here offer documentation without charge, under licences that enable you
freely copy and distribute the material.
</para>

<sect3 id="using-docandsup-online-sites" status="draft">
<title>&ubuntu; Web Sites</title>

<para>
Refer to these pages for both on-line documentation and downloadable books
produced by the &ubuntu; project:
</para>

<variablelist>
<varlistentry>
<term>
The main &ubuntu; documentation page 
</term>

<listitem>
<para>
<ulink url="&ubuntu-documentation;">Ubuntu Documentation</ulink>
</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>

<varlistentry>
<term>
The Edubuntu documentation page
</term>

<listitem>
<para>
<ulink url="http://www.edubuntu.org/Documentation">Edubuntu
Documentation</ulink>
</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
</variablelist>

</sect3>

<sect3 id="using-docandsup-online-others" status="draft">
<title>Other Documentation Web Sites</title>

<para>
Some of the most well-known providers of free Linux documentation include:
</para>

<variablelist>
<varlistentry>
<term>
The Debian Project
</term>
<listitem>
<para>
<ulink url="http://www.debian.org/doc/">Debian Documentation</ulink>
</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>

<varlistentry>
<term>
The Linux Documentation Project
</term>
<listitem>
<para>
<ulink url="http://www.tldp.org/">TLDP</ulink>
</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>

<varlistentry>
<term>
O'Reilly Media
</term>
<listitem>
<para>
<ulink url="http://www.oreilly.com/openbook/">Open Book</ulink>
</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
</variablelist>

</sect3>
</sect2>

<sect2 id="using-docandsup-questions" status="draft">
<title>Asking Questions Online</title>

<para>
The large number of Linux users today means that any issue that arises
is likely to have already been discussed on an Internet venue. Web search
engines such as Google are particularly useful for finding relevant information
in the text of the numerous on-line discussions held on forums, mailing lists,
blogs, and project bug tracking systems.
</para>

<para>
If you cannot find the answer to your question in the documentation or
with a search engine, choose a support venue and post your question there. The
section below explains the support venues for Edubuntu.
</para>

<sect3 id="using-docandsup-questions-search" status="draft">
<title>Using Web Search Engines</title>

<para>
Search engines provide as many matches as possible for the
words or phrases that you specify. To get the most useful and relevant possible
set of results from your searches, try to follow these general principles:

<itemizedlist>
<listitem>
<para>
Use the most specific words that you can.
</para>
</listitem>

<listitem>
<para>
Include at least three key words in your search.
</para>
</listitem>

<listitem>
<para>
If possible use a specific phrase, such as text from an error message.
</para>
</listitem>

<listitem>
<para>
Consider whether the advanced or power-user options of the search engine might
help you.
</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</para>

<para>
Use whichever search engine you prefer. Google users may find that the dedicated
Linux search facility at <ulink url="http://www.google.com/linux"/> provides
better results than the main Google search page.
</para>
</sect3>

<sect3 id="using-docandsup-online-community" status="draft">
<title>Community Support Facilities</title>

<para>
The main venues for discussing Edubuntu on-line are:
</para>

<variablelist>
<varlistentry>
<term>
The mailing list for Edubuntu users
</term>
<listitem>
<para>
<ulink
url="https://lists.ubuntu.com/mailman/listinfo/edubuntu-users">Edubuntu-Users
List</ulink>
</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>

<varlistentry>
<term>
The &ubuntu; Forums
</term>
<listitem>
<para>
<ulink url="&ubuntu-forums;">Ubuntu
Forums</ulink>
</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>

<varlistentry>
<term>
The IRC channel for live discussions on using and developing Edubuntu
</term>
<listitem>
<para>
<ulink url="http://www.edubuntu.org/Community">Community</ulink>
</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
</variablelist>

<para>
When you use these facilities, remember that the individuals
that answer questions are freely donating their time to help others, and may see
many requests for help. If you are new to on-line discussions, please read these
pages before you post your question:
</para>

<variablelist>
<varlistentry>
<term>
The Ubuntu Code of Conduct
</term>
<listitem>
<para>
<ulink url="http://www.ubuntu.com/community/conduct">Code of Conduct</ulink>
</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>

<varlistentry>
<term>
How to Ask Questions the Smart Way
</term>
<listitem>
<para>
<ulink url="http://www.catb.org/~esr/faqs/smart-questions.html">How to file a
bug</ulink>
</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
</variablelist>

</sect3>
</sect2>

<sect2 id="using-docandsup-commercial" status="draft">
<title>Commercial Support and Training Providers</title>

<para>
Refer to this page for information about obtaining commercial
support for Edubuntu: <ulink url="&ubuntu-paidsupport;">Paid Support</ulink> 
</para>

</sect2>
</sect1>

</chapter>
