<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.3//EN" 
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.3/docbookx.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % globalent SYSTEM "../../../libs/global.ent">
%globalent;
<!ENTITY % cdo-C SYSTEM "../../../libs/cdo-C.ent">
%cdo-C;
<!ENTITY % gnome-menus-C SYSTEM "../../libs/edubuntu-menus-C.ent">
%gnome-menus-C;
<!ENTITY % edubuntuent SYSTEM "../../libs/edubuntu.ent">
%edubuntuent;
<!ENTITY % xinclude SYSTEM "../../../libs/xinclude.mod">
%xinclude;
<!ENTITY language "en">
<!ENTITY ubuntu '<phrase>Ubuntu</phrase>'>
<!ENTITY edubuntu '<phrase>Edubuntu</phrase>'>
]>
<chapter id="workstation" status="review">
<title>Edubuntu Workstation</title>

<para>
A workstation installation of Edubuntu is ideal for:
</para>

<itemizedlist>
<listitem>
<para>
Home computers.
</para>
</listitem>

<listitem>
<para>
Small labs that lack the server power (See <xref
linkend="workstation-hw"/>) for thin client computing, but have workstations
capable of running Edubuntu standalone.
</para>
</listitem>

<listitem>
<para>
Laptops and other computers that will not always be connected to
the same network.
</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>

<para>
A workstation installation of Edubuntu is just what it sounds like: an
install that can boot and function on its own, with or without a network
connection. (An internet connection is needed when downloading new or
updated software.) The first user created on the system can perform
administration functions such as change settings that affect all users,
installing new software, etc. System files, applications, and user data are all
stored locally on the computer's hard disk, as opposed to being stored on a
central server as in other Edubuntu installations.
</para>

<!-- HARDWARE REQUIREMENTS -->
<sect1 id="workstation-hw" status="draft">
<title>Hardware requirements</title>

<para>
A workstation Edubuntu system needs at least:
</para>

<itemizedlist>
<listitem>
<para>
500 Mhz processor
</para>
</listitem>

<listitem>
<para>
128 MB of RAM
</para>
</listitem>

<listitem>
<para>
2.1 GB of hard disk space
</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>

<para>
Exceeding the minimums is always okay.  For example, if you have a
lot of user data, such as a large music or digital photo collection, that you
would like to keep on your hard disk, you will need a bigger hard disk.
</para>

</sect1>

<!-- INSTALLATION -->
<sect1 id="workstation-install" status="draft">
<title>Installing Edubuntu Standalone</title>

<para>
To make a workstation installation of Edubuntu, you will need:
</para>

<itemizedlist>
<listitem>
<para>
A computer that meets the hardware requirements for Edubuntu workstation.
</para>
</listitem>

<listitem>
<para>
A keyboard and monitor.
</para>
</listitem>

<listitem>
<para>
An Edubuntu install CD for your type of computer
(architecture). You can order free CDs using <ulink
url="http://shipit.edubuntu.com">Shipit</ulink>, or <ulink
url="http://www.edubuntu.org/Download">download</ulink> and burn your
own.
</para>
</listitem>

<listitem>
<para>
These instructions.
</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>

<para>
A mouse or trackball is optional, but extremely useful.
</para>

<!-- BOOTING -->
<sect2 id="workstation-install-booting" status="draft">
<title>Boot to the Edubuntu install CD</title>

<para>
Put the CD in your CD drive, shut down the computer, then turn it
back on, you should see the Edubuntu logo and install options appear on your
screen.
</para>

<para>
If this does not work, shut down the computer again and carefully
watch the messages that are displayed when you turn your computer on. Some
computers require you to tell them that you want to boot to a CD instead of to
your hard drive. If this is the case, your computer's start-up messages will
tell you what button(s) to press to boot to CD.
</para>

<para>
<emphasis role="bold">Option one:</emphasis> Look for a message
that contains the words "CD", "boot", and/or "media" and a button or buttons to
push. It will be similar (but not necessarily identical) to one of the
following:
</para>

<itemizedlist>
<listitem>
<para>
Press <keycap>F12</keycap> to change boot order.
</para>
</listitem>

<listitem>
<para>
Boot CD/DVD: <keycap>F2</keycap>
</para>
</listitem>

<listitem>
<para>
Press and hold the <keycap>Del</keycap> key to boot removable
media.
</para>
</listitem>

<listitem>
<para>
Press <keycombo>
<keycap>Ctrl</keycap>
<keycap>B</keycap>
</keycombo> to choose boot media
</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>

<para>
Pressing the button(s) when asked will give you a list of things
you can boot. Choose the drive your Edubuntu CD is in.
</para>

<para>
<emphasis role="bold">Option two:</emphasis> Look for a message
that contains the words "BIOS", "options", "set-up", or "configure", as well as
a button or buttons to press. It will look similar (but not necessarily
identical) to one of the following:
</para>

<itemizedlist>
<listitem>
<para>
Press the <keycap>Del</keycap> key to enter set-up.
</para>
</listitem>

<listitem>
<para>
Press <keycap>Esc</keycap> for options.
</para>
</listitem>

<listitem>
<para>
Press <keycap>F4</keycap> now to enter BIOS
configuration.
</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>

<para>
Pressing the correct button(s) when asked will bring up a
configuration screen. Each computer is slightly different, so just read the
displayed information and find the option to boot from your CD drive first. Make
certain that the hard drive boots after the CD drive, or your new Edubuntu
system will not boot properly after it is installed.
</para>

<note>
<para>
Often, these start-up messages scroll by so quickly that by
the time you've read which button to press, it is too late! Don't worry. Just
shutdown the computer and turn it on again. When the message comes up this time,
you will be ready.
</para>
</note>

</sect2>

<!-- CD TESTING -->
<sect2 id="workstation-install-cdtest" status="draft">
<title>Make sure your Edubuntu install CD is complete and
undamaged</title>

<para>
Sometimes a CD gets scratched or marked, or there is an error
while burning it. To prevent installation problems, it is wise to give the CD a
check-up before installing from it. Use your arrow keys, or the Tab key to
highlight <emphasis role="bold">"Check CD for defects"</emphasis> and press <keycap>Enter</keycap>.
</para>

<para>
Your computer will load some tools it needs, and then you will
see: "Warning: this check depends on your hardware and may take some time. Check
CD-ROM integrity?"
</para>

<para>
Use your tab or arrow keys to highlight <keycap>Yes</keycap> and
press
<keycap>Enter</keycap>. This is usually a good time to go grab a
snack.
</para>

<para>
If your CD passes its check-up, you will see: "Integrity test
successful. The CD-ROM integrity test was successful. The CD-ROM is valid."
</para>

<para>
<emphasis role="bold">*****If you do not see the success message,
do not use the CD! Get a new one. Damaged or faulty CDs will not work properly
and may cause your computer not to function.*****</emphasis>
</para>

<para>
    When you see the success message, press <keycap>Enter</keycap> to continue. You
will end up back at the "Warning: this check..." message. You are done, so
choose <keycap>No</keycap> to reboot.
</para>

<para>
If you had to press a button to boot your CD last time, you will
need to do so again.
</para>

</sect2>

<!-- INSTALLATION TIME -->
<sect2 id="workstation-install-gotime" status="draft">
<title>You are now ready to install Edubuntu</title>

<para>
Choose "Install a workstation" to begin installing Edubuntu. Your
computer will load some tools it needs.
</para>

</sect2>

<!-- LANGUAGE SELECTION -->
<sect2 id="workstation-install-lang" status="draft">
<title>Choose language</title>

<para>
Use your arrow keys to select the language you would like the
installer to use, and press <keycap>Enter</keycap>.
</para>

<para>
The next screen asks what country you are in. Highlight your
country and press <keycap>Enter</keycap>, or choose "<option>other</option>" if
your country is not listed.
</para>

</sect2>

<!-- KEYBOARD SELECTION -->
<sect2 id="workstation-install-kb" status="draft">
<title>Select keyboard layout</title>

<para>
The Edubuntu installer will guess what kind of keyboard your
computer has. If you are sure it is correct, just press <keycap>Enter</keycap>.
</para>

<para>
If the layout shown is incorrect, you may choose "Find your
layout by pressing some keys" and follow the on-screen instructions to help
Edubuntu learn what type of keyboard you have.
</para>

<para>
If you already know the name of your keyboard layout, you may
choose "Select from full keyboard list" to do just that.
</para>

<para>
If you would like to double-check that you have chosen the
correct keyboard layout, choose "Test whether this layout is correct" and type a
few letters, numbers, and symbols in the space provided.
</para>

<para>
Use the tab or arrow keys to select <keycap>Continue</keycap> and
press <keycap>Enter</keycap>.
</para>

<para>
If your typing displayed correctly during the test, you should
now highlight the keyboard name on this screen and press <keycap>Enter</keycap>.
</para>

<para>
If the test looked wrong, you should choose "Find your layout by
pressing some keys" and then test again when done.
</para>

<para>
Once your layout has been confirmed, your computer will take a
closer look at your CD-ROM drive and prepare for the rest of the installation.
</para>

</sect2>

<!-- NETWORK CONFIGURATION -->
<sect2 id="workstation-install-net" status="draft">
<title>Configure the network</title>

<para>
The Edubuntu installer will now ask you to choose the network
connection to use for the installation. If you are not sure which to choose, try
the interface that the installer has highlighted for you. (If this turns out to
be incorrect, you can always go back and try again.)
</para>

<para>
A network connection is optional. If you do not have one, you
will not be able to download updates to software packages at the end of the
install process, but you can still install all of the great software found on
your Edubuntu install CD.
</para>

<para>
If your only network connection is in a cafe or library, you may
not be able to use this connection to install and update from. These connections
often require that you visit a local web page from your computer and enter a
password or agree to a usage policy before connecting to the internet. This is
okay! Just perform the installation without a network connection, and then add
the connection after you boot to your new Edubuntu system.
</para>

<para>
If you are using a wireless network, the installer will ask you
for a WEP key. If you do not know what this is, you probably don't need one and
can just choose <keycap>Continue</keycap>.
</para>

<para>
The installer will try to detect your network settings for you.
However, in some cases this is not possible, and the installer will prompt you
for an IP address, netmask, and gateway. The person who manages your network
will know what the correct settings are. For a small home network, some good
guesses are:
</para>

<itemizedlist>
<listitem>
<para>
IP: 192.168.0.x or 192.168.1.x, where "x" is a whole number between 2 and 254
</para>
</listitem>

<listitem>
<para>
Netmask: 255.255.255.0
</para>
</listitem>

<listitem>
<para>
Gateway: 192.168.0.1 or 192.168.1.1
</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>

<para>
Still not sure? If you have another computer on this network,
look at its network settings and use the same netmask and gateway. Set the IP so
that the first three numbers are identical but set the last number slightly
higher than the other computer. For example, if the other computer's IP is
192.168.1.100 you might try 192.268.1.105.
</para>

</sect2>

<!-- UBUNTU ARCHIVE MIRROR SELECTION -->
<sect2 id="workstation-install-mirror" status="draft">
<title>Choose a mirror of the Ubuntu archive</title>

<para>
This section asks for proxy information. If you are unsure, you
probably don't need a proxy. In this case, just choose
<keycap>Continue</keycap>.
</para>

</sect2>

<!-- DISK PARTITIONING -->
<sect2 id="workstation-install-disks" status="draft">
<title>Partition Disks</title>

<para>
In this step, you tell the Edubuntu installer how to set up your
computer's hard drive.
</para>

<para>
Most people will want to choose the second option, "Erase entire
disk:..." ''This will erase everything on your hard disk'' and use the entire
hard disk for your new Edubuntu system.
</para>

<para>
If you plan to dual-boot Edubuntu and another operating system,
you probably want to choose the first option, "Resize..."
</para>

<para>
Do not choose the third or fourth options, "Erase entire disk and
use LVM..." and "Manually edit..." unless you are sure you know what you are
doing with them.
</para>

<para>
The next screen will tell you about the changes being made to
your hard disk. Select <keycap>Yes</keycap> to continue.
</para>

<para>
If your hard drive is large, this is a good time to go look for a
beverage to go with your snack.
</para>

</sect2>

<!-- TIME ZONE CONFIGURATION -->
<sect2 id="workstation-install-time" status="draft">
<title>Configure time zone</title>

<para>
    Select your time zone and press <keycap>Enter</keycap>.
</para>

</sect2>

<!-- USERNAME AND PASSWORD -->
<sect2 id="workstation-install-users" status="draft">
<title>Set up users and passwords</title>

<para>
This section walks you through creating a log-in for your first
user. This user is the one responsible for installing and removing software,
managing system-wide settings, and other maintenance.
</para>

<note>
<para>
If you have used other Linux distributions before, you may
be expecting to create a root login password. The user you are creating now is a
normal user, but will have sudo privileges for package management and other
tasks normally performed by root. By default, logging in directly as root is
disabled on Edubuntu. If you don't know what this note means, just ignore it.
You won't think anything is weird.
</para>
</note>

<para>
Once this user has been created, the Edubuntu installer will load
the Edubuntu operating system and a selection of great applications on to your
hard disk.
</para>

<note>
<para>
The "Select and install software" progress bar stays at 5%
for what seems like a very long time. Don't worry, the install is still
progressing normally. The progress bar will move again after a few minutes.
</para>
</note>

</sect2>

<!-- FINISHING THE INSTALLATION -->
<sect2 id="workstation-install-finish" status="draft">
<title>Finish the installation</title>

<para>
Take out your Edubuntu install CD and choose
<keycap>Continue</keycap> to restart your computer and begin using your newly
installed Edubuntu system.
</para>

<para>
<emphasis role="bold">Congratulations!</emphasis>
</para>

<para>
You now have a fully-functional Edubuntu system!
</para>

<para>
Enter the user name and password you created during the install process to log
in.
</para>

</sect2>
</sect1>

<sect1>
<title>The Edubuntu Addon CD</title>
<para>Due to the amount of great software included in Edubuntu, the
distribution doesn't all fit on one CD. We've split some of the educational
software into a separate CD, and made it easy to install the software from
there.</para>

<para>When you log in as an administrative user, and insert the Addon CD,
you'll see the following dialogue box pop up:</para>

<para>
<inlinemediaobject>
<imageobject>
<imagedata fileref="../../images/C/seconddisk.png" format="PNG" />
</imageobject>
<textobject>
<phrase>Addon Disk</phrase>
</textobject>
</inlinemediaobject>
</para>

<para>Click on the <emphasis role="bold">Start addon installer</emphasis>,
enter your password, and you'll see the following window pop up:
</para>

<para>
<inlinemediaobject>
<imageobject>
<imagedata fileref="../../images/C/addoninstaller.png" format="PNG" />
</imageobject>
<textobject>
<phrase>Addon Installer</phrase>
</textobject> 
</inlinemediaobject>
</para>

<para>Simply check off the applications you'd like to add to your Edubuntu
    system, and press <keycap>OK</keycap>.  They'll be installed from the CD.</para>
</sect1>


<!-- Future sections that didn't make it into Feisty -->
<!-- SECURITY -->
<!-- SECURITY - USERNAME AND PASSWORD MANAGEMENT -->
<!-- UPDATING -->
<!-- PRINTING -->
<!-- UPGRADING -->

</chapter>



