<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.3//EN" 
	"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.3/docbookx.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % globalent SYSTEM "../../../libs/global.ent">
%globalent;
<!ENTITY % cdo-C SYSTEM "../../../libs/cdo-C.ent">
%cdo-C;
<!ENTITY % gnome-menus-zh_TW SYSTEM "../../../ubuntu/libs/gnome-menus-zh_TW.ent">
%gnome-menus-zh_TW;
<!ENTITY % xinclude SYSTEM "../../../libs/xinclude.mod">
%xinclude;
<!ENTITY language "en">
<!ENTITY ubuntu '<phrase>Ubuntu</phrase>'>
]>
<chapter id="add-applications" status="complete">
	<title>新增、移除以及更新應用程式</title>

	<sect1 id="add-applications-introduction" status="complete">
		<title>What is a package manager?</title>
		<para>To add or remove applications in Ubuntu, you need to use a <emphasis>package manager</emphasis>. This is a program that installs and uninstalls software, and keeps track of all the components each piece of software needs.
		</para>
		<para>There are three main package managers you can use in Ubuntu:</para>
		<itemizedlist>
			<listitem><para><link linkend="gnome-app-install"><application>Add/Remove Programs</application></link> - The easiest way to install and uninstall programs.</para></listitem>
			<listitem><para><link linkend="synaptic"><application>Synaptic</application></link> - Advanced control of software and other system components.</para></listitem>
			<listitem><para><link linkend="apt"><application>Apt</application></link> - For if you prefer using the Terminal.</para></listitem>
		</itemizedlist>
		<para>If you open more than one of these programs at once, they may not work. Close them all and open just one.</para>
		<para>You need administrative access to use any of these programs.</para>
		<itemizedlist>
			<listitem><para><xref linkend="root-and-sudo"/></para></listitem>
		</itemizedlist>
	</sect1>
  <sect1 id="gnome-app-install" status="complete">
		<title>新增／移除應用程式</title>
		<para>With the <guimenuitem>Add/Remove…</guimenuitem> item in the <guimenu>Applications</guimenu> menu, you can install programs to do new things with Ubuntu. You can also remove programs you don’t want. You need administrative access to use <application>Add/Remove Programs</application>.</para>
		<itemizedlist>
			<listitem><para><xref linkend="root-and-sudo"/></para></listitem>
		</itemizedlist>
		<para>If you know the name of a program you want to install, enter it in the <guilabel>Search</guilabel> field. Otherwise, begin by choosing a software category on the left.</para>
		<para>Programs that are already installed begin with a check mark next to their name. Uncheck a program if you want to remove it from your computer.</para>
		<para>When you click <guibutton>Apply</guibutton> or <guibutton>OK</guibutton>, any new software will be downloaded from the Internet, and Ubuntu will make the changes you selected. If you have not activated the online package archive, you may be asked to insert your Ubuntu CD-ROM to install some packages.</para>
		<para>Some software cannot be installed or removed using <application>Add/Remove Applications</application>. If you cannot find the package you are looking for, click <guibutton>Advanced</guibutton> to open Synaptic.
		</para>
	</sect1>
	<sect1 id="synaptic" status="complete">
		<title>Synaptic 套件管理員</title>
		<para><application>Synaptic</application> is an advanced package management application that can install and remove every package available to your system. The interface is graphical like <application>Add/Remove Applications</application>, but presents much more information and gives you complete control over the software on your computer.</para>
		<para>To launch <application>Synaptic</application>, from the <guimenu>System</guimenu> menu choose  
			<menuchoice>
				<guisubmenu>Administration</guisubmenu>
				<guimenuitem>Synaptic Package Manager</guimenuitem>
			</menuchoice>.
			You need administrative access to use <application>Synaptic</application>.</para>
		<itemizedlist>
			<listitem><para><xref linkend="root-and-sudo"/></para></listitem>
		</itemizedlist>
		<para>If you know the name of the package you want to install or remove, click the <guibutton>Search</guibutton> button, and enter the package name or a short search term. You can also search for packages by description (for example, you can find all packages mentioning <quote><wordasword>arcade</wordasword></quote> or <quote><wordasword>mathematics</wordasword></quote>).</para>
		<para>Use the categories on the left to filter the list of packages. To return to the list of categories after doing a search, click <guibutton>Sections</guibutton>.</para>
		<para>To install a package, click the box next to it and choose <guimenuitem>Mark for installation</guimenuitem>. If you change your mind, choose <guimenuitem>Unmark</guimenuitem>. To remove a package that is already installed, choose <guimenuitem>Mark for Removal</guimenuitem>.</para>
		<para>When you’ve finished, click <guibutton>Apply</guibutton> and Ubuntu will make the changes you selected. If you don’t want to make any changes, close the window instead.</para>
	</sect1>
	<sect1 id="apt" status="complete">
		<title>Command-Line Package Management With APT</title>
		<para>If you are comfortable using the Terminal, you can use <application>apt</application> (Advanced Packaging Tool) to install or remove software. You need administrative access to use <application>apt</application>.</para>
		<itemizedlist>
			<listitem><para><xref linkend="root-and-sudo"/></para></listitem>
		</itemizedlist>
		<para>
			To update the local list of packages, enter in a Terminal:
			<screen>sudo apt-get update</screen>
		</para>
		<para>
			To install all available updates:
			<screen>sudo apt-get upgrade</screen>
		</para>
		<para>
			To install a package:
			<screen>sudo apt-get install <emphasis>package</emphasis></screen>
		</para>
		<para>
			To remove a package:
			<screen>sudo apt-get remove <emphasis>package</emphasis></screen>
		</para>
		<para>
			To list other <application>apt</application> commands and options:
			<screen>apt-get help</screen>
		</para>
		<para>For more information, see <ulink url="&debian-apt;">Debian’s <application>apt</application> manual</ulink>.</para>
	</sect1>
	<sect1 id="install-file" status="complete">
		<title>安裝單一套件檔案</title>
		<para>The preferred method of installing programs is via the package managers described in this chapter. However, although the Ubuntu package archives are very large, it is possible that you may wish to install a package that is not available in the Ubuntu archives. If this happens, you can also download and install files from websites.</para>
					<caution>
						<para>有件事情很重要：就是安裝任何檔案之前確保您下載的檔案是來自安全的來源。</para>
					</caution>
		<para>There are many different kinds of Linux package files. Most of these are associated with the package managers of specific Linux distributions. Examples are <emphasis>Debian Package</emphasis> files (<emphasis>.deb</emphasis> files), <emphasis>RPM Package Manager</emphasis> files (<emphasis>.rpm</emphasis> files), and <emphasis>Tarballs</emphasis> (<emphasis>.tar</emphasis> files).</para>
		<para>此章節詳細介紹如何安裝這些單獨檔案。</para>
		<warning><para>It is not guaranteed that these files will be compatible with your system and you will not receive security updates if you install these files. For these reasons, if you wish to install a program, always use a native Ubuntu package of the application available through a package manager, if there is one available.</para></warning>

		<sect2 id="install-deb" status="complete">
			<title>安裝／卸裝 <emphasis>.deb</emphasis> 檔案</title>
					<para>這些檔案是 <emphasis>Debian 套件</emphasis>。源於 Ubuntu 和 Debian GNU/Linux 的密切關係， Ubuntu 所使用的套件檔案都有 <emphasis>.deb</emphasis> 字尾。您需要管理權限才能安裝<emphasis>.deb</emphasis>檔案（參閱 <xref linkend="root-and-sudo"/>）。</para>
						<para>To install a <emphasis>.deb</emphasis> file, double-click on it. If you prefer using the Terminal, enter:
						<screen>sudo dpkg -i package_file.deb</screen>
						</para>
						<para>To uninstall a <emphasis>.deb</emphasis> file, deselect it in your package manager. Or from a Terminal, enter:
						<screen>sudo dpkg -r package_name</screen>
						</para>
		</sect2>
		<sect2 id="alien" status="complete">
			<title>將 <emphasis>.rpm</emphasis> 檔轉換為 <emphasis>.deb</emphasis> 檔</title>
					<para>另外一種套件擋是使用 <emphasis>.rpm</emphasis> 字尾的 <emphasis>Red Hat 套件管理員</emphasis> 檔。不建議您在 Ubuntu 系統安裝它們。在大部份情況下，您都能找到原生的 Ubuntu <emphasis>.deb</emphasis> 套件。但若真的需要，<emphasis>.rpm</emphasis> 檔是可以以 <application>alien</application> 程式轉換成 <emphasis>.deb</emphasis> 套件。</para>
						<para>
							In a terminal, enter:
							<screen>sudo alien <emphasis>package_file.rpm</emphasis></screen>
						</para>
						<para>
							If you get a <quote>command not found</quote> or similar error, install <application>alien</application> before trying again:
							<screen>sudo apt-get install alien</screen>
							
						</para>
			</sect2>
			<sect2 id="tarballs" status="complete">
				<title>安裝 <emphasis>tarballs</emphasis></title>
					<para>具有 <emphasis>.tar.gz</emphasis> 或 <emphasis>.tar.bz2</emphasis> 的檔案通常稱為 <emphasis>tarballs</emphasis> ，是廣泛於 Linux 和 Unix 的一種格式。</para>
					<para>如果 Ubuntu 軟體庫中沒有原生的 Ubuntu 套件，您可以以下的方法來安裝或卸裝這些 Tarball 檔案。</para>
					<para>Tarballs 通常是程式的原始碼，並且需要 <emphasis>編譯</emphasis>。要這樣做的話需要額外的軟體（參閱 <xref linkend="build-essential"/>）。</para>
		</sect2>
	</sect1>
	    <sect1 id="extra-repositories" status="complete">
		<title>Software Repositories</title>
			<sect2 status="review"><title>何謂軟體庫？</title>
			<para>Ubuntu 上有成千上萬個可以安裝的程式。這些程式都存放在軟體封存庫（<emphasis>軟體庫</emphasis>）中，並且可以從網際網路上自由安裝。這使在 Linux 上安裝新的程式變得很容易，而且也非常安全，因為每個您安裝的程式都是特別建立為 Ubuntu 而建立，以及安裝之前檢查過的。要組織這些軟體，Ubuntu 軟體庫分成四種組：<emphasis>Main</emphasis>、<emphasis>Restricted</emphasis>、<emphasis>Universe</emphasis>以及<emphasis>Multiverse</emphasis>。</para> 
			<para>決定軟體是屬於何種分類是跟據兩種因素：</para>
				<itemizedlist>
					<listitem>
						<para>提供此程式的軟體開發小組所提供的支援等級。</para>
					</listitem>
					<listitem>
						<para>The level of compliance the program has to the <ulink url="&ubuntu-philosophy;">Free Software Philosophy</ulink>.</para>
					</listitem>
				</itemizedlist>
			<para>You can find more information about the Repositories available <ulink url="&ubuntu-components;">on the website</ulink>.</para>
			<para>標準 Ubuntu 安裝光碟包含一些來自 <emphasis>Main</emphasis> 以及 <emphasis>Restricted</emphasis> 分類的軟體。一旦您的系統覺察到它可以使用在網際網路上的軟體庫，安裝時會有更多軟體程式可用。從您已安裝到系統的套件管理工具，您可以直接透過網際網路搜尋、安裝以及更新安裝這些軟體，而不需要該光碟片。</para>
		</sect2>
		<sect2 status="complete">
			<title>加入額外的軟體庫</title>
			<para>To install software from the <quote>Universe</quote> or <quote>Multiverse</quote> repositories:</para>
			<procedure>
				<step>
					<para>Open &software-properties;.</para>
				</step>
				<step>
					<para>選擇 <guibutton>加入</guibutton></para>
				</step>
				<step>
					<para>To use the <quote>Universe</quote> repository, turn on <guilabel>Community Maintained (Universe)</guilabel>.</para>
					<note>
						<para>加入此軟體庫表示大部分自由軟體都能被安裝到您的系統。此軟體是由 Ubuntu 社群謹慎決定的自願者群組支援，但並非由 Ubuntu 核心開發小組支援，且可能不包含安全性更新。</para>
					</note>
				</step>
				<step>
					<para>To use the <quote>Multiverse</quote> repository, turn on <guilabel>Non-free (Multiverse)</guilabel>.</para>
					<warning>
						<para>加入此軟體庫表示被分類為 <emphasis>non-free</emphasis> 的軟體都能被安裝到您的系統。這軟體可能某些地方的法律是不容許的。當透過此軟體庫安裝每套軟體時，應檢查您國家的法律是否容許您使用它。再一次提醒，此軟體可能沒有任何安全性更新。</para>
					</warning>
				</step>
				<step><para>點選 <guibutton>關閉</guibutton> 以儲存您的變更並離開。</para>
				</step>
			</procedure>
			</sect2>
		</sect1>
	    <sect1 id="updates" status="complete">
		<title>更新</title>
			<para>有時候 Ubuntu 的開發者會為 Ubuntu 系統上的應用程及套件發佈功能及安全性更新。</para>
			<para>當這些更新可用時，Ubuntu 將會用彈跳視窗及紅色圖示在您的通知區域通知您。要更新您的系統，點選該紅色按鈕，輸入您的密碼以及點選<guibutton>確定</guibutton>。</para>
			<para><application>更新管理員</application>程式會列出可用更新的清單：要下載以及安裝這些更新，點選<guibutton>安裝更新</guibutton>。Ubuntu 即將透過網際網路下載以及安裝可用的更新。</para>
			<para>當<application>更新管理員</application>完成更新您的系統，點選 <guibutton>關閉</guibutton>按鈕關閉彈跳視窗，然後關閉<application>更新管理員</application>以完成更新您的系統。</para>
			<note>
				<para>有時安裝過重要更新過後，必須要重新啟動您的電腦。如果這樣，Ubuntu 將會用彈跳視窗和圖示在您的通知區域通知您。</para>
			</note>
	   </sect1>
</chapter>

