<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.3//EN" 
 "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.3/docbookx.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % globalent SYSTEM "../../../libs/global.ent">
%globalent;
<!ENTITY % cdo-C SYSTEM "../../../libs/cdo-C.ent">
%cdo-C;
<!ENTITY % kde SYSTEM "../../libs/kde.ent">
%kde;
<!ENTITY % kde-menus-C SYSTEM "../../libs/kde-menus-C.ent">
%kde-menus-C;
<!ENTITY language "&EnglishAmerican;">
]>
<article id="art-about-kubuntu" status="review" lang="oc">
	<articleinfo>
	<title>A prepaus de Kubuntu</title>
	<legalnotice>
	<title>Mercejaments e licéncia</title>
	<para>The following Ubuntu Documentation Team author maintains this document:</para>
		<itemizedlist>
			<listitem>
				<para>Jonathan Jesse</para>
			</listitem>
		</itemizedlist>
	<para>Las personas seguentas an contribuit a-n aquel document :</para>
		<itemizedlist>
			<listitem>
				<para>Matthew East</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para>Jerome Gotangco</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para>Jonathan Riddell</para>
			</listitem>
		</itemizedlist>
		<para>Lo document es disponible amb una dobla licéncia : la licéncia GNU Free Documentation (GFDL) e la licéncia Creative Commons ShareAlike 2.0 (CC-BY-SA).</para>
		<para>Sètz liure de modificar, enriquir e melhorar la documentacion d'Ubuntu segon los tèrmes d'aquestas licéncias. Tot trabalh derivat deu èsser publicat jos una d'aquestas licéncias (o las doas).</para>
		<para>Sètz liure de modificar, enriquir e melhorar lo còdi de la documentacion d'Ubuntu segon los tèrmes d'aquestas licéncias. Tot trabalh derivat deu èsser publicat jos una d'aquestas licéncias (o las doas).</para>
		<para>This documentation is distributed in the hope that it will be useful, but WITHOUT ANY
			WARRANTY; without even the implied warranty of MERCHANTABILITY or FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR
			PURPOSE AS DESCRIBED IN THE DISCLAIMER.</para>
		<para>Copies of these licenses are available in the appendices section of this book. Online
			versions can be found at the following URLs:</para>
		<itemizedlist>
			<listitem>
				<para>&fdl-url;</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para>&cc-attrib;</para>
			</listitem>
		</itemizedlist>
	</legalnotice>
	&copyright;<copyright><year>2006 - ubuntu-l10n-oci@lists.ubuntu.com</year><holder>La còla occitana de revirada d'Ubuntu</holder></copyright>
	<authorgroup>
		&author-ubuntu-documentation-project;
	</authorgroup>
	<abstract>
		<para>This document is an introduction to Kubuntu. It explains the Kubuntu philosophy and roots, and introduces the Kubuntu desktop.</para>
	</abstract>
	&disclaimer;
	&publisher;
  </articleinfo>
 
 <para>Welcome to Kubuntu &distro-rev;: the &distro-version;
  	Release.</para>

 <para>Kubuntu is a user-friendly operating system based on KDE, the K
 Desktop Environment. With a predictable 6 month release cycle as part of
 the Ubuntu project, Kubuntu is the Linux distribution for
 everyone.</para>
  
 <para>The team behind Kubuntu makes the following commitment to its users:</para>
 <itemizedlist>
 
  <listitem>
  
   <para>Kubuntu uses the solid base of Ubuntu plus the latest KDE. We
    are part of the Ubuntu community and use their infrastructure
    and support. Our mission is to be the best KDE distribution
    available. </para>
    
  </listitem>
  
  <listitem>
  
   <para>Kubuntu will always be free of charge, and there is no extra
    fee for an <quote>enterprise edition</quote>, we make our very
    best work available to everyone on the same free terms. </para>
    
  </listitem>
  
  <listitem>
  
   <para>Kubuntu includes the very best translations and accessibility
    infrastructure that the Free Software community has to offer, to
    make Kubuntu usable by as many people as possible. </para>
    
  </listitem>
  
  <listitem>
  
   <para>Kubuntu is entirely committed to the principles of free
    software and open source development; we encourage people to use
    free and open source software, improve it, and pass it on.
   </para>
   
  </listitem>
  
 </itemizedlist>
 
 <para id="aboutkubuntu03">Kubuntu includes more than 1,000 pieces of software, starting with Linux
  version &linux-kernel-version; and KDE &kde-version;, and covering every standard desktop application from word processing and
  spreadsheet to Internet access applications, web server software, email software, programming
  languages and tools, and of course, several games. </para>
  
 <sect1 id="wonderful-linux" status="review">
 
  <title>Lo mond meravilhós de Linux.</title>
  
  <para>Kubuntu uses the <quote>Linux</quote> kernel, the software which
   has come to define the worldwide movement to embrace open source
   software. Find out about Linux at <ulink url="&linuxorg;">Linux.org</ulink>
  </para>
  
  <sect2 id="sect-kubuntu-difference" status="review">
  
   <title>La differencia</title>
   
   <para>There are many Linux distributions (e.g., Redhat, SuSE,
    Debian, Mandriva) but Kubuntu distinguishes itself as a
    different kind of distribution. </para>
    
   <para>Built on the solid and advanced base of Ubuntu, the Kubuntu
    team aims to create a distribution that provides an up-to-date and
    coherent Linux system for desktop and server computing.
    Kubuntu includes a number of selected packages from Ubuntu and is
    based on Debian's powerful <quote>Adept</quote> package management
    system. Adept allows easy installation and clean removal of
    programs, as well as automatic download of extra packages to
    satisfy dependencies. Unlike most distributions that ship a wide
    range of software packages that may or may not be of quality,
    Kubuntu's core list of packages is reduced only to the most
    important applications. (Although for maximum choice, you may
    choose from over 10,000 packages ready to download, rather than
    being limited to the selected core.) </para>
    
   <para>By focusing on quality, Kubuntu provides a robust and feature
    rich computing environment that is flexible for use in home and
    commercial environments. The project has more time to spend on the
    finer details and is able to release a version featuring the
    latest and greatest of today's software, every 6 months. Kubuntu
    ships with versions for PCs (Intel Pentium / AMD Athlon), 64-bit
    PCs (AMD64) and Mac (PowerPC) architectures. </para>
    
  </sect2>
  
  <sect2 id="sect-about-KDE" status="review">
  
   <title>KDE pels usuaris d'Ubuntu</title>
   
   <para>The default desktop environment for Kubuntu is KDE, a powerful Free Software graphical
    desktop environment for Linux and Unix workstations. It combines ease of use, contemporary
    functionality, and outstanding graphical design with the technological superiority of the Unix
    operating system. KDE is one of the two leading graphical desktop environments for Linux
    users. KDE sports an impressive array of easy to use, but powerful, graphical interface
    applications for users of all ages in both home and work environments. For developers, KDE
    provides a robust application development framework that enables rapid creation of first rate
    applications implementing cutting-edge technology. </para>
   
   <para>KDE is in many ways similar to GNOME, but there are a few distinct differences which
    distinguish KDE as a desktop environment. KDE uses C++ at its base, with Qt (the Q-toolkit),
    whereas GNOME, using GTK, is written in C. KDE is the older and most widely used
    desktop environment, and is known to stress more the importance of features, and more recently,
    usability. GNOME more notoriously prides itself on simplicity and ease of use.
    Popular criticisms of GNOME are that it's lacking in features and applications, while it's often
    commented that KDE has too many features which may themselves be hard to locate.</para>
   
    <para>Nevertheless, KDE and GNOME respectively target different audiences,
    and are fundamentally different in some respects, and the question of which
    desktop environment is superior is inherently a subjective opinion in many 
    ways. Because of this, to at least make a proper decision about which is 
    more suited to yourself, it is advised that you try them both out. 
    Thus, it is very easy to install GNOME from a Kubuntu distribution, and 
    equally easy to install KDE from an Ubuntu setup. </para>
  </sect2>
  
  <sect2 id="sect-switching-desktops" status="review">
  
   <title>Switching Desktops</title>
   
   <para>As an Ubuntu user, you may be concerned that your favorite
    GNOME applications will not run under Kubuntu. That
    is not the case. In recent times, much work has been done to
    increase compatibility between GNOME and KDE. Today, virtually
    all GNOME applications will run under KDE and vice versa. </para>
    
   <para>While the KDE desktop is very different from that of GNOME, all
    your favorite GNOME applications will be integrated with your
    KDE menu system. </para>
    
   <para>Another concern for users wanting to try Kubuntu may be that
    KDE will become their only desktop once it is installed. While
    we do indeed hope you will make KDE your desktop of choice, this
    is not the case; both desktop session types can be run after
    installing Kubuntu. Furthermore, during installation you will be
    given the choice of using either the GNOME Display Manager (GDM)
    or the K Display Manager (KDM) as your login manager. </para>
    
   <para>Either display manager will suffice, and after installation
    you will be able to run both GNOME and KDE session types.  Feel
    free to try KDM.  You can always switch back to GDM later if you
    like.  The only noticeable difference will be the artwork used 
	before you log in.</para>

    <para>Per installar Kubuntu, basta d'installar lo paquetatge <emphasis>kubuntu-desktop</emphasis>.</para>
    
  </sect2>
  
 </sect1>
 
</article>

