<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.3//EN" 
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.3/docbookx.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % globalent SYSTEM "../../../libs/global.ent">
%globalent;
<!ENTITY % cdo-C SYSTEM "../../../libs/cdo-C.ent">
%cdo-C;
<!ENTITY % kde SYSTEM "../../libs/kde.ent">
%kde;
<!ENTITY % kde-general SYSTEM "/usr/share/apps/ksgmltools2/customization/obsolete/general.entities">
%kde-general;
<!ENTITY % xinclude SYSTEM "../../../libs/xinclude.mod">
%xinclude;
<!ENTITY language "en">
]>
<chapter id="introduction" status="review">
    <title>Úvod</title>
    <para>Táto kapitola poskytuje niektoré informácie o Kubuntu, ako získať Kubuntu a ako sa dostať k pomoci s Kubuntu.</para>
    <sect1 id="about-kubuntu" status="complete">
        <title>O Kubuntu</title>
        <para>Thank you for your interest in Kubuntu &distro-rev;
            - the <emphasis>&distro-version;</emphasis> release.</para> 
        <para>Kubuntu is an entirely open source operating system built around the 
            Linux kernel. The Kubuntu community is built around the ideals
            enshrined in the <ulink url="&ubuntu-philosophy;">Ubuntu 
                Philosophy</ulink>: that software should be
            available free of charge, that software tools should be usable
            by people in their local language and despite any disabilities,
            and that people should have the freedom to customize and alter
            their software in whatever way they see fit. For those reasons: 
            <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Kubuntu bude vždy zadarmo, nikdy nebude požadovaná extra platba za "enterprise edíciu", robíme všetko preto aby každý dostal to isté pri tých istých slobodných podmienkach.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Kubuntu v sebe zahŕňa tie najlepšie preklady a dostupnú infraštruktúru, ktorú môže komunita Slobodného Software ponúknuť, tak aby bolo Kubuntu použiteľné pre čo najväčšie množstvo ľudí.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Kubuntu vychádza pravidelne každých 6 mesiacov. Môžete použiť terajšiu verziu na preskúmanie možností vyvíjanej verzie. Každá verzia je podporovaná 18 mesiacov.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Kubuntu je úplne oddané princípom vývoja sofvéru open source; povzbudzujeme všetkých, aby používali softvér open source, zlepšovali ho a šírili ho ďalej.</para>
                </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
        </para>
        <para>
            The Kubuntu community is comprised of developers, programmers,
            testers, tech-writers, documentation testers, translators, and
            most importantly, the people who use Kubuntu every day. We
            invite you to join this community and help make Kubuntu the
            operating system you, your family, your friends, and your
            colleagues will love to use. Help us translate Kubuntu into your
            language, try it on new and unusual hardware, improve the
            experience of other users with hints, tips, and FAQs, or help
            to shape the direction Kubuntu is headed by providing feedback
            about the software you love most.</para>
        <para>
            Find out more at <ulink url="&kubuntu-web;">the Kubuntu website</ulink>.
        </para>
        <sect2 id="about-kubuntu-name" status="complete">
            <title>About the Name</title>
            <para>Kubuntu is based on the Ubuntu system, but with the latest KDE packages. Kubuntu
                means "towards humanity" in Bemba. Kubuntu is pronounced
                "koo-boon-too". </para> 
            <!-- Needs some word foo -->
            <para>Ubuntu je juhoafrická idea ľudského prístupu jedného k druhému a spoločnosti voči jedincovi. Na túto myšlienku sa nazerá ako na originálny africký koncept zviazaný s africkým "obrodením" a zakladajúcimi princípmi novej Juhoafrickej republiky. Slovo Ubuntu pochádza z jazykov Zulu a Xhosa.</para>
            <para>Voľný preklad princípu Ubuntu je "ľudskosť voči ostatným". Iný možný preklad je "viera vo všadeprítomné puto spájajúce celé ľudstvo".</para>
            <blockquote><attribution>Arcibiskup Desmond Tutu</attribution>
                <para>Osoba s ubuntu je otvorená a dostupná pre všetkých, toleruje všetkých, necíti sa schopnými a dobrými ohrozená, pretože má sebaistotu a vie, že je časťou jedného celku a je sklamaná, ak sú druhí sklamaní, alebo ponížení, ak sú mučení, alebo utláčaní.</para>
            </blockquote>
            <para>
                As a platform based on Linux, the Kubuntu
                operating system brings the spirit of ubuntu to the software
                world.
            </para>
        </sect2>
        <sect2 id="free-software" status="complete">
            <title>Free Software</title>
            <para>The Kubuntu project is entirely committed to the
                principles of open source software development; people
                are encouraged to use open source software, improve it,
                and pass it on. This means that Kubuntu is and will
                always be free of charge.</para>
            <para>
                However, this means more than just being available at
                zero cost. The philosophy of Free Software is that
                people should be free to use software in all the ways
                that are "socially useful". "Free
                software" not only means that you shouldn't have
                to pay for it, it also means that you should be able to
                use the software in any way you wish.  The code that
                makes up Free Software is available for anyone to
                download, change, fix, and use in any way. So apart
                from the fact that Free Software is often available
                without charge, this freedom also has technical
                advantages: when programs are developed, the hard work
                of others can be used and built upon. This cannot
                happen with non-free Software, and when programs are
                developed, they have to start from scratch. For this
                reason the development of Free Software is fast,
                efficient and exciting!
            </para>
            <para>You can find out more about the philosophy of Free Software
                <ulink url="&gnu-philosophy;">here</ulink>.</para>
        </sect2>
        <sect2 id="kubuntu-difference" status="complete">
            <title>Rozdiel</title>
            <para>
                There are many different operating systems based on Linux:
                Debian, SUSE, Gentoo, RedHat, and Mandriva for example. 
                Kubuntu is yet another contender in what
                is already a highly competitive world. So what makes
                Kubuntu different?</para>
            <para>
                Based on Debian, one of the most widely acclaimed,
                technologically advanced, and well-supported
                distributions, Kubuntu
                aims to create a distribution that provides
                an up-to-date and coherent Linux system for desktop and
                server computing. Kubuntu includes a number of carefully
                selected packages from the Debian distribution and
                retains its powerful package management system, which
                allows easy installation and clean removal of programs. Unlike most
                distributions that ship with a large amount of software
                that may or may not be of use, Kubuntu's list of packages
                is reduced to a number of important applications of high
                quality.
            </para>
            <para>Zo zameraním sa na kvalitu, môžeme vyhlásiť, že Kubuntu je operačný systém robustný a bohatý na funkcie a je vhodný na domáce, alebo komerčné pužitie. Projekt má dosť času na to aby sa zameral na detaily a je schopný zaradiť do novej verzie to najlepšie a najnovšie z dnešného softvérového vývoja každých 6 mesiacov. Kubuntu je dostupné pre architektúry i386 (386/486/Pentium(II/III/IV) a Athlon/Duron/Sempron), x86_64 (Athlon64, Opteron, and nový 64-bit Intel procesor), a PowerPC (iBook/Powerbook, G4 and G5).</para>
        </sect2>
        <sect2 id="sect-kubuntu-desktop" status="complete">
            <title>Pracovné prostredie</title>
            <para>The default desktop environment for Kubuntu is <ulink url="&kde;">KDE</ulink>, a leading UNIX and
                Linux desktop suite and development platform.</para>
            <para>Another leading UNIX and Linux desktop is <ulink url="&gnome;">Gnome</ulink>. Kubuntu does not 
                make use of the Gnome desktop by default. However, the
                <ulink url="&ubuntu-main;">Ubuntu</ulink> project offers
                Kubuntu users a choice between these two excellent desktop
                environments. Thanks to the efforts of the Ubuntu team,
                Kubuntu users are able to install and use the Gnome
                desktop easily on their system. The Gnome desktop can 
                be found in and downloaded from the main Ubuntu archive.
                The easiest way to get a working install of Ubuntu is
                <command>sudo apt-get install ubuntu-desktop</command>.
                This will install the different packages required and set
                everything up correctly.</para>
            <para>Po ukončení inštalácie si môžete vybrať ktoré prostredie použijete: KDE, alebo Gnome.</para>
        </sect2>
        <sect2 id="version-numbers" status="complete">
            <title>Version and Release Numbers</title>
            <para>
                The Kubuntu version numbering scheme is based on the date we
                release a version of the distribution. The version number comes from the year
                and month of the release rather than reflecting the actual revision of the
                software. So, our first release (Hoary Hedgehog) was in April 2005, so its
                version was 5.04. The second release (Breezy Badger) was in October 2005, so
                its version number was 5.10, and our third release (Dapper Drake) was released in June 2006
		so its version number was 6.06. This version (&distro-version;) was released in
                &distro-release-date;, so its version number is &distro-rev;.
            </para>
        </sect2>

        <sect2 id="kubuntu-backing-support" status="complete">
            <title>Backing and Support</title>
            <para>Kubuntu is maintained by a quickly growing community.
                The project is sponsored by <ulink url="&canonical-url;">Canonical Ltd.</ulink>, a
                holding company founded by Mark Shuttleworth. Canonical
                employs the core Ubuntu developers and offers support and consulting services
                for Ubuntu.</para>
            <para>Canonical Ltd also sponsors a number of other open source software projects, more information about which can be found on the <ulink url="&canonical-url;">Canonical website</ulink>.</para>
        </sect2>
        <sect2 id="about-linux" status="complete">
            <title>What is Linux?</title>
            <para>The <ulink url="&kernel;">Linux kernel</ulink>, pronounced
                "lee-nucks" is the heart of the Kubuntu operating system.
                A kernel is an important part of
                any operating system, providing the communication bridge between 
                hardware and software.</para>
            <para>Linux priviedol k životu v roku 1991 fínsky študent Linux Torvalds. V tom čase sa bežal iba na systémoch i386 a bol v podstate nezávysle vytvoreným klonom UNIXového jadra, s úmyslom využiť výhody novej architektúry i386.</para>
            <para>Dnesk, vďaka znažčnému úsiliu vývojárov po celom svete, Linux sa dá virtuálne spustiť na každej modernej architektúre.</para>
            <para>Jadro Linuxu získalo ideologickú, ale aj technickú dôležitosť. Vytvorila sa veľká komunita ľudí, ktorí veria v ideály slobodného software a trávia svoj voľný čas úpravou slobodného software tak, aby bol čo najlepší.</para>
            <para>Ľudia z tejto komunity umožnili vznik iniciatív ako je Ubuntu, komisie štandardov, ktoré udávajú smer vývoja Internetu, organizácií ako je Mozilla Foundation, ktorej vďačíme za vytvorenie internetového prehliadača Firefox a nespočetné množstvo iných softvérových projektov, ktoré vám istotne prospievali v minulosti.</para>
            <para>Duch slobodného softvéru, bežne prisudzovaný Linuxu, všade ovplyvňuje vývojárov softvéru a používateľov, aby hnala komunity za spoločnými cieľmi.</para>
        </sect2>
        <sect2 id="about-gnu" status="complete">
            <title>Čo je GNU?</title>
            <para>The <emphasis>GNU Project</emphasis>, pronounced "guh-noo", was
                launched in 1984 to develop a complete
                UNIX-style operating system which is comprised of Free Software: the GNU
                system. Variants of the GNU operating system,
                which use the Linux kernel, are now widely used.</para>
            <para>Projekt GNU je blízko spojený s filozofiou slobodného software, ktorý je hlavným projektom, s ktorého sú odvodené projekty ako je Ubuntu. Koncept slobodného software je vysvetlený v <xref linkend="free-software"/>.</para>
        </sect2>
    </sect1>
    <sect1 id="get-kubuntu" status="complete">
        <title>Ziskanie Kubuntu</title>
        <para>There are a number of methods you may use to obtain a
            copy of Kubuntu, all of which are described on the Kubuntu
            Web site <ulink url="&kubuntu-download;">download
                page</ulink>.</para>
        <para>Prvou metódou je stiahnutie ISO obrazu zo serveru blízko vás a vyrobiť si inštalačné CD Kubuntu. Existujú dve možné CD:</para>
				<itemizedlist>
					<listitem><para><emphasis>Desktop CD</emphasis> - je CD, ktoré vám dovoľuje vyskúšať Kubuntu bez zásahu do vašeho počítača s dodatočnou možnosťou inštalácie. Tento tym je najčastejšie používaný.</para></listitem>
					<listitem><para><emphasis>CD inštalácia v textovom móde</emphasis> - je špecializovaná inštalaćia systému Kubutu. Táto možnosť inštalácie je pre tvorbu OEM systémov, alebo nastavenie automatických rozmiestnení, alebo sa môže využiť na uprgrade starších inštalacií.</para></listitem>
				</itemizedlist>
        <para>If you don't have a CD burner or you have limited or expensive bandwidth,
            we can send you pressed copies of the "Desktop
            CD" free of charge. You may request CDs via
            <ulink url="&ubuntu-shipit;">Shipit</ulink>, the Ubuntu CD Distribution System.</para>
        <tip>
            <para>Objednané CD môžu byť doručené až o niekoľko mesiacov (pozn. prekladateľa: určite do niekoľkých týždňov).</para>
        </tip>
        <para>Another method of obtaining Kubuntu is to join a local
            Linux Users Group (LUG) and ask if somebody with Kubuntu
            would mind making a Kubuntu CD for you. Normally, you
            will have to replace the CDs used for the duplication
            and reimburse any postage or delivery costs.</para>
        <para>If you do not know of an LUG near you, a list can be
            found at <ulink url="&lugww;">Linux Users Groups
                Worldwide</ulink>.</para>
    </sect1>
    <sect1 id="getting-help" status="review">
        <title>Pomoc</title>
        <para>There are a number of places from which you can obtain help with your Kubuntu desktop system,
            these include:
        </para>
        <sect2 id="help-system" status="writing">
            <title>KDE Help Center</title>
            <para>
                Kubuntu comes with a inbuilt help system, which can be accessed
                by choosing 
                <menuchoice>
                    <guimenu>K Menu</guimenu>
                    <guimenuitem>Help</guimenuitem>
                </menuchoice> 
                from the desktop menu system. 
                The <application>KDE Help Center</application> is the central
                location to all documentation available on your system. 
            </para>
            <para> A good place to start off learning more about KDE is the
                <ulink url="help:/khelpcenter/quickstart/index.html">KDE
                    Quickstart Guide</ulink>, which will familiarize you with
                some of the basic features of KDE.  </para>
        </sect2>
        <sect2 id="application-help" status="review">
            <title>Pomoc s Aplikáciou</title>
            <para>Najjednoduchšou cestou ako získať pomoc s aplikáciou je prečítať si príručku, ktorá je dostupná z menu <emphasis>Pomoc</emphasis> aplikácie.</para> 
        </sect2>
        <sect2 id="online-help" status="complete">
            <title>Online Pomoc</title>
            <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para>
                        <ulink url="&ubuntu-documentation;">The Ubuntu Documentation Website</ulink> contains HTML and PDF versions of this guide, and other guides produced by the Ubuntu Documentation Team for Ubuntu and Kubuntu.</para></listitem>
                <listitem> <para> You can buy this guide in book form from <ulink url="&lulu-store;">our Lulu store</ulink>. You will only pay for the price of printing and postage.  </para> </listitem> <listitem>
                    <para>
                        <ulink url="&wiki-UserDocumentation;">The Ubuntu Wiki</ulink> - this contains many other community maintained guides</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>
                        <ulink url="&kubuntu-forums2;">Kubuntu</ulink> and <ulink url="&ubuntu-forums;">Ubuntu</ulink> Community Forums - here you can ask questions on a forum and receive answers from the forum community.
                    </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para><ulink url="&kubuntu-lists;">Mailing Lists</ulink> - here you can ask questions by email, and receive answers from the mailing list community.
                    </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem><para>IRC chat: <phrase>&kubuntu-irc;</phrase> - chat in realtime with the Kubuntu community.</para></listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>
                        <ulink url="&kubuntu-web;">Kubuntu Homepage</ulink> - Get the latest news about Kubuntu. 
                    </para>
                </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
            <para>For more information, visit the <ulink url="&wiki-HowToGetHelp;">How to Get Help</ulink> wiki page.</para>
        </sect2>
    </sect1>
</chapter>

