<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.3//EN" 
	"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.3/docbookx.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % globalent SYSTEM "../../../libs/global.ent">
%globalent;
<!ENTITY % cdo-C SYSTEM "../../../libs/cdo-C.ent">
%cdo-C;
<!ENTITY % gnome-menus-C SYSTEM "../../../ubuntu/libs/gnome-menus-C.ent">
%gnome-menus-C;
<!ENTITY % xinclude SYSTEM "../../../libs/xinclude.mod">
%xinclude;
<!ENTITY language "en">
<!ENTITY ubuntu '<phrase>Ubuntu</phrase>'>
]>
<chapter id="add-applications" status="complete">
	<title>เพิ่ม,ลบออก,และ ปรับปรุง(Updating) โปรแกรมต่างๆ</title>

	<sect1 id="add-applications-introduction" status="complete">
		<title>What is a package manager?</title>
		<para>To add or remove applications in Ubuntu, you need to use a <emphasis>package manager</emphasis>. This is a program that installs and uninstalls software, and keeps track of all the components each piece of software needs.
		</para>
		<para>There are three main package managers you can use in Ubuntu:</para>
		<itemizedlist>
			<listitem><para><link linkend="gnome-app-install"><application>Add/Remove Programs</application></link> - The easiest way to install and uninstall programs.</para></listitem>
			<listitem><para><link linkend="synaptic"><application>Synaptic</application></link> - Advanced control of software and other system components.</para></listitem>
			<listitem><para><link linkend="apt"><application>Apt</application></link> - For if you prefer using the Terminal.</para></listitem>
		</itemizedlist>
		<para>If you open more than one of these programs at once, they may not work. Close them all and open just one.</para>
		<para>You need administrative access to use any of these programs.</para>
		<itemizedlist>
			<listitem><para><xref linkend="root-and-sudo"/></para></listitem>
		</itemizedlist>
	</sect1>
  <sect1 id="gnome-app-install" status="complete">
		<title>เพิ่ม/ลบออก โปรแกรม</title>
		<para>With the <guimenuitem>Add/Remove…</guimenuitem> item in the <guimenu>Applications</guimenu> menu, you can install programs to do new things with Ubuntu. You can also remove programs you don’t want. You need administrative access to use <application>Add/Remove Programs</application>.</para>
		<itemizedlist>
			<listitem><para><xref linkend="root-and-sudo"/></para></listitem>
		</itemizedlist>
		<para>If you know the name of a program you want to install, enter it in the <guilabel>Search</guilabel> field. Otherwise, begin by choosing a software category on the left.</para>
		<para>Programs that are already installed begin with a check mark next to their name. Uncheck a program if you want to remove it from your computer.</para>
		<para>When you click <guibutton>Apply</guibutton> or <guibutton>OK</guibutton>, any new software will be downloaded from the Internet, and Ubuntu will make the changes you selected. If you have not activated the online package archive, you may be asked to insert your Ubuntu CD-ROM to install some packages.</para>
		<para>Some software cannot be installed or removed using <application>Add/Remove Applications</application>. If you cannot find the package you are looking for, click <guibutton>Advanced</guibutton> to open Synaptic.
		</para>
	</sect1>
	<sect1 id="synaptic" status="complete">
		<title>โปรแกรมจัดการชุดโปรแกรมซิแน็บติ(Synaptic)</title>
		<para><application>Synaptic</application> is an advanced package management application that can install and remove every package available to your system. The interface is graphical like <application>Add/Remove Applications</application>, but presents much more information and gives you complete control over the software on your computer.</para>
		<para>To launch <application>Synaptic</application>, from the <guimenu>System</guimenu> menu choose  
			<menuchoice>
				<guisubmenu>Administration</guisubmenu>
				<guimenuitem>Synaptic Package Manager</guimenuitem>
			</menuchoice>.
			You need administrative access to use <application>Synaptic</application>.</para>
		<itemizedlist>
			<listitem><para><xref linkend="root-and-sudo"/></para></listitem>
		</itemizedlist>
		<para>If you know the name of the package you want to install or remove, click the <guibutton>Search</guibutton> button, and enter the package name or a short search term. You can also search for packages by description (for example, you can find all packages mentioning <quote><wordasword>arcade</wordasword></quote> or <quote><wordasword>mathematics</wordasword></quote>).</para>
		<para>Use the categories on the left to filter the list of packages. To return to the list of categories after doing a search, click <guibutton>Sections</guibutton>.</para>
		<para>To install a package, click the box next to it and choose <guimenuitem>Mark for installation</guimenuitem>. If you change your mind, choose <guimenuitem>Unmark</guimenuitem>. To remove a package that is already installed, choose <guimenuitem>Mark for Removal</guimenuitem>.</para>
		<para>When you’ve finished, click <guibutton>Apply</guibutton> and Ubuntu will make the changes you selected. If you don’t want to make any changes, close the window instead.</para>
	</sect1>
	<sect1 id="apt" status="complete">
		<title>Command-Line Package Management With APT</title>
		<para>If you are comfortable using the Terminal, you can use <application>apt</application> (Advanced Packaging Tool) to install or remove software. You need administrative access to use <application>apt</application>.</para>
		<itemizedlist>
			<listitem><para><xref linkend="root-and-sudo"/></para></listitem>
		</itemizedlist>
		<para>
			To update the local list of packages, enter in a Terminal:
			<screen>sudo apt-get update</screen>
		</para>
		<para>
			To install all available updates:
			<screen>sudo apt-get upgrade</screen>
		</para>
		<para>
			To install a package:
			<screen>sudo apt-get install <emphasis>package</emphasis></screen>
		</para>
		<para>
			To remove a package:
			<screen>sudo apt-get remove <emphasis>package</emphasis></screen>
		</para>
		<para>
			To list other <application>apt</application> commands and options:
			<screen>apt-get help</screen>
		</para>
		<para>For more information, see <ulink url="&debian-apt;">Debian’s <application>apt</application> manual</ulink>.</para>
	</sect1>
	<sect1 id="install-file" status="complete">
		<title>ติดตั้งชุดโปรแกรม(Single Package)เดียว</title>
		<para>The preferred method of installing programs is via the package managers described in this chapter. However, although the Ubuntu package archives are very large, it is possible that you may wish to install a package that is not available in the Ubuntu archives. If this happens, you can also download and install files from websites.</para>
					<caution>
						<para>มีความสำคัญเป็นอย่างยิ่งที่ท่านจะต้องแน่ใจว่าทุกไฟล์ที่ท่านดาวน์โหลดมาจากแหล่งที่ปลอดภัยก่อนที่ท่านจะทำการติดตั้ง.</para>
					</caution>
		<para>There are many different kinds of Linux package files. Most of these are associated with the package managers of specific Linux distributions. Examples are <emphasis>Debian Package</emphasis> files (<emphasis>.deb</emphasis> files), <emphasis>RPM Package Manager</emphasis> files (<emphasis>.rpm</emphasis> files), and <emphasis>Tarballs</emphasis> (<emphasis>.tar</emphasis> files).</para>
		<para>ส่วนนี้เกี่ยวกับการติดตั้งไฟล์เดี่ยวๆนี้</para>
		<warning><para>ไม่สามารถรับประกันได้ว่าไฟล์เหล่านี้จะสามารถใช้กับระบบของท่านได้และท่านก็จะไม่ได้รับการปรับปรุงด้านความปลอดภัยถ้าท่านติดตั้งไฟล์เหล่านี้.ด้วยเหตุผลนี้,ถ้าท่านยังอยากจะติดตั้งโปรแกรม,ควรใช้โปรแกรมสำหรับอูบันตูโดยเฉพาะที่สามารถเลือกได้จากโปรแกรมจัดการชุดโปรแกรม( package manager),ถ้าเป็นไปได้.</para></warning>

		<sect2 id="install-deb" status="complete">
			<title>ติดตั้ง/ลบออกไฟล์ <emphasis>.deb</emphasis></title>
					<para>ไฟลเหล่านี้คือ  <emphasis>Debian packages</emphasis>.ชุดไฟล์ที่ใช้กับอูบันตูจะลงท้ายด้วย <emphasis>.deb</emphasis> เพราะอูบันตูพื้นฐานมาจาก Debian GNU/Linux distribution. ท่านจะต้องมี่ความสามารถระดับจัดการระบบเพื่อที่จะทำการติดตั้งไฟล์ชุด <emphasis>.deb</emphasis> (ดู <xref linkend="root-and-sudo"/>).</para>
						<para>To install a <emphasis>.deb</emphasis> file, double-click on it. If you prefer using the Terminal, enter:
						<screen>sudo dpkg -i package_file.deb</screen>
						</para>
						<para>To uninstall a <emphasis>.deb</emphasis> file, deselect it in your package manager. Or from a Terminal, enter:
						<screen>sudo dpkg -r package_name</screen>
						</para>
		</sect2>
		<sect2 id="alien" status="complete">
			<title>เปลื่ยนไฟล์ <emphasis>.rpm</emphasis> ไปเป็น <emphasis>.deb</emphasis> ไฟล์</title>
					<para>ชุดไฟล์อีกแบบหนึ่งคือ <emphasis>Red Hat Package Manager</emphasis> ที่ลงท้านด้วย <emphasis>.rpm</emphasis>. ไม่แนะนำให้ติดตั้งในระบบของอูบันตู. ในกรณีส่วนใหญ่จะมีชุดโปรแกรมอูบันตูลงท้ายด้วย <emphasis>.deb</emphasis>อยู่แล้ว.อย่างไรก็ตามถ้าจำเป็นจริงๆ,ชุดไฟล์ <emphasis>.rpm</emphasis> สามารถเปลี่ยนไปเป็นชุดไฟล์ <emphasis>.deb</emphasis>ด้วยโปรแกรม<application>alien</application>.</para>
						<para>
							In a terminal, enter:
							<screen>sudo alien <emphasis>package_file.rpm</emphasis></screen>
						</para>
						<para>
							If you get a <quote>command not found</quote> or similar error, install <application>alien</application> before trying again:
							<screen>sudo apt-get install alien</screen>
							
						</para>
			</sect2>
			<sect2 id="tarballs" status="complete">
				<title>ติดตั้ง <emphasis>ทาร์ไฟล์ (tarballs)</emphasis></title>
					<para>ไฟล์ที่ลงท้ายด้วย <emphasis>.tar.gz</emphasis> or <emphasis>.tar.bz2</emphasis> คือชุดไฟล์ที่เป็นที่รู้จักว่าทาร์บอล(<emphasis>tarballs</emphasis>) ที่ใช้กันแพร่หลายใน ลีนุกซ์และยูนิกซ์.</para>
					<para>ถ้าไม่มีชุดโปรแกรมสำหรับอูบันตูโดยเฉพาะในแหล่งเก็บข้อมูลต่างๆของอูบันตู,ท่านสามารถใช้คำสั่งสำหรับติดตั้งหรือลบออกทาร์บอลไฟล์โดยทำตามวิธีที่แนะมาในชุดโปรแกรมนั้น.</para>
					<para>ทาร์บอล(Tarballs) ปกติจะมีซอส์โค๊ด(source code)ของโปรแกรมมาด้วย และจะต้อง <emphasis>compiled</emphasis> จึงจะสามารถเรียกใช้ได้. ถ้าจะทำแบบนี้ต้องติดตั้งซอฟแวร์เพิ่มเติมก่อน (see <xref linkend="build-essential"/>).</para>
		</sect2>
	</sect1>
	    <sect1 id="extra-repositories" status="complete">
		<title>Software Repositories</title>
			<sect2 status="review"><title>แหล่งเก็บข้อมูล (Repositories) คืออะไร</title>
			<para>โปรแกรมหลายพันโปรแกรมที่สามารถติดตั้งในอูบันตู. โปรแกรมเหล่านี้เก็บรักษาไว้ในแหล่งเก็บข้อมูล software archives (<emphasis>repositories</emphasis>) และ สามารถติดตั้งผ่านอินเตอร์ฟรี. ทำให้ง่ายมากในการติดตั้งโปรแกรมใหม่ในลีนุกซ์,และ ปลอดภัย เพราะ แต่ละโปรแกรมสร้างขึ้นโดยเฉพาะสำหรับอูบันตูและจะถูกตรวจสอบก่อนถูกติดตั้ง. สำหรับจัดเก็บซอหปแวร์แหล่งเก็บข้อมูลของอูบันตูจะแบ่งออกเป็น 4 กลุ่มใหญ่: <emphasis>หลัก(Main)</emphasis>, <emphasis>จำกัด(Restricted)</emphasis>, <emphasis>อานาเขต(Universe)</emphasis>, and <emphasis>หลายอนาเขต(Multiverse)</emphasis>.</para> 
			<para>เหตุผลที่ใช้ในการตัดสินใจว่าซอฟแวร์จะอยู่กลุ่มใหนขึ้นอยู่กับพื้นฐาน 2 ประการ</para>
				<itemizedlist>
					<listitem>
						<para>ระดับของการบริการที่กลุ่มพัฒนาซอฟแวร์ที่สามารถให้ได้สำหรับโปรแกรม.</para>
					</listitem>
					<listitem>
						<para>The level of compliance the program has to the <ulink url="&ubuntu-philosophy;">Free Software Philosophy</ulink>.</para>
					</listitem>
				</itemizedlist>
			<para>You can find more information about the Repositories available <ulink url="&ubuntu-components;">on the website</ulink>.</para>
			<para>อูบันตูซีดีฉบับมาตรฐานบรรจุซอฟแวร์บางตัวที่มาจากปหล่งเก็บข้อมูล <emphasis>หลัก (Main) </emphasis> และ <emphasis>จำกัด (Restricted)</emphasis>. หลังจากที่เครื่องของท่านได้ถูกกำหนดตำแหน่งของแหล่งเก็บข้อมูลในอินเตอร์เน็ต,จะมีซอฟแวร์จำนวนมากที่สามารถติดตั้งได้. ใช้โปรแกรม จัดการชุดโปรแกรม (software package management tools) ที่ติดตั้งมากับระบบของท่าน, ท่านสามารถเสาะหา,ติดตั้ง,ปรับปรุง, ซอฟแวร์โดยตรงจากอินเตอร์เน็ตโดยไม่ต้องใช้แผ่นซีดี.</para>
		</sect2>
		<sect2 status="complete">
			<title>เพิ่มแหล่งเก็บข้อมูลเสริม</title>
			<para>To install software from the <quote>Universe</quote> or <quote>Multiverse</quote> repositories:</para>
			<procedure>
				<step>
					<para>Open &software-properties;.</para>
				</step>
				<step>
					<para>เลือก <guibutton>เพิ่มเติม</guibutton></para>
				</step>
				<step>
					<para>To use the <quote>Universe</quote> repository, turn on <guilabel>Community Maintained (Universe)</guilabel>.</para>
					<note>
						<para>การเพิ่มแหล่งเก็บข้อมูลนี้จะทำให้ซอฟแวร์ส่วนใหญ่อานาเขตฟรีซอฟแวร์สามารถติดตั้งในระบบของท่านได้. ซอฟแวร์นี้ให้บริการดูแลโดยกลุ่มอาสาสมัครที่ได้ผ่านการคัดสรรมาแล้วจากชุมชนอูบันตู,แต่ยังไม่ได้ดูแลโดยกลุ่มนักพัฒนาหลักของอูบันตูและอาจจะไม่ได้รับการปรับปรุงในด้านความปลอดภัยด้วย(security updates).</para>
					</note>
				</step>
				<step>
					<para>To use the <quote>Multiverse</quote> repository, turn on <guilabel>Non-free (Multiverse)</guilabel>.</para>
					<warning>
						<para>การเพิ่มแหล่งเก็บข้อมูลนี้จำทำให้ซอฟแวร์ที่จัดไว้ในกลุ่มไม่ฟรี <emphasis>non-free</emphasis> สามารถติดตั้งในเครื่องของท่านได้. ซอฟแวร์นี้อาจจะมีปัญหาในเรื่องอนุญาติใช้งานในบางพื้นที่. เมื่อท่านได้ติดตั้งชุดโปรแกรมจากแหล่งเก็บข้อมูลนี้, กรุณาตรวจสอบว่าสามารถใช้ในประเทศของท่านได้. ซอฟแวร์นี้อาจจะไม่รวมอยู่ในการปรับปรุงด้านความปลอดภัย.</para>
					</warning>
				</step>
				<step><para>คลิก <guibutton>Close</guibutton> เพื่อเก็บรักษาข้อมูลที่ท่านเปลี่ยนและออกจากโปรแกรม.</para>
				</step>
			</procedure>
			</sect2>
		</sect1>
	    <sect1 id="updates" status="complete">
		<title>เพิ่มเติม</title>
			<para>บางครั้งทีมงานพัฒนาอูบันตูจะปล่อยซอฟแวร์ปรับปรุงทางด้านความปลอดภัยและความสามารถใหม่สำหรับโปรแกรมและชุดโปรแกรมในระบอูบันตู.</para>
			<para>เมื่อมีซอฟแวร์สำหรับปรับปรุงเครื่องใหม่,อูบนตูจะบอกท่านด้วย pop-up และสัญญาลักษณ์สีแดงในตำแหน่งเตือน(notification area). ทำการปรับปรุงระบบของท่านด้วยการกดปุมสีแดงและใส่รหัสผ่านและคลิก <guibutton>OK</guibutton>.</para>
			<para>โปรแกรม ปรับปรุงจัดการ <application>Update Manager</application> จะแสดงรายการที่พร้อมจะปรับปรุง, คลิก <guibutton>Install Updates</guibutton> เพื่อ ดาวน์โหลดและทำการติดตั้ง. อูบันตูจะทำการดาวน์และติดตั้งรายการทั้งหมดจากอินเตอร์เน็ต.</para>
			<para>เมื่อโปรแกรม ปรับปรุงจัดการเครื่อง <application>Update Manager</application> เสร็จการปรับปรุงเครื่องแล้ว, กรุณากดปุ่ม <guibutton>ปิด</guibutton>เพื่อปิดหน้าต่าง pop-up,แล้วปิดโปรแกรมจึงเสร็จสิ้นการปรับปรุงเครื่อง.</para>
			<note>
				<para>หลังจากที่ได้ติดตั้งปรับปรุงส่วนที่สำคัญของระบบ,จึงอาจจะมีความจำเป็นที่จะต้องปิดและเปิดเครื่องใหม่. ถ้าเป็นเช่นนั้น,อูบันตูจะเปิด popup และแสดงสัญญาลักษณ์ในตำแหน่งเตือนความจำ(notification area).</para>
			</note>
	   </sect1>
</chapter>

