<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.3//EN" 
	"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.3/docbookx.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % globalent SYSTEM "../../../libs/global.ent">
%globalent;
<!ENTITY % cdo-C SYSTEM "../../../libs/cdo-C.ent">
%cdo-C;
<!ENTITY % gnome-menus-C SYSTEM "../../../ubuntu/libs/gnome-menus-C.ent">
%gnome-menus-C;
<!ENTITY % xinclude SYSTEM "../../../libs/xinclude.mod">
%xinclude;
<!ENTITY language "en">
<!ENTITY ubuntu '<phrase>Ubuntu</phrase>'>
]>
<chapter id="root-and-sudo" status="review">
			<title>Administrative Tasks</title>
			<para>In Ubuntu, for security reasons, administrative tasks are confined to users with special privileges. Administrative access is given to individual users, who may use the <application>sudo</application> command to perform administrative tasks. The first user account you created on your system during installation will, by default, have access to sudo. You can restrict and enable sudo access to users with the <application>Users and Groups</application> application (see <xref linkend="users-and-groups"/> for more information).
			</para>
			<para>เมื่อท่านเรียกใช้โปรแกรมที่ต้องการใช้อำนาจจัดการ (root privileges), โปรแกรมมอบอำนาจ (sudo) จะขอให้ท่านพิมพ์รหัสลับของท่านเพื่อที่จะเป็นการยืนยันที่จะดำเนินการต่อไป. เป็นการเตือนท่านให้ใช้ความระมัดระวังเพราะท่านกำลังสั่งงานเกียวกับการจัดการระบบอยู่</para>
			<para>ท่านสามารถใช้โปรแกรมมอบอำนาจในขณะที่ใช้บรรทัดรับคำสั่งได้ด้วยการพิมพ์คำว่า "sudo" เข้าไปข้างหน้าคำสั่งที่ท่านจะเรียกใช้. โปรแกรมมอบอำนาจก็จะขอให้ท่านพิมพ์รหัสลับให้</para>
			<para>Sudo will remember your password for a set amount of time, which by default is 15 minutes, but can be changed. This feature was designed to allow users to perform multiple administrative tasks without being asked for a password each time.
			</para>
				   <note>
						<para>กรุณาใช้ความระมัดระวังขณะทำงานด้านการจัดการไม่เช่นนั้นท่านอาจทำให้ระบบเสียหายได้</para>
				   </note>
			<para>คำแนะนำเพิ่มเติมในการใช้โปรแกรมมอบอำนาจ (sudo):</para>
			<itemizedlist>
				<listitem>
				<para>ใช้จอของเจ้านายใหญ่ (root terminal),พิมพ์คำสั่ง "sudo -i"</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
				<para>ทุกเครื่องมือที่ใช้ปรับแต่งกราฟฟิกใน Ubuntu เรียกใช้ผ่านโปรแกรมมอบอำนาจอยู่แล้ว,ท่านต้องใส่รหัสลับเมื่อโปรแกรมต้องการ</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
				<para>For more information on the <application>sudo</application> program and the absence of a root user in Ubuntu, read the <ulink url="&wiki-RootSudo;">sudo page</ulink> on the Ubuntu wiki.
				</para>
				</listitem>

			</itemizedlist>
		</chapter>

