<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.3//EN" 
	"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.3/docbookx.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % globalent SYSTEM "../../../libs/global.ent">
%globalent;
<!ENTITY % cdo-C SYSTEM "../../../libs/cdo-C.ent">
%cdo-C;
<!ENTITY % gnome-menus-C SYSTEM "../../../ubuntu/libs/gnome-menus-C.ent">
%gnome-menus-C;
<!ENTITY % xinclude SYSTEM "../../../libs/xinclude.mod">
%xinclude;
<!ENTITY language "en">
<!ENTITY ubuntu '<phrase>Ubuntu</phrase>'>
]>
<chapter id="music" status="complete">
			<title>Music and Video</title>
				<para>This section describes the music and video players available to use with Ubuntu and how to configure them to listen to different types of multimedia files.</para>
			<sect1 id="music-files" status="complete">
					<title>เล่นและจัดการไฟล์เสียง</title>
				<para>To play and organize your music, Ubuntu comes with		    <application>Rhythmbox Music Player</application>, which looks similar to <application>iTunes</application>. When you first start <application>Rhythmbox</application>, it will scan your home directory for any supported music files you have and add it to the database. To start <application>Rhythmbox</application>, choose &rhythmbox;.</para>
					<para>Ubuntu does not directly support the <emphasis role="strong">MP3</emphasis> format, because it is restricted by patents and proprietary rights. Instead Ubuntu supports the <emphasis role="strong">Ogg Vorbis</emphasis> format out of the box, a completely free, open and non-patented format. Ogg Vorbis files also sound better then MP3 files of the same file size and are supported by many portable music players.</para>
					<itemizedlist>
						<listitem><para><ulink url="http://wiki.xiph.org/index.php/PortablePlayers">Players that work with Vorbis</ulink></para></listitem>
					</itemizedlist>
					<para>You can still play your old MP3 files by installing MP3 support (see <xref linkend="codecs"/>). Instructions for other formats, such as Windows Media Audio (wma/wmv) and other patent-encumbered formats can be found <ulink url="http://wiki.ubuntu.com/RestrictedFormats">on the Ubuntu Wiki</ulink>.</para>
				<para>โปรแกรม <application>Cowbell</application> เป็นโปรแกรมแก้ไข ID3 แท็กซึ่งสามารถแก้ไขmetadataในไฟล์เพลง mp3และอื่นๆของคุณ เรียกใช้โปรแกรม <application>Cowbell</application>:</para>
				<procedure>
						<step>
							<para>Install the <application>cowbell</application> package from the <quote>Universe</quote> repository (see <xref linkend="add-applications"/>);</para>
						</step>
						<step>
							<para>To run <application>Cowbell</application>, choose
								<menuchoice>
									<guimenu>Applications</guimenu>
									<guisubmenu>Sound &amp; Video</guisubmenu>
									<guimenuitem>Cowbell Music Organizer</guimenuitem>
								</menuchoice>.
							</para>
						</step>
				</procedure>
			</sect1>
			<sect1 id="audio-cds" status="complete">
				<title>เล่นและดูดข้อมูลจากแผ่นซีดี</title>
				<para>เมื่อคุณใส่แผ่นซีดีเพลง โปรแกรม<application>Sound Juicer</application>ซึ่งเป็นโปรแกรมเล่นและบันทึกแผ่นซีดีจะเรียกใช้โดยอัตโนมัติ เล่นแผ่นซีดีโดยคลิกปุ่ม  <guibutton>Play</guibutton> หรือกดแป้นพิมพ์ <keycombo><keycap>Ctrl</keycap><keycap>P</keycap></keycombo> เลือกเล่นเพลงใดเพลงหนึ่งโดยคลิกสองครั้งบนเพลงนั้นหรือเลือกเพลงนั้นแล้วคลิก <guibutton>Play</guibutton></para>
				<para>คัดลอก(rip) แผ่นซีดีของคุณ กรุณาแน่ใจว่าเพลงที่คุณต้องการถูกเลือกไว้จากนั้นคลิกปุ่ม <guibutton>Extract</guibutton>หรือกดแป้นพิมพ์ <keycombo><keycap>Ctrl</keycap><keycap>Enter</keycap></keycombo></para>
					<note>
						<para>If you are connected to the internet, <application>Sound Juicer</application> will retrieve the CD artist, title, and track data from <ulink url="http://musicbrainz.org">MusicBrainz.org</ulink>, a community-maintained database of over 360,000 albums.
						</para>
					</note>
				<para>To start <application>Sound Juicer</application> manually, choose 
				<menuchoice>
					<guimenu>Applications</guimenu>
					<guimenuitem>Sound &amp; Video</guimenuitem>
					<guimenuitem>Sound Juicer CD Extractor</guimenuitem>
				</menuchoice>.
				</para>
				<para>You can use the preferences window to control where the extracted audio files are stored on your computer, the filename of extracted audio files, and the file format and codec used for the files. In the main window, choose 
				<menuchoice>
					<guimenu>Edit</guimenu>
					<guimenuitem>Preferences</guimenuitem>
				</menuchoice>.
				</para>
				<para><application>Sound Juicer</application> can extract audio files to these formats:
					<itemizedlist>
						<listitem>
							<para><emphasis role="strong">Ogg Vorbis</emphasis> - A patent-free lossy audio compression format, which typically produces higher quality and greater compression than MP3.</para>
							<itemizedlist>
								<listitem><para><ulink url="http://vorbis.com/faq/">More about Vorbis from vorbis.com</ulink></para></listitem>
							</itemizedlist>
						</listitem>
						<listitem>
							<para><emphasis role="strong">FLAC</emphasis> - The Free Lossless Audio Codec. It can compress audio files up to 50% without removing any information from the audio stream.</para>
							<itemizedlist>
								<listitem><para><ulink url="http://flac.sourceforge.net/">FLAC Web site</ulink></para></listitem>
							</itemizedlist>
						</listitem>
						<listitem>
							<para><emphasis role="strong">WAV</emphasis> - Typically used for voice recordings. <application>Sound Juicer</application> uses this format for low quality mono audio files. 
							</para>
						</listitem>
					</itemizedlist>
				</para>
				<para>You can also extract CD audio files to the proprietary non-free <emphasis role="strong">MP3</emphasis> format. Instructions on how to rip to the MP3 format are in the help for <application>Sound Juicer</application>. Choose 
				<menuchoice>
					<guimenu>Help</guimenu>
					<guisubmenu>Contents</guisubmenu>
				</menuchoice> and navigate to the <emphasis>Preferences</emphasis> section.
				</para>
			</sect1>
			<sect1 id="burning-cds" status="complete">
					<title>เขียนแผ่นซีดี</title>
					<para>เมื่อคุณใส่แผ่นซีดีเปล่าเข้าไปในเครื่องอูบันตูจะถามคุณต้องการที่จะเขียนซีดีเพลงหรือซีดีข้อมูล คลิก <guibutton>Burn Audio CD</guibutton> จะเรียกโปรแกรม <application>Serpentine</application> เพิ่มเพลงลงในซีดีเพลงของคุณโดยลากไฟล์เพลงจากไฟล์เบราเซอร์หรือใช้ปุ่ม <guibutton>Add</guibutton> คุณจะต้องเลือกขนาดของแผ่นซีดีของคุณด้วย (21, 74, 80 หรือ 90 นาที) โปรแกรม Serpentine จะเตือนถ้าคุณใส่เกินขนาดที่ตั้งไว้</para>
					<para>To make a photo or data CD, click <guibutton>Burn Data CD</guibutton>. Ubuntu will open a CD/DVD Creator window. The CD Creator is built into the File Browser, and it allows you to add any file or folder you have permission to access. When you are ready to burn the CD, click <guibutton>Write to Disc</guibutton>. Ubuntu will then prompt you to select the drive containing the blank CD, and give you the opportunity to name the CD and select the write speed. Finally, click <guibutton>Write</guibutton> to create the new photo or data CD.
					</para>
			</sect1>

		<sect1 id="video">
		<title>Video Playback</title>
		<para>To play video, Ubuntu comes with <application>Totem Movie Player</application>, which looks and functions similar to Windows Media Player. Features of
		<application>Totem</application> include custom playlists and DVD playback. 
	        You can start <application>Totem</application> by clicking: &totem; from the desktop menu system.
		</para>
		<para>อ่านวีดีโอไฟล์ โปรแกรม <application>Totem</application> ใช้โครงสร้างของ <application>Gstreamer</application> เพื่อที่จะสามารถเล่นบางวีดีโอฟอร์แมตคุณอาจจะต้องเพิ่มการสนับสนุนรหัสบีบอัดอื่นๆ(อ่าน <xref linkend="codecs"/>).</para>
		<para>There are also other multimedia applications available. Examples include <application>Mplayer</application>, <application>Xine</application> and <application>Totem-xine</application> (which uses the <application>Xine</application> framework, instead of the <application>Gstreamer</application> framework). You may benefit from trying alternative video players.</para>
		</sect1>

		<sect1 id="codecs" status="complete">
		<title>รหัสแปลแสงสีเสียง</title>
			<para>หลายแอพพิเคชันในอูบันตูใช้โครงสร้างเปิดเผย <application>GStreamer</application> รหัสบีบอัดเสริมของ  <application>GStreamer</application> จัดเก็บในแพ็กเกจต่างๆขึ้นอยู่กับใบอนุญาตที่ใช้กับรหัสบีบอัดนั้น คุณสามารถตรวจสอบว่ารหัสบีบอัดใดอยู่กับโปรแกรมเสริมใดที่ <ulink url="http://gstreamer.freedesktop.org/documentation/plugins.html">GStreamer website</ulink>.</para>
			<para>Other applications, such as <application>Mplayer</application> and <application>Xine</application>, do not use the <application>Gstreamer</application> framework. Due to patent and copyright restrictions, codecs for these programs are not included at all in Ubuntu. For more information on these read the <ulink url="&restricted-formats;">Restricted Formats</ulink> wiki page.</para>
			<para>ติดตั้ง codecs เพิ่มเติมสำหรับโปรแกรม  <application>Gstreamer</application>:</para>
				<procedure>
					<step>
							<para>Install the following packages from the <quote>Universe</quote> and <quote>Multiverse</quote> repositories (see <xref linkend="add-applications"/>):
								<literallayout>gstreamer0.10-plugins-ugly
gstreamer0.10-plugins-ugly-multiverse
gstreamer0.10-plugins-bad
gstreamer0.10-plugins-bad-multiverse
gstreamer0.10-ffmpeg
								</literallayout>
							</para>
							<note>
								<para>You will need to use <application>Synaptic Package Manager</application> to install these packages.
								</para>
							</note>
							<warning>
								<para>บางชุดโปรแกรมอาจจะไม่อนุญาตให้ใช้ในประเทศของท่าน, กรุณาตรวจสอบความถูกต้องก่อนที่ท่านจะทำการติดตั้ง.</para>
							</warning>
					</step>
				</procedure>
	</sect1>

			<sect1 id="ipod" status="complete">
			        <title>Using an iPod</title>
				<para>You can play music directly off an iPod with <application>Rhythmbox Music Player</application>. Plug the iPod into the computer, and open <application>Rhythmbox</application>.</para>
				<para>To transfer music files to and from an iPod, you can use <application>gtkpod</application>:</para>
					<procedure>
					<step>
						<para>Install the <application>gtkpod</application> package from the <quote>Universe</quote> repository (see <xref linkend="add-applications"/>).
						</para>
					</step>
					<step>
						<para>To run <application>gtkpod</application>, choose
								<menuchoice>
									<guimenu>Applications</guimenu>
									<guisubmenu>Sound &amp; Video</guisubmenu>
									<guimenuitem>gtkpod</guimenuitem>
								</menuchoice>.
						</para>
					</step>
					</procedure>
			</sect1>
			<sect1 id="edit-audio-files" status="complete">
				<title>ปรับแต่งไฟล์เสียง</title>
					<para>โปรแกรม Audacity เป็นโปรแกรมแบบเปิดเผยสามารถใช้ได้ฟรีสำหรับอัดและปรังแต่งเสียงดนตรี. เรียกใช้โปรแกรม Audacity :</para>
					<procedure>
						<step>
							<para>Install the audacity package from the <quote>Universe</quote> repository (see <xref linkend="add-applications"/>).
							</para>
						</step>
						<step>
							<para>To run <application>Audacity</application>, choose
								<menuchoice>
									<guimenu>Applications</guimenu>
									<guisubmenu>Sound &amp; Video</guisubmenu>
									<guimenuitem>Audacity</guimenuitem>
								</menuchoice>.
							</para>
						</step>
						<step>
							<para>For further help with Audacity, use Audacity’s <guimenu>Help</guimenu> menu.</para>
						</step>							
					</procedure>
			</sect1>

		<sect1 id="dvdplayback" status="complete">
			<title>โปรแกรมเล่นแผ่นดีวีดี</title>
				<para>โปรแกรมเล่นภาพยนต์ที่มีมากับอูบันตูสามารถเล่นแผ่นดีวีดีที่ไม่ได้เข้ารหัสไว้ อย่างไรก็ตามแผ่นดีวีดีที่มีขายส่วนใหญ่จะเข้ารหัสด้วย CSS (the Content Scrambling System) และด้วยเหตุผลทางกฏหมายจึงไม่สามารถที่จะรวมการสนับสนุนแผ่นดีวีดีนี้ในอูบันตู อย่างไรก็ตามการสนับสนุนนี้สามารถทำได้โดย:</para>
				<warning><para>สถานะทางกฏหมายของ library นี้ไม่ชัดเจน ในบางประเทศกฏหมายไม่อนุญาตให้ใช้ library นี้ในการเล่นแผ่นหรือทำสำเนา กรุณาตรวจสอบว่าคุณมีสิทธิ์ที่จะใช้</para></warning>
				<procedure>
					<step>
						<para>ติดตั้งชุดโปรแกรม  <application>libdvdread3</application> (อ่าน <xref linkend="add-applications"/>).</para>
					<note><para>ท่านจะต้องใช้โปรแกรม  <application>Synaptic Package Manager</application> เพื่อที่จะติดตั้งชุดโปรแกรมนี้</para></note>
					</step>
					<step>
						<para>To activate DVD decryption, type the following line into a terminal prompt:<screen>sudo /usr/share/doc/libdvdread3/install-css.sh</screen>
						</para>
					</step>
					<step>
						<para>เพื่อที่จะสามารถเล่นแผ่นดีวีดีด้วยโปรแกรม  <application>Totem</application>,ท่านจะต้องติดตั้ง some extra codecs (อ่าน <xref linkend="codecs"/>).</para>
					</step>
					<step>
						<para>However, the <application>Gstreamer</application> framework (used by <application>Totem</application>) does not support menus or subtitles for DVD playback. For this reason, you can install a separate DVD player, <application>Xine</application>, which supports these. To install <application>Xine</application>, install the <application>gxine</application> package from the <quote>Universe</quote> repository (see <xref linkend="add-applications"/>).</para>
					</step>
					<step>
						<para>ท่านสามารถเรียกโปรแกรม <application>gxine</application> จากเมนู  Sound &amp; Video.</para>
					</step>
				</procedure>
		</sect1>

			<sect1 status="complete">
				<title>โปรแกรมสำรองข้อมูลใส่แผ่น ดีวีดี</title>
					<para>You can back up your DVDs to files or onto DVD+/- discs with <application>DVD::RIP</application>. To install
<application>DVD::RIP</application>:</para>
					<warning><para>ก่อนทำสำเนาแผ่นดีวีดี, ท่านต้องแน่ใจว่าจะไม่ทำผิดกฏหมายที่จะทำสำเนา</para></warning>
					<procedure>
						<step>
							<para>ติดตั้ง Multimedia Codecs (อ่าน <xref linkend="codecs"/>).</para>
						</step>
						<step>
							<para>เล่น DVD video (อ่าน <xref linkend="dvdplayback"/>).</para>
						</step>
						<step>
							<para>Install <application>dvdrip</application> and <application>transcode</application> from the <quote>Multiverse</quote> repository (see <xref linkend="add-applications"/>).
							</para>
						</step>
						<step>
							<para>You can run the program using the command <application>dvdrip</application> (see <ulink type="help" url="ghelp:user-guide#tools-run-app">the run application manual</ulink> for help on how to run an application without using the menu). If you wish, you can add a menu entry for the program <application>dvdrip</application> (see <ulink type="help" url="ghelp:user-guide#menu-editor">the menu editor manual</ulink> for help on how to add menu entries). We recommend you enter it in the Sound &amp; Video menu, and that you use the file <filename>/usr/share/perl5/Video/DVDRip/icon.xpm</filename> for the icon.
							</para>
						</step>
						<step>
							<para>To start  <application>dvd::rip</application>, choose
								<menuchoice>
									<guimenu>Applications</guimenu>
									<guisubmenu>Sound &amp; Video</guisubmenu>
									<guimenuitem>dvd::rip</guimenuitem>
								</menuchoice>.
							</para>
						</step>
					</procedure>
			</sect1>
		<sect1 status="complete">
			<title>RealPlayer</title>
					<procedure>
						<step>
							<para>Install the <application>realplay</application> package from the <emphasis>Commercial</emphasis> repository (see <xref linkend="add-applications"/>).</para>
						</step>
						<step>
							<para>To run <application>RealPlayer</application>, choose
								<menuchoice>
									<guimenu>Applications</guimenu>
									<guisubmenu>Sound &amp; Video</guisubmenu>
									<guimenuitem>RealPlayer 10</guimenuitem>
								</menuchoice>.
							</para>
						</step>
					</procedure>
			</sect1>
			<sect1 status="complete">
					<title>โปรแกรมสำหรับแก้ไขวีดิทัศน์</title>
					<para>โปรแกรม <application>Kino</application> เป็นโปรแกรมตัดต่อวีดีโอที่มีความสามารถสูง มีความสามารถเช่น  IEEE-1394สำหรับจับภาพเข้าเครื่อง VTR controlและบันทึกกลับไปที่กล้องได้ สามารถจับภาพลงดิสก์ด้วยฟอร์แมต Raw DV และ AVI ทั้งสองแบบ type-1 DV and type-2 DV (separate audio stream) encodings รายละเอียดเพิ่มเติมกรุณาอ่าน <ulink url="http://www.kinodv.org/article/static/2">the Kino website</ulink>. เรียกใช้:</para>
					<procedure>
						<step>
							<para>ติดตั้งชุดโปรแกรม <application>kino</application> (อ่าน <xref linkend="add-applications"/>).</para>
						</step>
						<step>
							<para>To run <application>Kino</application>, choose
								<menuchoice>
									<guimenu>Applications</guimenu>
									<guisubmenu>Sound &amp; Video</guisubmenu>
									<guimenuitem>Kino Video Editor</guimenuitem>
								</menuchoice>.
							</para>
						</step>
					</procedure>
					<para>You can also try the <application>PiTiVi</application> video editor by installing the <application>pitivi</application> package from the <quote>Universe</quote> repository (see <xref linkend="add-applications"/>). <application>PiTiVi</application> is a video editor for the GNOME desktop. It is still in fairly early development, but worth a try.</para>
			</sect1>
	   </chapter>

