<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.3//EN" 
	"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.3/docbookx.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % xinclude SYSTEM "../../libs/xinclude.mod">
%xinclude;
<!ENTITY % globalent SYSTEM "../../libs/global.ent">
%globalent;
]>
<chapter id="moreinfo-applicationmigration">
    <title>applications for Switchers</title>
    <para>This section will highlight and explain some of the applications available in Ubuntu 
		that are similar to standard stools on other operating systems, and allow for doing 
		tasks like word processing, image manipulation and video, media players, web browsing, 			local area networking, and instant messaging. Many of these applications look and act 
    similar to their counterparts on other operating systems.</para>
    <sect1 id="moreinfo-office-software">
        <title>Office Software</title>
        <para>The Open Office package is suite of tools for word processing, spreadsheet 
            creation, presentations, academic writing and other document creation common to an 
            office. Allot of the tasks you might do in the Microsoft Office suite on 
            Windows can be done using Open Office. The basic layout and functionality of the 
        two suites is very similar. All Open Office applications can be found under &open-office;.</para>
        <para>The word processing component of Open Office is called <application>Open Office
        Writer</application>. This program has it's own internal document
            format, but can also read and write Microsoft Word documents (.doc files) and 
        Microsoft Word template documents (.dot files).</para>
        <para>The spreadsheet component of Open Office is called <application>Open Office
        Spreadsheet</application>. This program has it's own internal document
            format, but can also read and write Microsoft Excel documents (.xls, .xlw files) 
        and Microsoft Excel template documents (.xlt files).</para>
        <para>The presentation component of Open Office is called <application>Open Office
        Presentation</application>. This program also has it's own internal format,
            but can also read and write Microsoft PowerPoint documents (.ppt, .pps files) and
        Microsoft PowerPoint template files (.pot files).</para>
        <para>All Open Office documents can also be exported to Portable Document Format (.pdf
            files) to ensure portability and consistency of layout across platforms and PDF Reader applications such as <application>Acrobat Reader</application>.</para>
    </sect1>
    <sect1 id="moreinfo-image-manipulation-video-software">
        <title>Image Manipulation and Video Software</title>
        <para>The <application>Gimp</application>, which stands for The GNU Image Manipulation Program, is a program for
            drawing, painting and editing images. Many of the tools and plugins available in 
			The Gimp are similar to the ones in Adobe Photoshop, or other bitmap based editors. 
			The Gimp also provides scriptable operations and manipulation with bindings to 
			various open source scripting languages.</para>
        <para>The Gimp has support for reading and writing a variety of media types including
            proprietary formats such as those of Adobe Photoshop (.psd files). Support for 
			scanners and printers is also available. There are Allot of other tools for image 
			manipulation covering a massive range of formats, though The Gimp is one of the 
			only applications that presents its tools and functionality through a Graphical 			User Interface similar to
            products on other platforms. The Gimp is available from the &apos;main&apos;
            repository from within Synaptic Package Manager (see <xref
                linkend="software-installremove" endterm="title-software-installremove"/> 
				for more information).</para>
    </sect1>
    <sect1 id="moreinfo-media-players">
        <!-- FIX ME: not finished -->
        <title>Media Players</title>
        <para>Ubuntu has a wide variety of tools for manipulating, formatting and editing  
			digital
            video. As there are many patent issues and fierce protection of proprietary 
			formats in digital media, Ubuntu GNU/Linux does not provide support for all the known  
			formats that are common on other platforms in the standard distribution. Ubuntu 
			comes with media players that don't support the most popular media formats used in 
			other operating systems (mp3, windows media, divx to name a few). This is hard to 
			get used to if you are coming to Ubuntu from Microsoft Windows or OSX.</para>
        <para>One of the first media types you are probably wanting to play if you have come 
			from another operating system is mp3. To do so you need to</para>
    </sect1>
    <sect1 id="moreinfo-others">
        <title>Other applications</title>
        <variablelist>
            <title>Other applications</title>
            <varlistentry>
                <term>Autocad</term>
                <listitem>
                    <para>qcad</para>
                </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
                <term>Matlab</term>
                <listitem>
                    <para>octave</para>
                </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
                <term>Nero Burning ROM</term>
                <listitem>
                    <para>A CD-Burning tool called <application>nautilus-cd-burner</application> is already
                        included in Nautilus, which is the main desktop file manager.</para>
                </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
                <term>Outlook</term>
                <term>Outlook Express</term>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Evolution</para>
                </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
        </variablelist>
    </sect1>
</chapter>
