<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE book PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.3//EN" 
	  "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.3/docbookx.dtd" [
	  <!ENTITY % xinclude SYSTEM "../../../libs/xinclude.mod">
	  %xinclude;
	  <!ENTITY % globalent SYSTEM "../../../libs/global.ent">
	  %globalent;
	  <!ENTITY % cdo-C SYSTEM "../../../libs/cdo-C.ent">
	  %cdo-C;
	  <!ENTITY % kde SYSTEM "../../libs/kde.ent">
	  %kde;
	  <!ENTITY % kde-menus-C SYSTEM "../../libs/kde-menus-C.ent">
	  %kde-menus-C;
	  <!ENTITY language "&EnglishAmerican;">
	  ]>
	  <book status="help" id="kuserguide" lang="&language;">
		  <title>The Kubuntu &kdistro-version; User Guide </title>
		  <bookinfo>
			  <title>The Kubuntu &kdistro-version; User Guide</title>
			  <revhistory>
				  <revision>
					  <revnumber>0.1</revnumber>
					  <date>June 22, 2005</date>
					  <authorinitials>SW</authorinitials>
					  <revdescription>
						  <para>Outline</para>
					  </revdescription>
				  </revision>
				  <revision>
					  <revnumber>0.2</revnumber>
					  <date>July 7, 2005</date>
					  <authorinitials>SW</authorinitials>
					  <revdescription>
						  <para>Start writing sections that we know will be the same
							  in breezy as they are in hoary.</para>
					  </revdescription>
				  </revision>
			  </revhistory> &copyright; &disclaimer; &legalnotice;
			  &publisher; <authorgroup> &author-sean-wheller;
				  &author-greg-taylor; &author-troy-williams;
				  <author>
					  <firstname>Jonathan</firstname>
					  <surname>Jesse</surname> 
			</author> </authorgroup>
			  <abstract>
				  <para>This document is the Kubuntu User Guide.</para>
			  </abstract>
		  </bookinfo>
		  <preface id="pref-kuserguide" status="help">
			  <title>Preface</title> &conventions; &feedback; <sect1
										id="sect-acknowledge" status="help">
				  <title>Acknowledgments</title>
				  <para>...</para>
			  </sect1>
			  <sect1 id="sect-audience" status="review">
				  <title>Audience</title>
				  <para>This book is written with the absolute Linux beginner in mind.
					  So, if Kubuntu is your first excursion into the world of Linux,
					  this book is for you. We hope, with help from this book, that
					  Kubuntu will make your experience a satisfactory one. Having
					  said this, the book is equally suitable for people who have used
					  a Linux distribution before and are just new to Kubuntu.</para>
			  </sect1>
			  <sect1 id="sect-related" status="review">
				  <title>Related Documents</title>
				  <para>Every GNU/Linux system installs manuals or documentation to
					  help users understand how command line programs and graphical
					  applications can be used to accomplish tasks. More information
					  about these document types and how they may be viewed is
					  provided in <xref linkend="chp-help"/>. These documents are an
					  integral part of the Kubuntu installation but, rather than being
					  specific to Kubuntu they are generic to the GNU/Linux operating
					  system or the K Desktop Environment (KDE). You will find these
					  documents on all GNU/Linux systems and K Desktop systems.</para>
				  <para>Unlike these GNU/Linux or KDE documents, this document and the
					  following related documents are not generic, but are specific to
					  Kubuntu. You will not find them installed by default on Linux
					  distributions other than Kubuntu.</para>
				  <itemizedlist>
					  <listitem>
						  <para>
							  <ulink
								url="help:/khelpcenter/kubuntu/about-kubuntu/C/index.html"
								>About Kubuntu</ulink>
						  </para>
					  </listitem>
					  <listitem>
						  <para>
							  <ulink
								url="help:/khelpcenter/kubuntu/krelease-notes/C/kreleasenotes.html"
								>Kubuntu &kdistro-version; Release Notes</ulink>
						  </para>
					  </listitem>
					  <listitem>
						  <para>
							  <ulink
								url="help:/khelpcenter/kubuntu/kquickguide/C/index.html"
								>The Kubuntu Quick Guide</ulink>
						  </para>
					  </listitem>
				  </itemizedlist>
				  <para>Kubuntu documents are specific to Kubuntu. In other words,
					  while they contain information that may also be found in the
					  generic GNU/Linux and KDE documents, Kubuntu documents describe
					  the implementation and usage of GNU/Linux and KDE that is
					  particular to Kubuntu as a distribution. As such, Kubuntu
					  documents are not a comprehensive reference to everything that
					  is GNU/Linux or KDE, you may still be required to access these
					  documents in order to gather additional information. Kubuntu
					  documents are primarily designed to orientate users to Kubuntu
					  and enable them to quickly become productive with Kubuntu as a
					  distribution. For this reason, Kubuntu documents often contain
					  excerpts from the information found in GNU/Linux and KDE
					  documents, often merging this information into a single resource
					  to provide a single point from which to contextualize
					  information and reference additional information.</para>
			  </sect1>
			  <sect1 id="sect-organization" status="writing">
				  <title>Organization</title>
				  <authorblurb>
					  <para>Sean Wheller: needs completion near end of
						  development.</para>
				  </authorblurb>
				  <para>The organization of this book is designed to familiarize you
					  with Kubuntu and enable you to accomplish a number of selected
					  tasks commonly performed by Kubuntu users.</para>
				  <!-- Outline organization of this book here -->
			  </sect1>
		  </preface>
		  <part id="prt-intro" status="review">
			  <title>Introducing Kubuntu</title>
			  <partintro>
				  <abstract>
					  <para>Kubuntu is a terrific new distribution, suitable for
						  desktops and servers. This section introduces Kubuntu, explains
						  what is new in this release and the options you have to
						  obtain support in resolving any problems you may encounter.
						  You will also find useful pointers on how you
						  can contribute to further the development of Kubuntu.</para>
					  <para>By the end of this section you will:</para>
					  <para>
						  <itemizedlist>
							  <listitem>
								  <para>Understand the relationship between Ubuntu and
									  Kubuntu and the Kubuntu relationship with
									  upstream projects such as KDE and Debian.</para>
							  </listitem>
							  <listitem>
								  <para>Know where to go for help when you encounter
									  problems.</para>
							  </listitem>
							  <listitem>
								  <para>Be aware of the variety of ways in which you
									  can contribute to improving and enhancing
									  Kubuntu.</para>
							  </listitem>
						  </itemizedlist>
					  </para>
				  </abstract>
			  </partintro>
			  <xi:include href="../../aboutkubuntu/C/about-kubuntu.xml"
				      xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
				  <xi:fallback>
					  <para>
						  <emphasis>FIXME: MISSING XINCLUDE CONTENT</emphasis>
					  </para>
				  </xi:fallback>
			  </xi:include>
			  <xi:include href="../../kreleasenotes/C/kreleasenotes.xml"
				      xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
				  <xi:fallback>
					  <para>
						  <emphasis>FIXME: MISSING XINCLUDE CONTENT</emphasis>
					  </para>
				  </xi:fallback>
			  </xi:include>
			  <chapter id="chp-help" status="review">
				  <title>Getting Help</title>
				  <para>Kubuntu is one of the easiest to use Debian-based
					  distributions but, as with any operating system, there always
					  comes a time when you need help. The level of help required will
					  depend on what you are trying to do. Most problems can be
					  quickly solved by reading this book and other documents that are
					  available in <xref linkend="sect-khelpcenter"
							     endterm="title-sect-khelpcenter"/>. When this fails your
					  next option is <xref linkend="sect-communitysupport"
							       endterm="title-sect-communitysupport"/> and thereafter <xref
										linkend="sect-paidsupport" endterm="title-sect-paidsupport"
										/>.</para>
				  <sect1 id="sect-khelpcenter" status="review">
					  <title id="title-sect-khelpcenter">KHelpCenter</title>
					  <para>The <application>KHelpCenter</application>, short for KDE
						  Help Center, is the application used to locate and read
						  various types of documentation, including:</para>
					  <variablelist>
						  <varlistentry>
							  <term>KDE Documents</term>
							  <listitem>
								  <para>The K Desktop Environment is one of the best
									  documented graphical user interface
									  environments. KDE Documents provide valuable
									  information on topics such as using the K
									  Desktop and the KDE applications installed on
									  your system. While reading this document you
									  will find many references to the KDE
									  Documents.</para>
							  </listitem>
						  </varlistentry>
						  <varlistentry>
							  <term>man pages</term>
							  <listitem>
								  <para>Man pages, or manual pages, are electronic
									  reference manuals describing the command syntax
									  and usage of programs, utilities or functions.
									  Manual pages mostly discuss GNU or Linux
									  commands and are therefore primary designed to
									  be read in a command line interface or prompt
									  environment. The <command>man</command> command
									  is an interface or pager program. To read a
									  manual page you would issue the
									  <command>man</command> command followed by the
									  name of the GNU or Linux program for which you need
									  documentation. For example, the
									  <application>man</application> program has a
									  manual page of its own. Issuing the following
									  command will display the manual page for the
									  <application>man</application> program.</para>
								  <screen>
									  man man
								  </screen>
								  <para>
									  <application>KHelpCenter</application> can
									  display the manual page file format so that you
									  can read manual pages without having to use the
									  command prompt.</para>
							  </listitem>
						  </varlistentry>
						  <varlistentry>
							  <term>Info documents</term>
							  <listitem>
								  <para>Like man pages, info documents are primarily
									  formatted to be displayed in a command line
									  environment. Info documents tend to be more
									  detailed and provide more navigation features
									  than manual pages. Like
									  <application>man</application>,
									  <application>info</application> is a program
									  called an <quote>info reader</quote>. To view an
									  info document using the <quote>info
										reader</quote> you issue the
									<command>info</command> command followed by the
									name of the program whose info document you want
									to read. For example, to read the info document
									for the <quote>info reader</quote> you would
									issue the following command.</para>
								<screen>
									info info
								</screen>
								<para>
									<application>KHelpCenter</application> can
									display the info document file format so that
									you can read info pages without having to use
									the command prompt.</para>
							</listitem>
						</varlistentry>
					</variablelist>
					<para>In addition to these documents, you will find Kubuntu
						documents in <application>KHelpCenter</application> (see
						<xref linkend="sect-related"/>).</para>
				</sect1>
				<sect1 id="sect-communitysupport" status="review">
					<title id="title-sect-communitysupport">Community Support</title>
					<para>One of the primary means of support available to users of
						free software comes from the community of open source
						software developers and users. Kubuntu enjoys terrific
						support in the open source community. As a result, Kubuntu
						users enjoy an unprecedented level of support from a diverse
						and large group of expert developers and users in the
						community. Anyone is free to direct questions to the
						community. The following is a list of key services commonly
						used as resources for getting support:</para>
					<itemizedlist>
						<listitem>
							<para>
								<ulink url="&kubuntu-lists;">Kubuntu-Users
									Mailing List</ulink>
							</para>
						</listitem>
						<listitem>
							<para>
								<ulink url="&kubuntu-wiki;">Kubuntu Wiki</ulink>
							</para>
						</listitem>
						<listitem>
							<para>
								<ulink url="&kubuntu-forums;">Kubuntu
									Forum</ulink>
							</para>
						</listitem>
					</itemizedlist>
					<para>These and many more Kubuntu resources are also indexed by
						<ulink url="&google;">Google</ulink> and other
						search engines. With so many people using Kubuntu there is a
						high probability that other people have had the same problem
						you are experiencing. Before posting questions to these
						resources, it is recommended that you use services such as
						Google to search these resources or the knowledge archive
						they represent. The advantage of using tools like Google
						before posting is that you may find the answer immediately
						and not have to wait for a response from somebody in the
						community.</para>
					<para>Google provides a very useful query syntax that ensures
						your search is limited to a specific web site. For example,
						assuming you want to change the Kubuntu login screen and are
						having difficulties doing so. You would use
						<application>Konqueror</application>, the KDE Web
						Browser, to access Google and then, in the search field,
						enter the following query:</para>
					<screen>
						change login screen site:http://lists.ubuntu.com/archives/kubuntu-users/
					</screen>
					<para>For more information on using Konqueror see <xref
										linkend="web-browsing"/>.</para>
					<para>The first part of this query is comprised of the words you
						are searching for, <quote>change login screen</quote>. The
						remainder of the query starts with the keyword
						<quote>site</quote> followed by a colon. This instructs
						Google to limit the query to the web site address, or
						<firstterm>Uniform Resource Locater</firstterm> (URL),
						that follows the colon. In this case, the site searched is
						limited to the Kubuntu users mailing list. Replace the web
						site address with any of the URLs listed above to limit your
						search accordingly.</para>
					<para>In addition to these resources it is also possible to use
						<firstterm>Internet Relay Chat</firstterm> (IRC) as a
						means to ask questions. This method of getting support is
						the most interactive of all support options. It involves
						using <application>Konversation</application>, the KDE IRC
						client, to connect to an IRC server, joining a channel or
						chat room, then asking your question to the group of people
						in the room. The IRC server where you will find Kubuntu
						users is <emphasis>irc.freenode.net</emphasis>. Kubuntu
						users tune in to the channel called, yes you guessed it,
						<emphasis>#Kubuntu</emphasis>. For more information on
						using <application>Konversation</application> and connecting
						to an IRC server see <xref linkend="irc"/>.</para>
				</sect1>
				<sect1 id="sect-paidsupport" status="help">
					<title id="title-sect-paidsupport">Paid Support</title>
					<authorblurb>
						<para>Sean Wheller: I find no company advertising support
							for Kubuntu. There are many companies in the Ubuntu
							Marketplace advertising support for Ubuntu, but not
							Kubuntu.</para>
					</authorblurb>
					<para>...</para>
				</sect1>
			</chapter>
			<chapter id="chp-contributions" status="help">
				<title>Contributing to Kubuntu</title>
				<para>...</para>
			</chapter>
		</part>
		<part id="prt-confighardware" status="help">
			<title>Configuring Hardware</title>
			<partintro>
				<abstract>
					<para>The first few weeks after installing an operating system
						are often spent configuring and tweaking the environment so
						that it works the way you want it. While Kubuntu does a
						great job of supporting a wide range of hardware and
						devices, the task of installing or configuring some devices
						can be daunting to a person. This part covers the
						installation and configuration of common devices so that you
						can make the most of your computer. </para>
				</abstract>
			</partintro>
			<chapter status="help">
				<title>System Settings</title>
				<sect1>
					<title>Section Tittle</title>
					<para>...</para>
				</sect1>
			</chapter>
			<chapter status="help">
				<title>Configuring Screen Resolution</title>
				<sect1>
					<title>Section Tittle</title>
					<para>...</para>
				</sect1>
			</chapter>
			<chapter status="help">
				<title>Configuring a Sound Card</title>
				<sect1>
					<title>Section Tittle</title>
					<para>...</para>
				</sect1>
			</chapter>
			<chapter status="writing">
				<!-- Troy Williams: Writing this Part -->
				<title>Configuring a Printer</title>
				<sect1>
					<title>Connecting to a Printer</title>
					<para>Kubuntu features the impressive KDE Printing Manager, which sports a host of
						useful features. <mousebutton>Click</mousebutton> on the <guibutton>K
							Menu</guibutton> button in your Toolbar and choose <menuchoice>
							<guimenu>Utilities</guimenu>
							<guimenuitem>Printing Manager</guimenuitem>
						</menuchoice> to start the Printing Manager Control Module. You can add, or connect
						to, a printer using this module.</para>
					<screenshot>
						<mediaobject>
							<imageobject>
								<imagedata fileref="../../images/&language;/kubuntu-printers.png" format="PNG"/>
							</imageobject>
							<textobject>
								<phrase>Printing Manager</phrase>
							</textobject>
						</mediaobject>
					</screenshot>
					<para>To add a printer, <mousebutton>click</mousebutton>
						<menuchoice>
							<guimenu>Add</guimenu>
							<guimenuitem>Add Printer/Class...</guimenuitem>
						</menuchoice> to launch the <application>Add Printer Wizard</application>, which
						will walk you through the process of adding a local printer or connecting to a
						printer on your network.</para>
					<screenshot>
						<mediaobject>
							<imageobject>
								<imagedata fileref="../../images/&language;/kubuntu-printwizard.png" format="PNG"/>
							</imageobject>
							<textobject>
								<phrase>Printer Wizard</phrase>
							</textobject>
						</mediaobject>
					</screenshot>
					<para>Follow the directions presented in the Wizard to add a local printer or connect to
						a printer on your network.</para>
					<note>
						<para>You may need to click the <guibutton>Administrator Mode</guibutton> button
							before making changes to your printer settings.</para>
					</note>
					<tip>
						<para>If you'd like to see an icon in your <emphasis>System Tray</emphasis> when
							there are pending print jobs, start <application>KJobViewer</application>, which
							you will find in <menuchoice>
								<guimenu>K Menu</guimenu>
								<guimenuitem>Utilities</guimenuitem>
								<guimenuitem>Print Jobs (KJobViewer)</guimenuitem>
							</menuchoice>. <mousebutton>Clicking</mousebutton> on the tray icon when it
							appears during printing will bring up a dialogue that will allow you to easily
							move, pause, and cancel print jobs. Note that the tray icon is only present
							while you are in the process of printing a document(s).</para>
					</tip>
				</sect1>
			</chapter>
			<chapter status="help">
				<title>Configuring a Scanner</title>
				<sect1>
					<title>Section Tittle</title>
					<para>...</para>
				</sect1>
			</chapter>
			<chapter status="help">
				<title>Configuring a Fax Modem</title>
				<sect1>
					<title>Section Tittle</title>
					<para>...</para>
				</sect1>
			</chapter>
		</part>
		<part id="prt-kdesktop" status="help">
			<title>The Kubuntu Desktop</title>
			<partintro>
				<abstract>
					<para>This part is an orientation to the Kubuntu Desktop.</para>
				</abstract>
			</partintro>
			<chapter status="help">
				<title>The Kicker</title>
				<sect1>
					<title>Section Tittle</title>
					<para>...</para>
				</sect1>
			</chapter>
			<chapter status="writing">
				<!-- Jonathan Jesse: Writing this Part -->
				<title>The K Menu</title>
				
				<para>The K Menu is to Kubuntu as the Start Menu is to Microsoft
					Windows and the three buttons (Applications, Places and
					System) are to Ubuntu. Through the K Menu one can access any
					of the other applications mentioned in this guide, along
					with anything that is installed. The K Menu is divided into
					the various sections that are represented in this UserGuide.</para>
				<para>The Menu Editor allows a person to edit the exact
					applications that appear on the K Menu. To open the Menu
					Editor, right click on the K and select Menu Editor. The
					editor is a simple to use program that allows one to create
					links to new applications and even subfolders to further
					organize one&apos;s K Menu. Make sure that when one is
					done editign the menu to save the changes or everything will
					be lost. </para>
				<para> When the menu editor is opened for the first time, there
					maybe more folders showing then what is currently in K Menu.
					These folders are all the possible types of folders that can
					be installed in Kubuntu.</para>
				
			</chapter>
			<chapter status="writing">
				<!-- Jonathan Jesse: Writing this Part -->
				<title>Customizing the Desktop</title>
				
				<para>The easiest way to configure one's destkop is to simply right click 
					on the desktop and select "Configure Desktop," or through the Control
					Center. There are four sections that make up Configure Desktop.</para>
				
				<sect1>
					<title>Background</title>
					<para> The most common item changed on a desktop is the background.
						Kubuntu provides the standard KDE backgrounds and also for any user to
						save his/her own images and create a background from them.  Also more 
						background images can be download from KDE.org by selecting <quote>Get New
							Wallpapers.</quote> </para>
					<para>Each desktop can be sized according to the users needs and also
						can be blended in.  Also in Kubuntu one can have either the same
						background for each desktop or different images. </para>
				</sect1>
				<sect1>
					<title>Beahvoir</title>
					<para>This section of "Confiugre Desktop" controls how one interacts
						with the desktop, either thru configuring mouse behaviors or how a file
						device appears on the desktop. </para>
				</sect1>
				<sect1>
					<title>Multiple Desktops</title>
					<para>One of the bonuses to using Kubuntu is the ability to have multiple
						desktops to increase the amount of viewable space one has.  Kubuntu can
						support up to 20 different desktops and this section allows the uses to
						specify how many desktops to use and if each desktop has a differnt title
						(The default title is Desktop1, Destkop2, etc).</para>
				</sect1>
				<sect1>
					<title>Screen Saver</title>
					<para>This section allows for configuration of the all important screen saver.
						Kubuntu comes with some screen savers already installed, but one can also
						download others from the web.  One can also set the time and whether or not
						the screen saver will lock.</para>
				</sect1>
				
				
			</chapter>
			<chapter status="writing">
				<!-- Jonathan Jesse: Writing this Part -->
				<title>Managing Desktops and Applications</title>
				<para>...</para>
			</chapter>
			<chapter status="help">
				<title>The File System</title>
				<para>...</para>
			</chapter>
			<chapter status="help">
				<title>Adding User Accounts</title>
				<para>Kubuntu is a multi-user system, which allows for multiple people to have different accounts 
					on the same system.  The first user created in the installation is also the super user and other
					accounts can be used throughout the system.</para>
				<para> To manage Users in Kubuntu, access the User Manager (KUser) from the K Menu and then under
					the System folder.  Upon launching this application, the password for the super user (first account)
					is requested.  There are two tabs in KUser, one that deals with Users and the second that deals with
					groups.</para>
				<sect1>
					<title>Users</title>
					<para>
						The Users section of KUser will first display all of the users on the system.  Information displayed
						in this section are the UID, the User Login (username), the Full Name, the Home Directory, and also 
						what shell that user will be using.  One can create new users either through the buttons or through
						the different menus.</para>
				</sect1>
				<sect1>
					<title>Creating a new user</title>
					<para>To create a new user, selct User and then Add User.  First one will be prompted for the user name and
						then a new window will open up.  This window will allow one to fill in the details such as full name, office
						and select the shell for this user.  The second tab allows for password management choices such as password time
						out, how long after changing the password one can change the password, etc.  The final tab allows for changes to
						the groups this new user is a part of.
					</para>
				</sect1>
				<sect1>
					<title>Groups</title>
					<para>The groups section of KUser lists the different groups that are setup in the system.  To add a new group,
						select either the button or from the menu Group and then Add.  This brings up the section that allows for the 
						creation of new groups and also select the different users that are on the system.
					</para>
				</sect1>
				
			</chapter>
		</part>
		<part id="prt-internet" status="help">
			<title>Using the Internet</title>
			<partintro>
				<abstract>
					<para>This part explains how to connect to the Internet and use
						common applications.</para>
				</abstract>
			</partintro>
			<chapter status="help">
				<title>Setup an Internet Connection</title>
				<sect1>
					<title>Section Tittle</title>
					<para>...</para>
				</sect1>
			</chapter>
			<chapter id="web-browsing" status="help">
				<title>Web Browsing</title>
				<sect1>
					<title>Section Tittle</title>
					<para>...</para>
				</sect1>
			</chapter>
			<chapter status="help">
				<!-- Jonathan Jesse: Writing this Part -->
				<title>Instant Messaging</title>
				<sect1>
					<title>Using Koptoe</title>
					<!-- The semantics were not valid so I just moved stuff around in no logical order to the prose so that I could validate the xml -->
					<para>Koptoe is the default Instant Messaging application in KUbuntu.  Upon
						launching Koptoe for the first time a setup window appears that allows for
						configuration and addition of accounts.</para>
					<para>Kopote works like any other Instant Messaging progrm used.  Chatting with Kopote works the same as using
						one of the commercial programs (MSN Messenger, AIM, etc)</para>
					<sect2>
						<title> Managing Accounts </title>
						<para>The beauty of Kopote is that it can connect to almost any instant
							messaging service out there.  The list includes Jabber, ICQ, AIM, MSN 
							Messenger, IRC, Google Talk(through Jabber) and others.  First select new on the right hand side and
							then double-click on the service and fill out the needed information.
							Repeat for each service that one would like to setup. </para>
					</sect2>
					
					
				</sect1>
			</chapter>
			<chapter status="help">
				<title>RSS News Feeds</title>
				<sect1>
					<title>Section Tittle</title>
					<para>...</para>
				</sect1>
			</chapter>
			<chapter id="irc" status="help">
				<title>Internet Relay Chat</title>
				<sect1>
					<!-- Jonathan Jesse: Writing this Part -->
					<title>Konversation</title>
					<para>While one could connect to an IRC server through Kopote, the default program in Kubuntu is Konversatation
						Konversatation allows for each user to connect to different IRC servers and to manage multiple identies on those
						servers. </para>
					
					<sect2>
						<title>Configuring Konversatation </title>
						<para> Upon opening Konversatation for the first time the Server List opens up.  It is thru this section, one sets
							up the different servers and also the different channels to auto-join. </para>
						<para>
							To join the Kubuntu support channel, #kubuntu, the server name is FreeNode and the address is irc.freenode.net.
						</para></sect2>
					
				</sect1>
			</chapter>
			<chapter status="help">
				<title>Desktop Sharing</title>
				<sect1>
					<title>Section Tittle</title>
					<para>...</para>
				</sect1>
			</chapter>
		</part>
		<part id="prt-office" status="help">
			<title>Using Office Applications</title>
			<partintro>
				<abstract>
					<para>This part explain the use of various office productivity
						applications.</para>
				</abstract>
			</partintro>
			<chapter status="help">
				<title>Personal Information Management</title>
				<para>...</para>
				<sect1 status="help">
					<title>Working with Electronic Mail</title>
					<para>...</para>
				</sect1>
				<sect1 status="help">
					<title>Managing Contacts</title>
					<para>...</para>
				</sect1>
				<sect1 status="help">
					<title>Using the Calendar</title>
					<para>...</para>
				</sect1>
				<sect1 status="help">
					<title>Writing a Journal</title>
					<para>...</para>
				</sect1>
				<sect1 status="help">
					<title>Using Notes</title>
					<para>...</para>
				</sect1>
				<sect1 status="help">
					<title>Reading RSS Feeds</title>
					<para>...</para>
				</sect1>
				<sect1 status="help">
					<title>Synchronizing with other devices</title>
					<para>...</para>
				</sect1>
				<sect1 status="help">
					<title>Viewing a Summary</title>
					<para>...</para>
				</sect1>
			</chapter>
			<!-- OOo or KOffice -->
			<chapter status="help">
				<title>Chapter Title</title>
				<authorblurb>
					<para>Sean Wheller: There was talk about using KOffice instead
						of OOo.</para>
				</authorblurb>
				<sect1>
					<title>Section Tittle</title>
					<para>...</para>
				</sect1>
			</chapter>
			<!-- OOo or KOffice -->
			<chapter status="help">
				<title>Chapter Title</title>
				<authorblurb>
					<para>Sean Wheller: There was talk about using KOffice instead
						of OOo.</para>
				</authorblurb>
				<sect1>
					<title>Section Tittle</title>
					<para>...</para>
				</sect1>
			</chapter>
			<!-- OOo or KOffice -->
			<chapter status="help">
				<title>Chapter Title</title>
				<authorblurb>
					<para>Sean Wheller: There was talk about using KOffice instead
						of OOo.</para>
				</authorblurb>
				<sect1>
					<title>Section Tittle</title>
					<para>...</para>
				</sect1>
			</chapter>
			<!-- OOo or KOffice -->
			<chapter status="help">
				<title>Chapter Title</title>
				<authorblurb>
					<para>Sean Wheller: There was talk about using KOffice instead
						of OOo.</para>
				</authorblurb>
				<sect1>
					<title>Section Tittle</title>
					<para>...</para>
				</sect1>
			</chapter>
			<!-- OOo or KOffice -->
			<chapter status="help">
				<title>Chapter Title</title>
				<authorblurb>
					<para>Sean Wheller: There was talk about using KOffice instead
						of OOo.</para>
				</authorblurb>
				<sect1>
					<title>Section Tittle</title>
					<para>...</para>
				</sect1>
			</chapter>
		</part>
		<part id="prt-graphics" status="help">
			<title>Working with Graphics</title>
			<partintro>
				<abstract>
					<para>This chapter explains how to use the graphic viewing and
						drawing applications installed with Kubuntu. It also covers
						viewing of PDF documents and tasks such as scanning.</para>
				</abstract>
			</partintro>
			<chapter status="help">
				<title>Viewing Graphics</title>
				<sect1>
					<title>Section Tittle</title>
					<para>...</para>
				</sect1>
			</chapter>
			<chapter status="help">
				<title>Viewing PDF Files</title>
				<sect1>
					<title>Section Tittle</title>
					<para>...</para>
				</sect1>
			</chapter>
			<chapter status="help">
				<title>Drawing Graphics</title>
				<sect1>
					<title>Section Tittle</title>
					<para>...</para>
				</sect1>
			</chapter>
			<chapter status="help">
				<title>Scanning Graphics and Text</title>
				<sect1>
					<title>Section Tittle</title>
					<para>...</para>
				</sect1>
			</chapter>
			<chapter status="help">
				<title>Viewing Faxes</title>
				<sect1>
					<title>Section Tittle</title>
					<para>...</para>
				</sect1>
			</chapter>
			<chapter status="help">
				<title>Taking Screen Captures</title>
				<sect1>
					<title>Section Tittle</title>
					<para>...</para>
				</sect1>
			</chapter>
		</part>
		<part id="prt-multimedia" status="help">
			<title>Playing with Multimedia</title>
			<partintro>
				<abstract>
					<para>This part explains working how to play music and video and
						accomplish tasks such as burning CDs and DVDs.</para>
				</abstract>
			</partintro>
			<chapter status="help">
				<title>Playing Music</title>
				<sect1>
					<title>Section Tittle</title>
					<para>...</para>
				</sect1>
			</chapter>
			<chapter status="help">
				<title>Playing Video</title>
				<sect1>
					<title>Section Tittle</title>
					<para>...</para>
				</sect1>
			</chapter>
			<chapter status="help">
				<title>Burning CDs and DVDs</title>
				<sect1>
					<title>Section Tittle</title>
					<para>...</para>
				</sect1>
			</chapter>
			<chapter status="help">
				<title>Recording Sound</title>
				<sect1>
					<title>Section Tittle</title>
					<para>...</para>
				</sect1>
			</chapter>
			<chapter status="help">
				<title>Controlling Sound</title>
				<sect1>
					<title>Section Tittle</title>
					<para>...</para>
				</sect1>
			</chapter>
		</part>
		<part id="pt-expanding" status="writing">
			<title>Expanding Kubuntu</title>
			<!-- Sean Wheller: Writing this part -->
			<partintro>
				<abstract>
					<para>The Kubuntu Install CD contains many software programs,
						but what do you do when the program you want is not on the
						Kubuntu Install CD. In this part of the book you will learn
						how to expand the choice of software available for
						installation from a few hundred to a thousands. You will
						learn about software repositories and how to safely make
						your system aware of their existence. Once your system is
						expanded with these repositories you will learn how to
						install and update your system software using the package
						management tools already installed on your system.</para>
				</abstract>
			</partintro>
			<chapter status="review">
				<title>Software Sources</title>
				<para>There are thousands of software programs available for
					installation on Kubuntu. These programs are stored in software
					repositories and are made freely available for installation over
					the Internet. To organise the software, Kubuntu repositories are
					categorized into four groups.</para>
				<itemizedlist spacing="compact">
					<listitem>
						<para>Main</para>
					</listitem>
					<listitem>
						<para>Restricted</para>
					</listitem>
					<listitem>
						<para>Universe</para>
					</listitem>
					<listitem>
						<para>Multiverse</para>
					</listitem>
				</itemizedlist>
				<para>These four groups of software are also known as
					<quote>components.</quote> The rational used to determine
					which software goes into which category, or component, is based
					on two factors:</para>
				<itemizedlist>
					<listitem>
						<para>The level of support software development teams are
							prepared to provide for a program.</para>
					</listitem>
					<listitem>
						<para>The programs level of compliance to <ulink
										url="&ubuntu-philosophy;">Free Software
								Philosophy</ulink>.</para>
					</listitem>
				</itemizedlist>
				<para>The standard Kubuntu Install CD contains a subset of software
					available from the <quote>main</quote> and
					<quote>restricted</quote> categories. Once your system is made
					aware of the Internet-based locations for these repositories,
					many more software programs are made available for installation.
					Using the software package management tools already installed on
					your system, you can search for, install and update any piece of
					software directly over the network, without the need for
					physical installation media.</para>
				<sect1 id="sect-reposnature" status="review">
					<title>The Nature of Repositories</title>
					<para>Before making new software repositories available to your
						system you should understand the nature of those
						repositories. Understanding the nature of a software
						repository will help you to determine whether or not to make
						your system aware of it. The following sections describe
						each of the software repositories.</para>
					<sect2 status="review">
						<title>The <quote>Main</quote> Software Repository</title>
						<para>The <quote>Main</quote> repository contains
							applications that are free software. They can be freely
							redistributed and are fully supported by the Kubuntu
							team. This includes the most popular and most reliable
							open source applications available, much of which is
							installed by default when you install Kubuntu.</para>
						<para>Software in <quote>Main</quote> includes a
							hand-selected list of applications that the Kubuntu
							developers, community, and users feel are important and
							that the Kubuntu security and distribution team are
							willing to support. When you install software from the
							<quote>Main</quote> component you are assured that
							the software will come with security updates and
							technical support.</para>
						<para>The licences for software applications in
							<quote>Main</quote> must be free, but
							<quote>Main</quote> may also contain binary firmware and
							selected fonts that cannot be modified without
							permission from their authors. In all cases
							redistribution is unencumbered.</para>
					</sect2>
					<sect2 status="review">
						<title>The <quote>Restricted</quote> Software Repository</title>
						<para>The <quote>Restricted</quote> repository is reserved
							for software that is commonly used, and which is
							supported by the Kubuntu team even though it is not
							available under a completely free licence. Take note
							that it may not be possible to provide complete support
							for software in this category since the Kubuntu
							developers are unable to fix the software themselves,
							but can only forward problem reports to the actual
							authors.</para>
						<para>Some software from restricted is installed on the
							Kubuntu Install CD. These packages are clearly separated
							to ensure that it is easy to remove. In these cases the
							software is provided on the Install CD because it is
							deemed essential in order for Kubuntu to run on certain
							computers. An example of such a case would be the binary
							drivers that some video card vendors publish.</para>
					</sect2>
					<sect2 status="review">
						<title>The <quote>Universe</quote> Software Repository</title>
						<para>The <quote>Universe</quote> repository is a snapshot
							of the free, open source, and Linux world. In
							<quote>Universe</quote> you can find almost every
							piece of known open source software, and software
							available under a variety of less open licences, all
							built automatically from a variety of public sources.
							All of this software is compiled against the libraries
							and using the tools that form part of
							<quote>Main,</quote> so it should install and work well
							with the software in main, but it comes with no
							guarantee of security fixes and support. The
							<quote>Universe</quote> component includes thousands
							of pieces of software. Through <quote>Universe,</quote>
							users are able to have the diversity and flexibility
							offered by the vast open source world on top of a stable
							Kubuntu core.</para>
						<para>The packages in the <quote>Universe</quote> repository
							are looked after by a Community Team called the
							<quote>Masters of the Universe</quote> (MOTU).
							However, there is no support from the core development
							team on the software packages residing in
							<quote>Universe</quote> and no guarantee of regular
							security updates, although the MOTU team will often
							provide security updates.</para>
					</sect2>
					<sect2 status="review">
						<title>The <quote>Multiverse</quote> Software Repository</title>
						<para>The <quote>Multiverse</quote> repository contains
							software that is <quote>not free,</quote> which means
							the licensing requirements of this software do not meet
							the <ulink
								  url="http://www.ubuntulinux.org/ubuntu/licensing"
								  >Kubuntu <quote>Main</quote> component Licence
								Policy</ulink>.</para>
						<para>The onus is on you to verify your rights to use this
							software and comply with the licensing terms of the
							copyright holder.</para>
						<para>This software is not supported and usually cannot be
							fixed or updated by anyone else except those who created
							it. Use it at your own risk.</para>
					</sect2>
				</sect1>
				<sect1 status="review">
					<title>Adding Software Repositories</title>
					<para>The package management system used by Kubuntu is called
						<application>APT</application>, the Advanced Packaging
						Tool. This program provides a practical and efficient
						command line tool that enables installation and removal of
						software packages while automatically managing software
						dependencies and taking care of their configuration files
						while upgrading.</para>
					<para>As part of its configuration,
						<application>APT</application> uses a configuration file to
						lists the repositories from which packages can be obtained.
						This file is located in
						<filename>/etc/apt/sources.list</filename>. It can be viewed
						using a plain text editor like
						<application>Kate</application>, as follows.</para>
					<procedure>
						<step>
							<para>Open the <interface>Run command</interface> dialog (<keycombo>
									<keycap>Alt</keycap>
									<keycap>F2</keycap>
								</keycombo>)</para>
						</step>
						<step>
							<para>In the <guilabel>Command</guilabel> field enter
								the following command, then click
								<guibutton>Run</guibutton>.</para>
							<para>
								<command>kdesu kate /etc/apt/sources.list</command>
							</para>
						</step>
						<step>
							<para>When prompted, enter your password, then click
								<guibutton>OK</guibutton>. This will start
								<application>Kate</application> and open the
								file for viewing and editing.</para>
						</step>
					</procedure>
					<para>Repositories are defined using the syntax:</para>
					<para>
						<literallayout>
							deb http://host/ubuntu distribution section1 section2 section3
							deb-src http://host/ubuntu distribution section1 section2 section3
						</literallayout>
					</para>
					<para>A default <filename>sources.list</filename> file looks
						something like the following program listing. In this sample
						the syntax for defining Kubuntu repositories can be seen. A
						number of standard repositories are defined, some are
						commented out using the hash character (#). Removing the
						hash character makes the repository known to
						<application>APT</application>. In addition to these
						standard repositories, many other repositories can be added.
						We have commented the sample file to further explain each of
						the standard repositories and added one more to demonstrate
						that you can add new repositories. If you add repositories,
						just save the <filename>sources.list</filename> file then
						follow the instructions in <xref linkend="sect-update-lists"
										/>.</para>
					<programlisting>
						deb cdrom:[Kubuntu 5.04 _Hoary Hedgehog_ - Release i386 (20050407)]/ hoary main restricted<co id="deb-cdrom-co" linkends="deb-cdrom"/>
						
						deb http://za.archive.ubuntu.com/ubuntu hoary main restricted<co id="deb-main-co" linkends="deb-main"/>
						deb-src http://za.archive.ubuntu.com/ubuntu hoary main restricted<co id="deb-src-main-co" linkends="deb-src-main"/>
						
						## Major bug fix updates produced after the final release of the
						## distribution.
						deb http://za.archive.ubuntu.com/ubuntu hoary-updates main restricted<co id="deb-updates-main-co" linkends="deb-updates-main"/>
						deb-src http://za.archive.ubuntu.com/ubuntu hoary-updates main restricted
						
						## Uncomment the following two lines to add software from the &apos;universe&apos;
						## repository.
						## N.B. software from this repository is ENTIRELY UNSUPPORTED by the Ubuntu
						## team, and may not be under a free licence. Please satisfy yourself as to
						## your rights to use the software. Also, please note that software in
						## universe WILL NOT receive any review or updates from the Ubuntu security
						## team.
						#deb http://za.archive.ubuntu.com/ubuntu hoary universe<co id="deb-universe-co" linkends="deb-universe"/>
						#deb-src http://za.archive.ubuntu.com/ubuntu hoary universe
						
						deb http://security.ubuntu.com/ubuntu hoary-security main restricted<co id="deb-securitymain-co" linkends="deb-security-main"/>
						deb-src http://security.ubuntu.com/ubuntu hoary-security main restricted
						
						#deb http://security.ubuntu.com/ubuntu hoary-security universe<co id="deb-security-universe-co" linkends="deb-security-universe"/>
						#deb-src http://security.ubuntu.com/ubuntu hoary-security universe
						
						# Additional repositories
						# multiverse
						deb http://us.archive.ubuntu.com/ubuntu hoary multiverse<co id="deb-multiverse-co" linkends="deb-multiverse"/>
						deb-src http://us.archive.ubuntu.com/ubuntu hoary multiverse
						deb http://us.archive.ubuntu.com/ubuntu hoary-updates multiverse
						deb-src http://us.archive.ubuntu.com/ubuntu hoary-updates multiverse
					</programlisting>
					<calloutlist>
						<callout arearefs="deb-cdrom-co" id="deb-cdrom">
							<para>This line defines the primary source from which
								the installation was performed. In this case a
								CD-ROM was used for installation.</para>
						</callout>
						<callout arearefs="deb-main-co" id="deb-main">
							<para>This line defines where the primary binary
								software repository is located. In this case the
								binary packages (deb) are located on a server
								(http://za.archive.ubuntu.com/ubuntu). The name of
								the distribution in the example is
								&apos;hoary&apos; the
								&apos;main&apos; and
								&apos;restricted&apos; sections of this
								repository are selected. As described in <xref
										linkend="sect-reposnature"/> software from the
								&apos;main&apos; and
								&apos;restricted&apos; categories are
								included in the base installation. </para>
						</callout>
						<callout arearefs="deb-src-main-co" id="deb-src-main">
							<para>This line defines where the source packages
								(deb-src) for the primary binary software (deb) are
								located. For each binary location listed in the
								sources list a source location is usually also
								listed.</para>
						</callout>
						<callout arearefs="deb-updates-main-co"
							 id="deb-updates-main">
							<para>This line defines the location from which updates,
								to the packages installed from
								&apos;main&apos; and
								&apos;restricted&apos; categories, can be
								obtained.</para>
						</callout>
						<callout arearefs="deb-universe-co" id="deb-universe">
							<para>This line defines the location for the universe
								component of the repository as described in <xref
										linkend="sect-reposnature"/>. You can delete the
								# character at the start of the line to add the
								universe component category to list of software
								known to your system.</para>
						</callout>
						<callout arearefs="deb-securitymain-co"
							 id="deb-security-main">
							<para>This line defines the location from which security
								updates to packages installed from
								&apos;main&apos; and
								&apos;restricted&apos; categories, can be
								obtained.</para>
						</callout>
						<callout arearefs="deb-security-universe-co"
							 id="deb-security-universe">
							<para>Here is the location for security updates on
								software installed from
								&apos;universe.&apos;</para>
						</callout>
						<callout arearefs="deb-multiverse-co" id="deb-multiverse">
							<para>Here is an example of a repository that we have
								added to <filename>sources.list</filename>. These
								lines define the locations from which binary and src
								files can be obtained in the
								&apos;multiverse&apos; software component
								category. Then adds the lines to define the location
								from which updates to packages installed from
								&apos;multiverse&apos; will come
								from.</para>
						</callout>
					</calloutlist>
				</sect1>
				<sect1 id="sect-update-lists" status="writing">
					<title>Updating Software Lists</title>
					<para>...</para>
				</sect1>
			</chapter>
			<chapter status="writing">
				<title>Software Management</title>
				<authorblurb>
					<para>Sean Wheller: need to resolve which package management
						front-end will be used.</para>
				</authorblurb>
				<sect1 status="writing">
					<title>Installing Software</title>
					<para>...</para>
				</sect1>
				<sect1 status="writing">
					<title>Updating Software</title>
					<para>...</para>
				</sect1>
				<sect1 status="writing">
					<title>Removing Software</title>
					<para>...</para>
				</sect1>
			</chapter>
		</part> &cc-by-sa; &fdl; &glossary; <index/>
	</book>
