<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.3//EN" 
	"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.3/docbookx.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % globalent SYSTEM "../../../libs/global.ent">
%globalent;
<!ENTITY % cdo-C SYSTEM "../../../libs/cdo-C.ent">
%cdo-C;
<!ENTITY % xubuntu-ent SYSTEM "../../../xubuntu/libs/xubuntu.ent">
%xubuntu-ent;
<!ENTITY % xinclude SYSTEM "../../../libs/xinclude.mod">
%xinclude;
<!ENTITY language "en">
<!ENTITY ubuntu '<phrase>Ubuntu</phrase>'>
]>
<article id="desktop-effects" status="complete">
	<articleinfo>
		<title>Desktop Effects</title>
    	&legalnotice;
	</articleinfo>
	<sect1 id="compiz-intro" status="complete">
		<title>What are Desktop Effects?</title>
			<para>Ubuntu now includes the option to activate special desktop effects, which can make your desktop more fun and easier to use. These include:</para>
			<itemizedlist>
				<listitem>
					<para>Translucent windows</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>3D desktop capabilities</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>Shadow effects</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>Motion effects and animations</para>
				</listitem>
			</itemizedlist>
			<para>Desktop effects are optional, and it is not necessary to have them turned on. In addition, users of computers with certain graphics cards may find that desktop effects do not work well on their computer, or cause the computer to operate more slowly than it would with the effects turned off.</para>
	</sect1>
	<sect1 id="compiz-install" status="complete">
		<title>Activating Desktop Effects</title>
			<para>To activate desktop effects, open &desktop-effects; and click <guibutton>Enable Desktop Effects</guibutton>. Your screen may flicker briefly while the effects are being enabled. You will then be asked if you would like to keep the new settings.</para>
			<itemizedlist>
				<listitem>
				<para>If the desktop effects have been turned on correctly, press <guibutton>Keep settings</guibutton>.</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
				<para>If the desktop effects do not appear to be working properly (for example, if you cannot see the desktop or your screen looks strange), press <guibutton>Use previous settings</guibutton> to turn-off desktop effects. Alternatively, wait for 40 seconds without pressing any keys. After this period, desktop effects will be turned off automatically and your screen should return to normal.</para>
				</listitem>
			</itemizedlist>
	</sect1>
	<sect1 id="compiz-configure" status="complete">
		<title>Configuring Desktop Effects</title>
			<para>Press &desktop-effects; to change basic options relating to desktop effects.</para>
			<itemizedlist>
				<listitem>
				<para>Tick <guilabel>Windows Wobble when Moved</guilabel> if you would like windows to wobble when you drag them around the screen.</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
				<para>Tick <guilabel>Workspaces on a Cube</guilabel> if you would like to see a spinning cube effect when you change workspaces.</para>
				</listitem>
			</itemizedlist>
			<sect2 id="compiz-configure-advanced" status="complete">
				<title>Advanced configuration</title>
				<para>Further configuration of desktop effects is possible, although less straightforward.</para>
				<orderedlist>
					<listitem><para>Press <keycombo><keycap>Alt</keycap><keycap>F2</keycap></keycombo>, type <quote>gconf-editor</quote> and then press <guibutton>Run</guibutton> to start the <application>Configuration Editor</application>.</para></listitem>
					<listitem><para>Navigate to <guilabel>/apps/compiz</guilabel> and change the relevant settings.</para></listitem>
				</orderedlist>
				<para>It is possible to change many settings relating to desktop effects using the <application>Configuration Editor</application>. See the <ulink url='http://compiz.org/Gconf-Editor'>Compiz documentation website</ulink> for full instructions on how to do this.</para>
			</sect2>
			<sect2 id="compiz-configure-moreinfo" status="complete">
				<title>Further information</title>
				<itemizedlist>
				<listitem>
				<para>See the <ulink url='https://help.ubuntu.com/community/CompositeManager'>Ubuntu Community Support pages</ulink> for more information on desktop effects in Ubuntu. </para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
			<para>See the <ulink url='http://compiz.org/Documentation/Documentation'>Compiz documentation website</ulink> for more information on advanced configuration of desktop effects.</para>
				</listitem>
			</itemizedlist>
			</sect2>
	</sect1>
</article>
