<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.3//EN" 
	"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.3/docbookx.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % globalent SYSTEM "../../../libs/global.ent">
%globalent;
<!ENTITY % cdo-C SYSTEM "../../../libs/cdo-C.ent">
%cdo-C;
<!ENTITY % xubuntu-ent SYSTEM "../../../xubuntu/libs/xubuntu.ent">
%xubuntu-ent;
<!ENTITY % xinclude SYSTEM "../../../libs/xinclude.mod">
%xinclude;
<!ENTITY language "en">
]>
<chapter id="common-tasks-chap">
	<chapterinfo>
		<authorblurb>
			<para></para>
		</authorblurb>
	</chapterinfo>
	<title>Common Tasks</title>
	<sect1 id="config-desktop">
		<title>Desktop</title>
		<sect2 id="change-background">
			<title>Change the desktop background image</title>
			<para>
				If you want to set up a different background image, do:
			</para>
			<procedure>
				<step>
					<para>
						Launch &settings-manager;.
					</para>
				</step>
				<step>
					<para>
						Choose <option>Desktop</option>. 
					</para>
				</step>
				<step>
					<para>
						In the section <option>Image</option>, click on the file icon. This will bring up up an <emphasis>open file</emphasis> dialog, where you can choose an alternative image. 
					</para>
				</step>
			</procedure>
		</sect2>
		<sect2 id="minimized-application-icons">
			<title>Application icons on the Desktop (CDE style)</title>
			<para>
				To have minimized application icons instead of file/launcher icons displayed on your desktop, do this:
			</para>
			<procedure>
				<step>
					<para>
						Launch &settings-manager;.
					</para>
				</step>
				<step>
					<para>
						Choose <option>Desktop</option>, and then the <option>Behaviour</option> tab. 
					</para>
				</step>
				<step>
					<para>
						Change the <option>Desktop Icons</option> entry from <option>File/launcher Icons</option> to <option>Minimized Application Icons</option>.
					</para>
				</step>
			</procedure>
		</sect2>
		<sect2 id="panel-plugins">
			<title>Add Panel Plugins</title>
			<para>
				Here is a list of available Plugins for your Xfce Panel:
			</para>
			<note>
				<para>
					You will need super-user privileges to install the non-default plugins. See <xref linkend="root-and-sudo"/>.
				</para>
			</note>
			<variablelist>
				<varlistentry>
					<term id="xkb-plugin"><application>Xfce XKB Plugin</application></term>
					<listitem>
						<para>
							Displays your current keyboard layout and allows to easily switch between multiple layouts. (For configuring layouts, see <xref linkend="switch-keyboard-layout"/>). Installation: Installed by default.
						</para>
					</listitem>
				</varlistentry>
				<varlistentry>
					<term id="weather-plugin"><application>Xfce Weather Plugin</application></term>
					<listitem>
						<para>
							The weather plugin displays information about the current weather according your timezone and settings. It allows to search for weather location codes in the same plugin and displays weather status in little icons. Installation: Installed by default.
						</para>
					</listitem>
				</varlistentry>
				<varlistentry>
					<term id="wavelan-plugin"><application>Xfce Wavelan Plugin</application></term>
					<listitem>
						<para>
							The WaveLAN plugin displays information about a WaveLAN device. Installation: <screen>sudo apt-get install xfce4-wavelan-plugin</screen>
						</para>
					</listitem>
				</varlistentry>
				<varlistentry>
					<term id="verve-plugin"><application>Xfce Verve Plugin</application></term>
					<listitem>
						<para>
							The plugin displays a mini-command line on the Xfce panel. Installation: Installed by default.
						</para>
					</listitem>
				</varlistentry>
				<varlistentry>
					<term id="systemload-plugin"><application>Xfce Systemload Plugin</application></term>
					<listitem>
						<para>
							This plugin displays the current CPU load, the memory in use, and the swap space. Installation: Installed by default.
						</para>
					</listitem>
				</varlistentry>
				<varlistentry>
					<term id="screenshoter-plugin"><application>Xfce Screenshoter Plugin</application></term>
					<listitem>
						<para>
							Xfce4-screenshooter-plugin is a simple plugin to take screenshots
							of your desktop. Installation: Installed by default.
						</para>
					</listitem>
				</varlistentry>
				<varlistentry>
					<term id="quicklauncher-plugin"><application>Xfce Quicklauncher Plugin</application></term>
					<listitem>
						<para>
							Application launcher plugin for the Xfce panel. It supports multline launchers, zoom effect, and more. Installation: Installed by Default.
						</para>
					</listitem>
				</varlistentry>
				<varlistentry>
					<term id="netload-plugin"><application>Xfce Netload Plugin</application></term>
					<listitem>
						<para>
							This plugin displays the current load of the network interfaces of your choice. Installation: Installed by default.
						</para>
					</listitem>
				</varlistentry>
				<varlistentry>
					<term id="mount-plugin"><application>Xfce Mount Plugin</application></term>
					<listitem>
						<para>
							This plugin for Xfce displays a list of the various devices available, giving
							the opportunity to mount/umount them. Note that most removable media are mounted automatically by the File Manager in &xubuntu;. Installation: Installed by default.
						</para>
					</listitem>
				</varlistentry>
				<varlistentry>
					<term id="mailwatch-plugin"><application>Xfce Mailwatch Plugin</application></term>
					<listitem>
						<para>
							Mail checker panel plugin with support for local, POP3, IMAP, and Gmail accounts.  Installation: Installed by default.
						</para>
					</listitem>
				</varlistentry>
				<varlistentry>
					<term id="genmon-plugin"><application>Xfce Generic Monitor Plugin</application></term>
					<listitem>
						<para>
							This plugin repeatedly spawns the indicated script/program, displaying its output as a string in the panel. It is useful for periodic status monitoring. Installation: <screen>sudo apt-get install xfce4-genmon-plugin</screen>
						</para>
					</listitem>
				</varlistentry>
				<varlistentry>
					<term id="fsguard-plugin"><application>Xfce Filesystem Guard Plugin</application></term>
					<listitem>
						<para>
							The fsguard plugin checks free space on a chosen mountpoint frequently and displays an alarm if free space is less than given alarm limit. Installation: Installed by default.
						</para>
					</listitem>
				</varlistentry>
				<varlistentry>
					<term id="cpugraph-plugin"><application>Xfce CPU Graph Plugin</application></term>
					<listitem>
						<para>
							The CPU graph plugin displays a graph of your current system load. Installation: Installed by default.
						</para>
					</listitem>
				</varlistentry>
				<varlistentry>
					<term id="clipman-plugin"><application>Xfce Clipman Plugin</application></term>
					<listitem>
						<para>
							Store and recall sequential X clipboard selections in Xfce4 with this plugin. Installation: Installed by default.
						</para>
					</listitem>
				</varlistentry>
				<varlistentry>
					<term id="battery-plugin"><application>Xfce Battery Plugin</application></term>
					<listitem>
						<para>
							A battery monitor panel plugin for Xfce4 compatible with APM and ACPI. Installation: Installed by default.
						</para>
					</listitem>
				</varlistentry>
				<varlistentry>
					<term id="diskperf-plugin"><application>Disk Performace Plugin</application></term>
					<listitem>
						<para>
							The DiskPerf plugin displays disk/partition performance statistics. Installation: <screen>sudo apt-get install xfce4-diskperf-plugin</screen>
						</para>
					</listitem>
				</varlistentry>
				<varlistentry>
					<term id="messenger-plugin"><application>Dbus Messenger Plugin</application></term>
					<listitem>
						<para>
							Xfce4 Messenger Plugin for Xfce4 Panel is a plugin that listens for DBus
messages and displays received messages in the panel and/or a popup
window, and maintains a log of received messages. Installation: <screen>sudo apt-get install xfce4-messenger-plugin</screen>
						</para>
					</listitem>
				</varlistentry>
				<varlistentry>
					<term id="minicmd-plugin"><application>Mini Command Plugin</application></term>
					<listitem>
						<para>
							The plugin displays a mini-command line on the Xfce4 panel. Installation: <screen>sudo apt-get install xfce4-minicmd-plugin</screen>
						</para>
					</listitem>
				</varlistentry>
				<varlistentry>
					<term id="radio-plugin"><application>VLC Radio Plugin</application></term>
					<listitem>
						<para>
							This is an Xfce panel plugin which allows you to control your
video4linux radio device. You can turn your radio on/off, tune
it to some frequency, and manage station presets. Installation: <screen>sudo apt-get install xfce4-radio-plugin</screen>
						</para>
					</listitem>
				</varlistentry>
				<varlistentry>
					<term id="sensors-plugin"><application>Sensors Plugin</application></term>
					<listitem>
						<para>
							The sensors plugin reads your hardware sensor values and displays
then in your panel. Installation: <screen>sudo apt-get install xfce4-sensors-plugin</screen>
						</para>
					</listitem>
				</varlistentry>
				<varlistentry>
					<term id="xfapplet-plugin"><application>XfApplet Plugin</application></term>
					<listitem>
						<para>
							XfApplet is a plugin for the Xfce 4 panel. The plugin itself has no special
functionality. Its only purpose is to enable one to use Gnome applets inside
the Xfce 4 panel just as they are used inside the Gnome panel. Installation: <screen>sudo apt-get install xfce4-xfapplet-plugin</screen>
						</para>
					</listitem>
				</varlistentry>
				<varlistentry>
					<term id="xmms-plugin"><application>Xmms Plugin</application></term>
					<listitem>
						<para>
							The xmms plugin for the Xfce 4.4 panel is a simple tool which
allows you to control xmms. Installation: <screen>sudo apt-get install xfce4-xmms-plugin</screen>
						</para>
					</listitem>
				</varlistentry>
			</variablelist>
		</sect2>
		<sect2 id="window-manager-style">
			<title>Add new Window Manager Style</title>
			<para>
				When you download new window manager styles, they usually come in a .tar or .zip archive. Extract the contents, and do:
				<screen>sudo cp -r folder-with-new-theme /usr/share/themes/</screen>
			</para>
			<note>
				<para>
					You will need super-user privileges to do this. See <xref linkend="root-and-sudo"/>.
				</para>
				
			</note>

		</sect2>
	</sect1>
				
	<sect1 id="multimedia">
		<title>Get Multimedia support</title>
		<para>
			Please note that &xubuntu; comes with very limited multimedia support. The reason for this is that many popular multimedia formats are not free; they are protected by patent or license restrictions. To prevent problems, &xubuntu; ships without support for these formats. Please consider using and supporting open and free multimedia formats such as <ulink url=" http://www.vorbis.com/">Ogg Vorbis</ulink> (Audio) and <ulink url="http://theora.org/">Ogg Theora</ulink> (Video).
		</para>
		<para>
			If, however, you still want to use restricted multimedia formats, you will need to enable the <emphasis>Universe</emphasis> and <emphasis>Multiverse</emphasis> repositories (see <xref linkend="extra-repositories"/>). You will want to install at least the following packages: 
			<screen>
libxine-extracodecs 
ffmpeg 
lame 
faad 
sox 
mjpegtools 
libxine-main1
gxineplugin</screen>
			
			With these packages installed, you should be able to play many multimedia formats. Please refer to <ulink url="https://wiki.ubuntu.com/RestrictedFormats"/> for detailed information on getting even more formats to play. 
		</para>
	</sect1>
	<sect1 id="switch-keyboard-layout">
		<title>Switching the keyboard layout</title>
		<para>
			There is currently no graphical tool to switch the keyboard layout in &xubuntu;. To do this, you will need to edit the file <emphasis>/etc/X11/xorg.conf</emphasis>.
		</para>
		<warning>
			<para>
				Be warned that this is an important file for the system and you should be careful with it. You will need administrative privileges to edit it (Cf. <xref linkend="root-and-sudo"/>). It is recommended to make a backup of this file before editing it: <screen>sudo cp /etc/X11/xorg.conf /etc/X11/xorg.conf.BACKUP</screen>
			</para>
		</warning>
		<para>
			Find the section that looks like this:
			<screen>
				Section "InputDevice"
				Identifier    "Generic Keyboard"
				Driver        "keyboard"
				Option        "CoreKeyboard"
				Option        "XkbRules"    "xorg"
				Option        "XkbModel"    "pc104"
				Option        "XkbLayout"   "us"
				EndSection</screen>
			Change &quot;us&quot; to whatever language code you prefer. Next, type this from a terminal:
			<screen>setxkbmap &lt;language_code&gt;</screen> That's it.
		</para>
		<tip>
			<para>
				If you enter more than one language code, e.g. "us,de" for US-American and German layout, you can easily switch between these two with the the <link linkend="xkb-plugin">XKB Layout Switcher Plugin</link> panel plugin.
			</para>
		</tip>
	</sect1>
	<sect1 id="printer-configuration">
		<title>Printer configuration</title>
		<para>
			Getting your printer to work on &xubuntu; may require some work. Most likely, your printer will be auto-detected by &xubuntu;. However, you will still need to configure it by hand. You can either do this in your browser, or in a terminal:
		</para>
		<note>
			<para>
				You will need super-user privileges to configure a printer. See <xref linkend="root-and-sudo"/>.
			</para>
		</note>
		<sect2 id="cups-web-admin">
			<title>Printer Configuration with the Browser</title>
			<para>
				First, you will need to enable the web administration interface of CUPS (Common UNIX Printing System).
			</para>
			<procedure>
				<step>
					<para>
						Launch &users-groups; and hit <guibutton>Manage Groups</guibutton>.
					</para>
				</step>
				<step>
					<para>
						Click on <emphasis>lpadmin</emphasis> and then <guilabel>Properties</guilabel>.
					</para>
				</step>
				<step>
					<para>
						Check your username.
					</para>
				</step>
				<step>
					<para>
						Restart CUPS with this command:
						<screen>
$sudo /etc/init.d/cupsys restart</screen>
					</para>
				</step>
			</procedure>
			<para>
				Next, visit the web interface by entering <emphasis>http://localhost:631/admin</emphasis> in your browser's location bar. Once there, you will be able to see, install, and configure the detected printers on your system. 
			</para>
		</sect2>
		<sect2 id="cups-terminal">
			<title>Printer Configuration with the Terminal (Advanced Users)</title>
			<para>
				To manage printers in the terminal, CUPS provides the commands <emphasis>lpadmin, lpinfo, lpoptions</emphasis>. Please refer to the CUPS online manual <ulink url="http://www.cups.org/doc-1.1/sam.html#4_3">Managing Printers from the Command-Line</ulink> for detailed information on how to use these commands. 
			</para>
			<para>
				To check if your printer has been detected correctly, do:
				<screen>
lpinfo -v</screen>
			</para>
			<para>
				To add a printer, do something similar to:
				<screen>
lpadmin -p DeskJet -E -v parallel:/dev/lp1 -m deskjet.ppd</screen>
			</para>
			<note>
				<para>
					If you experience problems getting your printer to work, you may consider installing <application>gnome-cups-manager</application>. It is available by the usual manner described in <xref linkend="add-applications"/> and will offer a nice graphical tool to set up your printer. WARNING: installing <application>gnome-cups-manager</application> will bring in many dependencies to the Gnome desktop, thus increasing the installed size of your system. It is therefore not recommended to install <application>gnome-cups-manager</application> on &xubuntu;. In some cases, however, it may be worth the trade-off to get your printer working.
				</para>
			</note>
	</sect2>
	</sect1>
	<sect1 id="users-and-groups">
		<title>Managing Users and Groups</title>
		<para>
			To add users or groups to your system, you can use the <application>Users And Groups</application> application located in &users-groups;.
		</para>
		<note>
			<para>
				You will need super-user privileges to launch the <application>Users and Groups</application> tool. See <xref linkend="root-and-sudo"/>.
			</para>
		</note>
		<para>
			To add a new user, click on <guilabel>Add user</guilabel>, fill-in the data fields, then click <guilabel>OK</guilabel>.  To edit the properties of each user, click the <guilabel>Properties</guilabel> button located in the main window.
		</para>
		<para>
			To add a new group, hit the <guilabel>Manage Groups</guilabel> button and click <guilabel>Add group</guilabel>. Choose a name for the new group and, if you want, change the value for the <guilabel>Group ID</guilabel> from the default. If you try to allocate a <guilabel>Group ID</guilabel> that is in use, the system will warn you.
		</para>
		<para>
			You can add users to the newly created group by checking the user's name from the menu. Removing a user is as simple as adding one: select the group you want, hit <guilabel>Properties</guilabel>, and uncheck the user.
		</para>
		<para>
			To remove a user or group from the system, select the user or group you want to delete and click <guilabel>Delete</guilabel>.
		</para>
	</sect1>
	<sect1 id="networking">
		<title>Networking</title>
		<sect2 id="configure-networking">
			<title>Configure Networking</title>
			<para>
				&xubuntu; comes with a graphical networking utility. Launch it with &networking;. 
			</para>
			<para>
				This tool will allow you to configure all aspects of your network connection - setting up DHCP, static IP addresses, configuring modem dialup, and more. It will also allow you to set up different profiles for use with a laptop. This is very convenient if you need location-dependent networking setups.
			</para>
			<note>
				<para>
					You will need super-user privileges to run the Networking utility. See <xref linkend="root-and-sudo"/>.
				</para>
				
			</note>
		</sect2>
		<sect2 id="connect-to-internet">
			<title>Connect to the Internet</title>
			<para>
				This task is usually very simple.  However, it requires a minimum of involvement on your part. Of course, you will need to have subscribed to an <emphasis>Internet Service Provider</emphasis>, and your Internet connection must be installed and functional.
			</para>
			<para>
				There are several ways to connect to the Internet.  Depending on what type of connection you have, you could have broadband (e.g. ADSL), dialup (e.g. a 56 kbit/s modem) or access to Internet directly, via your Local Area Network for instance.
			</para>
			<para>
				Go to the following section corresponding to your type of connection. 
			</para>
			<sect3>
				<title>Broadband</title>
				<para>
					If you have an ADSL or cable modem, there are several possibilities, depending on the type of modem.
				</para>
				<sect4>
					<title>Ethernet Modem (pppoe)</title>
					<para>
						If your modem connects to your PC with an ethernet network cable you probably want to set up a <emphasis>pppoe connection</emphasis>. However, nowadays many modems also integrate a router.  In this case you should follow the instructions provided by the manufacturer.  You may find extra help in the Local Area Network section below (if you configure the device via a web interface, it probably has an integrated router).
					</para>
					<sect5>
						<title>ADSLPPPoE</title>
						<para>
							Prerequisites are:
							<itemizedlist>
								<listitem>
									<para>
										A DSL account with an Internet Service Provider (ISP).
									</para>
								</listitem>
								<listitem>
									<para>
										Username and password for that account.
									</para>
								</listitem>
								<listitem>
									<para>
										A DSL modem to which you connect using an Ethernet network card.
									</para>
								</listitem>
								<listitem>
									<para>
										Your Ubuntu machine with its Ethernet card configured for DHCP.
									</para>
								</listitem>
								<listitem>
									<para>
										Knowledge of installing packages with synaptic.
									</para>
								</listitem>
							</itemizedlist>
						</para>
						<tip>
							<para>
								Make sure that your ADSL connection has been activated by your ISP before starting this procedure. Generally there is a "DSL" light on your modem that is lit, indicating whether your connection is activated.
							</para>
						</tip>
						<para>
							Ubuntu by default installs the "pppoeconf" package. If you are not sure if you have it you can check by typing this in a terminal window: 
							<screen>dpkg -s pppoeconf</screen>
							If it is not installed yet, do it yourself, following the hints in <xref linkend="add-applications"/>.
						</para>
						<para>
							Once you are sure that you have the package installed, it's time to configure your connection. Type in a terminal:
							<screen>sudo pppoeconf</screen>
							A text-based installer will take you through the setup. To manually connect using your configured setup, type:
							<screen>pon dsl-provider</screen>
						</para>
					</sect5>
				</sect4>
				<sect4>
					<title>USB modem</title>
					<para>
						This is probably the most demanding type of modem to set up.  USB is far from the ideal method for network access. If you have a modem that can connect both via USB and ethernet it will be best to use the ethernet connection.
					</para>
					<para>
						If you have a USB modem, you should refer to <ulink url="https://wiki.ubuntu.com/UsbAdslModem"/>
					</para>
					<para>
						More support for installing a USB modem can be found at:
						<itemizedlist>
							<listitem>
								<para>
									<ulink url="http://ubuntuforums.org/showthread.php?p=189972#post189972"/>
								</para>
							</listitem>
							<listitem>
								<para>
									<ulink url="http://forum.eagle-usb.org/"/>
								</para>
							</listitem>
							<listitem>
								<para>
									<ulink url="http://eciadsl.flashtux.org/"/>
								</para>
							</listitem>
						</itemizedlist>
					</para>
				</sect4>
			</sect3>
			<sect3>
				<title>Dialup</title>
				<para>
					If you have a dialup connection, a 56 kbit/s or slower modem, you should refer to <ulink url="https://wiki.ubuntu.com/DialupModemHowto"/>.
				</para>
			</sect3>
			<sect3>
				<title>Local Area Network</title>
				<para>
					If you connect to the Internet via a Local Area Network (ethernet or wireless for example), the configuration depends entirely on your network.
				</para>
				<para>
					Configuration information should be provided by your network administrator.
				</para>
				<para>
					If you connect via a router on a home network, you should read the router's documentation.
				</para>
				<para>
					You may have to configure the interface through which you connect to use DHCP (dynamic configuration, usually the default) or specify an IP address, default gateway and DNS server. 
				</para>
			</sect3>
		</sect2>
		<sect2 id="change-computer-name">
			<title>Change the Computer's Name</title>
			<note>
				<para>
					You will need super-user privileges for this task. See <xref linkend="root-and-sudo"/>.
				</para>
			</note>
			<procedure>
				<step>
					<para>
						&networking;
					</para>
				</step>
				<step>
					<para>Select the <guibutton>General</guibutton> tab.
						Enter the name of the computer in the
						<guilabel>Hostname</guilabel> field.</para>
				</step>
				<step>
					<para>Click <guibutton>OK</guibutton>, close all
						open applications and log out and back in for the changes to take effect.</para>
				</step>
			</procedure>
		</sect2>
     </sect1>
	<sect1 id="system-tasks">
		<title>System Tasks</title>
<!--
		<sect2 id="listpartitiontables">
			<title>Check disk space usage and view the partition table</title>
			<note>
				<para>
					You will need super-user privileges for this task. See <xref linkend="root-and-sudo"/>.
				</para>
			</note>
			<procedure>
				<step>
					<para>Launch &disks; </para>
				</step>
				<step>
					<para>Select <guibutton>Hard Disk</guibutton>, then the <guibutton>Partitions</guibutton> tab</para>
				</step>
				<step>
					<para>Each partition will be listed under <guilabel>Partition List</guilabel>, with disk space and mount point.</para>
				</step>
			</procedure>
		</sect2>
-->
		<sect2>
			<title>List devices</title>
			<procedure>
				<step>
					<para>To list mounted devices, run the following command in a terminal:</para>
					<screen>mount</screen>
					<para>The listing shows the device (such as a hard disk partition), the mount point (where you access the files), the filesystem type, and the mount options.</para>
					<para>This example shows the hda2 hard disk partition mounted as '/', with the filesystem type ext3. The partition is mounted with two options: one to allow the device to be read from and written to and the other to remount the device as read-only in the event of any errors.</para>
					<screen>/dev/hda2 on / type ext3 (rw,errors=remount-ro)</screen>				
				</step>
				<step>
					<para>To list PCI devices:</para>
					<screen>lspci</screen>
				</step>
				<step>
					<para>To list USB devices:</para>
					<screen>lsusb</screen>
				</step>
			</procedure>
		</sect2>
		
		<sect2>
			<title>Mount/unmount CD/DVD-ROMs manually</title>
			<note>
				<para>
					You will need super-user privileges for this task. See <xref linkend="root-and-sudo"/>.
				</para>
			</note>
			<procedure>
				<step>
					<para>Assuming that <filename class="devicefile">/media/cdrom0/</filename> is the mount point of your CD/DVD-ROM device</para>
				</step>
				<step>
					<para>To mount a CD/DVD-ROM:</para>
					<para>
						<screen>
sudo mount /media/cdrom0/ -o unhide</screen>
					</para>
				</step>
				<step>
					<para>To unmount CD/DVD-ROM:</para>
					<para>
						<screen>
sudo umount /media/cdrom0/</screen>
					</para>
				</step>
			</procedure>
		</sect2>
	</sect1>	
	<sect1 id="hardware">
		<title>Setting up Hardware</title>
		<para>
		</para>
		<sect2 id="wireless-cards">
			<title>Set up Wireless Cards</title>
			<para>Many wireless cards are automatically detected by Ubuntu during installation. A complete listing of wireless cards which are known to work with Ubuntu can be found on <ulink url="https://wiki.ubuntu.com/HardwareSupportComponentsWirelessNetworkCards">the Ubuntu Wiki</ulink>. Please add your wireless card to the list if it works with Ubuntu and is not already listed.</para> 
			<para>Some cards may not work automatically with Ubuntu. If this is the case, please look at the <ulink url="https://wiki.ubuntu.com/WirelessTroubleshootingGuide">Wireless Troubleshooting Guide</ulink>, which is an excellent resource for troubleshooting wireless cards, on the Ubuntu Wiki.
			</para>
			<para>All information regarding wireless networking on Ubuntu is collected at <ulink url="https://wiki.ubuntu.com/WifiDocs">Wireless Networking Central</ulink> on the Ubuntu Wiki.
			</para>
		</sect2> 
		<sect2 id="modems">
			<title>Set up Modems</title>
			<sect3 id="winmodems">		
				<title>Winmodems</title>
				<para>Most winmodems are not supported by Ubuntu, but drivers can be found that will enable the use of such modems. First you need to identify what chipset your winmodem is using:</para>
				<para>
					<screen>
wget -c <ulink url="&scanmodem-url;">&scanmodem-url;</ulink> 
gunzip -c &scanmodem-gz; &gt; scanModem 
chmod +x scanModem
sudo ./scanModem 
mousepad Modem/ModemData.txt</screen>
				</para>
				<para>Read this file; it should list what modem chipset you have. Once you are aware of the chipset you have, see <ulink url="&linmodem;">&linmodem;</ulink> and follow the directions for your modem. More infomation can be found at <ulink url="https://wiki.ubuntu.com/SettingUpModems">SettingUpModems</ulink> on the Ubuntu Wiki.</para>
			</sect3>
			<sect3 id="adsl">
				<title>ADSL Modems</title>
				<para>All PPPOE and router-style ADSL modems (that use ethernet for the connections) are supported by Ubuntu, and some USB ADSL modems are supported too. For router-style ADSL modems, just connect it, configure the modem per your ISP's instructions, and configure networking in Ubuntu. For information on PPPOE modems see <ulink url="https://wiki.ubuntu.com/ADSLPPPoE">this guide</ulink> on the Ubuntu Wiki.</para>
			</sect3>
		</sect2>
	</sect1> 

 </chapter>
