<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.3//EN" 
	"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.3/docbookx.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % globalent SYSTEM "../../../libs/global.ent">
%globalent;
<!ENTITY % cdo-C SYSTEM "../../../libs/cdo-C.ent">
%cdo-C;
<!ENTITY % xubuntu-ent SYSTEM "../../../xubuntu/libs/xubuntu.ent">
%xubuntu-ent;
<!ENTITY % xinclude SYSTEM "../../../libs/xinclude.mod">
%xinclude;
<!ENTITY language "en">
]>
<chapter id="guided-tour-chap">
	<chapterinfo>
		<authorblurb>
			<para></para>
		</authorblurb>
	</chapterinfo>
	<title id="guided-tour">Guided Tour</title>
	<para>
		Welcome to the Guided Tour around the &xubuntu; Desktop. This guide will take you on a trip around your new desktop, show you the most important places, introduce you to some of the included programs, and explain how to accomplish basic tasks. It is recommended to have an actual &xubuntu; system ready and to try out the stuff described while reading this document.
	</para>
	<para>
		The readers are generally assumed to have access to the Internet, since this guide will often just provide links to wiki pages and to other documentation on the Web. 
	</para>
	<sect1 id="desktop">
		<title>Desktop</title>
		<para>
			When your computer has finished booting up, and after entering your login data, you will arrive at the Xubuntu desktop. It comes with many features that make your life easy, and it is well worth the time to get to know your way around it.
		</para>
		<para>
			As you can see, your desktop has two panels: one on top, and one on the bottom of the screen. 
		</para>
		<sect2>
			<title>Top Panel</title>
			<para>
				The top panel is mainly used for starting applications and navigating to different places on your computer. It also comes with a logout button, system tray and a clock.
			</para>
			<para>
				Clicking on <guimenuitem>Applications</guimenuitem> will open the system menu, offering you many choices of applications to start. Note that you can also access your Settings, Help, and a logout dialog from the <guimenuitem>Applications</guimenuitem> menu.
			</para>
			<para>
				Clicking on the <emphasis>logout button</emphasis> (looks like a door with a red arrow) will bring up a menu with choices for logging out, shutting down, rebooting, and, depending on your hardware, suspending or hibernating your computer.
			</para>
			<note>
				<para>
					Use the checkbox <option>Save session for future logins</option> to have all the currently running programs auto-started the next time you log in.
				</para>
			</note>
			<para>
				Next to the clock is a small area called the <emphasis>system tray</emphasis>. Some programs will show up as a small icon in the system tray while they are running in the background. The system tray is also used for informing you about updates to your system. If such an update becomes available, you will see a small speech bubble pop up giving you the necessary information to keep your system up to date and secure.
			</para>
			<para>
				Besides that, the top panel is quite empty. It has lots of additional room to add items besides the browser launcher. You may want to go ahead and <emphasis>add some custom items</emphasis> to it. Right-click on the panel, and choose <option>Add New Item</option>. Choose one of the many panel plugins available, or create a custom program launcher. The item will be permanently attached to your panel. Anything you add here will be reachable with just a single click, directly from your panel.
			</para>
		</sect2>
		<sect2>
			<title>Bottom Panel</title>
			<para>
				This panel contains a show-desktop button, a tasklist, and a pager.
			</para>
			<para>
				The <emphasis>show-desktop button</emphasis> will minimize all applications to clear your view onto the desktop. This is very helpful in case you are trying to access icons on the desktop and need to get all the windows out of the way.
			</para>
			<para>
				The <emphasis>taskbar</emphasis> will have an entry for every window that is currently open. Use it to quickly change between running applications. 
			</para>
			<para>
				The <emphasis>pager</emphasis> allows you to navigate between the different desks you use. Note that small icons on the pager give an indication about the current windows on the different desks.
			</para>
		</sect2>
		<sect2>
			<title>Desktop</title>
			<para>
				At first, the desktop will show you icons for your home directory, the filesystem, and the trash bin. 
			</para>
			<tip>
				<para>
					You may also configure the desktop to show minimized application icons instead of folders/file launchers. Refer to <xref linkend="minimized-application-icons"/>.
				</para>
			</tip>
			<para>
				To change the desktop background image, launch &settings-manager;, and choose <option>Desktop</option>. In the lower part, where it says <option>Image</option>, click on the <option>Browse</option> icon and choose a different picture. 
			</para>
			<para>
				The desktop offers a bunch of features that are real time-savers in everyday tasks:
				<itemizedlist>
					<listitem>
						<para>
							Right-clicking it will open the system menu just as clicking on <guimenuitem>Applications</guimenuitem> does. 
						</para>
					</listitem>
					<listitem>
						<para>
							Using the scroll wheel on your mouse (if it has one) will allow you to switch between the different desks. This does the same thing as clicking on the pager in the lower panel, but is usually quicker, since you (probably) do not have to move the mouse. 
					</para>
					</listitem>
					<listitem>
						<para>
							Pressing <keycombo><keycap>Alt</keycap><keycap>Tab</keycap></keycombo> will allow you to rotate between the currently open windows. This allows for lightning-fast switching between applications without taking your hands off the keyboard.
					</para>
					</listitem>
				</itemizedlist>
			</para>
		</sect2>
	</sect1>
	<sect1 id="browse-files">
		<title>Browse the Files on your Computer</title>
		<para>
			&xubuntu; comes with &xfce;'s brand new file manager called <application>Thunar</application>. For simplicity's sake, we will just refer to it as the <application>File Manager</application>. Load it by clicking &thunar;.
		</para>
		<mediaobject>
			<imageobject>
				<imagedata fileref="../images/C/thunar.png" format="PNG"  width="100%" scalefit="1" />
			</imageobject>
		</mediaobject>
		<sect2 id="navigation">
			<title>Navigation</title>
			<para>
				The <application>File Manager</application>'s default view consists of a shortcut pane on the left side, the main area on the right, and a pathbar above the main area. 
			</para>
			<para>
				The <emphasis>shortcut pane</emphasis> provides shortcuts to different folders on your system. The first shortcut will lead to your home directory, the directory where you store all your personal data, and will therefore have the name of the current user. That directory will probably appear empty. The second shortcut will take you to the root of your filesystem - you may want to explore it a bit, even though it will be confusing to you if you are new to Linux. Just click on the different folders and see what's inside. When you're done, return to your home directory by clicking on the top shortcut.
				<tip>
					<para>
						Add your own shortcuts by simply dragging folders to the shortcut pane. This will allow you to access important folders instantly!
					</para>
				</tip>
			</para>
			<para>
				The <emphasis>main area</emphasis> will always display the contents of the current folder. Double-click on folders to enter them, and right-click on files/folders to get a pop-up window offering you some choices of what to do with it. Select multiple files by dragging a rectangle over them with the mouse. Alternatively, select one file, hold down the <emphasis>Shift</emphasis> key, and increase/decrease the selection using the arrows.
			</para>
			<para>
				The <emphasis>pathbar</emphasis> will always show you the path you took to get to the place you are currently at. You can click on any pathbar icon to change to the directory it represents. Note that right-clicking on pathbar icons will also bring up a pop-up window with some options.
			</para>
		</sect2>
		<sect2 id="creating-and-deleting-files">
			<title>Creating and Deleting Files</title>
			<para>
				To create a new document, right-click on some empty space in your home directory and select <menuchoice><guimenu>Create New Document</guimenu><guimenuitem>Empty File</guimenuitem></menuchoice> from the pop-up menu. The <application>File Manager</application> will prompt you for a name - just go with the suggested name for now. After this, you will see the new file in your home directory. 
			</para>
			<para>
				Right-click on it to have a menu pop up - choose <option>Properties</option>. This will show you some details about the file:
				<mediaobject>
					<imageobject>
						<imagedata fileref="../images/C/file-properties.png" format="PNG"/>
					</imageobject>
				</mediaobject>
				
			</para>
			<para>
				Right-click on the file once more, and choose <option>Delete</option> to remove it. The file will be put into the trash bin.
			</para>
			<note>
				<para>
					If you ever want to undo the deleting of a file, open the trash bin, and drag or copy/paste the file out of it.
				</para>
			</note>
			<para>
				To create a new folder, right-click on the empty space, and choose <option>Create Folder...</option>. You will be asked for a name. Type something and hit Enter. You will see this new folder in your home directory. Double click on it to enter it. 
			</para>

			<para>
				To rename or remove the folder, right-click on it and choose the appropriate option from the pop-up menu.
			</para>
		</sect2>
		<sect2 id="copying-and-moving-files">
			<title>Copying and Moving Files</title>
			<para>
				To copy and move files on your computer, just click and drag files and folders to other folders. As a default, the files will always be copied. If you want them to be moved instead, right-click and drag files to folder: This will offer you some options instead of just copying.
			</para>
		</sect2>
		<sect2 id="removable-devices">
			<title>Removable Devices</title>
				<para>
					When inserting CDs, floppys, USB sticks or other removable media into your computer, or hooking up removable devices like a musicplayer, it will be set up automatically by your system. After inserting a CD into your CD Drive, you will see a new shortcut in the left pane of the <application>File Manager</application>, representing the CD. Clicking on it will open the CD in the main area, just like clicking on a regular folder. To remove the CD, right-click on the shortcut, and choose <option>eject</option>. The same applies for any other removable media.
				</para>
				<note>
					<para>
						Please note that pressing the <option>eject</option> button on your CD drive may not work. This may be surprising to some users, but it is in fact the expected behaviour. Before the CD can be ejected, it needs to be properly &quot;released&quot; (unmounted) by the system. To remove a CD, always right-click on its shortcut and choose <option>Eject Volume</option>.
					</para>
				</note>
		</sect2>
		<sect2 id="customizing-file-manager">
			<title>Customizing the File Manager</title>
			<para>
				There are many ways to customize the <application>File Manager</application>. In case you do not like the way the icons are displayed, choose <menuchoice><guimenu>View</guimenu><guimenuitem>View as Detailed List</guimenuitem></menuchoice> to have the contents of the current directory displayed as a list. 
			</para>
			<para>
				You can have the <application>File Manager</application> display a location bar instead of the pathbar by selecting <menuchoice><guimenu>View</guimenu><guimenuitem>Location Selector</guimenuitem><guimenuitem>Toolbar Style</guimenuitem></menuchoice>.
			</para>
			<para>
				In case you prefer a tree view in the left pane, choose <menuchoice><guimenu>View</guimenu><guimenuitem>Side Pane</guimenuitem><guimenuitem>Tree</guimenuitem></menuchoice>.
			</para>
		</sect2>
	</sect1>
	<sect1 id="surf-internet">
		<title>Surfing the Internet</title>
		<para>
			Before surfing the Internet, you need to make sure you have a working Internet connection. In case you are not connected yet, consult <xref linkend="connect-to-internet"/>.
		</para>
		<para>
			&xubuntu; comes with the popular <application>Firefox</application> Web browser preinstalled. Firefox is well known for its outstanding security, standards compliance, extensibility, usability, and speed. Launch it from &firefox;.
		</para>
		<mediaobject>
			<imageobject>
				<imagedata fileref="../images/C/firefox.png" format="PNG" width="100%" scalefit="1" />
			</imageobject>
		</mediaobject>
		<tip>
			<para>
				If you are new to Firefox, see <ulink url="http://opensourcearticles.com/articles/firefox_15/english/part_01">An introduction to Firefox</ulink>. More help is available from <ulink url="http://www.mozilla.org/support/firefox/"/>.
			</para>
		</tip>
	</sect1>
	<sect1 id="write-emails">
		<title>Writing Emails</title>
		<para>
			<application>Thunderbird</application> is the default mail client of &xubuntu;. It comes with all desired features, including junk filtering, thread display, POP/IMAP support, security features, themes, an extension mechanism, and more. Before you start, make sure you have a working Internet connection (See <xref linkend="connect-to-internet"/>).
		</para>
		<para>
			Launch <application>Thunderbird</application> from &thunderbird;.
		</para>
		<para>After this, the Thunderbird Account Wizard will guide you through the process of entering your account data.</para>
		<mediaobject>
			<imageobject>
				<imagedata fileref="../images/C/thunderbird.png" format="PNG" width="100%" scalefit="1" />
			</imageobject>
		</mediaobject>
		<tip>
			<para>
				If you are new to Thunderbird, see <ulink url="http://opensourcearticles.com/articles/thunderbird_15/english/part_01">An introduction to Thunderbird</ulink>. More help is available from <ulink url="http://www.mozilla.org/support/thunderbird/"/>.
			</para>
		</tip>
	</sect1>
	<sect1 id="im-chat">
		<title>Instant Messaging / Chatting</title>
		<para>
			Use <application>Gaim</application> for chatting and instant messaging. Launch it from &gaim;. Before you start, make sure you have a working Internet connection (See <xref linkend="connect-to-internet"/>).
		</para>
		<tip>
			<para>
				Please consult the <ulink url="http://gaim.sourceforge.net/documentation.php">Gaim Online Documentation</ulink> Web page for further information.
			</para>
		</tip>
	</sect1>
	<sect1 id="write-text-documents">
		<title>Writing Text Documents</title>
		<sect2 id="mousepad">
			<title>Editing Textfiles with Mousepad</title>
			<para>
				Launch &mousepad;. This will open up <application>Mousepad</application> - a simple, fast text editor. This is what it looks like:
				<mediaobject>
					<imageobject>
						<imagedata fileref="../images/C/mousepad.png" format="PNG"/>
					</imageobject>
				</mediaobject>
				Use <application>Mousepad</application> for viewing and editing simple text files, such as configuration or log files. <application>Mousepad</application> is, however, not suited for creating formatted text files. For this, see the following section.
			</para>
		</sect2>
		<sect2 id="abiword">
			<title>Word Processing with Abiword</title>
			<para>
				For regular Word Processing, AbiWord is the program to use. AbiWord is a state of the art word processor that reads and writes both OpenDocument (OpenOffice) and Microsoft Word documents and is very fast. It features everything you need for standard word processing: tables, lists, images, footnotes, styles, spellchecking, and more. It also has good internationalization and is easy to use. Start it with &abiword;
			</para>
			<tip>
				<para>
					Please consult the <ulink url="http://www.abisource.com/support/manual/">AbiWord Manual</ulink> on the project's website for detailed information on how to use AbiWord.
				</para>
			</tip>
			<mediaobject>
				<imageobject>
					<imagedata fileref="../images/C/abiword.png" format="PNG" width="100%" scalefit="1"/>
				</imageobject>
			</mediaobject>
			<note>
				<para>
					In case you need more features or better Microsoft Word compatibility, you may want to install OpenOffice. It is readily available for installation from the Ubuntu software repositories (refer to <xref linkend="add-applications"/>). Just be warned that it is a lot bigger and slower than AbiWord! 
				</para>
			</note>
		</sect2>
	</sect1>
	<sect1 id="gnumeric">
		<title>Spreadsheet calculations with Gnumeric</title>
		<para>
			Gnumeric is the <ulink url="http://www.gnome.org">Gnome Project</ulink>'s Spreadsheet program, and it is the recommended application for working with spreadsheets on &xubuntu;. It is - in its own words - &quot;free, fast and accurate&quot;. Start it with &gnumeric;.
		</para>
		<note>
			<para>
				A <ulink url="http://www.gnome.org/projects/gnumeric/doc/chapter-quick-start.html">Quick Guide</ulink> and the full <ulink url="http://www.gnome.org/projects/gnumeric/doc/">User Manual</ulink> are available from the project's website.
			</para>
		</note>
		<note>
			<para>
				In case you need more features or better Microsoft Excel compatibility, you may want to install OpenOffice. It is readily available for installation from the Ubuntu software repositories (refer to <xref linkend="add-applications"/>). Just be warned that it is a lot bigger and slower than Gnumeric! 
			</para>
		</note>
	</sect1>
	<sect1 id="add-applications">
		<title>Adding, Removing and Updating Applications</title>
		<sect2 id="synaptic"> 
			<title>Synaptic Package Manager</title>
			<para>Sooner or later, you will have the need to install additional programs on your computer. Ubuntu comes with a special tool called <application>Synaptic</application> that will help you with this task. <application>Synaptic</application> is an advanced package management application that can install and remove every package available to your system. It gives you complete control over the package management of your system.</para>
			<para>To launch <application>Synaptic</application>, choose &synaptic; on the desktop menu system.
			</para>
			<note>
				<para>Running <application>Synaptic</application> requires administrative privileges (see <xref linkend="root-and-sudo"/>).
				</para>
			</note>
			
			<para>The <application>Synaptic</application> screen is divided up into four sections, the two most important being the package categories on the left side, and the packages on the right.
			</para>
			<para>If you know the name of the package, the quickest way to install it is to click on the <guibutton>Search</guibutton> toolbar button, enter the name in the search text field and click the <guibutton>Search</guibutton> button. <application>Synaptic</application> will now show you a short list from which to select your application for installation. This is usually much easier than having to look through the very long list of applications in the category section. Now right-click on it and choose "<guimenuitem>Mark this package for installation</guimenuitem>". Once you are satisfied with your selections click  <guibutton>Apply</guibutton> on the top button bar. <application>Synaptic</application> will then download and install the required packages from the online repositories and/or from your Ubuntu installation CD.
			</para>
			<para>In case you do not know the name of the package, choose <guibutton>section</guibutton> in the lower left part of the window, choose the appropriate category, and find the package name in the list. 
			</para>
			<para>When the installation process has finished, you should have a new option for the program you installed available in the menu.
			</para>
			
		</sect2>
		<sect2 id="extra-repositories">
			<title>Extra Repositories</title>
			<para>Many software packages you might need are not in the <emphasis>Main</emphasis> repository, so let us learn how to add extra repositories.
			</para>
			<sect3><title>What are Repositories?</title>
				<para>There are thousands of programs available to install on Ubuntu. These programs are stored in software archives (<emphasis>repositories</emphasis>) and are made freely available for installation over the Internet. This makes it very easy to install new programs in Linux, and it is also very secure, because each program you install is built specially for Ubuntu and checked before it is installed. To organize the software, Ubuntu repositories are categorized into four groups: <emphasis>Main</emphasis>, <emphasis>Restricted</emphasis>, <emphasis>Universe</emphasis>, and <emphasis>Multiverse</emphasis>.</para> 
				<para>The rationale used to determine which software goes into which category is based on two factors:</para>
				<itemizedlist>
					<listitem>
						<para>The level of support software development teams provide for a program.</para>
					</listitem>
					<listitem>
						<para>The level of compliance the program has to the <ulink url="&ubuntu-philosophy;">Free Software Philosophy</ulink>.</para>
					</listitem>
				</itemizedlist>
				<para>You can find more information about the Repositories available <ulink url="&ubuntu-components;">on the website</ulink>.</para>
				<para>The standard Ubuntu Install CD contains some software from the <emphasis>Main</emphasis> and <emphasis>Restricted</emphasis> categories. Once your system is made aware of the Internet-based locations for these repositories, many more software programs are made available for installation. Using the software package management tools already installed on your system, you can search for, install and update any piece of software directly over the Internet, without the need for the CD.</para>
			</sect3>
			<sect3>
				<title>Adding Extra Repositories</title>
				<para>To enable the extra repositories:</para>
				<procedure>
					<step>
						<para>Open &software-sources;.</para>
					</step>
					<step>
						<para>To enable the <emphasis>Universe</emphasis> repository, check the <guibutton>Community maintained Open Source software (Universe)</guibutton> checkbox.</para>
						<note>
							<para>Adding this repository will mean that the majority of the Free Software universe will be available to install on your system. This software is supported by a carefully selected group of volunteers within the Ubuntu Community, but is not supported by the core Ubuntu development team and may not include security updates.</para>
						</note>
					</step>
					<step>
						<para>To enable the <emphasis>Multiverse</emphasis> repository, check the <guibutton>By copyright or legal issues restricted software (Multiverse)</guibutton> button.</para>
						<warning>
							<para>Adding this repository will mean that software which has been classified as <emphasis>non-free</emphasis> will be available to install on your system. This software may not be permitted in some jurisdictions. When installing each package from this repository, you should verify that the laws of your country permit you to use it. Again, this software may not include security updates.</para>
						</warning>
					</step>
					<step><para>Click <guibutton>Close</guibutton> to save your changes and exit.</para>
					</step>
				</procedure>
			</sect3>
		</sect2>
		<sect2 id="updates">
			<title>Updates</title>
			<para>Sometimes the Ubuntu developers release feature and security updates for applications and packages within the Ubuntu system.
			</para>
			<para>The <application>Update Manager</application> program will list the available updates. You will find it at &update-manager;. To download and install available updates click <guibutton>Install Updates</guibutton>. Ubuntu will then download and install the available updates from the Internet.
			</para>
			<para>When <application>Update Manager</application> has finished updating your system, close <application>Update Manager</application> to finish updating your system. 
			</para>
			<para>
				After installing some important updates, it may be necessary to restart your computer. 
			</para>
		</sect2>		
	</sect1>
	<sect1 id="orage">
		<title>Calendar</title>
		<para>
			<application>Orage</application> is &xfce;'s calendar application. You will find it at &orage;. Use it to manage your appointments, set weekly reminders, schedule alarms, and more.
		</para>
		<mediaobject>
			<imageobject>
				<imagedata fileref="../images/C/orage.png" format="PNG"/>
			</imageobject>
		</mediaobject>
	</sect1>
	<sect1 id="play-music">
		<title>Play Music</title>
		<para>
			Launch &gxine; for playing audio files. <application>Gxine</application> is a simple, easy-to-use media player based on the xine engine.
		</para>
		<note>
			<para>
				Please note that &xubuntu; comes with very limited multimedia support out of the box. Please read <xref linkend="multimedia"/> for an explanation, and what you can do about it.
			</para>
		</note>
<!--
		<mediaobject>
			<imageobject>
				<imagedata fileref="../images/C/xfmedia.png" format="PNG"/>
			</imageobject>
		</mediaobject>
-->
	</sect1>
	<sect1>
		<title>Watch a Movie</title>
		<para>
			<application>Gxine</application> is the default program to watch movies. Launch it from &gxine;.
		</para>
		<note>
			<para>
				Please note that &xubuntu; comes with very limited multimedia support out of the box. Playback of DVDs, for example, is not supported by default. Please read <xref linkend="multimedia"/> for an explanation, and what you can do about it.
			</para>
		</note>

	</sect1>
	<sect1 id="manipulate-pictures">
		<title>Manipulate a Picture</title>
		<para>
			&xubuntu; ships with the <application>GIMP</application> - the GNU Image Manipulation Program. It can be used for things like photo retouching, image composition and image authoring. Start it from &gimp;.
		</para>
		<tip>
			<para>
				Extensive documentation on using the GIMP may be found here: <ulink url="http://www.gimp.org/docs/"/>.
			</para>
		</tip>
	</sect1>
	<sect1 id="browse-pictures">
		<title>Browse Pictures</title>
		<para>
			For browsing picture image collections, you will find the application <application>GQview</application> convenient. To launch it, click &gqview;.
			
		</para>
		<para>
			You will find a file browsing area on the left side that lets you navigate to the pictures on your hard drive. The pictures will subsequently be shown in the main area of <application>GQview</application>.
		</para>
		<tip>
			<para>
				Please refer to the online manual: <ulink url="http://gqview.sourceforge.net/docs/index.html"/>.
			</para>
		</tip>
	</sect1>
	<sect1 id="burn-cd">
		<title>Burn a CD</title>
		<para>
			For burning CDs, use <application>Xfburn</application>. To launch it, click &xfburn;.
			
		</para>
		<para>
			The tool has the usual options of erasing CDRW disks, burning ISO images, copying CDs, or making Data CDs from files on your PC.
		</para>
	</sect1>
	<sect1 id="settings-manager">
		<title>The Settings Manager</title>
		<para>
			The <application>Settings Manager</application> is located at &settings-manager;. This is the central place for customizing your desktop. Among the things you can do with the <application>Settings Manager</application> are:
			<itemizedlist>
				<listitem>
					<para>
						Change the desktop background image in the section <emphasis>Desktop</emphasis>.
					</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>
						Change the GTK theme and the icon theme in <emphasis>User Interface</emphasis>.
					</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>
						Choose a different screensaver in <emphasis>Screensaver</emphasis>.
					</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>
						Choose a different audio device in <emphasis>Sound</emphasis>.
					</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>
						Add new keyboard shortcuts in <emphasis>Keyboard</emphasis>, tab <emphasis>Shortcuts</emphasis>.
					</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>
						Lots more...
					</para>
				</listitem>
			</itemizedlist>
		</para>
		<mediaobject>
			<imageobject>
				<imagedata fileref="../images/C/xfce-settings-manager.png" format="PNG"/>
			</imageobject>
		</mediaobject>
		<note>
			<para>
				Please note that these settings control the look and behaviour of your <emphasis>desktop</emphasis> only. It is important to know that it is not a settings manager for your <emphasis>system</emphasis>, and therefore does not let you configure printers, set up your networking configuration, switch keyboard layouts, or similar. To accomplish these tasks, read <xref linkend="printer-configuration"/>, <xref linkend="networking"/> and <xref linkend="switch-keyboard-layout"/>. 
			</para>
		</note>
	</sect1>
	<sect1 id="finding-right-program">
		<title>Finding the Right Program</title>
		<para>
			The wealth of software offered on an Ubuntu system is enormous, so finding the right tool for the right job can be difficult at times. The following table may help you with this. It shows programs which are installed on &xubuntu; by default, some which are recommended to be added by you, and other programs available in the software archives, grouped by tasks. Please note that you may have to <link linkend="extra-repositories">enable restricted repositories</link> to install some of the listed programs.
		</para>
		<informaltable frame='all' style='border-collapse:collapse'>
			<tgroup cols='3' align='left' >
				<colspec colname='c1' />
				<colspec colname='c2'/>
				<colspec colname='c3'/>
				<thead>
					<row>
						<entry>Task</entry>
						<entry>Installed Program</entry>
						<entry>Also available</entry>
					</row>
				</thead><tbody>
					<row>
						<entry>Webbrowser</entry>
						<entry><link linkend="surf-internet">Firefox</link></entry>
						<entry>Epiphany (Gnome), Konqueror (KDE), Dillo</entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry>Email Client</entry>
						<entry><link linkend="write-emails">Thunderbird</link></entry>
						<entry>Sylpheed-Claws</entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry>File Manager</entry>
						<entry><link linkend="browse-files">Thunar</link></entry>
						<entry>Nautilus (Gnome), Konqueror (KDE), Xffm (old Xfce Filemanager), ROX-Filer</entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry>Text Editor</entry>
						<entry><link linkend="mousepad">Mousepad</link></entry>
						<entry>Gedit (Gnome), Kate (KDE), Gvim, XEmacs, Nedit, Nano</entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry>Word Processing</entry>
						<entry><link linkend="abiword">Abiword</link></entry>
						<entry>OpenOffice, KOffice (KDE), LaTeX</entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry>Spreadsheet Calculation</entry>
						<entry><link linkend="gnumeric">Gnumeric-gtk</link></entry>
						<entry>OpenOffice, KOffice (KDE)</entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry>Multimedia Playback (Audio/Video)</entry>
						<entry><link linkend="play-music">Xfmedia</link></entry>
						<entry>XMMS, Beep Media Player, Xine, Mplayer, Totem (Gnome), Rhythmbox (Gnome)</entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry>Image Manipulation</entry>
						<entry><link linkend="manipulate-pictures">Gimp</link></entry>
						<entry>Krita (KDE, part of KOffice)</entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry>Picture Browsing</entry>
						<entry><link linkend="browse-pictures">GQview</link></entry>
						<entry>gThumbview (Gnome), KView (KDE)</entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry>Chat / Instant Messanger</entry>
						<entry>Gaim</entry>
						<entry>XChat</entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry>PDF Viewer</entry>
						<entry>Evince-gtk</entry>
						<entry>Acroread</entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry>Calendar</entry>
						<entry>Orage</entry>
						<entry></entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry>Package Management</entry>
						<entry><link linkend="add-applications">Synaptic</link></entry>
						<entry></entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry>Software Telephone</entry>
						<entry></entry>
						<entry>Ekiga (Gnome)</entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry>Archiving Tool</entry>
						<entry>Xarchiver, Thunar Archive Plugin</entry>
						<entry></entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry>CD/DVD Burning</entry>
						<entry>Xfburn</entry>
						<entry>GnomeBaker (Gnome), K3b (KDE)</entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry>FTP Client</entry>
						<entry></entry>
						<entry>Nautilus (Gnome), Konqueror (KDE)</entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry>Printer Administration</entry>
						<entry><link linkend="printer-configuration">CUPS Web Administration</link></entry>
						<entry>Gnome Cups Manager (Gnome)</entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry>P2P</entry>
						<entry></entry>
						<entry>aMule</entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry>Vector Graphics</entry>
						<entry></entry>
						<entry>Inkscape</entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry>Desktop Publishing (DTP)</entry>
						<entry></entry>
						<entry>Scribus</entry>
					</row>
				</tbody>
			</tgroup>
		</informaltable>
	</sect1>
</chapter>
