<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.3//EN" 
	"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.3/docbookx.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % globalent SYSTEM "../../../libs/global.ent">
%globalent;
<!ENTITY % cdo-C SYSTEM "../../../libs/cdo-C.ent">
%cdo-C;
<!ENTITY % pg-common SYSTEM "../pg-common.ent">
%pg-common;
<!ENTITY % xinclude SYSTEM "../../../libs/xinclude.mod">
%xinclude;
<!ENTITY language "en">
<!ENTITY ubuntu '<phrase>Ubuntu</phrase>'>
]>
<chapter id="intro-chap" status="review">
	<title id="intro">Introducción</title>
	
	<para>Welcome to the <phrase>Ubuntu</phrase> Packaging Guide! This guide is
		primarily addressed to those who would like to make and
		maintain <phrase>Ubuntu</phrase> packages. Although many of the concepts in
		this guide could be used to make binary packages for personal
		use, it is designed for those people wanting to distribute
		their packages to and for others. While it is also written
		with the <phrase>Ubuntu</phrase> Linux distribution in mind, it should also
		be useful for any Debian-based distribution.</para>

	<para>There are several reasons you might want to learn how to
		package for Ubuntu.  First, building and fixing <phrase>Ubuntu</phrase>
		packages is a great way to contribute to the <phrase>Ubuntu</phrase>
		community. It is also a good way to learn how <phrase>Ubuntu</phrase> and the
		applications you have installed work. Maybe you want to
		install a package that is not in the <phrase>Ubuntu</phrase>
		repositories. Hopefully after you have completed this guide
		you will have the tools and knowledge you need to do all of
		these things.</para>

	<para> HTML and PDF versions of the manual are available online
			at <ulink url="http://help.ubuntu.com">the Ubuntu
			Documentation website</ulink>.  </para>
	
	<para> You can buy this guide in book form from <ulink url="http://www.lulu.com/ubuntu-doc">our Lulu store</ulink>. You will only pay for
		the price of printing and postage.  </para>

	<sect1 id="intro-wtb" status="writing">
	  <title>Where to Begin</title>
	  <para>If you are completely new to Debian-based packaging then
	  you will want to read this guide completely through, paying
	  special attention to <xref linkend="intro-prereq"/>,
	  <xref linkend="gs-chap"/>, and
	  <xref linkend="basic-chap"/>. People who are experienced with
	  Debian-based packaging will find <xref linkend="ubuntu-chap"/>
	  and <xref linkend="bugs-chap"/> most helpful. </para>
	</sect1>

	<sect1 id="intro-prereq" status="review">
		<title>Prerequisitos</title>
			
		<para>This guide assumes that the reader has a reasonable
			knowledge of building and installing software from source
			on Linux distributions. The guide also uses the Command
			Line Interface (CLI) throughout, so you should be
			comfortable using a terminal. You should be able to at
			least use the following:</para>

		<itemizedlist>
		  <listitem><para><emphasis role="bold">make:</emphasis> GNU
				Make is a very important software building tool. It is
				used to transform a complex compilation task into a
				trivial one. It is important that you know how to use
				it, because we will store most of the information
				about the packaging process in a
				Makefile. Documentation is available at
				the <ulink url="http://www.gnu.org/software/make/manual/make.html">GNU
			</ulink> website.</para></listitem>

		  <listitem><para><emphasis role="bold">./configure:</emphasis>This script is
				included in almost all Linux source, especially for
				software written in compiled languages such as C and
				C++. It is used to generate a Makefile (file used
				by <application>make</application>) that is properly
				configured for your system. Standard Debian packaging
				tools use it, so it is important that you know what
				the <filename>configure</filename> script
				does. Information on <filename>./configure</filename>
				can be found in the <application>make</application>
				documentation.</para></listitem>
							
		  <listitem><para><emphasis role="bold">Apt/Dpkg:</emphasis>
				Beyond the basic use of installing
				programs, <application>apt</application>
				and <application>dpkg</application> have many features
				that are useful for packaging.</para>
			<itemizedlist>
				
			  <listitem><para><emphasis role="bold">apt-cache dump</emphasis> - lista todos los paquetes de en la caché. Esta orden es especialmente útil en combinación con una tubería <application>grep</application> tal como <application>apt-cache dump | grep foo</application> para buscar paquetes que incluyan <quote>foo</quote> en sus nombres o dependencias.</para></listitem>

				<listitem><para><emphasis role="bold">apt-cache policy</emphasis> - lista los repositorios (main/restructed/universe/multiverse) en los que existe un paquete.</para></listitem>

				<listitem><para><emphasis role="bold">apt-cache show</emphasis> - muestra información sobre un paquete binario.</para></listitem>

				<listitem><para><emphasis role="bold">apt-cache showsrc</emphasis> - muestra información sobre un paquete fuente.</para></listitem>

				<listitem><para><emphasis role="bold">apt-cache rdepends</emphasis> - muestra dependencias inversas de un paquete (los paquetes que requiere el paquete consultado).</para></listitem>

				<listitem><para><emphasis role="bold">dpkg -S </emphasis> - muestra el paquete binario al que pertenece un determidado fichero.</para></listitem>

				<listitem><para><emphasis role="bold">dpkg -l </emphasis> - enumera los paquetes instalados actualmente. Esto es similar a <application>apt-cache dump</application> pero para paquetes instalados.</para></listitem>
	
				<listitem><para><emphasis role="bold">dpkg -c </emphasis> - enumera los contenidos de los paquetes binarios. Es útil para asegurarse que los ficheros se instalan en los lugares correctos.</para></listitem>

				<listitem><para><emphasis role="bold">dpkg -f </emphasis> - muestra el fichero control de un paquete binario. Es útil para asegurarse de que las dependencias son correctas.</para></listitem>

				<listitem><para><emphasis role="bold">grep-dctrl</emphasis> - busca información especializada en los paquetes. Es un uso específico del paquete <application>grep</application> (pero no instalado por defecto).</para></listitem>

			</itemizedlist>
				
		  </listitem>

		  <listitem><para><emphasis role="bold">diff and
				patch:</emphasis> The <application>diff</application>
				program can be used to compare two files and to make
				patches. A typical example might be <application>diff
				-ruN file.old file.new &gt;
				file.diff</application>. This command will create a
				diff (recursively if directories are used) that shows
				the changes, or
				<quote>delta</quote>, between the two files.</para>

			<para>El programa <application>patch</application> se usa para aplicar un parche (normalmente creado mediante <application>diff</application> u otro programa similar) a un fichero o directorio. Para aplicar el parche creado arriba, podemos invocar <application>patch -p0 &lt; file.diff</application>. La <emphasis>-p</emphasis> indica a <application>patch</application> cuánto debería quitar de la ruta de los ficheros en el parche. -p0 significa que no quita nada, o dejar la ruta intacta.</para>
			
		  </listitem>

		</itemizedlist>
		
	</sect1>

</chapter>

