<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.3//EN" 
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.3/docbookx.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % globalent SYSTEM "../../../libs/global.ent">
%globalent;
<!ENTITY % cdo-C SYSTEM "../../../libs/cdo-C.ent">
%cdo-C;
<!ENTITY % kde SYSTEM "../../libs/kde.ent">
%kde;
<!ENTITY % kde-general SYSTEM "/usr/share/apps/ksgmltools2/customization/obsolete/general.entities">
%kde-general;
<!ENTITY % xinclude SYSTEM "../../../libs/xinclude.mod">
%xinclude;
<!ENTITY language "en">
]>
<chapter id="common-tasks-chap" status="complete">
    <title id="common-tasks">Common Tasks</title>
    <para>This chapter contains information on common tasks that you might want to perform on your computer.</para>
    <!-- To do: Add help links to application documentation link help://blah-kde-app/index.hml -->
    <sect1 id="music" status="complete">
        <title>Music</title>
        <sect2 id="audio-cds" status="complete">
            <title>Playing Audio CDs</title>
            <para>
                When you insert an Audio CD into Kubuntu, the system will recognize it, mount it, and start the <application>KDE Daemon</application>. Choose <guibutton>Play</guibutton> to start playing the CDs in <application>KSCD</application>. If you are connected to the Internet, <application>KSCD</application> will retrieve the CD artist, title, and track data from <ulink url="http://freedb.org">freedb.org</ulink>. You can also retrieve information from other sources by clicking on the <guibutton> Extras</guibutton>
            </para>
            <para>
                To start <application>KSCD</application> manually, choose 
                <menuchoice>
                    <guimenu>K-Menu</guimenu>
                    <guisubmenu>Multimedia</guisubmenu>
                    <guimenuitem>KsCD (CDPlayer)</guimenuitem>
                </menuchoice>.
            </para>
            <para>
                To play the CD, click the <guibutton>Play</guibutton> button. To play a particular track, select the track from the drop down list at the top. 
            </para>
        </sect2>
        <sect2 id="ripping" status="complete">
            <title>Ripping Audio CDs</title>
            <procedure>
                <step>
                    <para>
                        When you insert an Audio CD into Kubuntu, the system will recognize it, mount it, and start the <application>KDE Daemon</application>. Choose <guibutton>Extract and Encode audio tracks</guibutton> to launch <application>KaudioCreator</application>.
                    </para>
                </step>
                <step>
                    <para>
                        To start <application>KaudioCreator</application> manually, choose
                        <menuchoice>
                            <guimenu>K-Menu</guimenu>
                            <guisubmenu>Multimedia</guisubmenu>
                            <guimenuitem>KAudioCreator (CD Ripper)</guimenuitem>
                        </menuchoice> 
                        from the desktop menu system.
                    </para>
                </step>
                <step>
                    <para>
                        Inside <application>KaudioCreator</application>, you will be greeted with the list of songs, in order of their track number. If the CD you are ripping is an original CD (not a mix/back-up disk), then most of the song titles should be detected automatically if you are connected to the Internet. If not, click the disk in the top left hand corner to try again.
                    </para>
                </step>
                <step>
                    <para>
                        Select what tracks you want to rip, or all of them by pressing <guibutton>Select all tracks</guibutton>
                    </para>
                </step>
                <step>
                    <para>
                        To begin the ripping process, press the <guibutton>Rip Selection</guibutton> in the toolbar. When the ripping process has started, you can watch your progress by pressing the <guilabel>Jobs</guilabel> tab. By default, the files rip into <filename>/home/username/ogg</filename> directory, and are in the Ogg Vorbis (ogg) format. They are neatly sorted by artist, followed by album, and lastly song. 
                    </para>
                </step>
                <step>
                    <para>
                        When you are done ripping your CD tracks, press the <guibutton>eject</guibutton> button to eject your CD-Rom.
                    </para>
                </step>
            </procedure>
            <tip>
                <para>
                    You can use the preferences window to control where the extracted audio files are stored on your computer, the filename of extracted audio files, and the file format and codec used for the files. In the main window, choose 
                    <menuchoice>
                        <guimenu>Settings</guimenu>
                        <guisubmenu>Configure KAudioCreator...</guisubmenu>
                    </menuchoice>.
                </para>
            </tip>
            <para>
                <application>KAudioCreator</application> can extract audio files to the following formats:
                <itemizedlist>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>
                            <emphasis role="strong">Ogg Vorbis</emphasis> - Ogg Vorbis is a patent-free lossy audio compression format which typically produces higher quality and greater compression than MP3. See the <ulink url="http://www.vorbis.com/faq/">Vorbis website</ulink> for more information.
                        </para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para><emphasis role="strong">FLAC</emphasis> - FLAC is the Free Lossless Audio Codec. It can compress audio files up to 50% without removing any information from the audio stream. For more information on this format, see the <ulink url="http://flac.sourceforge.net/">FLAC homepage</ulink> on sourceforge.net.
                        </para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para><emphasis role="strong">WAV</emphasis> - Wav is an uncompressed audio format, which can be compressed into OGG Vorbis or a codec of your choice. It is often used while working on sound in applications like Audacity, before being compressed.
                        </para>
                    </listitem>
                </itemizedlist>
            </para>
            <para>
                You can also extract CD audio files to the proprietary non-free <emphasis role="strong">MP3</emphasis> format by using the lame encoder. See the <ulink url="http://docs.kde.org/stable/en/kdemultimedia/kaudiocreator/index.html"> KAudioCreator Handbook </ulink> (<ulink url="help:/kaudiocreator/index.html">Offline Help</ulink>).
                
            </para>
        </sect2>
        <sect2 id="music-files" status="complete">
            <title>Playing and Organizing Music Files</title>
            <para>
                Kubuntu does not directly support the <emphasis role="strong">MP3</emphasis> format, because it is restricted by patents and proprietary rights. Instead Kubuntu supports the <emphasis role="strong">Ogg Vorbis</emphasis> format out of the box, a completely free, open and non-patented format. Ogg Vorbis files also sound better then MP3 files of the same file size and are supported by many popular music players (a list of players is <ulink url="http://wiki.xiph.org/index.php/PortablePlayers">here</ulink>).
            </para>
            <para>
                You can still play your old MP3 files by installing MP3 support (see <xref linkend="codecs"/>). Instructions for other formats, such as Windows Media Audio (wma/wmv) and other patent encumbered formats can be found <ulink url="http://wiki.ubuntu.com/RestrictedFormats">on the Ubuntu Wiki</ulink>.
            </para>
            <para>
                The default music application on your Kubuntu system is the <application>Amarok</application> Music Player, a music management and playback application that looks like <application>iTunes</application>. When you first start <application>Amarok</application>, it will scan your home directory for any supported music files you have and add it to the database. To start <application>Amarok</application>, choose  
                <menuchoice>
                    <guimenu>K-Menu</guimenu>
                    <guisubmenu>Multimedia</guisubmenu>
                    <guimenuitem>Amarok (Audio Player)</guimenuitem>
                </menuchoice>.
            </para>
            <para>
                <application>Amarok</application> has an inbuilt ID3 tag editor that can edit the metadata on your OGG and other music files. Please see the <ulink url="http://docs.kde.org/stable/en/extragear-multimedia/amarok/index.html"> amaroK handbook </ulink> (<ulink url="help:/amarok/index.html">Offline Help</ulink>) for details on how to edit the metadata.
            </para>
        </sect2>
        <sect2 id="iPod" status="complete">
            <title>Using your iPod</title>
            <para>
                You can play music directly off your iPod with <application>Amarok</application>. Simply plug your iPod into the computer, and open <application>Amarok</application>.
            </para>
            <para>
                To transfer music files to and from an iPod, you can use <application>Amarok</application> as well. Please see the <ulink url="http://docs.kde.org/stable/en/extragear-multimedia/amarok/index.html"> amaroK handbook </ulink> (<ulink url="help:/amarok/index.html">Offline Help</ulink>) on how to manage media files in your iPod.
            </para>
        </sect2>
        <sect2 id="edit-audio-files" status="complete">
            <title>Edit Audio Files</title>
            <para>Audacity is a free, open source software for recording and editing sounds. To use Audacity:</para>
            <procedure>
                <step>
                    <para>Install the <application>audacity </application>package from the <emphasis>Universe</emphasis> repository (see <xref linkend="extra-repositories"/>).
                    </para>
                </step>
                <step>
                    <para>To run <application>Audacity</application>, choose
                        <menuchoice>
                            <guimenu>K-Menu</guimenu>
                            <guisubmenu>Multimedia</guisubmenu>
                            <guimenuitem>Audacity</guimenuitem>
                        </menuchoice>.
                    </para>
                </step>
                <step>
                    <para>For further help about using Audacity, consult the program's help by choosing 
                        <menuchoice>
                            <guimenu>Help</guimenu>
                            <guisubmenu>Contents</guisubmenu>
                        </menuchoice>.
                    </para>
                </step>
            </procedure>
        </sect2>
    </sect1>
    <sect1 id="video" status="complete">
        <title>Video</title>
        <para>Many video formats can be played in Kubuntu using free codecs found in the repositories. This includes formats such as MPEG and other common video formats. To install further codec support see <xref linkend="codecs"/>.</para>
        <para>In Kubuntu, videos can be played with the <application>Kaffeine</application> Media Player. Some features of
            <application>Kaffeine</application> include custom playlists, DVD playback and more. 
            You can start <application>Kaffeine</application> by clicking: 
            <menuchoice>
                <guimenu>K-Menu</guimenu>
                <guisubmenu>Multimedia</guisubmenu>
                <guimenuitem>Kaffeine (Media Player)</guimenuitem>
            </menuchoice>.
    </para>
    <sect2 id="dvdplayback" status="help">
        <!-- Heard this was going to change in dapper, verify -->
        <title>DVD Playback</title>
        <warning><para>The legal status of this library is not fully clear. In some countries it is possible that the use of this library to play or copy DVDs is not permitted by law. Verify that you are within your rights in using it.</para></warning>
        <para>The movie players provided in Kubuntu are capable of reading DVDs that are not encrypted. However, most commercial DVDs are encrypted with CSS (Content Scrambling System) and currently, for legal reasons, it is not possible to include support for these DVDs in Kubuntu. However it is possible to enable support as follows:</para>
        <procedure>
            <step>
                <para>Install the <application>libdvdread3</application> package (see <xref linkend="extra-repositories"/>).
                </para>
                <note><para>You will need to use <application>Adept Package Manager</application> to install this package</para></note>
            </step>
            <step>
                <para>Type the following command into a terminal prompt:<screen>sudo /usr/share/doc/libdvdread3/examples/install-css.sh</screen>
                </para>
            </step>
        </procedure>
    </sect2>
		<sect2 status="complete">
			<title>RealPlayer 10</title>
					<procedure>
						<step>
							<para>Install the <application>realplay</application> package from the <emphasis>Commercial</emphasis> repository (see <xref linkend="add-applications"/>).</para>
						</step>
            <step>
                <para>To run <application>Real Player 10</application>, choose
                    <menuchoice>
                        <guimenu>K-Menu</guimenu>
                        <guisubmenu>Multimedia</guisubmenu>
                        <guimenuitem>RealPlayer 10 (Media Player)</guimenuitem>
                    </menuchoice>.
                </para>
            </step>
            <step>
                <para> Debian packages are not available for <emphasis>PowerPC</emphasis> or <emphasis>AMD64</emphasis> architectures. However, you can try to see if a player is available on the <ulink url="https://player.helixcommunity.org/">Helix Player</ulink> Community Site.</para>
            </step>
					</procedure>
			</sect2>

    <sect2 status="complete">
        <title>Video Editing</title>
        <para><application>Kino</application> is an advanced video editor. It features excellent integration with IEEE-1394 (Firewire) for capture, VTR control, and recording back of the camera. It captures video to disk in Raw DV and AVI format, in both type-1 DV and type-2 DV (separate audio stream) encoding. For more information, see <ulink url="http://www.kinodv.org/article/static/2">the Kino website</ulink>. To use it:</para>
        <procedure>
            <step>
                <para>Install the <application>kino</application> package (see <xref linkend="add-applications"/>).</para>
            </step>
            <step>
                <para>To run <application>Kino</application>, choose
                    <menuchoice>
                        <guimenu>Applications</guimenu>
                        <guisubmenu>Sound &amp; Video</guisubmenu>
                        <guimenuitem>Kino Video Editor</guimenuitem>
                    </menuchoice>.
                </para>
            </step>
        </procedure>
    </sect2>
</sect1>
<sect1 id="codecs" status="complete">
    <title>Multimedia Codecs</title>
    <para>
        Codecs for playing non-free formats are not included in Kubuntu by default. You can get support for the extra codecs by installing the <application>libxine-extracodecs</application> package from the <emphasis>Multiverse</emphasis> repository (see <xref linkend="extra-repositories"/>).
    </para>
    <warning>
        <para>Some of these packages may not be permitted in some countries: you should verify that you are permitted to use them before installing them.
        </para>
    </warning>
    <para>Due to patent and copyright restrictions, some codecs are not included at all in Kubuntu. For more information on these, go to <ulink url="&restricted-formats;">&restricted-formats;</ulink>.
    </para>
</sect1>
<sect1 id="burning-cds" status="complete">
    <title>Burning and Ripping CDs/DVDs</title>
    <sect2 status="complete">
        <title>Burning a Photo or Data CD/DVD</title>
        <procedure>
            <step>
                <para>
                    Launch <application>k3b</application> by choosing 
                    <menuchoice>
                        <guimenu>K-Menu</guimenu>
                        <guisubmenu>Multimedia</guisubmenu>
                        <guimenuitem>k3b (CD and DVD Burning)</guimenuitem>
                    </menuchoice> 
                </para>
            </step>
            <step>
                <para>Follow the  <ulink url="http://docs.kde.org/stable/en/extragear-multimedia/k3b/cdcopyhowto.html"> steps to burn a data CD </ulink> (<ulink url="help:/k3b/cdcopyhowto.html">Offline Help</ulink>) in the K3B handbook.
                </para>
            </step>
        </procedure>      
    </sect2>
    <sect2 status="complete">
        <title>Burning an Audio CD/DVD</title>
        <procedure>
            <step>
                <para>
                    If you want to burn mp3 files into audio CDs, you will need to install the <application>libk3b2-mp3</application> package from the <emphasis>Universe</emphasis> repository (see <xref linkend="extra-repositories"/>).
                </para>
            </step>
            <step>
                <para>
                    Launch <application>k3b</application> by choosing 
                    <menuchoice>
                        <guimenu>K-Menu</guimenu>
                        <guisubmenu>Multimedia</guisubmenu>
                        <guimenuitem>k3b (CD and DVD Burning)</guimenuitem>
                    </menuchoice> 
                </para>
            </step>
            <step><para>Follow the  <ulink url="http://docs.kde.org/stable/en/extragear-multimedia/k3b/audiocdcdreating.html">steps to burn an audio CD</ulink> (<ulink url="help:/k3b/audiocdcdreating.html">Offline Help</ulink>) in the K3B handbook.
            </para>
        </step>
    </procedure>
</sect2>
<sect2 status="complete">
    <title>Rip a DVD with K3B</title>
    <procedure>
        <step>
            <para>
                Install the following packages
                <simplelist>
                    <member>transcode</member>
                    <member>libxvidcore4</member>
                    <member>sox</member>
                    <member>mjpegtools</member>
                    <member>toolame</member>
                    <member>libdvdread</member>
                </simplelist> 
            from the <emphasis>Universe</emphasis> and <emphasis>Multiverse</emphasis> repository (see <xref linkend="extra-repositories"/>).
            </para>
        </step>
        <step>
            <para>
                Launch <application>k3b</application> by choosing 
                <menuchoice>
                    <guimenu>K-Menu</guimenu>
                    <guisubmenu>Multimedia</guisubmenu>
<guimenuitem>k3b (CD and DVD Burning)</guimenuitem>
                </menuchoice> 
            </para>
        </step>
        <step><para>Follow the <ulink url="http://docs.kde.org/stable/en/extragear-multimedia/k3b/howtos.html#videointroduction">steps to Rip a DVD and Encode it </ulink> (<ulink url="help:/k3b/howtos.html#videointroduction">Offline Help</ulink>) in the K3B handbook.
            </para>
    </step>
    </procedure>
</sect2>
        <sect2 status="complete">
            <title>Generate MD5 Checksum files</title>
            <procedure>
                <step>
		<para>To save the md5sum of file.iso to a file, run:</para>
                    <para>
                        <screen>md5sum file.iso &gt; file.iso.md5</screen>
                    </para>
                </step>
            </procedure>
        </sect2>
        <sect2 status="complete">
            <title>Check MD5 checksum of an ISO image</title>
            <procedure>
                <step>
                    <para>
                        Assuming that <filename>file.iso</filename>
                        and <filename>file.iso.md5</filename> are in the
                        same folder.
                    </para>
                </step>
                <step>
                    <para>
                        <screen>md5sum -c file.iso.md5</screen>
                    </para>
                </step>
            </procedure>
        </sect2>
        <sect2 status="complete">
            <title>Mount/unmount Image (ISO) files without burning to CD</title>
            <procedure>
                <step>
                    <para>To mount Image (ISO) file</para>
                    <screen>sudo mkdir /media/iso
sudo modprobe loop 
sudo mount file.iso /media/iso/ -t iso9660 -o loop</screen>
                </step>
                <step>
                    <para>To unmount Image (ISO) file</para>
                    <screen>sudo umount <filename>/media/iso/</filename></screen>
                </step>
            </procedure>
        </sect2>

</sect1>
<sect1 id="internet" status="complete">
    <title>Internet</title>
    <sect2 id="connect-to-internet" status="complete">
        <title>Connecting to the Internet</title>
        <para>To connect to the Internet, do the following:</para>
        <procedure>
            <step><para>If you have a Modem or ADSL connection, read <xref linkend="modems"/> first.</para></step>
            <step>
                <para>
                    <menuchoice>
                        <guimenu>K-Menü</guimenu>
                        <guisubmenu>System Settings</guisubmenu>
                        <guimenuitem>Network Settings</guimenuitem>
                    </menuchoice>
                </para>
            </step>
            <step>
                <para>
                    Click on the <guibutton>Administrator Mode...</guibutton> and enter your user password to gain administrator privileges.</para></step>
            <step>
                <para>Select the <guilabel>Network Interfaces</guilabel> tab. Select the interface to configure from the list, then click the <guibutton>Configure Interface...</guibutton> button. </para></step>
            <step>
                <para> 
                    Enter the relevant details of the connection like DHCP or Static IP address, or the wireless network name (in case of a wireless connection). Click <guibutton>OK</guibutton> to accept the settings. 
                </para>
            </step>
            <step>
                <para>Sometimes it may be necessary to configure the DNS settings. If needed, select the <guibutton>Domain Name System</guibutton> tab to add edit or delete DNS Servers in the <guilabel>DNS
                        Servers</guilabel> list.</para>
            </step>
        </procedure>
        <para>To activate or deactivate network connections, do the following:</para>
        <procedure>
            <step>
                <para>
                    <menuchoice>
                        <guimenu>K-Menü</guimenu>
                        <guisubmenu>System Settings</guisubmenu>
                        <guimenuitem>Network Settings</guimenuitem>
                    </menuchoice>
                </para>
            </step>
            <step>
                <para>
                    Click on the <guibutton>Administrator Mode...</guibutton> and enter your user password to gain administrator privileges.</para></step>
            <step>
                <para>Select the <guilabel>Network Interfaces</guilabel> tab. Select the interface to enable/disable from the list, then click the <guibutton>Enable Interface</guibutton> or the <guibutton> Disable Interface</guibutton> button. </para></step>
        </procedure>
    </sect2>
    <sect2 status="writing">
        <title>Browse Network Computers</title>
        <procedure>
            <step>
                <para>To view computers on the network, choose
                    <menuchoice>
                        <guimenu>System Menu</guimenu>
                        <guimenuitem>Remote Places</guimenuitem>
                    </menuchoice>
                    from the <application>Kicker</application> (the taskbar).
                </para>
            </step>
            <step>
                <para>You may need to enter a username and password, and a domain. You should obtain these from your network administrator.
                </para>
            </step>
        </procedure>
        <note>
          <para>
            Windows PCs sharing files on a local network can be found in <emphasis>Samba Shares</emphasis>.
          </para>
        </note>
    </sect2>
    <sect2 id="web-konqueror" status="complete">
        <title>Web Browser</title>
        <para>Kubuntu comes with a very powerful web browser, file management tool and network browser, called <application> Konqueror</application>. <application> Konqueror</application> can support all major web protocols, and allows basic plugins for Macromedia Flash, and Real Media. When you first start up Kubuntu, <application>Konqueror</application> will be in the bottom panel (known as the "kicker"). It may also be invoked through the K-menu by clicking
            <menuchoice>
                <guimenu>K-Menu</guimenu>
                <guisubmenu>Internet</guisubmenu>
                <guimenuitem>Web Browser (Konqueror)</guimenuitem>
            </menuchoice>
        </para>
        <para>
            Alternatively, the powerful and secure <application>Mozilla
                Firefox</application> web browser may be obtained in addition
            to Konqueror. <application>Mozilla Firefox</application> features
            tabbed browsing, pop-up blocking, in-built search facilities, live
            bookmarks and more. Also supported are popular plug-ins such as
            Java, Macromedia Flash, and Real Player just
            to name a few. <application>Mozilla Firefox</application> is not
            installed in Kubuntu by default. <application>Mozilla
                Firefox</application> can be obtained by installing the
              <application>firefox</application> package (see <xref linkend="add-applications"/>).
        </para>
        <para>
            After installation, it can be launched from 
            <menuchoice>
                <guimenu>K-Menu</guimenu>
                <guisubmenu>Internet</guisubmenu>
                <guimenuitem>Firefox Web Browser</guimenuitem>
            </menuchoice> from the desktop menu system.
        </para>
        <note>
          <para>
            <application>Mozilla Firefox</application> has many <emphasis>Extensions</emphasis> available. <application>Konqueror</application>, on the other, is much more tightly integrated into <application>KDE</application>.
          </para>
        </note>
        <sect3 status="complete">
            <sect3info>
                <authorblurb>
                     <para>Verified by asking in #kubuntu-offtopic</para>
                </authorblurb>
            </sect3info>
            <title>Macromedia Flash for Konqueror</title>
            <procedure>
                <para>
                    The following instructions are only for <emphasis>i386</emphasis> computers.
                </para>
                <step>
                    <para>To view flash graphics from the Konqueror web
                        browser, you need to install the
                        <application>flashplugin-nonfree</application> package
                        from the <emphasis>Multiverse</emphasis> repository
                        (see <xref linkend="add-applications"/>).
                    </para>
                </step>
                <step>
                    <para>To download and install the plugin, enter the following command in a terminal:<screen>sudo update-flashplugin</screen></para>
                </step>
                <step>
                    <para>The plug-in will be available the next time you start <application>Konqueror</application>.</para>
                </step>
            </procedure>
        </sect3>
        <sect3 status="complete">
            <title>How do I change Konqueror back to the default KDE profiles?</title>
            <para>
            Kubuntu comes with a simplified Konqueror profile to make things
            more user friendly compared to default KDE. To get back to the
            default KDE profiles:
        </para>
        <procedure>
            <step>
                <para>
                    Open a terminal by choosing 
                    <menuchoice>
                        <guimenu>K-Menu</guimenu>
                        <guisubmenu>System</guisubmenu>
                        <guimenuitem>Konsole (Terminal Program)</guimenuitem>
                    </menuchoice>
                    from the desktop menu system.
                </para>
            </step>
            <step>
                <para>
                Execute the following commands
                <screen>
sudo rm -r /usr/share/kubuntu-default-settings/kde-profile/default/share/apps/konqueror
sudo cp /usr/share/apps/konqueror/konqueror-orig.rc /usr/share/apps/konqueror/konqueror.rc
</screen>
                </para>
            </step>
    </procedure>
        </sect3>
    </sect2>
    <sect2 id="email" status="complete">
        <title>Email</title>
        <para>The <application>Kontact</application> groupware suite can handle all your email, contacts, calendar events, todo lists, newsgroups, notes and RSS/Atom feeds. <application>Kontact</application> can be launched by clicking
            <menuchoice>
                <guimenu>K-Menu</guimenu>
                <guisubmenu>Office</guisubmenu>
                <guimenuitem>Personal Information Manager (Kontact) </guimenuitem>
            </menuchoice> 
            from the desktop menu system.</para>
        <para>Alternatively, the <application>Mozilla Thunderbird</application> email
          client is available. To install this popular email client, install the <application>mozilla-thunderbird</application> package (see <xref linkend="add-applications"/>).</para>
        <para>To start <application>Thunderbird</application>, choose
            <menuchoice>
                <guimenu>K-Menu</guimenu>
                <guisubmenu>Internet</guisubmenu>
                <guimenuitem>Thunderbird Mail Client</guimenuitem>
            </menuchoice> from the desktop menu system.
        </para>
        <sect3 id="email-client-mozilla" status="review">
            <title>Change the preferred email client to
                <application>Mozilla Thunderbird</application></title>
            <procedure>
                <step>
                    <para>Choose 
                        <menuchoice>
                            <guimenu>K-Menu</guimenu>
                            <guisubmenu>System Settings</guisubmenu>
                            <guisubmenu>User Account</guisubmenu>
                        </menuchoice>.
                    </para>
                </step>
                <step>
                    <para>
                        In the <guilabel> User Account, </guilabel>click the <guimenuitem>Preferred Applications</guimenuitem> and click the <guibutton> Email Client</guibutton> and select the <guilabel>Use a different email client</guilabel> option. 
                    </para>
                </step>
                <step>
                    <para>In the <guilabel>Use a different email client</guilabel> text box, type
                        <userinput>
                            <command>mozilla-thunderbird %s</command></userinput>, then click <guibutton>Apply</guibutton> to save your settings. 
                    </para>
                </step>
            </procedure>
        </sect3>
    </sect2>
    <sect2 id="news-readers" status="complete">
        <title>News Readers</title>
        <sect3 status="complete">
            <title>Akregator Feed Reader</title>
            <para>
                <application>Akregator</application> is a fast and intuitive feed reader program which is installed by default in Kubuntu. <application>Akregator</application> can be launched as a standalone application by choosing
                <menuchoice>
                    <guimenu>K-menu</guimenu>
                    <guisubmenu>Internet</guisubmenu>
                    <guimenuitem>Akregator (RSS Feed Reader)</guimenuitem>
                </menuchoice> from the Desktop Menu System.
            </para>
            <para>
                <application>Akregator</application>  is also available as a Kontact Component.  Launch Kontact by choosing 
                <menuchoice>
                    <guimenu>K-menu</guimenu>
                    <guisubmenu>Office</guisubmenu>
                    <guimenuitem>Kontact (Personal Information Manager)</guimenuitem>
                </menuchoice> from the Desktop Menu System.
                Click the <guilabel>Feeds</guilabel> button on the sidebar at the left to access and configure the News Reader.
            </para>
        </sect3>
        <sect3 status="complete">
            <title>Knode News Reader</title>
            <para>The default newsreader for Kubuntu applications is in the <application>Kontact</application> application. It provides the capability to install and download your favorite newsgroups and manage their content. However, the news reader component is not installed by default.</para>
            <procedure>
                <step>
                    <para>Install the <application>knode</application> package from the <emphasis>Universe</emphasis> repository (see <xref linkend="extra-repositories"/>).</para>
                </step>
                <step>
                    <para>
                        Launch Kontact by choosing 
                        <menuchoice>
                            <guimenu>K-menu</guimenu>
                            <guisubmenu>Office</guisubmenu>
                            <guimenuitem>Kontact (Personal Information Manager)</guimenuitem>
                        </menuchoice> from the Desktop Menu System.
                    </para>
                </step>
                <step>
                    <para>
                        Click the <guilabel>News</guilabel> button on the sidebar at the left to access and configure the News Reader.
                    </para>
                </step>
            </procedure>
        </sect3>
    </sect2>
    <sect2 id="web-development" status="complete">
        <title>Web Development</title>
        <sect3 status="complete">
            <title>Quanta Plus</title>
            <para><application>Quanta Plus</application> is a powerful editor for web designers and programmers. <application> Quanta Plus </application>supports many programming and markup languages, and includes many utilities for designers and programmers.
            </para>
            <procedure>
                <step>
                    <para>Install the <application>Quanta Plus</application> package (see <xref linkend="add-applications"/>).</para>
                </step>
                <step><para>To start <application>Quanta Plus</application>, choose
                        <menuchoice>
                            <guimenu>K-Menu</guimenu>
                            <guisubmenu>Development</guisubmenu>
                            <guisubmenu>Web Development</guisubmenu>
                            <guimenuitem>Quanta Plus (Web Development Environment)</guimenuitem>
                    </menuchoice></para>
                </step>
            </procedure>
        </sect3>
        <sect3 status="complete">
            <title>NVU Web Authoring System</title>
            <para><application>NVU</application> is a <emphasis>WYSIWYG</emphasis> (What You See Is What You Get) graphical web design application, similar to Dreamweaver.</para>
            <procedure>
                <step>
                    <para>Install the <application>nvu</application> package from the <emphasis>Universe</emphasis> repository (see <xref linkend="extra-repositories"/>).</para>
                </step>
                <step>
                    <para>To start <application>Nvu</application>, choose
                        <menuchoice>
                            <guimenu>K-Menu</guimenu>
                            <guisubmenu>Development</guisubmenu>
                            <guimenuitem>Nvu</guimenuitem>
                        </menuchoice> from the desktop menu system.
                    </para>
                </step>
            </procedure>
        </sect3>
    </sect2>
    <sect2 id="chat-internet" status="complete">
        <title>Chat</title>
        <sect3 id="instant-messaging" status="complete">
            <title>Kopete</title>
            <para>Kopete is the default instant messenger client in Kubuntu.
                With Kopete you can talk to people who use: AIM/ICQ,
                Gadu-Gadu, Groupwise, IRC, Jabber, MSN, SMS and Yahoo.
                The ability to use one client instead of one per network is a great
                benefit and allows you to have all of your buddies in one
                window. To start <application>Kopete</application>, choose
                <menuchoice>
                    <guimenu>K-menu</guimenu>
                    <guisubmenu>Internet</guisubmenu>
                    <guimenuitem>Kopete (Instant Messenger)</guimenuitem>
                </menuchoice> from the desktop menu system.
            </para>
        </sect3>
        <sect3 status="complete">
            <title>Konversation</title>
            <para> Konversation is a client for the Internet Relay Chat (IRC) protocol. It has a clean and easy to use interface. To start <application>Konversation</application>, choose 
                <menuchoice>
                    <guimenu>K-menu</guimenu>
                    <guisubmenu>Internet</guisubmenu>
                    <guimenuitem>Konversation (Instant Messenger)</guimenuitem>
                </menuchoice> from the desktop menu system.
            </para>
        </sect3>
    </sect2>
    <sect2 id="P2P" status="complete">
        <title>Peer To Peer</title>
        <sect3 status="complete">
            <title>BitTorrent</title>
            <para>No default bit torrent capability is installed with Kubuntu. However, you may install <application>Ktorrent</application> from the universe repositories. Be sure that the universe repository is enabled and download it via Adept (See <xref linkend="extra-repositories"/>).
            </para>
        </sect3>
        <sect3 status="complete">
            <title>aMule File Sharing Client</title>
            <procedure>
		<para> aMule is a peer to peer (P2P) application for the ed2k network, from which you can download a variety of files.</para>
                <step>
                    <para>Install the <application>amule</application> package from the <emphasis>Universe</emphasis> repository (see <xref linkend="extra-repositories"/>).</para>
                </step>
                <step>
                    <para>To open <application>aMule</application>, choose 
                        <menuchoice>
                            <guimenu>K-menu</guimenu>
                            <guisubmenu>Internet</guisubmenu>
                            <guimenuitem>amule</guimenuitem>
                        </menuchoice> from the desktop menu system.
                    </para>
                </step>
            </procedure>
        </sect3>
        <sect3 status="writing">
            <title>Apollon</title>
            <para>
                <application>Apollon</application> is an easy to use peer to peer client for the KDE Desktop. It supports the Gnutella, OpenFT, and FastTrack networks. This makes installing applications like <application>Limewire</application> redundant.
            </para>
            <procedure>
                <step>
                    <para>Install <application>Apollon</application> and <application>gift</application> packages from the <emphasis>Universe</emphasis> repository (see <xref linkend="extra-repositories"/>).
                    </para>
                </step>
                <step>
                    <para>
                        Configure the <application>giFT</application> daemon by, opening a <application>Konsole</application> and run the command <screen>gift-setup</screen> and follow the instructions on the screen.
                    </para>
                    <note><para>Make sure you enable the OpenFT and Gnutella plugins by typing <emphasis>OpenFT:Gnutella</emphasis> in the plugin section.</para></note> 
                </step>
                <step>
                    <para>
                        See the following files for examples:
                        <orderedlist>
                            <listitem>
                                <para>
                                    <ulink url="../sample/giftd.conf">$HOME/.giFT/giftd.conf</ulink>
                                </para>
                            </listitem>

                            <listitem>
                                <para>
                                    <ulink url="../sample/OpenFT.conf">$HOME/.giFT/OpenFT/OpenFT.conf</ulink>
                                </para>
                            </listitem>

                            <listitem>
                                <para>
                                    <ulink url="../sample/Gnutella.conf">$HOME/.giFT/Gnutella/Gnutella.conf</ulink>.
                                </para>
                            </listitem>
                        </orderedlist>
                    </para>
                </step>
            </procedure>
        </sect3>
    </sect2>
</sect1>
<sect1 id="office" status="complete">
    <title>Office</title>
        <sect2 status="complete">
            <title>OpenOffice.org Suite</title>
            <para>
                OpenOffice.org is a suite of applications to support word processing, presentations, spreadsheets, drawing and complex math documents. The suite is the open source equivalent of the Microsoft Office Suite. For details about the OpenOffice.org, visit the <ulink url="http://www.openoffice.org">OpenOffice.org homepage</ulink>.
            </para>
            <orderedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para>
                      Open Office Writer is a fully featured word processor similar to Microsoft Word that can create simple or complex documents. Writer can open most Microsoft Word documents and can save in the .doc format. OpenOffice.org Writer can be launched from   
                        <menuchoice>
                            <guimenu>K-Menu</guimenu>
                            <guisubmenu>Office</guisubmenu>
                            <guimenuitem>OpenOffice.org Writer</guimenuitem>
                        </menuchoice>
                    </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>
                        OpenOffice.org Impress is the functional equivalent of PowerPoint, and provides the capability to create slide presentations. Most PowerPoint files may be opened and edited in Impress.
                        OpenOffice.org Impress can be launched from   
                        <menuchoice>
                            <guimenu>K-Menu</guimenu>
                            <guisubmenu>Office</guisubmenu>
                            <guimenuitem>OpenOffice.org Impress</guimenuitem>
                        </menuchoice>
                    </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>
                        OpenOffice.org Calc is a fully featured spreadsheet program with similar functions found in Microsoft Excel. The module supports multiple spreadsheets, built-in functions and can read most Microsoft Excel documents.
                        OpenOffice.org Calc can be launched from   
                        <menuchoice>
                            <guimenu>K-Menu</guimenu>
                            <guisubmenu>Office</guisubmenu>
                            <guimenuitem>OpenOffice.org Calc</guimenuitem>
                        </menuchoice>
                    </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>
                        OpenOffice.org Draw provides complex functionality to allow the creation of drawings, diagrams, charts, and other business presentations. The program is object oriented and allows for layering of various panes of work.
                        OpenOffice.org Draw can be launched from   
                        <menuchoice>
                            <guimenu>K-Menu</guimenu>
                            <guisubmenu>Office</guisubmenu>
                            <guimenuitem>OpenOffice.org Draw</guimenuitem>
                        </menuchoice>
                    </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>
                        OpenOffice.org Math allows the user to create and assemble math-oriented documents. There are special functions here that allow the creation of mathematical formulas and table nomenclature not easily assembled in the standard Writer application.
                        OpenOffice.org Math can be launched from   
                        <menuchoice>
                            <guimenu>K-Menu</guimenu>
                            <guisubmenu>Office</guisubmenu>
                            <guimenuitem>OpenOffice.org Math</guimenuitem>
                        </menuchoice>
                    </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>
                        OpenOffice.org Base allows the user to manipulate database data from within OpenOffice.org, like Microsoft Access. 
                        OpenOffice.org Base can be launched from   
                        <menuchoice>
                            <guimenu>K-Menu</guimenu>
                            <guisubmenu>Office</guisubmenu>
                            <guimenuitem>OpenOffice.org Base</guimenuitem>
                        </menuchoice>
                    </para>
                </listitem>
            </orderedlist>
        </sect2>
        <sect2 status="complete">
            <title>KMyMoney2 Personal Finance</title>
            <para>KMyMoney2 is an excellent personal and/or business cash management application similar to Quicken or Microsoft Money. Quicken QIF import and export is supported within accounts so KMyMoney2 can read files exported from other programs or downloaded from online banking institutions.
            </para>
            <procedure>
                <step>
                    <para>Install the <application>kmymoney2</application> package from the <emphasis>Universe</emphasis> repository (see <xref linkend="extra-repositories"/>).</para>
                </step>
                <step>
                    <para>To open <application>Kymoney</application>, choose 
                        <menuchoice>
                            <guimenu>K-menu</guimenu>
                            <guisubmenu>Office</guisubmenu>
                            <guimenuitem>KmyMoney</guimenuitem>
                        </menuchoice> from the Desktop Menu System.
                    </para>
                </step>
            </procedure>
        </sect2>
        <sect2 status="complete">
            <title>Kivio Flowchart and Diagram Editor</title>
            <para>
                <application>Kivio</application> is a flowchart and diagram editor for creating and editing organizational charts, flowcharts, ERDs, or other kinds of diagrams. It is analagous to Gnome <application>Dia</application> and Microsoft Visio.
            </para>
            <procedure>
                <step>
                    <para>
                        Install the <application>kivio</application> package using <application>Adept</application> (see <xref linkend="adept"/>). 
                    </para>
                </step>
                <step>
                    <para>Launch <application>Kivio</application>, by choosing
                        <menuchoice>
                            <guimenu>K-Menu</guimenu>
                            <guisubmenu>Office</guisubmenu>
                            <guimenuitem>Kivio</guimenuitem>
                        </menuchoice>
                    </para>
                </step>
            </procedure>
        </sect2>
    </sect1>
    <sect1 id="graphics" status="complete">
        <title>Graphics &amp; Drawing</title>
        <para>Kubuntu has some very powerful, world-class graphics and drawing applications available.</para>
        <sect2 id="krita" status="complete">
            <title>Krita</title>
            <para><application>Krita</application> lets you draw, paint, edit images, and much more! Krita
                includes the functionality and plug-ins of other famous image
                editing and processing programs.
            </para>
            <para>Krita is installed in Kubuntu by default. Launch Krita by selecting 
                <menuchoice>
                    <guimenu>K-Menu</guimenu>
                    <guisubmenu>Graphics</guisubmenu>
                    <guimenuitem>Krita (Image Manipulation Program)</guimenuitem>
                </menuchoice>
            </para>
            <para>More information is available from the <ulink url="http://www.koffice.org/krita/">Krita homepage.</ulink>
            </para>
        </sect2>
        <sect2 id="inkscape" status="complete">
            <title>Inkscape Vector Graphics Editor</title>
            <para><application>Inkscape</application> is a powerful editor for working with the SVG (Scalable Vector Graphics) format.
            </para>
            <procedure>
                <step>
                    <para>Install the <application>inkscape</application> package (see <xref linkend="add-applications"/>).
                    </para>
                </step>
                <step>
                    <para>To start <application>Inkscape</application> choose 
                        <menuchoice>
                            <guimenu>K-Menu</guimenu>
                            <guisubmenu>Graphics</guisubmenu>
                            <guimenuitem>InkScape Vector Illustrator</guimenuitem>
                        </menuchoice>
                    </para>
                </step>
            </procedure>
        </sect2>
        <sect2 id="blender" status="complete">
            <title>Blender 3d Modeler</title>
            <para><application>Blender</application> is an integrated 3d suite for modeling, animation, rendering, post-production, interactive creation and playback (games).
            </para>
            <procedure>
                <step>
                    <para>Install the <application>blender</application> package (see <xref linkend="add-applications"/>).
                    </para>
                </step>
                <step>
                    <para>To start <application>Blender</application>, choose 
                        <menuchoice>
                            <guimenu>K-Menu</guimenu>
                            <guisubmenu>Graphics</guisubmenu>
                            <guimenuitem>Blender 3D Modeler</guimenuitem>
                        </menuchoice>
                    </para>
                </step>
            </procedure>
        </sect2>
        <sect2 status="complete">
            <title>Scribus Desktop Publishing Application</title>
            <procedure>
                <step>
                    <para>Install the <application>scribus</application> package (see <xref linkend="extra-repositories"/>).</para>
                </step>
                <step>
                    <para>To install additional templates, install the <application>scribus-template</application> package from the <emphasis>Universe</emphasis> repository (see <xref linkend="extra-repositories"/>).</para>
                </step>
                <step>
                    <para>To start <application>Scribus</application>, choose
                        <menuchoice>
                            <guimenu>K-Menu</guimenu>
                            <guisubmenu>Office</guisubmenu>
                            <guimenuitem>Scribus (Page Layout)</guimenuitem>
                        </menuchoice>
                    </para>
                </step>
            </procedure>
        </sect2>
    </sect1>
    <sect1 id="games" status="complete">
        <title>Games</title>
        <sect2 status="complete">
            <title>Frozen-Bubble</title>
            <para>In <application>Frozen-Bubble</application> you attempt to shoot bubbles into groups of the same color to cause them to pop.
            </para>
            <procedure>
                <step>
                    <para>Install the <application>frozen-bubble</application> package from the <emphasis>Universe</emphasis> repository (see <xref linkend="extra-repositories"/>).</para>
                </step>
                <step>
                    <para>
                        To start <application>Frozen-Bubble</application>, choose
                        <menuchoice>
                            <guimenu>K-Menu</guimenu>
                            <guisubmenu>Games</guisubmenu>
                            <guisubmenu>Arcade</guisubmenu>
                            <guimenuitem>Frozen-Bubble</guimenuitem>
                        </menuchoice>.
                    </para>
                </step>
            </procedure>
        </sect2>
        <sect2 status="complete">
            <title>PlanetPenguin Racer</title>
            <para>Race Tux, the Linux mascot, down a snow and ice-covered mountain as quickly as possible, avoiding the trees and rocks that will slow you down. Don't forget to grap all the fish!
            </para>
            <para>
                <note>
                    <para>Ensure you have hardware accelerated 3D drivers installed for your video card.
                        For more information, see <xref linkend="hardware"/>.
                    </para>
                </note>
            </para>
            <procedure>
                <step>
                    <para>Install the <application>planetpenguin-racer</application> package from the <emphasis>Universe</emphasis> repository (see <xref linkend="extra-repositories"/>).</para>
                </step>
                <step>
                    <para>To start <application>PlanetPenguin Racer</application>, choose
                        <menuchoice>
                            <guimenu>K-Menu</guimenu>
                            <guisubmenu>Games</guisubmenu>
                            <guisubmenu>Arcade</guisubmenu>
                            <guimenuitem>PlanetPenguin-Racer</guimenuitem>
                        </menuchoice>.
                    </para>
                </step>
            </procedure>
        </sect2>
        <sect2 status="complete">
            <title>Scorched3D</title>
            <para>Scorched3D is a 3D remake of Worms/Scorched Earth.
                <note>
                    <para>Ensure you have hardware accelerated 3D drivers installed for your video card.
                        For more information, see <xref linkend="hardware"/>.</para>
                </note>
            </para>
            <procedure>
                <step>
                    <para>Install the <application>scorched3d</application> package from the <emphasis>Universe</emphasis> repository (see <xref linkend="extra-repositories"/>).</para>
                </step>
                <step>
                    <para>To start <application>Scorched3D</application>, choose
                        <menuchoice>
                            <guimenu>K-Menu</guimenu>
                            <guisubmenu>Games</guisubmenu>
                            <guisubmenu>Arcade</guisubmenu>
                            <guimenuitem>Scorched 3d</guimenuitem>
                        </menuchoice>.
                    </para>
                </step>
            </procedure>
        </sect2>
        <sect2 status="complete">
            <title>Suggested Games</title> 
            <para>The following is a list of games that fellow Kubuntu users suggest. All of them are available for installation using the <application>Adept Package Manager</application> from the <emphasis>Universe</emphasis> repository (See <xref linkend="extra-repositories"/>).
            </para>
            <para>
                <itemizedlist>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>armagetron - 3D Tron-like high speed game</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>wesnoth - fantasy turn-based strategy game
                        </para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>neverball - 3D arcade games: neverball and neverputt</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>atlantik - KDE client for Monopoly-like network games
                        </para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>kdegames - A package containing several small, and addicting games</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>freeciv - Civilization turn based strategy game</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>bzflag - a 3D first person tank battle game
                        </para>
                    </listitem>
                </itemizedlist>
            </para>
            <para>There are also two "classic" text based dungeon crawl games:
            <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Nethack</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Crawl</para>
                </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
            </para>
            <note>
                <para>Remember, these 2 games are text based, which means they MUST be run inside the terminal.
                </para>
            </note>
            <para>All of these games will install themselves to your KDE menu, but can always run them from the command line by typing in the name of the game, and pressing enter.
            </para>
        </sect2>
        <sect2 status="complete">
            <title>Windows Games</title>
            <para>Many games which are available for Windows can be run on Linux through special compatibility layers like <application>Wine</application> and <application>Cedega</application>.</para>
            <procedure>
                <step>
                    <para>For information about Wine, see <ulink url="&wiki-Wine;">the Ubuntu wiki</ulink>.
                    </para>
                </step>
                <step>
                    <para>
                        For information about Cedega, see <ulink url="&wiki-Cedega;">the Ubuntu wiki</ulink>. See the <ulink url="http://www.linux-gamers.net/modules/wiwimod/index.php?page=HOWTO%20Cedega%20CVS"> Cedega CVS Howto</ulink> for instructions on compiling and installing Cedega.
                    </para>
                </step>
            </procedure>
        </sect2>
    </sect1>
    <sect1 id="programming" status="complete">
        <title>Programming</title>
        <sect2 status="complete">
            <title>Basic Compilers</title>
            <procedure>
                <para>In order to be able to compile programs, some extra packages are necessary. These can be installed all in one go, as follows:
                </para>
                <step>
                    <para>Install the <application>build-essential</application> package (see <xref linkend="add-applications"/>).
                    </para>
                </step>
            </procedure>
        </sect2>
        <sect2 id="java" status="complete">
            <title>Java Runtime Environment (1.5)</title>
            <note>
                <para>
                    The following instructions are only for <emphasis>i386</emphasis> and <emphasis>amd64</emphasis> computers. For <emphasis>PowerPC</emphasis> machines, please look at the <ulink url="https://wiki.ubuntu.com/JavaPPC">Ubuntu Wiki.</ulink>
                </para>
            </note>
            <procedure>
                <step>
                    <para>Install the <application>sun-java5-bin</application> package from the <emphasis>Multiverse</emphasis> repository (see <xref linkend="extra-repositories"/>).</para>
                </step>
                <step>
                    <para>
                        Some websites require the <application>Java</application> plugin for Mozilla Firefox. To install the java plugin, install the <application>sun-java5-plugin</application> package (for i386 machines) or the <application>j2re-1.4-mozilla-plugin</application> package (for amd64 machines) from the <emphasis>Multiverse</emphasis> repository.</para>
                </step>
            </procedure>
        </sect2>
        <sect2 status="complete">
            <title>Development Tools</title>
            <para>
                This section has a list of handy open source development
                tools for use on Kubuntu such as Integrated Development
                Environments and powerful Editors. Most of these applications
                can be installed by using <application>Adept</application>
                (see <xref linkend="add-applications"/>).
            </para>
            <itemizedlist>
                <listitem><para><ulink url="http://www.kdevelop.org/">KDevelop</ulink> is an IDE for KDE which supports many programming languages.</para></listitem>
                <listitem><para><ulink url="http://www.die-offenbachs.de/detlev/eric3.html">Eric</ulink> is a full featured Python and Ruby IDE.</para></listitem>
                <listitem><para><ulink url="http://www.riverbankcomputing.co.uk/pyqt/">PyQt</ulink> is a set of Python bindings for the Qt toolkit.</para></listitem>
                <listitem><para><ulink url="http://www.trolltech.com/products/qt/designer.html">Qt Designer</ulink> is the User Interface designer for building KDE applications. </para></listitem>
                <listitem><para><ulink url="http://www.python.org/idle/">IDLE</ulink> is the Python IDE built with the Tkinter GUI toolkit.</para></listitem>
                <listitem><para><ulink url="http://www.monodevelop.com/Main_Page">MonoDevelop</ulink> is an IDE for writing mono/.net applications in C# and other languages.</para></listitem>
                <listitem><para><ulink url="http://www.bazaar-ng.org/">Bazaar-NG</ulink> is a distributed version control system used for Ubuntu development.</para></listitem>
                <listitem><para><ulink url="http://www.eclipse.org/">Eclipse</ulink> is an IDE for Java and other programming languages. It forms the basis for closed-source programs such as JBuilder.</para></listitem>
                <listitem><para><ulink url="http://www.netbeans.org/index.html">NetBeans</ulink> is a Java IDE that features support for CVS and a form builder.</para></listitem>
                <listitem><para><ulink url="http://bluefish.openoffice.nl/index.html">Bluefish</ulink> is a powerful editor for experienced web designers and programmers.</para></listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
        </sect2>
        <sect2 status="complete">
            <title>Programming Documentation</title>	
            <para>This is a list of useful documentation for programming with Kubuntu.</para>
            <sect3 id="diveintopython" status="writing">
                <title>Dive Into Python</title>
                <para><application>Dive Into Python</application> is a book on
                    learning how to program in the preferred Kubuntu language,
                    Python. Aimed at programmers with some previous
                    experience, it comes installed with every Kubuntu
                    installation.
                </para>
                <para>
                    You can read <application>Dive Into Python</application>
                    <ulink url="file:///usr/share/doc/diveintopython/html/toc/index.html">here</ulink>.
                </para>
            </sect3>
            <sect3 id="qt3doc" status="review">
                <title>Qt3 Documentation</title>
                <para>
                    The Qt3 Documentation package provides the complete
                    reference to programming in Qt.
                </para>
                <procedure>
                    <step>
                        <para>Install the <application>qt3-doc</application> package (see <xref linkend="add-applications"/>).
                        </para>
                    </step>
                    <step>
                        <para>To access the documentation, visit
                            <ulink url="file:///usr/share/doc/qt3-doc/html/index.html">Qt3
                                Documentation Index</ulink>.
                        </para>
                    </step>
                </procedure>
            </sect3>
        </sect2>
    </sect1>
</chapter>

