<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.3//EN" 
	"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.3/docbookx.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % globalent SYSTEM "../../../libs/global.ent">
%globalent;
<!ENTITY % cdo-C SYSTEM "../../../libs/cdo-C.ent">
%cdo-C;
<!ENTITY % gnome-menus-C SYSTEM "../../../ubuntu/libs/gnome-menus-C.ent">
%gnome-menus-C;
<!ENTITY % xinclude SYSTEM "../../../libs/xinclude.mod">
%xinclude;
<!ENTITY language "en">
<!ENTITY ubuntu '<phrase>Ubuntu</phrase>'>
]>
	<article id="office" status="complete">
	<articleinfo>
		<title>Office</title>
    	&legalnotice;
	</articleinfo>
		<para>Ubuntu comes with a variety of software for performing office tasks &#8212; word processing and publishing, spreadsheets, and presentations.</para>

        <sect1 id="openoffice-suite" status="complete">
            <title>OpenOffice.org Suite</title>
            <para>
		    The default office application is <application>OpenOffice.org</application>. Compatible with other major office suites including Microsoft Windows, OpenOffice.org is free to download, use, and distribute. It includes:</para>
	    <para>
For more details about the OpenOffice.org suite, visit <ulink url="http://www.openoffice.org">OpenOffice.org homepage</ulink>.
	    </para>
        <orderedlist>
				<listitem><para>Writer – a word processor you can use for anything from writing a quick letter to producing an entire book. It can be started with &openoffice-writer;.</para></listitem>
				<listitem><para>Spreadsheet – a powerful spreadsheet with all the tools you need to calculate, analyse, and present your data in numerical reports or sizzling graphics. It can be started with &openoffice-spreadsheet;</para></listitem>
				<listitem><para>Presentation – the fastest, most powerful way to create effective multimedia presentations. It can be started with &openoffice-presentation;</para></listitem>
				<listitem><para>Draw – lets you produce everything from simple diagrams to dynamic 3D illustrations. It can be started from inside another Openoffice.org program.</para></listitem>
				<listitem><para>Database – lets you manipulate databases seamlessly. Create and modify tables, forms, queries, and reports, all from within OpenOffice.org. It can be started with &openoffice-base;</para></listitem>
				<listitem><para>Mathematical function creator – lets you create mathematical equations with a graphic user interface or by directly typing your formulas into the equation editor. It can be started from inside another Openoffice.org program.</para></listitem>
            </orderedlist>
        </sect1>
		<sect1 status="complete">
			<title>GNOME Office</title>
				<para>The GNOME desktop features a separate office suite. These programs are generally lighter and faster than the programs in the <application>OpenOffice.org suite</application>, and have fewer features as a result. But this may be exactly what you want. The Suite has excellent compatibility with other major Office suites, such as Microsoft Office.</para>
				<para>The GNOME Office Suite includes the following software:</para>
					<itemizedlist>
						<listitem><para>A word processor (<application>Abiword</application>);</para></listitem>
						<listitem><para>A spreadsheet (<application>Gnumeric</application>);</para></listitem>
						<listitem><para>A database management program (<application>GNOME-DB</application>);</para></listitem>
						<listitem><para>A diagram editor (<application>Dia</application>);</para></listitem>
						<listitem><para>Two graphics applications (<application>Inkscape</application> and <application>The GIMP</application>); and</para></listitem>
						<listitem><para>A project management application (<application>Planner</application>).</para></listitem>
					</itemizedlist>
				<note><para>Each of these applications can also be installed separately.</para></note>
				<para>To install the GNOME Office suite:</para>
				<procedure>
					<step><para>Install the <application>gnome-office</application> package from the <quote>Universe</quote> repository (see <ulink type="help" url="ghelp:add-applications">Add Applications</ulink>).</para></step>
					<step>
						<para>The Office applications can then be found in the menu at 
							<menuchoice>
								<guimenu>Applications</guimenu>
								<guisubmenu>Office</guisubmenu>
							</menuchoice>, and the Graphics applications can be found at 
							<menuchoice>
								<guimenu>Applications</guimenu>
								<guisubmenu>Graphics</guisubmenu>
							</menuchoice>.
						</para>
					</step>
				</procedure>
		</sect1>

			<sect1 status="complete">
				<title>GnuCash Accounting Application</title>
					<para><application>GnuCash</application> is a program to manage your personal or business finances. <application>GnuCash</application> lets you track bank accounts, stocks, income and expenses. As quick and intuitive as a checkbook register, it is based on professional accounting principles to ensure balanced books and accurate reports.</para>
					<itemizedlist>
						<listitem><para><ulink url="http://gnucash.org/">GnuCash Web site</ulink></para></listitem>
					</itemizedlist>
					<para>To use <application>GnuCash</application>:</para>
					<procedure>
						<step>
							<para>Install the <application>gnucash</application> package from the <quote>Universe</quote> repository (see <ulink type="help" url="ghelp:add-applications">Add Applications</ulink>).</para>
						</step>
						<step>
							<para>To start <application>GnuCash</application>, choose &gnucash;.</para>
						</step>
					</procedure>
			</sect1>
			<sect1 status="complete">
				<title>Scribus Desktop Publishing Application</title>
				<para><application>Scribus</application> is a professional desktop publishing program. For more information, see the <ulink url="http://www.scribus.net/">Scribus website</ulink>.</para>
				<procedure>
					<step>
						<para>Install the <application>scribus</application> package (see <ulink type="help" url="ghelp:add-applications">Add Applications</ulink>).</para>
					</step>
					<step>
						<para>To install additional templates, install the <application>scribus-template</application> package from the <quote>Universe</quote> repository (see <ulink type="help" url="ghelp:add-applications">Add Applications</ulink>).</para>
						<note><para>You will need to use <application>Synaptic Package Manager</application> to install this package</para></note>
					</step>
					<step>
						<para>To start <application>Scribus</application>, choose &scribus;.
						</para>
					</step>
				</procedure>
			</sect1>
			<sect1 status="complete">
				<title>Sending documents to other people</title>
				<para>Sometimes, you may wish to send a document to someone who is using a different operating system, such as <application>Microsoft Windows</application>. They may use an office application which is not capable of understanding the <emphasis>OpenDocument</emphasis> file type used by Ubuntu&apos;s default office suite (<application>OpenOffice.org</application>). This can cause confusion if they find that they are unable to open the document you sent.</para>
				<para>The solution to this problem is to save the document in a format which they can use before you send it.</para>
				<caution>
						<para>By saving your file in a different format, the way the document looks could be changed slightly. This is due to small differences between the way different programs read file formats. You may receive a warning message about this when trying to save a document in another format; it should be safe to press <guibutton>Yes</guibutton>, which will save the file in the new format you chose.</para>
				</caution>
				<para>The instructions given below are for <application>OpenOffice.org</application>:</para>
				<procedure>
					<step>
						<para>Open the document you wish to send using <application>OpenOffice.org</application>.</para>
					</step>
					<step>
						<para>Press <menuchoice><guimenuitem>File</guimenuitem><guimenuitem>Save As...</guimenuitem></menuchoice> and then press <guilabel>File type</guilabel>. A list of available file types should appear.</para>
					</step>
					<step>
						<para>Select an appropriate file type. For example, if you are sending your file to a user of <application>Microsoft Word</application>, the file type <guilabel>Microsoft Word 97/2000/XP</guilabel> is a sensible choice.</para>
					</step>
					
					<step>
						<para>Select a location to save the file in, then press <guibutton>Save</guibutton>.</para>
					</step>
					<step>
						<para>Send the file as normal, for example by attaching it to an email by pressing <menuchoice><guimenuitem>File</guimenuitem><guimenuitem>Send</guimenuitem><guimenuitem>Document as E-mail...</guimenuitem></menuchoice>.</para>
					</step>
				</procedure>
				<note>
						<para>A quick way of sending your document by email and in the <application>Microsoft Word</application> format from the <application>OpenOffice.org Word Processor</application> is to press <menuchoice><guimenuitem>File</guimenuitem><guimenuitem>Send</guimenuitem><guimenuitem>E-mail as Microsoft Word...</guimenuitem></menuchoice>. Equivalent commands are available for the other applications in the <application>OpenOffice.org</application> suite, such as <guilabel>E-mail as Microsoft Excel...</guilabel> in <application>OpenOffice.org Spreadsheet</application>.</para>
					</note>
			</sect1>
			<sect1 status="complete">
				<title>Finding clipart to use in documents</title>
				<para>Clipart is a picture or drawing used to illustrate a document. Follow the instructions below to install and use a selection of clipart in <application>OpenOffice.org</application>:</para>
				<procedure>
					<step>
						<para>Install the <application>openclipart-openoffice.org</application> package from the <quote>Universe</quote> repository (see <ulink url="../add-applications/add-applications.xml">Add Applications</ulink>).</para>
					<caution>
						<para>The <application>openclipart-openoffice.org</application> package is very large, so it could take a long time to download and install it.</para>
					</caution>
					</step>
					<step>
						<para>Open an <application>OpenOffice.org</application> application and press <menuchoice><guimenuitem>Tools</guimenuitem><guimenuitem>Gallery</guimenuitem></menuchoice>. A list of available clipart should appear.</para>
					</step>
					<step>
						<para>Browse the clipart until you find an item that you would like to use. To insert the item, either drag it into the document or right-click the item and press <menuchoice><guimenuitem>Insert</guimenuitem><guimenuitem>Copy</guimenuitem></menuchoice>.</para>
					</step>
				</procedure>
			</sect1>
	</article>
