<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.3//EN" 
 "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.3/docbookx.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % globalent SYSTEM "../../../libs/global.ent">
%globalent;
<!ENTITY % cdo-C SYSTEM "../../../libs/cdo-C.ent">
%cdo-C;
<!ENTITY % kde SYSTEM "../../libs/kde.ent">
%kde;
<!ENTITY % kde-menus-C SYSTEM "../../libs/kde-menus-C.ent">
%kde-menus-C;
<!ENTITY language "&EnglishAmerican;">
]>
<article id="art-about-kubuntu" status="review" lang="zh_TW">
	<articleinfo>
	<title>關於 Kubuntu</title>
	<legalnotice>
	<title>貢獻者與授權</title>
	<para>本文件由下列 Ubuntu 文件團隊的作者維護：</para>
		<itemizedlist>
			<listitem>
				<para>Jonathan Jesse</para>
			</listitem>
		</itemizedlist>
	<para>本文件由下列人士提供：</para>
		<itemizedlist>
			<listitem>
				<para>Matthew East</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para>Jerome Gotangco</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para>Jonathan Riddell</para>
			</listitem>
		</itemizedlist>
		<para>本文件採用雙重授權政策，包含 GNU 自由文件授權 (GFDL) 和創意公用相同方式分享 2.0 授權 (CC-BY-SA) 。</para>
		<para>在此授權下，你可以自由修改、增加和改進 Ubuntu 文件。所有衍生的作品必須採用一個以上的同等授權發佈。</para>
		<para>在此授權下，你可以自由修改、增加和改進 Ubuntu 文件的原始碼。所有衍生的作品必須採用一個以上的同等授權發佈。</para>
		<para>本文件發佈的目的是期望它有所用途，但不提供任何擔保﹔對免責條款裡提及的適銷性和用於某一特定目的適用性，也不承擔任何默示的擔保。</para>
		<para>本文件的附錄部分提供了上述兩份授權許可的副本，此外您可以經由下列網址獲取其線上版本：</para>
		<itemizedlist>
			<listitem>
				<para>&fdl-url;</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para>&cc-attrib;</para>
			</listitem>
		</itemizedlist>
	</legalnotice>
	&copyright;
	<authorgroup>
		&author-ubuntu-documentation-project;
	</authorgroup>
	<abstract>
		<para>本文件簡介 Kubuntu。它將會說明 Ubuntu 的哲學和根源，並且提供如何幫助 Ubuntu 以及使用 Ubuntu 時如何獲得幫助的相關資訊。</para>
	</abstract>
	&disclaimer;
	&publisher;
  </articleinfo>
 
 <para>Welcome to Kubuntu &distro-rev;: the &distro-version;
  	Release.</para>

 <para>Kubuntu is a user-friendly operating system based on KDE, the K
 Desktop Environment. With a predictable 6 month release cycle as part of
 the Ubuntu project, Kubuntu is the Linux distribution for
 everyone.</para>
  
 <para>Kubuntu 團隊對其使用者的承諾：</para>
 <itemizedlist>
 
  <listitem>
  
   <para>Kubuntu 充份運用 Ubuntu 的堅固基礎，並再加上最新版本的 KDE。我們是 Ubuntu 社群的一部份，使用他們的基建及支援。我們的任務是成為最好的 KDE 分發版本。</para>
    
  </listitem>
  
  <listitem>
  
   <para>Kubuntu 永遠免費，即使是「企業版」也無須額外費用，我們要把最好的工作成果免費提供給所有人，一視同仁。</para>
    
  </listitem>
  
  <listitem>
  
   <para>Kubuntu 包含了出色的翻譯和無障礙環境架構，唯有如此，自由軟體社群才能讓盡可能多的人使用 Kubuntu。</para>
    
  </listitem>
  
  <listitem>
  
   <para>Kubuntu 完全遵守開放原始軟體發展的原則；我們鼓勵人們使用、改進並散佈開放原始碼套件。</para>
   
  </listitem>
  
 </itemizedlist>
 
 <para id="aboutkubuntu03">Kubuntu includes more than 1,000 pieces of software, starting with Linux
  version &linux-kernel-version; and KDE &kde-version;, and covering every standard desktop application from word processing and
  spreadsheet to Internet access applications, web server software, email software, programming
  languages and tools, and of course, several games. </para>
  
 <sect1 id="wonderful-linux" status="review">
 
  <title>Linux 的美好世界</title>
  
  <para>Kubuntu uses the <quote>Linux</quote> kernel, the software which
   has come to define the worldwide movement to embrace open source
   software. Find out about Linux at <ulink url="&linuxorg;">Linux.org</ulink>
  </para>
  
  <sect2 id="sect-kubuntu-difference" status="review">
  
   <title>不同之處</title>
   
   <para>There are many Linux distributions (e.g., Redhat, SuSE,
    Debian, Mandriva) but Kubuntu distinguishes itself as a
    different kind of distribution. </para>
    
   <para>Built on the solid and advanced base of Ubuntu, the Kubuntu
    team aims to create a distribution that provides an up-to-date and
    coherent Linux system for desktop and server computing.
    Kubuntu includes a number of selected packages from Ubuntu and is
    based on Debian's powerful <quote>Adept</quote> package management
    system. Adept allows easy installation and clean removal of
    programs, as well as automatic download of extra packages to
    satisfy dependencies. Unlike most distributions that ship a wide
    range of software packages that may or may not be of quality,
    Kubuntu's core list of packages is reduced only to the most
    important applications. (Although for maximum choice, you may
    choose from over 10,000 packages ready to download, rather than
    being limited to the selected core.) </para>
    
   <para>注重品質，Kubuntu 提供了一個健壯、功能豐富的運算環境，既適合家用又適用於商業環境。本計劃花費了大量必要的時間，努力精益求精，每六個月就會發佈一個版本，以提供最新最強大的軟體。Kubuntu 支援各種形形色色的架構，包括 PC (Intel Pentium / AMD Athlon)、64 位元 PC (AMD64)、以及 Mac (PowerPC) 。</para>
    
  </sect2>
  
  <sect2 id="sect-about-KDE" status="review">
  
   <title>KDE for Ubuntu Users</title>
   
   <para>The default desktop environment for Kubuntu is KDE, a powerful Free Software graphical
    desktop environment for Linux and Unix workstations. It combines ease of use, contemporary
    functionality, and outstanding graphical design with the technological superiority of the Unix
    operating system. KDE is one of the two leading graphical desktop environments for Linux
    users. KDE sports an impressive array of easy to use, but powerful, graphical interface
    applications for users of all ages in both home and work environments. For developers, KDE
    provides a robust application development framework that enables rapid creation of first rate
    applications implementing cutting-edge technology. </para>
   
   <para>KDE is in many ways similar to GNOME, but there are a few distinct differences which
    distinguish KDE as a desktop environment. KDE uses C++ at its base, with Qt (the Q-toolkit),
    whereas GNOME, using GTK, is written in C. KDE is the older and most widely used
    desktop environment, and is known to stress more the importance of features, and more recently,
    usability. GNOME more notoriously prides itself on simplicity and ease of use.
    Popular criticisms of GNOME are that it's lacking in features and applications, while it's often
    commented that KDE has too many features which may themselves be hard to locate.</para>
   
    <para>Nevertheless, KDE and GNOME respectively target different audiences,
    and are fundamentally different in some respects, and the question of which
    desktop environment is superior is inherently a subjective opinion in many 
    ways. Because of this, to at least make a proper decision about which is 
    more suited to yourself, it is advised that you try them both out. 
    Thus, it is very easy to install GNOME from a Kubuntu distribution, and 
    equally easy to install KDE from an Ubuntu setup. </para>
  </sect2>
  
  <sect2 id="sect-switching-desktops" status="review">
  
   <title>切換桌面</title>
   
   <para>As an Ubuntu user, you may be concerned that your favorite
    GNOME applications will not run under Kubuntu. That
    is not the case. In recent times, much work has been done to
    increase compatibility between GNOME and KDE. Today, virtually
    all GNOME applications will run under KDE and vice versa. </para>
    
   <para>While the KDE desktop is very different from that of GNOME, all
    your favorite GNOME applications will be integrated with your
    KDE menu system. </para>
    
   <para>Another concern for users wanting to try Kubuntu may be that
    KDE will become their only desktop once it is installed. While
    we do indeed hope you will make KDE your desktop of choice, this
    is not the case; both desktop session types can be run after
    installing Kubuntu. Furthermore, during installation you will be
    given the choice of using either the GNOME Display Manager (GDM)
    or the K Display Manager (KDM) as your login manager. </para>
    
   <para>Either display manager will suffice, and after installation
    you will be able to run both GNOME and KDE session types.  Feel
    free to try KDM.  You can always switch back to GDM later if you
    like.  The only noticeable difference will be the artwork used 
	before you log in.</para>

    <para>要安裝 Kubuntu，只需安裝 <emphasis>kubuntu-desktop</emphasis> 套件。</para>
    
  </sect2>
  
 </sect1>
 
</article>

