<chapter id="chap12-advanced" status="draft">
	<title>Advanced Topics</title>
	<sect1 id="chap12-sect01" status="draft">
		<title>Incorporating your Linux lab into an existing Windows network.</title>
		<para>Edubuntu may easily be accommodated within an existing Windows network. If you want the Windows workstations to double as thin clients in Edubuntu, see the note about dual booting in <xref linkend="chap06-sect07" />. If Edubuntu is a separate lab, you can set it up as usual, but the second network card in the classroom server can act as a bridge to the Windows network. </para>
	</sect1>
	<sect1 id="chap12-sect02" status="draft">
		<title>Community WANs?</title>
		<para>Using affordable wireless technology, it is possible for nearby schools to create direct links between their Edubuntu <acronym>LAN</acronym>s, binding them into a <acronym>WAN</acronym> without exposing them to the Internet or incurring <acronym>ISP</acronym> costs. Computers at home for teachers or learners may be connected to the Edubuntu <acronym>LAN</acronym> in the same way. Note that to enable authentication and security for wireless access, the connection needs to be established using <acronym>PPPoE</acronym>: the Point-to-Point protocol tunneled over Ethernet. This is because <acronym>PPP</acronym> offers some features that Ethernet doesn't, specifically authentication and access control.</para>
	</sect1>
	<sect1 id="chap12-sect03" status="draft">
		<title>Alternate sources of information</title>
		<para>Aside from the growing Edubuntu community worldwide, your local Linux users' group is a good place to turn with your questions. With some patience, politeness and carefully formulated questions, these groups are inexhaustible founts of expert knowledge and assistance. By the time you have run out of questions to ask, there will be many newbies asking questions that you will be able to answer!</para>
	</sect1>
	<sect1 id="chap12-sect04" status="draft">
		<title>Programming, running each other&apos;s scripts</title>
		<para>While writing programs for your own edification and amusement does have its own appeal, sooner or later you&apos;ll want to share. Here, the system administrator has a couple of options.</para>
		<itemizedlist>
			<listitem>
				<para>If the home directories of learners on the classroom server are left world-readable (i.e. everyone, or at least every learner, with an account on the server is able to see the contents of someone else&apos;s files), then learners need only tell their classmates the location of their scripts for them to be able to find and run them. As long as they don't have write access to each other&apos;s directories, they&apos;ll only be able to delete their own files.
				<footnote>
					<para>Of course, it&apos;s always possible to trick someone into running a script that will damage their data. This is how many viruses work. Rather than trying to manage this through technology, in the classroom situation it&apos;s probably better to teach learners that it&apos;s better to help one another (and keep backups in case things go wrong).</para>
				</footnote>
				</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para>Alternatively, the system administration team could put scripts into a directory where everyone has execution rights after auditing the code themselves. While this may be a bit safer, it is likely to be an inhibiting factor.</para>
			</listitem>
		</itemizedlist>
		<para></para>
	</sect1>
</chapter>