<chapter id="chap04-gettingalab">
	<title>Getting a Lab</title>
	<sect1 id="chap04-sect01">
		<title>Steps involved in getting a lab</title>
		<itemizedlist>
			<listitem>
				<para><emphasis role="bold">Get in contact.</emphasis> Contact the tuXlab team to gain information. The telephone number is 0860 OS HELP (0860 674 357); the website, from which you can download documentation, is <ulink url="http://www.tuXlab.org.za">http://www.tuXlab.org.za</ulink>. You should also get in contact with the tuXlab closest to you, to see how you may assist each other.</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para><emphasis role="bold">Get on the mailing list.</emphasis> Join the tuXlab mailing list by registering at <ulink url="http://www.slug.org.za">http://www.slug.org.za</ulink>. You should join both the <emphasis>announce</emphasis> and <emphasis>schools</emphasis> mailing lists.</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para><emphasis role="bold">Submit questionnaire.</emphasis> Submit the completed questionnaire by sending a fax to 0860 674 357. Please complete the questionnaire electronically, or take care to write legibly if you fill it out by hand. You may find the questionnaire at the <!-- THIS LINK DOESN'T SEEM TO PLAY NICE WITH UNLINK <ulink url="http://tuxlab.org.za/index.php?option=content&task=blogsection&id=30">tuXlab page</ulink>-->.
</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para><emphasis role="bold">Attend your first tuXlab installation.</emphasis> Attend a tuXlab installation, to gain knowledge of the technology platform and installation process. The times and dates of installations are announced on the <emphasis>announce</emphasis> mailing list mentioned above.</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para><emphasis role="bold">Attend tuXlab induction installation; prepare proposal.</emphasis> Register to attend a tuXlab induction session. Prepare proposal as well as infrastructure requirements.</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para><emphasis role="bold">Attend your second tuXlab installation, finalise.</emphasis> After your second tuXlab installation, you can contact the tuXlab team to finalise outstanding requirements as well as await final approval.</para>
			</listitem>
		</itemizedlist>
	</sect1>
	<sect1 id="chap04-sect02">
		<title>Drawing up a business plan</title>
		<para>In order to qualify as the recipient of a tuXlab, you must have a business plan that shows that you will be able to integrate the lab in your school's curriculum, that you can muster the resources to keep the lab in good operating condition, and that you will be able to involve the wider community to benefit from the lab. Look at <xref linkend="chap16-sect01" /> for a good starting point.</para>
	</sect1>
	<sect1 id="chap04-sect03">
		<title>The lab in community context</title>
		<sect2 id="chap04-sect03.01">
			<title>Clusters of schools</title>
			<para>Schools will be selected in clusters. Through clustering, schools are able to jointly plan and prepare for their tuXlabs, and can share resources and community support. Clustering is a method of ensuring that schools remain self-sufficient in the future.</para>
			<para>A cluster consists of at least three schools. Each cluster will form a committee consisting of at least two representatives from each cluster school. These cluster committees should meet on a regular basis (at least quarterly) to discuss and share ideas, experiences and methodologies. Cluster communities should be in a position to setup a future Shuttleworth tuXlab with their collaborative knowledge and experience.</para>
		</sect2>
		<sect2 id="chap04-sect03.02">
			<title>Volunteers</title>
			<para>Open source communities are generally formed by developers, administrators and users that freely provide their expertise and time to the projects that interest them or that further their way of making a living. Contributing to an open source project does not just take the form of submitting source code, but rather any activity which benefits the community or open source in general. Establishing tuXlabs is similar in many respects to an open source software project --- rather than developing software, the Shuttleworth Foundation is installing labs, but still using the concept of open source volunteerism to facilitate this process. Establishing a volunteer group is a daunting task; however, with many possible methods to solicit volunteers, it is possible.</para>
		</sect2>
	</sect1>
</chapter>