<chapter id="chap05-lablayout" status="draft">
	<title>Lab Layout<!-- <footnote><para>See <ulink url="http://www.shuttleworthfoundation.org/images/stories/docs/tuxlablayout.pdf">tuXlab room layout</ulink> from the Shuttleworth Foundation's site.</para></footnote> --></title>
   <para>Before you carry a lot of computers into a room, there needs to be a good deal of preparation. A classroom will need to be modified to include special features, such as a lockable cabinet to secure the switch and server, and a layout that accommodates the re-arrangement, addition, or removal of furniture. Electricity is another consideration: every computer needs power, and in order to protect them from power surges, the computers need to be on a separate power circuit.</para>
   <para>Security is also an important consideration, and will involve at least burglar bars on the windows and an alarm system. The exact security measures that should be taken will differ from school to school. Several factors should be considered: for example, the known crime rate in the area, the isolation of the school, and the affordability of the security measures.</para>
<!-- Insert image lablayout.png here -->
	<sect1 id="chap05-sect01" status="draft">
		<title>Security<!-- <footnote><para>See <ulink url="http://www.shuttleworthfoundation.org/images/stories/docs/infrastructurespecs.pdf">Infrastructure and Security</ulink></para></footnote> --></title>
		<para>Here are some guidelines to consider when selecting a room for an Edubuntu lab. They aren't hard and fast rules, and when you look through them, you'll notice where there's room for initiative. They should however be taken as a baseline to improve upon where there's opportunity.</para>
		<sect2 id="chap05-sect01.01" status="draft">
			<title>Window security</title>
			<para><emphasis role="bold">Specifications:</emphasis></para>
			<itemizedlist>
				<listitem>
					<para>Frame: 25mm square metal tubing, bolted to the wall.</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>Vertical Bars: 16mm round, 120mm c/c.</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>Centre Horizontal Bar: 30mm x 5mm flat bar.</para>
				</listitem>
			</itemizedlist>
			<para>While the above may be used as a guide, the diameter and the finish of the bars can be further determined by the school authorities and the project manager, as is deemed necessary according to the known risk in the area.</para>
		</sect2>
		<sect2 id="chap05-sect01.02" status="draft">
			<title>Stone guards</title>
			<para>Galvanized metal mesh should be fitted on all outside windows.</para>
			<para>The sides of the frame should be closed. For fasteners, use tamperproof coach screws with turn-off heads.</para>
			<!-- Insert image coach-screw.png here-->
			<para>A coach screw. Note the double head. The top part turns off, making the screw very hard to remove once it's in.</para>
		</sect2>
		<sect2 id="chap05-sect01.03" status="draft">
			<title>Non-concrete ceiling security</title>
			<para>Wherever possible, the room identified for the lab should have a concrete floor above it. This means that in schools with two levels, it is preferable to select a room on the lower level. Where this is not possible and the ceiling is of hardboard or something equally flimsy, the ceiling should be covered with wire mesh or razor wire. In order to notice tampering, it's probably best for the wire to be <emphasis>beneath</emphasis> the ceiling.</para>
		</sect2>
		<sect2 id="chap05-sect01.04" status="draft">
			<title>Door security</title>
			<para>Since the gate is the key security feature, it should be made of steel of substantial thickness. In some cases, an internal security cage with steel gate or double steel gates are advised, depending on finances and risks. Methods of securing and fitment of locks should be strategic to make breaking in as difficult as possible.</para>
			<para><emphasis role="bold">Specifications:</emphasis></para>
			<itemizedlist>
				<listitem>
					<para>Frame: 50mm x 50mm x 5mm. Angle Iron bolted to the wall on 3 sides.</para>
					<!-- Insert image angleironbracket.png here -->
					<para>Angle iron and bracket</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>Bolts should be welded shut, or tamperproof.</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>The fitting of two barrel type locks covered with metal plates is advised.</para>
					<!-- Insert image barreltypelock.png here -->
				</listitem>
			</itemizedlist>
		</sect2>
		<sect2 id="chap05-sect01.05" status="draft">
			<title>Alarm system</title>
			<para>A security alarm system with at least two room sensors is required. If the lab has a ceiling, a sensor in the ceiling is advised. The alarm must be monitored around the clock, with armed response in the event of an alarm event.</para>
			<para>The number and location of sensors should be determined with input from security companies.</para>
		</sect2>
	</sect1>
	<sect1 id="chap05-sect02" status="draft">
		<title>Infrastructure</title>
		<sect2 id="chap05-sect02.01" status="draft">
			<title>Specifications for desktops</title>
			<para>The design and length of desktops in most cases is determined by the number of computers and learners, and the size of the room. If there is room, it's advisable to install desktops for future expansion of computer network at once, depending on the finances available.</para>
			<para>New desktops should be postform, minimum 28mm thick or similar stock, with a melamine/formica/varnished finish. They must be 900mm deep, to accommodate the keyboard, screen, and cabling without crowding and with proper ventilation. Depending on the chair height and the age of the learners, the top of the desktops should be 700 to 720mm from the floor. It is important for the desks to be at an appropriate height for the learners who will be using the lab, as an awkward posture can impair concentration.</para>
			<!-- Insert gat-v-draad.png here -->
			<para>For every workstation, the desktops have a hole that collects and passes through the network and power cables to the trunking under the desks.</para>
		</sect2>
		<sect2 id="chap05-sect02.02" status="draft">
			<title>Wall brackets are centre aisle framework</title>
			<para>Desktops should be mounted on 40mm x 40mm x 5mm angle iron brackets. They should only have legs if brackets are not a option, as legs tend to get in the way of learners sharing workstations. Each bracket must be a minimum of 750mm x 650mm. The brackets must be no less than 1000mm apart and each must be fixed with at two heavy duty rawlbolts, one of which must be as high up as possible.</para>
			<para>Where appropriate, provision should be made for ducting along which to run wiring and network cabling underneath the work surfaces, with holes in the desktops to allow the cables to reach the computers and peripherals.</para>
			<para>Where possible, the length of the desk should be chosen to allow 1200mm of space for each computer.</para>
		</sect2>
		<sect2 id="chap05-sect02.03" status="draft">
			<title>Specification for server cabinet</title>
			<para>If it's at all possible, put the server in a separate room, where it's out of sight and locked away permanently. All that is necessary is for a network flylead to reach from the server to the network switch. Otherwise, a well ventilated, lockable cabinet should be built.</para>
			<para>This cabinet should be at least 900mm square inside, as it will house the classroom server, another server acting as internet gateway, and a modem. The cabinet will be set away from the wall to allow for ventilation, since a pair of servers will generate a good deal of heat.</para>
			<para><emphasis role="bold">Notes:</emphasis></para>
			<itemizedlist>
				<listitem>
					<para>A wall mounted steel mesh cabinet can also be installed.</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>Dimensions for steel mesh cage: LxDxH: 1200mm x 750mm x 720mm.</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>Height: 720mm Includes a 32mm x 900mm Postform Top.</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>Doors: 2 doors 450mm wide is required on the 900mm section.</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>Suitable locks must be fitted so that the doors cannot be easily opened.</para>
				</listitem>
			</itemizedlist>
		</sect2>
	</sect1>
	<sect1 id="chap05-sect03" status="draft">
		<title>Electrical requirements</title>
		<sect2 id="chap05-sect03.01" status="draft">
			<title>Specification of electrical wall points</title>
			<para>It's important that all electrical work be done by a qualified technician, who should issue a certificate of compliance to the school upon completion of the work.</para>
			<para>There must be enough 15 amp 3-point plugs to accommodate each computer on a separate plug, and in addition, there should be enough plugs for peripherals as well. A good rule of thumb is to have a double plug for each computer point. For safety reasons, electrical wiring must be in conduit piping below the work surfaces, but Surfix-type cable and wall mounted sockets are also acceptable and should be installed below desktops.</para>
			<!-- Insert image surfixcable.png here -->
			<para>This is a cross section of a Surfix cable.</para>
			<!-- Insert image wallsocket.gif here -->
			<para>To avoid power spikes and dips, which are extremely damaging to workstations, the computer lab must be on its own electrical circuit. The circuit must be broken into segments, each adequate to accommodate the computers and peripherals on that segment. Air conditioners, or other equipment that use a lot of electricity, must not share the circuit with the computers.</para>
			<!-- Insert image onwettige-plug.png here -->
			<para>Don't use extension leads or multi-plugs. They can cause shorts and power spikes that may damage your equipment.</para>
			<para>Electrical wires to an island worktop in the middle of the room must preferably be under the floor or must have suitable ducting. Otherwise, it is a perfect certainty that someone will fall over the wires, breaking their neck and bringing all the workstations within reach crashing to the floor.</para>
		</sect2>
		<sect2 id="chap05-sect03.02" status="draft">
			<title>Subdistribution of electrical board</title>
			<para>The subdistribution board should be fitted with earth leakage protection, if required. A maximum of five wall plug sockets should be connected to one circuit, and each circuit should be protected by a 20 amp circuit breaker.</para>
		</sect2>
	</sect1>
	<sect1 id="chap05-sect04" status="draft">
		<title>Network infrastructure</title>
		<sect2 id="chap05-sect04.01" status="draft">
			<title>Switch cabinet</title>
			<para>Where required, a 4U cabinet will be installed to house a minimum of two 24-port switches <footnote><para>See <xref linkend="chap08-networking" /> for an explanation of what switches do.</para></footnote>, leaving some space for expansion. Server equipment is a bit like bricks: they're all the same basic shape. One switch is 1U (or unit) big, so a 4U cabinet has room for four of them. Computer suppliers will know what you're talking about.</para>
			<para>The placing of the switch cabinet should determined by the lab layout, and to minimize the required cable lengths, it should be placed in a central position. If installed in the lab, the cabinet should be 1000mm above or below desktops.</para>
			<!-- Insert image switch.gif here -->
			<para>Cabinet to house switches</para>
		</sect2>
		<sect2 id="chap05-sect04.02" status="draft">
			<title>Network trunking</title>
			<para>Network cabling must run in 40mm x 40mm square trunking. If financial considerations require that network cabling share the trunking of the electrical cabling, it is imperative for the electricity to be switched off at the subdistribution board whenever the trunking is opened during network troubleshooting.</para>
			<!-- Insert image trunking.gif here -->
			<para>Trunking running under the desks.</para>
			<para>Ensure that 10mm holes are made in trunking for the cable ends to reach their workstations. Allow at least 500mm of free network cable per computer, and loop and tie the extra length neatly. Network cables that are too short can be just as irritating as socks that are two sizes too small, and moreover lead to high blood pressure and increased risk of cardiac arrest. Cabling to an island desktop must preferably be under the floor or must have suitable ducting that will ensure the safety of pupils who have to walk over these cables.</para>
		</sect2>
	</sect1>
</chapter>