<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.3//EN" 
	"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.3/docbookx.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % globalent SYSTEM "../../../libs/global.ent">
%globalent;
<!ENTITY % cdo-C SYSTEM "../../../libs/cdo-C.ent">
%cdo-C;
<!ENTITY % gnome-menus-sv SYSTEM "../../../ubuntu/libs/gnome-menus-sv.ent">
%gnome-menus-sv;
<!ENTITY % xinclude SYSTEM "../../../libs/xinclude.mod">
%xinclude;
<!ENTITY language "en">
<!ENTITY ubuntu '<phrase>Ubuntu</phrase>'>
]>
<chapter id="graphics" status="complete">
		<title>Graphics &amp; Photos</title>
			<para>This section describes the photo management and graphic design applications available to use with Ubuntu, and describes how to set up 3d graphics devices.</para>
		<sect1 id="digital-cameras" status="complete">
			<title>Digitalkameror</title>
				<para>Ubuntu detects most USB digital cameras automatically. Plug in and switch on the camera, and Ubuntu will then ask you if you would like to import the photos it contains. Click on <guibutton>Import</guibutton>, and Ubuntu will show you a preview of the photos. Choose a location to save your photos to, then click on <guibutton>Import</guibutton>, and Ubuntu will save your photos to your hard drive.</para>
				<para>If Ubuntu does not ask you if it can import the photos:</para>
				<procedure>
					<step><para>Open &gthumb;.</para></step>
					<step>
						<para>Choose
					<menuchoice>
						<guimenu>File</guimenu>
						<guimenuitem>Import Photos</guimenuitem>
					</menuchoice>.</para>
					</step>
				</procedure>
				<para>See <xref linkend="gthumb"/> for more on <application>gThumb</application>.</para>
		</sect1>

		<sect1 id="graphics-cards" status="complete">
			<title>3D-grafikkort</title>
				<sect2 id="video-acceleration-introduction">
					<title>Introduktion till 3D-acceleration</title>
					<para>Most video hardware should work automatically with Ubuntu. With some types of video hardware, 3D acceleration (which is needed by some games) is not supported automatically, but you may be able to fix this yourself.</para>
					<para>To find out whether 3D acceleration is working, enter in a terminal:</para>
					<screen>glxinfo | grep rendering</screen>
					<para>If 3D acceleration is working, the result will be:
					<screen>direct rendering: Yes</screen>
					If not, follow these instructions to activate 3D acceleration.</para>
				</sect2>
        	       	 <sect2 id="nvidia" status="complete">
        		        <title>3D-drivrutin för Nvidia-grafikkort</title>
					<para>Inga Nvidia-grafikkort har 3D-acceleration aktiverat automatiskt i Ubuntu, eftersom tillverkaren inte släpper drivrutiner som är öppen källkod. Det är dock möjligt att aktivera 3D-acceleration. Hur du går till väga beror på vilken sorts grafikkort du har.</para>
					<itemizedlist>
						<listitem>
							<para>If you have an older TNT, TNT2, TNT Ultra, GeForce1 or GeForce2 card, install the <application> nvidia-glx-legacy</application> and <application>nvidia-settings</application> packages from the <quote>Restricted</quote> repository (see <xref linkend="add-applications"/>).</para>
						</listitem>
						<listitem>
				<para>If you have a newer card, install the <application>nvidia-glx</application> package from the <quote>Restricted</quote> repository (see <xref linkend="add-applications"/>).
				</para>
						</listitem>
					</itemizedlist>
				<para>To set up the new driver, enter in a terminal:</para>
                                <screen>
sudo nvidia-glx-config enable </screen>
				<para>You can adjust the settings of the new drivers by running <application>nvidia-settings</application> (see <ulink type="help" url="ghelp:user-guide#tools-run-app">the run application manual</ulink> for help on how to run an application without using the menu). If you wish, add a menu entry for this program (see <ulink type="help" url="ghelp:user-guide#menu-editor">the menu editor manual</ulink> for help on how to add menu entries).</para>
            </sect2>
            <sect2 id="installatidriver" status="complete">
                <title>3D-drivrutin för ATI-grafikkort</title>
				<para>Many ATI video cards work well with Ubuntu automatically. To check that 3D acceleration works with your card, see <xref linkend="video-acceleration-introduction"/>.</para>
				<para>If it doesn’t work:</para>
				<procedure>
					<step><para>Install the <application>xorg-driver-fglrx</application> package from the <quote>Restricted</quote> repository (see <xref linkend="add-applications"/>).</para></step> 
					<step>
					<para>To set up the new driver, enter in a terminal:</para>
				<screen>sudo dpkg-reconfigure xserver-xorg</screen>
				<para>Agree to automatic detection of your video, and choose the driver <guibutton>fglrx</guibutton> when asked.</para>
					</step>
				</procedure>
				<para>Restart the computer for the changes to take effect.</para>
	    </sect2>
	    </sect1>

		<sect1 id="gthumb" status="complete">
			<title>Bildvisaren gThumb</title>
				<para><application>gThumb</application> är en avancerad bildvisare och -bläddrare. Den har många användbara funktioner, som att bläddra genom filsystemet, bildspel, bildkataloger, skapa webbalbum, importera från kameror, bränna till CD-skivor, utför samma sak på många filer, och enklare bildredigeringsfunktioner som transformering och färgmanipulation.</para>
				<para><application>gThumb</application> is included in Ubuntu by default. To start it, choose &gthumb;.
				</para>
				<para>For help with <application>gThumb</application>, use the items in its <guimenu>Help</guimenu> menu.
				</para>
				<para>For more advanced photo &amp; image editing, see <application>The GIMP</application>.
				</para>
		</sect1>
		<sect1 id="gimp" status="complete">
			<title>The GIMP (Gnu Bildmanipuleringsprogram)</title>
			<para><application>The GIMP</application> lets you draw, paint, edit images, and much more. GIMP
includes the functionality and plug-ins of other famous image editing and processing programs.
				</para>
				<para><application>The GIMP</application> is installed in Ubuntu by default, and can be started by choosing &gimp;.
				</para>
			<itemizedlist>
				<listitem><para><ulink url="http://gimp.org/">GIMP Web site</ulink></para></listitem>
			</itemizedlist>
		</sect1>
		<sect1 id="inkscape" status="complete">
			<title>Vektorgrafikredigeraren Inkscape</title>
				<para><application>Inkscape</application> är ett kraftfullt program för att arbeta med SVG-filer (Scalable Vector Graphics).</para>
				<procedure>
					<step>
						<para>Installera paketet <application>inkscape</application> (se <xref linkend="add-applications"/>).</para>
					</step>
					<step>
						<para>To start <application>Inkscape</application> choose &inkscape;.
						</para>
					</step>
				</procedure>
		</sect1>
		<sect1 id="blender" status="complete">
			<title>3d-modelleraren Blender</title>
				<para><application>Blender</application> är ett helt integrerad 3d-svit för modellering, animering, rendering, postproduktion, interaktivt skapande och uppspelning.</para>
				<procedure>
					<step>
						<para>Installera paketet <application>blender</application> (se <xref linkend="add-applications"/>).</para>
					</step>
					<step>
						<para>To start <application>Blender</application> choose &blender3d;.
						</para>
					</step>
				</procedure>
		</sect1>
	</chapter>

