<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.3//EN" 
	"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.3/docbookx.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % globalent SYSTEM "../../../libs/global.ent">
%globalent;
<!ENTITY % cdo-C SYSTEM "../../../libs/cdo-C.ent">
%cdo-C;
<!ENTITY % gnome-menus-sv SYSTEM "../../../ubuntu/libs/gnome-menus-sv.ent">
%gnome-menus-sv;
<!ENTITY % xinclude SYSTEM "../../../libs/xinclude.mod">
%xinclude;
<!ENTITY language "en">
<!ENTITY ubuntu '<phrase>Ubuntu</phrase>'>
]>
<chapter id="music" status="complete">
			<title>Music and Video</title>
				<para>This section describes the music and video players available to use with Ubuntu and how to configure them to listen to different types of multimedia files.</para>
			<sect1 id="music-files" status="complete">
					<title>Spela och organisera musikfiler</title>
				<para>To play and organize your music, Ubuntu comes with		    <application>Rhythmbox Music Player</application>, which looks similar to <application>iTunes</application>. When you first start <application>Rhythmbox</application>, it will scan your home directory for any supported music files you have and add it to the database. To start <application>Rhythmbox</application>, choose &rhythmbox;.</para>
					<para>Ubuntu does not directly support the <emphasis role="strong">MP3</emphasis> format, because it is restricted by patents and proprietary rights. Instead Ubuntu supports the <emphasis role="strong">Ogg Vorbis</emphasis> format out of the box, a completely free, open and non-patented format. Ogg Vorbis files also sound better then MP3 files of the same file size and are supported by many portable music players.</para>
					<itemizedlist>
						<listitem><para><ulink url="http://wiki.xiph.org/index.php/PortablePlayers">Players that work with Vorbis</ulink></para></listitem>
					</itemizedlist>
					<para>You can still play your old MP3 files by installing MP3 support (see <xref linkend="codecs"/>). Instructions for other formats, such as Windows Media Audio (wma/wmv) and other patent-encumbered formats can be found <ulink url="http://wiki.ubuntu.com/RestrictedFormats">on the Ubuntu Wiki</ulink>.</para>
				<para>ID3-tagsredigeraren <application>Cowbell</application> kan redigera metadata om dina ljudfiler, som t ex mp3-filer. För att använda <application>Cowbell</application>:</para>
				<procedure>
						<step>
							<para>Install the <application>cowbell</application> package from the <quote>Universe</quote> repository (see <xref linkend="add-applications"/>);</para>
						</step>
						<step>
							<para>To run <application>Cowbell</application>, choose
								<menuchoice>
									<guimenu>Applications</guimenu>
									<guisubmenu>Sound &amp; Video</guisubmenu>
									<guimenuitem>Cowbell Music Organizer</guimenuitem>
								</menuchoice>.
							</para>
						</step>
				</procedure>
			</sect1>
			<sect1 id="audio-cds" status="complete">
				<title>Spela och extrahera ljud-CD-skivor</title>
				<para>När du stoppar in en ljud-CD kommer den kombinerade CD-spelaren och -extraheraren <application>Sound Juicer</application> att öppnas automatiskt. För att spela CD-skivan, klicka på knappen <guibutton>Spela</guibutton> eller tryck <keycombo><keycap>Ctrl</keycap><keycap>P</keycap></keycombo>. För att spela ett speciellt spår, dubbelklicka på spåret eller markera spåret och klicka på <guibutton>Spela</guibutton>.</para>
				<para>För att extrahera ("rippa") din ljud-CD-skiva, se till att spåren du vill extrahera är markerade, och klicka sedan på knappen <guibutton>Extrahera</guibutton>, alternativt använd tangentkombinationen <keycombo><keycap>Ctrl</keycap><keycap>Enter</keycap></keycombo>.</para>
					<note>
						<para>If you are connected to the internet, <application>Sound Juicer</application> will retrieve the CD artist, title, and track data from <ulink url="http://musicbrainz.org">MusicBrainz.org</ulink>, a community-maintained database of over 360,000 albums.
						</para>
					</note>
				<para>To start <application>Sound Juicer</application> manually, choose 
				<menuchoice>
					<guimenu>Applications</guimenu>
					<guimenuitem>Sound &amp; Video</guimenuitem>
					<guimenuitem>Sound Juicer CD Extractor</guimenuitem>
				</menuchoice>.
				</para>
				<para>You can use the preferences window to control where the extracted audio files are stored on your computer, the filename of extracted audio files, and the file format and codec used for the files. In the main window, choose 
				<menuchoice>
					<guimenu>Edit</guimenu>
					<guimenuitem>Preferences</guimenuitem>
				</menuchoice>.
				</para>
				<para><application>Sound Juicer</application> can extract audio files to these formats:
					<itemizedlist>
						<listitem>
							<para><emphasis role="strong">Ogg Vorbis</emphasis> - A patent-free lossy audio compression format, which typically produces higher quality and greater compression than MP3.</para>
							<itemizedlist>
								<listitem><para><ulink url="http://vorbis.com/faq/">More about Vorbis from vorbis.com</ulink></para></listitem>
							</itemizedlist>
						</listitem>
						<listitem>
							<para><emphasis role="strong">FLAC</emphasis> - The Free Lossless Audio Codec. It can compress audio files up to 50% without removing any information from the audio stream.</para>
							<itemizedlist>
								<listitem><para><ulink url="http://flac.sourceforge.net/">FLAC Web site</ulink></para></listitem>
							</itemizedlist>
						</listitem>
						<listitem>
							<para><emphasis role="strong">WAV</emphasis> - Typically used for voice recordings. <application>Sound Juicer</application> uses this format for low quality mono audio files. 
							</para>
						</listitem>
					</itemizedlist>
				</para>
				<para>You can also extract CD audio files to the proprietary non-free <emphasis role="strong">MP3</emphasis> format. Instructions on how to rip to the MP3 format are in the help for <application>Sound Juicer</application>. Choose 
				<menuchoice>
					<guimenu>Help</guimenu>
					<guisubmenu>Contents</guisubmenu>
				</menuchoice> and navigate to the <emphasis>Preferences</emphasis> section.
				</para>
			</sect1>
			<sect1 id="burning-cds" status="complete">
					<title>Bränna CD-skivor</title>
					<para>När du stoppar in en tom CD-skiva i CD-läsaren kommer Ubuntu fråga dig om du vill bränna en ljud-CD eller en data-CD. Om du klickar på <guibutton>Bränn ljud-CD</guibutton> kommer <application>Serpentine</application> att startas. För att lägga musik till din ljud-CD kan du aningen dra musiken från din filbläddrare eller använda knappen <guibutton>Lägg till</guibutton>. Du måste också välja hur stor CD-skivan är (21, 74, 80 eller 90 minuter). Serpentine kommer att varna dig om du överskrider den valda gränsen.</para>
					<para>To make a photo or data CD, click <guibutton>Burn Data CD</guibutton>. Ubuntu will open a CD/DVD Creator window. The CD Creator is built into the File Browser, and it allows you to add any file or folder you have permission to access. When you are ready to burn the CD, click <guibutton>Write to Disc</guibutton>. Ubuntu will then prompt you to select the drive containing the blank CD, and give you the opportunity to name the CD and select the write speed. Finally, click <guibutton>Write</guibutton> to create the new photo or data CD.
					</para>
			</sect1>

		<sect1 id="video">
		<title>Video Playback</title>
		<para>To play video, Ubuntu comes with <application>Totem Movie Player</application>, which looks and functions similar to Windows Media Player. Features of
		<application>Totem</application> include custom playlists and DVD playback. 
	        You can start <application>Totem</application> by clicking: &totem; from the desktop menu system.
		</para>
		<para>För att läsa filmfiler använder <application>Totem</application> ramverket <application>Gstreamer</application>. För att kunna spela vissa filmformat kan du behöva installera ytterligare codec-stöd (se <xref linkend="codecs"/>).</para>
		<para>There are also other multimedia applications available. Examples include <application>Mplayer</application>, <application>Xine</application> and <application>Totem-xine</application> (which uses the <application>Xine</application> framework, instead of the <application>Gstreamer</application> framework). You may benefit from trying alternative video players.</para>
		</sect1>

		<sect1 id="codecs" status="complete">
		<title>Multimediacodecs</title>
			<para>Många program i Ubuntu använder det öppna multimediaramverket <application>GStreamer</application>. Codec-plugins för <application>GStreamer</application> är organiserade i olika paket, beroende på den licens som gäller olika codecs. Du kan se vilka codecs som ligger i vilket paket på <ulink url="http://gstreamer.freedesktop.org/documentation/plugins.html">GStreamers webbsida</ulink>.</para>
			<para>Other applications, such as <application>Mplayer</application> and <application>Xine</application>, do not use the <application>Gstreamer</application> framework. Due to patent and copyright restrictions, codecs for these programs are not included at all in Ubuntu. For more information on these read the <ulink url="&restricted-formats;">Restricted Formats</ulink> wiki page.</para>
			<para>För att installera extra codecs till <application>Gstreamer</application>:</para>
				<procedure>
					<step>
							<para>Install the following packages from the <quote>Universe</quote> and <quote>Multiverse</quote> repositories (see <xref linkend="add-applications"/>):
								<literallayout>gstreamer0.10-plugins-ugly
gstreamer0.10-plugins-ugly-multiverse
gstreamer0.10-plugins-bad
gstreamer0.10-plugins-bad-multiverse
gstreamer0.10-ffmpeg
								</literallayout>
							</para>
							<note>
								<para>You will need to use <application>Synaptic Package Manager</application> to install these packages.
								</para>
							</note>
							<warning>
								<para>Vissa av dessa paket är inte tillåtna i vissa länder: du bör kontrollera att du har tillåtelse att använda dem innan du installerar dem.</para>
							</warning>
					</step>
				</procedure>
	</sect1>

			<sect1 id="ipod" status="complete">
			        <title>Using an iPod</title>
				<para>You can play music directly off an iPod with <application>Rhythmbox Music Player</application>. Plug the iPod into the computer, and open <application>Rhythmbox</application>.</para>
				<para>To transfer music files to and from an iPod, you can use <application>gtkpod</application>:</para>
					<procedure>
					<step>
						<para>Install the <application>gtkpod</application> package from the <quote>Universe</quote> repository (see <xref linkend="add-applications"/>).
						</para>
					</step>
					<step>
						<para>To run <application>gtkpod</application>, choose
								<menuchoice>
									<guimenu>Applications</guimenu>
									<guisubmenu>Sound &amp; Video</guisubmenu>
									<guimenuitem>gtkpod</guimenuitem>
								</menuchoice>.
						</para>
					</step>
					</procedure>
			</sect1>
			<sect1 id="edit-audio-files" status="complete">
				<title>Redigera ljudfiler</title>
					<para>Audacity är ett fritt öppenkällkodsprogram för att spela in och redigera ljud. För att använda Audacity:</para>
					<procedure>
						<step>
							<para>Install the audacity package from the <quote>Universe</quote> repository (see <xref linkend="add-applications"/>).
							</para>
						</step>
						<step>
							<para>To run <application>Audacity</application>, choose
								<menuchoice>
									<guimenu>Applications</guimenu>
									<guisubmenu>Sound &amp; Video</guisubmenu>
									<guimenuitem>Audacity</guimenuitem>
								</menuchoice>.
							</para>
						</step>
						<step>
							<para>For further help with Audacity, use Audacity’s <guimenu>Help</guimenu> menu.</para>
						</step>							
					</procedure>
			</sect1>

		<sect1 id="dvdplayback" status="complete">
			<title>Spela DVD-skivor</title>
				<para>Filmspelarna som Ubuntu erbjuder kan läsa DVD-skivor som inte är krypterade. Dock så är de flesta kommersiella DVD-skivorna krypterade med CSS (Content Scrambling System) och av juridiska skäl är det inte möjligt att inkludera stöd för dessa DVD-skivor i Ubuntu för närvarande. Dock är det möjligt att aktivera stöd för det såhär:</para>
				<warning><para>De juridiska omständigheterna kring det här biblioteket är inte helt klara. I vissa länder är det möjligt att det är olagligt att använda detta bibliotek till att spela och kopiera DVD-skivor. Kontrollera att du har rätt att använda detta bibliotek.</para></warning>
				<procedure>
					<step>
						<para>Installera paketet <application>libdvdread3</application> (se <xref linkend="add-applications"/>).</para>
					<note><para>Du behöver använda <application>Pakethanteraren Synaptic</application> för att installera det här paketet</para></note>
					</step>
					<step>
						<para>To activate DVD decryption, type the following line into a terminal prompt:<screen>sudo /usr/share/doc/libdvdread3/install-css.sh</screen>
						</para>
					</step>
					<step>
						<para>För att spela DVD-skivor med <application>Totem</application> kommer du att behöva installera några extra codecs (se <xref linkend="codecs"/>).</para>
					</step>
					<step>
						<para>However, the <application>Gstreamer</application> framework (used by <application>Totem</application>) does not support menus or subtitles for DVD playback. For this reason, you can install a separate DVD player, <application>Xine</application>, which supports these. To install <application>Xine</application>, install the <application>gxine</application> package from the <quote>Universe</quote> repository (see <xref linkend="add-applications"/>).</para>
					</step>
					<step>
						<para>Du kan sedan öppna <application>gxine</application> från menyn Ljud och video.</para>
					</step>
				</procedure>
		</sect1>

			<sect1 status="complete">
				<title>Göra backup på DVD-skivor</title>
					<para>You can back up your DVDs to files or onto DVD+/- discs with <application>DVD::RIP</application>. To install
<application>DVD::RIP</application>:</para>
					<warning><para>Innan du gör backup på en DVD måste du se till att du har rätt enligt lag att göra kopior av den.</para></warning>
					<procedure>
						<step>
							<para>Installera multimedia-codecs (se <xref linkend="codecs"/>).</para>
						</step>
						<step>
							<para>Aktivera DVD-uppspelning (se <xref linkend="dvdplayback"/>).</para>
						</step>
						<step>
							<para>Install <application>dvdrip</application> and <application>transcode</application> from the <quote>Multiverse</quote> repository (see <xref linkend="add-applications"/>).
							</para>
						</step>
						<step>
							<para>You can run the program using the command <application>dvdrip</application> (see <ulink type="help" url="ghelp:user-guide#tools-run-app">the run application manual</ulink> for help on how to run an application without using the menu). If you wish, you can add a menu entry for the program <application>dvdrip</application> (see <ulink type="help" url="ghelp:user-guide#menu-editor">the menu editor manual</ulink> for help on how to add menu entries). We recommend you enter it in the Sound &amp; Video menu, and that you use the file <filename>/usr/share/perl5/Video/DVDRip/icon.xpm</filename> for the icon.
							</para>
						</step>
						<step>
							<para>To start  <application>dvd::rip</application>, choose
								<menuchoice>
									<guimenu>Applications</guimenu>
									<guisubmenu>Sound &amp; Video</guisubmenu>
									<guimenuitem>dvd::rip</guimenuitem>
								</menuchoice>.
							</para>
						</step>
					</procedure>
			</sect1>
		<sect1 status="complete">
			<title>RealPlayer</title>
					<procedure>
						<step>
							<para>Install the <application>realplay</application> package from the <emphasis>Commercial</emphasis> repository (see <xref linkend="add-applications"/>).</para>
						</step>
						<step>
							<para>To run <application>RealPlayer</application>, choose
								<menuchoice>
									<guimenu>Applications</guimenu>
									<guisubmenu>Sound &amp; Video</guisubmenu>
									<guimenuitem>RealPlayer 10</guimenuitem>
								</menuchoice>.
							</para>
						</step>
					</procedure>
			</sect1>
			<sect1 status="complete">
					<title>Videoredigering</title>
					<para><application>Kino</application> är en avancerad videoredigerare. Det har bland annat lysande integrering med IEEE-1394 för att hämta film, VTR-kontroll och stöd för att spela in tillbaka till kameran. Det hämtar film till hårddisken i formatet Raw DV och AVI, i både formaten type-1 DV och type-2 DV (separata ljudströmmar). För mer information, läs på ulink url="http://www.kinodv.org/article/static/2"&gt;Kinos hemsida</para>
					<procedure>
						<step>
							<para>Installera  paketet <application>kino</application> (se <xref linkend="add-applications"/>).</para>
						</step>
						<step>
							<para>To run <application>Kino</application>, choose
								<menuchoice>
									<guimenu>Applications</guimenu>
									<guisubmenu>Sound &amp; Video</guisubmenu>
									<guimenuitem>Kino Video Editor</guimenuitem>
								</menuchoice>.
							</para>
						</step>
					</procedure>
					<para>You can also try the <application>PiTiVi</application> video editor by installing the <application>pitivi</application> package from the <quote>Universe</quote> repository (see <xref linkend="add-applications"/>). <application>PiTiVi</application> is a video editor for the GNOME desktop. It is still in fairly early development, but worth a try.</para>
			</sect1>
	   </chapter>

