<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.3//EN" 
	"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.3/docbookx.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % globalent SYSTEM "../../../libs/global.ent">
%globalent;
<!ENTITY % cdo-C SYSTEM "../../../libs/cdo-C.ent">
%cdo-C;
<!ENTITY % gnome-menus-C SYSTEM "../../../ubuntu/libs/gnome-menus-C.ent">
%gnome-menus-C;
<!ENTITY % xinclude SYSTEM "../../../libs/xinclude.mod">
%xinclude;
<!ENTITY language "en">
<!ENTITY ubuntu '<phrase>Ubuntu</phrase>'>
]>
<article id="add-applications" status="complete">
	<articleinfo>
	<title>Keeping Your Computer Safe</title>
    	&legalnotice;
	</articleinfo>
	<para>Placeholder</para>
		<section id="users" status="writing">
			<title>Using separate users</title>
					<para>During installation of Ubuntu, a single user and password is created. However, in order to keep your computer and documents safe, it is important to use a separate user for each person that uses the computer. Any modern operating system permits multiple users to operate the computer while preserving their own personal settings and files. On Ubuntu, each user has their own <emphasis>home directory</emphasis> in which files and settings are stored. Further, each user can be part of one or more <emphasis>groups</emphasis>, which define which parts of the system that user has access to.</para>
			<para>To modify the users or groups on your system, you can use the <application>Users And Groups</application> application located in &users-groups;.
			</para>
			<note>
				<para>You need administrative rights to use this application (see <ulink url="../newtoubuntu/administrative.xml">Administrative tasks</ulink>). You need to log out and in again in order for the changes to become effective.
				</para>
			</note>
			<para>To add a new user, click on <guilabel>Add user</guilabel>, fill-in the data fields then click <guilabel>OK</guilabel>.  To edit the properties of each user, click the <guilabel>Properties</guilabel> button located in the main <guilabel>Users</guilabel> window.
			</para>
				<note><para>To give a new user administrative rights (see <ulink url="../newtoubuntu/administrative.xml">Administrative Tasks</ulink>), edit that user's properties, and under the <guilabel>User Privileges</guilabel> tab, ensure that the <guilabel>Administer the system</guilabel> box is checked.</para></note>
			<para>To add a new group, select the <guilabel>Groups</guilabel> tab and click <guilabel>Add group</guilabel>. Choose a name for the new group and, if you want, change the default value for the <guilabel>Group ID</guilabel>. If you try to allocate a <guilabel>Group ID</guilabel> that is in use, the system will warn you.
			</para>
			<para>You can add users to the newly created group by selecting a user from the left menu and clicking on the <guilabel>Add</guilabel> button. Removing a user is as simple as adding one: select a user from the right menu then click <guilabel>Remove</guilabel>.  When you are ready, click <guilabel>OK</guilabel> and the new group with its users, if inserted, will be created.
			</para>
			<para>To edit the properties of a group, from within the <guilabel>Groups</guilabel> main window, choose a group name and click on the <guilabel>Properties</guilabel> button.
			</para>
			<para>To remove a user or a group from the system, select the user or group you want to delete and click <guilabel>Delete</guilabel>.
			</para>
		</section>
	    <section id="updates" status="complete">
		<title>Keeping your computer updated</title>
			<para>Sometimes the Ubuntu developers release feature and security updates for applications and packages within the Ubuntu system. You should update your computer in order to keep it safe.
			</para>
			<para>When updates are available, Ubuntu will inform you with a pop-up and a red icon in your notification area. To update your system, click the red button, enter your password and click <guibutton>OK</guibutton>.
			</para>
			<para>The <application>Update Manager</application> program will list the available updates: to download and install these updates click <guibutton>Install Updates</guibutton>. Ubuntu will then download and install the available updates from the Internet.
			</para>
			<para>When <application>Update Manager</application> has finished updating your system, close the pop-up window with the <guibutton>Close</guibutton> button, then close <application>Update Manager</application> to finish updating your system. 
			</para>
			<note>
				<para>After installing some important updates, it may be necessary to restart your computer. If so, Ubuntu will inform you with a popup and an icon in your notification area.
				</para>
			</note>
	   </section>
		<section id="lock-screen" status="review">
<!-- This section is thieved from the Gnome upstream document, it needs to be rewritten or the matter resolved in another way -->
			<title>Lock your screen while away</title>
				<para>[Intro blurb]</para>
				    <indexterm>
      				<primary>locking screen</primary>
				    </indexterm>
				    <indexterm>
					<primary>locking screen</primary>
				    </indexterm>
				    <indexterm>
				    <primary>Lock button</primary>
    				</indexterm>
    			<para>Locking your screen allows you to leave your computer unattended and prevent access to your applications and information. While your screen is locked, the <link linkend="prefs-screensaver">screensaver</link> runs.</para>
				<para>To lock the screen, perform
one of the following actions:</para>
				    <itemizedlist>
				      <listitem>
        					<para>Choose <menuchoice><guimenu>System</guimenu><guimenuitem>Lock Screen</guimenuitem></menuchoice>.</para>
      				  </listitem>
      				  <listitem>
        					<para>If the <guibutton>Lock Screen</guibutton> button is present on a
panel, click on the <guibutton>Lock Screen</guibutton> button.</para>
        					<note><para>The <guibutton>Lock Screen</guibutton> is not present on the panels by default. To add it, see <xref linkend="panels-addobject"/>.</para></note>
				      </listitem>
				    </itemizedlist>
		    <para>To unlock the screen, move your mouse or press any key, enter your password in the locked screen dialog, then press <keycap>Return</keycap>.</para>
		    <para>If you share your computer with others, the one can switch the user and start a new session; when finish and end his session, you can unlock your screen as above.</para>
		</section>
		<section id="firewall">
			<title>Set up a firewall</title>
			<para>TODO</para>
		</section>		
</article>
