<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.3//EN" 
	"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.3/docbookx.dtd" [

]>
<article lang="en" id="UbuntuReleaseNotesVersion1.0" status="review">
    <title>Ubuntu 5.10 Release Notes</title>
    <articleinfo>
        <revhistory>
            <revision>
                <revnumber>1.0</revnumber>
                <date>October 4, 2005</date>
                <authorinitials>JSG</authorinitials>
                <revdescription>
                    <para>Version 1.0 for Ubuntu 5.10 <email>jgotangco@ubuntu.com</email></para>
                </revdescription>
            </revision>
        </revhistory> 
        <authorgroup>
        		<author>
        			<firstname>Matt</firstname>
        			<surname>Zimmerman</surname> 
        			<email>mdz@ubuntu.com</email>
        		</author>
            <author>
                <firstname>Jerome</firstname>
                <surname>Gotangco</surname>
                <email>jgotangco@ubuntu.com</email>
            </author>
        </authorgroup>
        <abstract>
            <para>These are the Release Notes for Ubuntu 5.10</para>
        </abstract>
    </articleinfo>
<para>Ubuntu is a Linux distribution for your desktop or server, with a fast and easy install, regular releases, a tight selection of excellent applications installed by default, and every other software you can imagine available from the network. Ubuntu provides security updates for 18 months after each release, and professional technical support is available from many companies around the world.</para>
<para>These Release Notes cover new features in Ubuntu 5.10, download and installation notes, known issues, and frequently asked questions. Please read these notes before, during, and after installation and configuration of Ubuntu 5.10 before reporting bugs in <ulink url="http://bugzilla.ubuntu.com">Bugzilla</ulink>.</para>
<para>We hope you enjoy Ubuntu 5.10.</para>
    <sect1 id="sect1-whatsnew" status="review">
        <title>What's New</title>
        <para>Ubuntu is released <emphasis>regulary and predictably</emphasis>. Since our April 2005 release (Ubuntu 5.04), we've made a lot improvements to give you the best Linux experience possible. Here's what's new with Ubuntu 5.10:</para>
        <sect2 id="desktop" status="review">
            <title>On The Desktop</title>
            <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para> GNOME 2.12.1</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>OpenOffice.org 2.0 beta 2</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para> X.org 6.8.2 with wider hardware support</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>An enhanced tool for easily installing new applications (see <emphasis>&apos;Add Applications&apos;</emphasis> on the Applications menu)</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                		<para>A new tool which makes it easy to install support for multiple languages (<emphasis>Language Selector</emphasis>)</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                		<para>Editable GNOME menus with <emphasis>SMEG</emphasis> (Simple Menu Editor for GNOME)</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                		<para>Applications are now linked into the Launchpad infrastructure (new entries on the Help menus for translation and support)</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                		<para>Support for writing audio CDs (<emphasis>Serpentine</emphasis>)</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                		<para>Graphical boot process with progress bar (<emphasis>USplash</emphasis>)</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                		<para>New documentation (<emphasis>Ubuntu 5.10 Quick Tour</emphasis> and <emphasis>Ubuntu 5.10 FAQ Guide</emphasis>)</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                		<para>Language packs with updates from the Rosetta translation platform, which makes contributing translations easy for everybody</para>
                </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
            </sect2>
            <sect2 id="server" status="review">
            	<title>On the Server</title>
            	<itemizedlist>
            			<listitem>
            					<para>Plone 2.1 and Zope 2.8.1</para>
            			</listitem>
            			<listitem>
            					<para>PHP5</para>
            			</listitem>
            			<listitem>
            					<para>Support for installing directly onto LVM volumes</para>
            			</listitem>
            			<listitem>
            					<para> Built-in thin client functionality produced in cooperation with the LTSP project</para>
            			</listitem>
            			<listitem>
            					<para> Simple NFS root setup with automatic hardware detection through <emphasis>initramfs-tools</emphasis></para>
            			</listitem>
            			<listitem>
            					<para>Support for up to 4 gigabytes of RAM by default on 32-bit architectures</para>
            			</listitem>
            			<listitem>
            					<para>Kernel support for cluster filesystems (<emphasis>OCFS2</emphasis> and <emphasis>GFS</emphasis>)</para>
            			</listitem>
            	</itemizedlist>
            </sect2>
            <sect2 id="hardware-support" status="review">
            	<title>Hardware Support Improvements</title>
            	<itemizedlist>
            			<listitem>
            					<para> Linux 2.6.12.6 with many updated drivers from third parties</para>
            			</listitem>
            			<listitem>
            					<para> Further enhancements to laptop support (hot keys, and working suspend/resume on more models)</para>
            			</listitem>
            			<listitem>
            					<para>All-in-one printer/scanner devices from <emphasis>Hewlett-Packard</emphasis> (HP) are supported out of the box</para>
            			</listitem>
            			<listitem>
            					<para> Bluetooth input devices (such as keyboards and mice) are supported out of the box</para>
            			</listitem>
            			<listitem>
            					<para> Multiple audio devices are handled more gracefully (and one can easily select the default device)</para>
            			</listitem>
            			<listitem>
            					<para>64-bit kernel for PowerPC</para>
            			</listitem>
            	</itemizedlist>
            </sect2>
            <sect2 id="installation" status="review">
            	<title>Installation</title>
            	<itemizedlist>
            			<listitem>
            					<para>A new <acronym>OEM</acronym> mode to simplify the process of preinstalling Ubuntu on computers for resale or redistribution</para>
            			</listitem>
            			<listitem>
            					<para> Automatically makes existing hard drive partitions available to the desktop</para>
            			</listitem>
            			<listitem>
            					<para> Simple &quot;dual boot&quot; configuration with automatic resizing of an existing installed operating system</para>
            			</listitem>
            			<listitem>
            					<para>The second stage of the installation now has a progress bar</para>
            			</listitem>
            	</itemizedlist>
            </sect2>
            <sect2 id="under-the-hood" status="review">
            	<title>&quot;Under the Hood&quot;</title>
            	<itemizedlist> 
            	<listitem> 
            			<para>GCC 4.0.1</para>
            	</listitem> 
            	<listitem> 
            			<para>glibc 2.3.5</para>
            	</listitem> 
            	<listitem> 
            			<para>New early userspace infrastructure based on <emphasis>initramfs-tools</emphasis></para>
            	</listitem> 
            	<listitem> 
            			<para>More modular X.org packaging</para>
            	</listitem>
            	<listitem>
            			<para>Python 2.4.2</para>
            	</listitem>
            	</itemizedlist>
            	 <para>As always, Ubuntu includes the very best of the <emphasis role="bold">100% free/libre</emphasis> application software world, and each new release incorporates countless new features and bugfixes from the global development community.</para>
            </sect2>
    </sect1>
    <sect1 id="sect1-downlading-installing" status="review">
    		<title>Downlading and Installing</title>
    		<sect2 id="system-requirements" status="review">
    			<title>System Requirements</title>
    			<para>Ubuntu 5.10 supports three (3) major architectures: Intel x86, AMD64, and PowerPC. Depending on your needs, you might manage with less than some of the recommended hardware listed in the table below. However, most users risk being frustrated if they ignore these suggestions.</para>
				<table>
				<title>Recommended Minimum Requirements</title>
					<tgroup cols="3">
						<colspec colname="1"/>
						<colspec colname="2"/>
						<colspec colname="3"/>
						<thead>
							<row>
								<entry><para>Install Type</para></entry>
								<entry><para>RAM</para></entry>
								<entry><para>Hard Drive Space</para></entry>
							</row>
						</thead>
						<tbody>
							<row>
								<entry><para>Desktop</para></entry>
								<entry><para>128 megabytes</para></entry>
								<entry><para>2 gigabytes</para></entry>
							</row>
							<row>
								<entry><para>Server</para></entry>
								<entry><para>64 megabytes</para></entry>
								<entry><para>500 megabytes</para></entry>
							</row>
						</tbody>
					</tgroup>
				</table>
				<para>Here are some common Ubuntu 5.10 system configurations. Once again, the size of the installation will greatly depend on the software you install during setup. For most users, the default applications are suitable enough for general use.</para>
				<variablelist>
					<varlistentry>
						<term><emphasis role="bold">Desktop</emphasis></term>
						<listitem><para>A standard desktop box, including the X window system, full desktop environment, sound, office suite, email clients, etc. You'll need about 2 gigabytes of hard drive space using the standard desktop task.</para></listitem>
					</varlistentry>
					<varlistentry>
						<term><emphasis role="bold">Server</emphasis></term>
						<listitem><para>This is a small server profile, which provides a common base for all sorts of server applications. It's minimal and designed to have the desired services added on top, such as file/print services, web hosting, email hosting, etc. For these services at least 500MB of disk space would suffice, but consider adding more space depending on the services you'd like to host with your server.</para></listitem>
					</varlistentry>
				</variablelist>
				<para>Remember that these sizes don't include all the other materials which are usually to be found, such as user files, mail, and data. It is always best to be generous when considering the space for your own files and data.</para>
    		</sect2>
    		<sect2 id="downloading-ubuntu" status="review">
    			<title>Downloading Ubuntu 5.10</title>
    			<para>You can download Ubuntu 5.10 from the following mirrors located worldwide:</para>
    			<itemizedlist>
    				<listitem>
    					<para>United States: <ulink url="http://us.releases.ubuntu.com/releases/5.10">http://us.releases.ubuntu.com/releases/5.10</ulink>
</para>
    				</listitem>
    				<listitem>
    					<para>Europe: <ulink url="http://se.releases.ubuntu.com/5.10">http://se.releases.ubuntu.com/5.10</ulink></para>
    				</listitem>
    				<listitem>
    					<para>United Kingdom: <ulink url="http://releases.ubuntu.com/5.10">http://releases.ubuntu.com/5.10</ulink></para>
    				</listitem>
    				<listitem>
    					<para>Rest of the World: <ulink url="http://releases.ubuntu.com/5.10">http://releases.ubuntu.com/5.10</ulink>
</para>
    				</listitem>
    			</itemizedlist>
    			<para>You can also download all architecture types of Ubuntu 5.10 using Bittorrent and Jigdo.</para>
    		</sect2>
    		<sect2 id="requesting" status="review">
    			<title>Requesting Free Ubuntu 5.10 CDs</title>
    			<para>Ubuntu can mail pressed CDs worldwide free of charge. To receive a complimentary copy of the Official Ubuntu 5.10 CD, to give to your friends, your school or LUG - place your request at:</para>
    			<itemizedlist>
    				<listitem>
    					<para><ulink url="http://shipit.ubuntu.com">http://shipit.ubuntu.com</ulink></para>
    				</listitem>
    			</itemizedlist>
    		</sect2>
    		<sect2 id="installing-ubuntu" status="review">
    			<title>Installing Ubuntu 5.10</title>
    			<para>Once you have a copy of Ubuntu 5.10, follow these instructions to install:</para>
    		</sect2>
    </sect1>
    <sect1 id="sect1-known-issues" status="review">
        <title>Known Issues</title>
        <itemizedlist>
        		<listitem>
        				<para>Selecting the &quot;Use free space for LVM&quot; auto partitioning option in the Ubuntu Installer will most likely leave a system unbootable. This feature will be fixed in the next release. It is however possible to use it, given that a <emphasis>/boot</emphasis> partition is created manually (not on LVM volumes). See Ubuntu Bugzilla Entry <ulink url="http://bugzilla.ubuntu.com/show_bug.cgi?id=15017">#15017</ulink> for more details.</para>
        		</listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
    </sect1>
    <sect1 id="sect1-FAQ" status="review">
    		<title>Frequently Asked Questions</title>
    		<para></para>
    		<note><para>You can read more in-depth FAQs in the <ulink url="///usr/share/ubuntu-docs/generic/faqguide/C/faqguide.xml">Ubuntu 5.10 FAQ Guide</ulink>
.</para></note>

    </sect1>
    <sect1 id="sect1-feedback" status="review">
    		<title>Getting Help and Technical Support</title>
    		<para>Ubuntu 5.10 gives users an easy way to get help in most applications installed by default. Once you have an active internet connection, from an open application, just click on
    		<menuchoice>
    			<guimenu>Help</guimenu>
    			<guimenuitem>Get Help Online</guimenuitem>
    		</menuchoice>
    		and you'll be directed to an online webpage that gives you help and support options for the application.
    		</para>
    		<para>Technical Support for Ubuntu 5.10 is available from a variety of sources: from the community, from Canonical Ltd, from recognized organizations, and from developers directly through open web forums, mailing lists and IRC channels:</para>
    		<itemizedlist>
    			<listitem>
    				<para><ulink url="http://www.ubuntu.com/support">http://www.ubuntu.com/support</ulink>
</para>
    			</listitem>
    		</itemizedlist>
    		<para>If you have a question, or if you think you may have found a bug but aren&apos;t sure, first try asking on the #ubuntu IRC channel on Freenode, on the Ubuntu Users mailing list, or on the Ubuntu forums:</para>
    		<itemizedlist>
    			<listitem>
    				<para><ulink url="http://lists.ubuntu.com/mailman/listinfo/ubuntu-users">http://lists.ubuntu.com/mailman/listinfo/ubuntu-users</ulink>
</para>
    			</listitem>
    			<listitem>
    				<para><ulink url="http://www.ubuntuforums.org">http://www.ubuntuforums.org</ulink>
</para>
    			</listitem>
    		</itemizedlist>
    </sect1>
    <sect1 id="sect-bugs">
    		<title>Reporting Bugs</title>
    		<para>Your comments, bug reports, patches and suggestions will help fix bugs and improve future Ubuntu releases. Please report bugs through <emphasis>Bugzilla</emphasis>:</para>
    		<itemizedlist>
    			<listitem>
    				<para><ulink url="http://bugzilla.ubuntu.com">http://bugzilla.ubuntu.com</ulink>
</para>
    			</listitem>
    		</itemizedlist>
    </sect1>
    <sect1 id="sect-participate">
    		<title>Participate in Ubuntu</title>
    		<para>If you would like to help shape Ubuntu, take a look at the list of ways you can participate at:</para>
    		<itemizedlist>
    			<listitem>
    				<para><ulink url="http://www.ubuntu.com/community/participate"> http://www.ubuntu.com/community/participate</ulink></para>
    			</listitem>
    		</itemizedlist>
    </sect1>
    <sect1 id="sect-moreinfo" status="review">
    		<title>More Information</title>
    		<para>You can find out more about Ubuntu and about the 5.10 release on our website, IRC channel and wiki. If you're new to Ubuntu, please visit <ulink url="http://www.ubuntu.com">http://www.ubuntu.com</ulink>.</para>
			<para>To sign up for future Ubuntu announcements, please subscribe to Ubuntu's announcement list at <ulink url="http://lists.ubuntu.com/mailman/listinfo/ubuntu-announce">http://lists.ubuntu.com/mailman/listinfo/ubuntu-announce</ulink>.</para>
    </sect1>
</article>
