<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE bookinfo PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.3//EN" 
	"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.3/docbookx.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % globalent SYSTEM "../../../libs/global.ent">
%globalent;
<!ENTITY % cdo-C SYSTEM "../../../libs/cdo-C.ent">
%cdo-C;
<!ENTITY % pg-common SYSTEM "../pg-common.ent">
%pg-common;
<!ENTITY % xinclude SYSTEM "../../../libs/xinclude.mod">
%xinclude;
<!ENTITY language "en">
<!ENTITY ubuntu '<phrase>Ubuntu</phrase>'>
]>
<bookinfo>
	<title>우분투 패키징 안내서</title>
	<legalnotice id="Credits-And-License">
	    <title>명예와 저작권</title>
	    <para>다음의 우분투 문서화 팀 작성자가 이 문서를 유지관리 합니다:</para>
		 <itemizedlist>
			<listitem>
		    <para>Jordan Mantha</para>
			</listitem>
		</itemizedlist>
		<para>우분투 패키징 안내서는 또한 이 분들의 공헌에 기반 합니다:</para>
		<itemizedlist>
			<listitem>
		    <para>Alexandre Vassalotti</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
	            <para>Jonathan Patrick Davies</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para>Ankur Kotwal</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para>Rapha&euml;l Pinson</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para>Daniel Chen</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para>Martin Pitt</para>
			</listitem>
		</itemizedlist>

		<para>Portions of the Ubuntu Packaging Guide are derived from the
			Debian New Maintainer's Guide and the Debian Policy Manual.</para>
		
		<para>이 문서는 GNU 일반 공개 저작권 (GPL) 하에 사용하도록 만들어 졌습니다.</para>
	    <para>여러분의 이 라이센스 하에 우분투 문서의 소스 코드를 변경, 확장 그리고 개선하는데 자유롭습니다. 모든 파생된 작업은 반드시 이 라이센스 하에 발표되어야 합니다.</para>
	    <para>이 문서는 유용하게 사용될 것이라는 희망으로 배포 합니다만, 어떠한 품질 보증; 즉 매매의 암묵적인 보장 또는 경고문에 기술된 특정 목적을 위한 적합 같은 보증이 없습니다.</para>
	    <para>Copies of the license are available in the appendices section of this book
			and online at <ulink url="http://www.gnu.org/licenses/gpl.html">GNU General Public License</ulink>.</para>
	</legalnotice>
        
<copyright>
    <year>2004, 2005, 2006</year>
    <holder>Canonical Ltd. and members of the Ubuntu Documentation Project</holder>
</copyright>

        <authorgroup>
            
<corpauthor>Ubuntu Documentation Project <emphasis>&lt;ubuntu-doc@lists.ubuntu.com&gt;</emphasis>
</corpauthor>

        </authorgroup>
        <abstract>
            <para>우분투 패키징 안내서는 우분투와 여타 데비안 기반 배포판을 위한 프로그램을 패키징하는 소개 입니다.</para>
        </abstract>
        
<legalnotice>
    <title>Disclaimer</title>
    <para>Every effort has been made to ensure that the information compiled in this publication is
        accurate and correct. However, this does not guarantee complete accuracy. Neither
        Canonical Ltd., the authors, nor translators shall be held liable for possible errors or
        the consequences thereof.</para>
    <para>Some of the software and hardware descriptions cited in this publication may be registered trademarks and may thus fall under copyright restrictions and trade protection laws. In no way do the authors make claim to any such names.</para>
    <para>THIS DOCUMENTATION IS PROVIDED BY THE AUTHORS "AS IS" AND ANY EXPRESS OR
        IMPLIED WARRANTIES, INCLUDING, BUT NOT LIMITED TO, THE IMPLIED WARRANTIES OF MERCHANTABILITY
        AND FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE ARE DISCLAIMED. IN NO EVENT SHALL THE AUTHORS BE LIABLE
        FOR ANY DIRECT, INDIRECT, INCIDENTAL, SPECIAL, EXEMPLARY, OR CONSEQUENTIAL DAMAGES
        (INCLUDING, BUT NOT LIMITED TO, PROCUREMENT OF SUBSTITUTE GOODS OR SERVICES; LOSS OF USE,
        DATA, OR PROFITS; OR BUSINESS INTERRUPTION) HOWEVER CAUSED AND ON ANY THEORY OF LIABILITY,
        WHETHER IN CONTRACT, STRICT LIABILITY, OR TORT (INCLUDING NEGLIGENCE OR OTHERWISE) ARISING
        IN ANY WAY OUT OF THE USE OF THIS SOFTWARE, EVEN IF ADVISED OF THE POSSIBILITY OF SUCH DAMAGE.</para>
</legalnotice>

        
<publisher>
    <publishername>The Ubuntu Documentation Project</publishername>
</publisher>

</bookinfo>

