<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.3//EN" 
	"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.3/docbookx.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % globalent SYSTEM "../../../libs/global.ent">
%globalent;
<!ENTITY % cdo-C SYSTEM "../../../libs/cdo-C.ent">
%cdo-C;
<!ENTITY % gnome-menus-C SYSTEM "../../../ubuntu/libs/gnome-menus-C.ent">
%gnome-menus-C;
<!ENTITY % xinclude SYSTEM "../../../libs/xinclude.mod">
%xinclude;
<!ENTITY language "en">
<!ENTITY distro-rev "6.04">
<!ENTITY distro-version "Dapper Drake">
<!ENTITY distro-release-date "April 2006">
<!ENTITY ubuntu '<phrase>Ubuntu</phrase>'>
]>
<chapter id="add-applications" xreflabel="Adding, Removing and Updating Applications" status="complete">
	<title>Adding, Removing and Updating Applications</title>
		<para>There are several ways to manage your applications in Ubuntu. In order to add or remove applications you need to use a <emphasis>package manager</emphasis>. The following package managers are described in this section:</para>
		<itemizedlist>
			<listitem><para><application>Add/Remove Applications</application> - this is the simplest way to manage programs;</para></listitem>
			<listitem><para><application>Synaptic</application> - this graphical program provides a more advanced means of managing programs;</para></listitem>
			<listitem><para><application>APT</application> - this is a powerful command line program to manage programs.</para></listitem>
		</itemizedlist>
		<para>You may also wish to increase the number of programs available to install through your package managers. Not all the programs that exist for Ubuntu are available by default. You may have to add extra repositories in order to make them available: that is also described in this section.</para>
		<para>Finally, this section explains how to update your system.</para>
			<note>
				<para>You can only have one package management application running at a time. For example, if you are running <application>Add/Remove Applications</application> and try to launch <application>Synaptic</application>, it will fail with an error. Close the running application before you relaunch the new one.
				</para>
			</note>
	    <sect1 id="gnome-app-install" status="complete">
		<title>Add/Remove Applications</title>
			<para><application>Add/Remove Applications</application> is a simple graphical way of installing and removing applications in Ubuntu. To launch Add/Remove Applications click
				<menuchoice>
					<guimenu>Applications</guimenu>
					<guimenuitem>Add/Remove Applications</guimenuitem>
				</menuchoice> on the desktop menu system.
			</para>
			<note>
			<para>Running <application>Add/Remove Applications</application> requires administrative privileges (see <xref linkend="root-and-sudo"/>).
			</para>
			</note>
			<para>To install new applications select the category on the left, then check the box of the application you want to install. When finished click <guimenu>Apply</guimenu>, then your chosen programs will be downloaded and installed automatically, as well as installing any additional applications that are required.</para>
			<para>Alternatively, if you know the name of the program you want, use the search tool at the top.</para>
			<note><para>If you have not activated the online package archive, you may be asked to insert your Ubuntu CD-ROM to install some packages.</para></note>
			<para>Some applications and packages are not available to install using <application>Add Programs</application>. If you cannot find the package you are looking for, click <guibutton>Advanced</guibutton> which will open the Synaptic package manager (see below).
			</para>
		</sect1>

	    <sect1 id="synaptic" xreflabel="Synaptic Package Manager" status="review">
		<title>Synaptic Package Manager</title>
			<para><application>Synaptic</application> is an advanced package management application that can install and remove every package available to your system. The interface is graphical like <application>Add/Remove Applications</application>  but a lot more information is presented to the user, which means that <application>Synaptic</application> gives you complete control over the package management of your system.</para>
			<note>
			<para>Running <application>Synaptic</application> requires administrative privileges (see <xref linkend="root-and-sudo"/>).
			</para>
			</note>
			<para>To launch <application>Synaptic</application>, choose 
				<menuchoice>
					<guimenu>System</guimenu>
					<guisubmenu>Administration</guisubmenu>
					<guimenuitem>Synaptic Package Manager</guimenuitem>
				</menuchoice> on the desktop menu system.
			</para>
			<para>The <application>Synaptic</application> screen is divided up into four sections, the two most important being the package categories on the left side, and the packages on the right.
			</para>
			<para>To install packages, just choose the category, find the package name in the list, right click on it and choose "<guimenuitem>Mark this package for installation</guimenuitem>". Once you are satisfied with your selections click <guibutton>Apply</guibutton> on the top button bar. <application>Synaptic</application> will then download and install the required packages from the online repositories and/or from your Ubuntu installation CD.
			</para>
			<para>Alternatively you can click the <guibutton>Search</guibutton> tool bar button, enter the package name or a short search term in the search text field and click the <guibutton>Search</guibutton> button.
			</para>
			<para><application>Synaptic</application> will now show you a much shorter list from which to select your application for installation. This is usually much easier than having to look through the very long list of applications on your own.
			</para>
		</sect1>
		<sect1 id="apt-get" status="complete">
			<title>APT</title>
				<para><application>APT</application> (Advanced Packaging Tool) is a powerful package management system, on which the graphical programs described above like <application>Add/Remove Applications</application> and <application>Synaptic</application> are based. <application>APT</application> automatically handles dependencies and performs other operations on system packages to allow the installation of the desired package/s.</para>
			<note>
			<para>Running <application>APT</application> requires administrative privileges (see <xref linkend="root-and-sudo"/>).
			</para>
			</note>

			<para>Some common commands that can be used with <application>APT</application>:</para>
			<itemizedlist>
				<listitem>
					<para>Install packages:
					<screen>sudo apt-get install <emphasis>packagename</emphasis></screen>
					</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>Remove packages:
					<screen>sudo apt-get remove <emphasis>packagename</emphasis></screen>
					</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>Retrieve new lists of packages:
					<screen>sudo apt-get update</screen>
					</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>Upgrade system with available updates:
					<screen>sudo apt-get upgrade</screen>
					</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>List further commands and options:
					<screen>apt-get help</screen>
					</para>
				</listitem>
			</itemizedlist>
			<tip>
				<para>For further information about the use of <application>APT</application>, you can read the comprehensive <ulink url="&debian-apt;">Debian APT User Manual</ulink>.
				</para>
			</tip>
		</sect1>

	    <sect1 id="extra-repositories" xreflabel="Adding Extra Repositories" status="review">
		<title>Extra Repositories</title>
			<sect2 status="review"><title>What are Repositories?</title>
			<para>There are thousands of programs available to install on Ubuntu. These programs are stored in software archives (<emphasis>repositories</emphasis>) and are made freely available for installation over the Internet. This makes it very easy to install new programs in Linux, and it is also very secure, because each program you install is built specially for Ubuntu and checked before it is installed. To organise the software, Ubuntu repositories are categorised into four groups: <emphasis>Main</emphasis>, <emphasis>Restricted</emphasis>, <emphasis>Universe</emphasis>, and <emphasis>Multiverse</emphasis>.</para> 
			<para>The rationale used to determine which software goes into which category is based on two factors:</para>
				<itemizedlist>
					<listitem>
						<para>The level of support software development teams provide for a program.</para>
					</listitem>
					<listitem>
						<para>The level of compliance the program has to the <ulink url="&ubuntu-philosophy;">Free Software Philosophy</ulink>.</para>
					</listitem>
				</itemizedlist>
			<para>You can find more information about the Repositories available <ulink url="&ubuntu-components;">on the website</ulink>.</para>
			<para>The standard Ubuntu Install CD contains some software from the <emphasis>Main</emphasis> and <emphasis>Restricted</emphasis> categories. Once your system is made aware of the Internet-based locations for these repositories, many more software programs are made available for installation. Using the software package management tools already installed on your system, you can search for, install and update any piece of software directly over the Internet, without the need for the CD.</para>
		</sect2>
		<sect2 status="review">
			<title>Adding Extra Repositories</title>
			<para>To enable the extra repositories:</para>
			<procedure>
				<step>
					<para>Open &gnome-app-install;.</para>
				</step>
				<step>
					<para>To enable the <emphasis>Universe</emphasis> repository, check the <guibutton>Show unsupported applications</guibutton> button.</para>
					<note>
						<para>Adding this repository will mean that the majority of the Free Software universe will be available to install on your system. This software is supported by a carefully selected group of volunteers within the Ubuntu Community, but is not supported by the core Ubuntu development team and may not include security updates.</para>
					</note>
				</step>
				<step><para>To enable the <emphasis>Multiverse</emphasis> repository, check the <guibutton>Show proprietary applications</guibutton> button.</para>
					<warning>
						<para>Adding this repository will mean that software which has been classified as <emphasis>non-free</emphasis> will be available to install on your system. This software may not be permitted in some jurisdictions. When installing each package from this repository, you should verify that the laws of your country permit you to use it. Again, this software may not include security updates.</para>
					</warning>
				</step>
				<step><para>Click <guibutton>Apply</guibutton> to save your changes, and then exit using <guibutton>OK</guibutton>.</para>
				</step>
			</procedure>
			</sect2>
		</sect1>
	    <sect1 id="updates" xreflabel="Update Ubuntu" status="complete">
		<title>Updates</title>
			<para>Sometimes the Ubuntu developers release feature and security updates for applications and packages within the Ubuntu system.
			</para>
			<para>When these updates are available, Ubuntu will inform you with a pop-up and a red icon in your notification area. To update your system, click the red button, enter your password and click <guibutton>OK</guibutton>.
			</para>
			<para>The <application>Update Manager</application> program will list the available updates: to download and install these updates click <guibutton>Install Updates</guibutton>. Ubuntu will then download and install the available updates from the Internet.
			</para>
			<para>When <application>Update Manager</application> has finished updating your system, close the pop-up window with the <guibutton>Close</guibutton> button, then close <application>Update Manager</application> to finish updating your system. 
			</para>
			<note>
				<para>After installing some important updates, it may be necessary to restart your computer. If so, Ubuntu will inform you with a popup and an icon in your notification area.
				</para>
			</note>
	   </sect1>
</chapter>
