<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.3//EN" 
	"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.3/docbookx.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % globalent SYSTEM "../../../libs/global.ent">
%globalent;
<!ENTITY % cdo-C SYSTEM "../../../libs/cdo-C.ent">
%cdo-C;
<!ENTITY % gnome-menus-C SYSTEM "../../../ubuntu/libs/gnome-menus-C.ent">
%gnome-menus-C;
<!ENTITY % xinclude SYSTEM "../../../libs/xinclude.mod">
%xinclude;
<!ENTITY language "en">
<!ENTITY distro-rev "6.04">
<!ENTITY distro-version "Dapper Drake">
<!ENTITY distro-release-date "April 2006">
<!ENTITY ubuntu '<phrase>Ubuntu</phrase>'>
]>
<chapter id="add-applications" xreflabel="Adding, Removing and Updating Applications" status="writing">
	<title>Adding, Removing and Updating Applications</title>
		<para>There are several ways to manage your applications in Ubuntu. Each method of managing applications involves a different level of complexity. This section describes the following methods of adding, removing and updating applications:</para>
		<itemizedlist>
			<listitem><para>the Add Applications program - this is the simplest way to add and remove programs</para></listitem>
			<listitem><para>the Synaptic package manager - this graphical program provides a more advanced means of handling programs</para></listitem>
		<!--think about whether to include a section on apt from the command line here (mdke)-->	
		</itemizedlist>
	    <sect1 id="gnome-app-install" status="writing">
		<title>Add/Remove Applications</title>
			<para>Add/Remove Applications is a simple graphical way of installing and removing applications in Ubuntu. To launch Add/Remove Applications click
				<menuchoice>
					<guimenu>Applications</guimenu>
					<guimenuitem>Add/Remove Applications</guimenuitem>
				</menuchoice> on the desktop menu system.
			</para>
			<para>Running <application>Add/Remove Applications</application> requires administrative privileges (see <xref linkend="root-and-sudo"/>).
			</para>
			<para>To install new applications select the category on the left, then check the box of the application you want to install. When finished click <guimenu>Apply</guimenu>, then your chosen programs will be downloaded and installed automatically, as well as installing any additional applications that are required.</para>
			<para>Alternatively, if you know the name of the program you want, use the search tool at the top.</para>
			<note><para>If you have not activated the online package archive, you may be asked to insert your Ubuntu CD-ROM to install some packages.</para></note>
			<para>Some applications and packages are not available to install using <application>Add Programs</application>. If you cannot find the package you are looking for, click <guibutton>Advanced</guibutton> which will open the Synaptic package manager (see below).
			</para>
		</sect1>

	    <sect1 id="synaptic" xreflabel="Synaptic Package Manager" status="writing">
		<title>Synaptic Package Manager</title>
			<para>Synaptic is an advanced package management application that can install and remove every package available to your system. The interface is graphical but a lot more information is presented to the user, however this means that Synaptic gives you complete control over the package management of your system.
To launch Synaptic, choose 
				<menuchoice>
					<guimenu>System</guimenu>
					<guisubmenu>Administration</guisubmenu>
					<guimenuitem>Synaptic Package Manager</guimenuitem>
				</menuchoice> on the desktop menu system.
			</para>
			<para>The Synaptic screen is divided up into four sections, the two most important being the package categories on the left side, and the packages on the right. To install packages, just choose the category, find the package name in the list, right click on it and choose "Mark this package for installation". Once you are satisfied with your selections click <guibutton>Apply</guibutton> on the top menu bar. Synaptic will then download and install the required packages from the online repositories and/or from your Ubuntu installation CD.
			</para>
			<para>Alternatively you can click the Search tool bar button, enter the package name in the search text field and click the Search button. Synaptic will now show you a much shorter list from which to select your application for installation. This can be much easier than having to look through the very long list of applications on your own.
			</para>
		</sect1>

	    <sect1 id="extra-repositories" xreflabel="Adding Extra Repositories" status="writing">
		<title>Extra Repositories</title>
			<sect2 status="writing"><title>What are Repositories?</title>
			<para>There are thousands of programs available to install on Ubuntu. These programs are stored in software archives (<emphasis>repositories</emphasis>) and are made freely available for installation over the Internet. This makes it very easy to install new programs in Linux, and it is also very secure, because each program you install is built specially for Ubuntu and checked before it is installed. To organise the software, Ubuntu repositories are categorised into four groups: <emphasis>Main</emphasis>, <emphasis>Restricted</emphasis>, <emphasis>Universe</emphasis>, and <emphasis>Multiverse</emphasis>.</para> <!-- backports? -->
			<para>The rational used to determine which software goes into which category is based on two factors:</para>
				<itemizedlist>
					<listitem>
						<para>The level of support software development teams provide for a program.</para>
					</listitem>
					<listitem>
						<para>The level of compliance the program has to the <ulink url="&ubuntu-philosophy;">Free Software Philosophy</ulink>.</para>
					</listitem>
				</itemizedlist>
			<para>The standard Ubuntu Install CD contains some software from the <emphasis>Main</emphasis> and <emphasis>Restricted</emphasis> categories. Once your system is made aware of the Internet-based locations for these repositories, many more software programs are made available for installation. Using the software package management tools already installed on your system, you can search for, install and update any piece of software directly over the Internet, without the need for the CD.</para>
		</sect2>
		<sect2 status="writing">
			<title>Adding Extra Repositories</title>
			<para>To enable the extra repositories:</para>
			<procedure>
				<step>
					<para>Open &gnome-app-install;.</para>
				</step>
				<step>
					<para>To enable the <emphasis>Universe</emphasis> repository, check the <guibutton>Show unsupported applications</guibutton> button.</para>
				</step>
				<step><para>To enable the <emphasis>Multiverse</emphasis> repository, check the <guibutton>Show proprietary applications</guibutton> button.</para>
				</step>
				<step><para>Click <guibutton>Apply</guibutton> to save your changes, and then exit using <guibutton>OK</guibutton>.</para>
				</step>
			</procedure>
			</sect2>
		</sect1>
	    <sect1 id="updates" xreflabel="Update Ubuntu" status="writing">
		<title>Updates</title>
			<para>Sometimes the Ubuntu developers release feature and security updates for applications and packages within the Ubuntu system. When these updates are available, Ubuntu will inform you with a pop-up from your notification area. When you see this pop-up, click <guibutton>Show Updates</guibutton>, enter your password and click <guibutton>OK</guibutton>. The Ubuntu Update manager will list the available updates: to download and install these updates click <guibutton>Install</guibutton>. Ubuntu will then download and install the available updates from the Internet.  When Ubuntu Update manager has finished updating your system, click <guibutton>Close</guibutton>, then close Ubuntu Update Manager to finish updating your system. 
			</para>
	   </sect1>
</chapter>
