<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.3//EN" 
	"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.3/docbookx.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % globalent SYSTEM "../../../libs/global.ent">
%globalent;
<!ENTITY % cdo-C SYSTEM "../../../libs/cdo-C.ent">
%cdo-C;
<!ENTITY % gnome-menus-C SYSTEM "../../../ubuntu/libs/gnome-menus-C.ent">
%gnome-menus-C;
<!ENTITY % xinclude SYSTEM "../../../libs/xinclude.mod">
%xinclude;
<!ENTITY language "en">
<!ENTITY distro-rev "6.04">
<!ENTITY distro-version "Dapper Drake">
<!ENTITY ubuntu '<phrase>Ubuntu</phrase>'>
]>
<chapter id="getting-started-chap">
	<title id="getting-started">Getting Started</title>
	<sect1 id="introduction" status="writing">
	    <title>Introduction</title>
            <para>Thank you for your interest in Ubuntu Linux &distro-rev;
                -- our &distro-version; release.</para>
            <para id="about1">Ubuntu Linux is an entirely open source operating
                system built around the Linux kernel. The Ubuntu community is
                comprised of developers, programmers, testers, techwriters,
                documentation testers, translators, and most importantly, the
                people who use Ubuntu every day. We invite you to join this
                community and help make Ubuntu the operating system you, your
                family, your friends, and your colleages will love to use. Help
                us translate Ubuntu into your language, try it on new and
                unusual hardware, improve the experience of other users with
                hints, tips, and FAQs, or help to shape the direction Ubuntu is
                headed by providing feedback about the software you love most.</para>
            <para id="about2">The Ubuntu community is built around the ideals
                enshrined in the Ubuntu Manifesto: that software should be
                available free of charge, that software tools should be usable
                by people in their local language and despite any disabilities,
                and that people should have the freedom to customize and alter
                their software in whatever way they see fit. For those reasons: <itemizedlist>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Ubuntu will always be free of charge, and there is
                            no extra fee for the &quot;enterprise
                            edition,&quot; we make our very best work
                            available to everyone on the same Free terms.</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Ubuntu includes the very best in translations and
                            accessibility infrastructure that the Free Software
                            community has to offer, to make Ubuntu usable for as
                            many people as possible.</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Ubuntu is released regularly and predictably; a
                            new release is made every six months. You can use
                            the current stable release or the current
                            development release. Each release is supported for
                            at least 18 months.</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Ubuntu is entirely committed to the principles of
                            open source software development; we encourage
                            people to use open source software, improve it and
                            pass it on.</para>
                    </listitem>
                </itemizedlist>
            </para>
            <para id="about3">Find out more at <ulink url="&ubuntu-web;">&ubuntu-web;</ulink> or take a look
                at some of the following: <itemizedlist>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>The Ubuntu <ulink url="&ubuntu-lists;">Mailing
                                Lists</ulink>, where the community discusses new
                            ideas and issues with Ubuntu.</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>The <ulink url="&ubuntu-wiki;">Ubuntu
                            Wiki</ulink>, where we collaborate on the policies
                            and strategy documents that define the direction
                            Ubuntu will follow.</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Chat with the community on Freenode IRC Channel:
                            #ubuntu.</para>
                    </listitem>
                </itemizedlist>
            </para>
            <sect2 id="about-ubuntu" status="writing">
                <title>About Ubuntu</title>
                <indexterm>
                    <primary>What is Ubuntu</primary>
                    <secondary>What does the word mean</secondary>
                </indexterm>
                <sect3 id="sect-ubuntu-name" status="writing">
                    <title>About the Name</title>
                    <para>On hearing the name &quot;Ubuntu&quot;, many
                        people are curious about the meaning of the word.</para>
                    <para>Ubuntu is a South African ethic ideology focusing on
                        people's allegiances and relations with each other. The
                        word comes from the Zulu and Xhosa languages. Ubuntu,
                        pronounced &quot;oo-BOON-too,&quot; is seen as a
                        traditional African concept and is held as one of the
                        founding principles of the new republic of South Africa
                        and connected to the idea of an African Renaissance.</para>
                    <para>A rough translation of Ubuntu's principles could be
                        &quot;humanity towards others.&quot; Another
                        translation could be: &quot;The belief in a
                        universal bond of sharing that connects all
                        humanity.&quot;</para>
                    <para>&quot;A person with ubuntu is open and available
                        to others, affirming of others, does not feel threatened
                        that others are able and good, for he or she has a
                        proper self-assurance that comes from knowing that he or
                        she belongs in a greater whole and is diminished when
                        others are humiliated or diminished, when others are
                        tortured or oppressed.&quot; <emphasis>-- Archbishop
                            Desmond Tutu</emphasis>.</para>
                    <para>As a platform based on GNU/Linux, the Ubuntu
                        distribution brings the spirit of Ubuntu to the software
                        world.</para>
                </sect3>
                <sect3 id="sect-ubuntu-difference" status="writing">
                    <title>The Difference</title>
                    <para>There are many GNU/Linux distributions in the world,
                        some are built from the ground up and some are based on
                        others; each has aimed to perfect the platform and its
                        desktop. However, only a few survive, with names such as
                        Debian, SuSE, Gentoo, RedHat, and Mandrake being the
                        most notable.</para>
                    <para>Based on Debian, one of the most widely acclaimed,
                        technologically advanced, and well-supported
                        distributions, Ubuntu is yet another contender in what
                        is already a highly competitive world. So what makes
                        Ubuntu different?</para>
                    <para>With its solid and advanced Debian foundation, Ubuntu
                        aims to create a Debian-based distribution that provides
                        an up-to-date and coherent Linux system for desktop and
                        server computing. Ubuntu includes a number of carefully
                        selected packages from the Debian distribution and
                        retains its powerful package management system which
                        allows easy installation and clean removal of programs,
                        as well as automatically handling any dependencies
                        programs may have on each other. Unlike most
                        distributions that ship with a large amount of software
                        that may or may not be of use, Ubuntu's list of packages
                        is reduced to a number of important applications of high
                        quality.</para>
                    <para>By focusing on quality, Ubuntu produces a robust and
                        feature-rich computing environment that is suitable for
                        use in both home and commercial environments. The
                        project takes the time required to focus on finer
                        details and is able to release a version featuring the
                        latest and greatest of today's software once every 6
                        months. Ubuntu is available in flavours for the i386
                        (386/486/Pentium(II/III/IV) and Athlon/Duron/Sempron
                        processors), AMD64 (Athlon64, Opteron, and new 64-bit
                        Intel processors), and PowerPC (iBook/Powerbook, G4 and
                        G5) architectures.</para>
                </sect3>
                <sect3 id="sect-ubuntu-desktop" status="writing">
                    <title>The Desktop</title>
                    <para>The default desktop environment for Ubuntu is <ulink
                            url="&gnome;">GNOME</ulink>, a leading UNIX and
                        Linux desktop suite and development platform.</para>
                    <para>Another leading UNIX and Linux desktop is <ulink
                            url="&kde;">KDE</ulink>. Ubuntu does not
                        currently make use of the KDE desktop by default. The
                        reason for this is that the Ubuntu project does not, at
                        this stage, have the resources to put the same level of
                        pre-release work into the KDE packages as it devotes to
                        those comprising GNOME. However, the <ulink
                            url="&kubuntu-main;">Kubuntu</ulink> project has
                        sprung up which aims to offer Ubuntu users a choice
                        between these two excellent desktop environments. Thanks
                        to the efforts of the Kubuntu team, Ubuntu users are now
                        able to install and use the KDE desktop easily on their
                        system. The KDE software can now be found in and
                        downloaded from the main Ubuntu archive.  The easiest way
			to get a working install of kubuntu is sudo apt-get install
			kubuntu-desktop.  This will install the different packages
			required and set everything up correctly.</para>
		  <para>After everything is installed, one can choose which 
			  enviroment to use, either Gnome or KDE.
		  </para>
                    <!-- the section on Kubuntu needs to be better expressed, drawing on (hopefully incorporating) the kde/userguide -->
                </sect3>
                <sect3 id="sect-ubuntu-ooo" status="writing">
                    <title>OpenOffice.org</title>
                    <para>Ubuntu includes the excellent
                            <application>OpenOffice.org</application> Business
                        Productivity software suite. It includes a word
                        processor, a spreadsheet, and presentation software, all
                        of which is largely compatible with popular proprietary
                        software. Read more about the OpenOffice.org project at
                            <ulink url="&ooo;">OpenOffice.org
                    </ulink>.</para>
                </sect3>
                <sect3 id="sect-ubuntu-cost" status="writing">
                    <title>The Cost</title>
                    <para>The Ubuntu project is entirely committed to the
                        principles of open source software development; people
                        are encouraged to use open source software, improve it,
                        and pass it on. This means that Ubuntu is and will
                        always be free of charge. That's right -- this is not a
                        typo -- Ubuntu does not and will never cost anything.
                        There is no purchase price or license cost associated
                        with Ubuntu.</para>
                    <para>However, this means more than just being available at
                        zero cost -- it's &apos;free&apos; as in
                        &apos;free speech.&apos; In addition to the fact
                        that you don't need to pay a cent for the software
                        (media and download costs excluded), you may use,
                        modify, and redistribute any and all parts of all open
                        source software freely. Look at and borrow from the
                        source code if you happen to be curious, or contribute
                        to a project you like. Of course, there's nothing wrong
                        with just using the software for your own purposes --
                        not everyone has to be a programmer.</para>
                </sect3>
                <sect3 id="sect-ubuntu-backing-support" status="writing">
                    <title>Backing and Support</title>
                    <para>Ubuntu is maintained by a quickly growing community.
                        The project initiative is sponsored by <ulink
                            url="&canonical-url;">Canonical Ltd.</ulink>, a
                        holding company founded by Mark Shuttleworth. Canonical
                        mainly works to provide support and consulting services
                        centred around Ubuntu.</para>
                    <para>As an open source project, the primary source of
                        support for the distribution is found in the forms of
                        its documentation and community. These forms of support
                        are free for everyone. However, a number of people are
                        not computer fanatics and may find themselves in need of
                        additional support. Furthermore, in many commercial
                        environments, these free forms of support may prove
                        inadequate and a dedicated source of support may be
                        required.</para>
                    <para>In such cases, private individuals and commercial
                        organizations have the option of contracting commercial
                        support, too. More information about <ulink
                            url="&ubuntu-paidsupport;">paid technical
                            support</ulink> can be found on the <ulink
                            url="&ubuntu-paidsupport;">Ubuntu Web
                        Site</ulink>.</para>
                    <para>It is worth noting once more that Ubuntu and all
                        community support and documentation is entirely free;
                        Canonical sells <emphasis>support</emphasis> for Ubuntu,
                        not the software itself.</para>
                </sect3>
            </sect2>
            <sect2 id="about-linux" status="writing">
            <title>What is Linux?</title>
            <para>Contrary to what you may have heard from the media, from
                friends, or from the Internet, Linux is not an operating system.
                No, really. It isn't an OS. What is commonly referred to as
                "Linux" is actually a combination of <ulink url="&gnu;"
                >GNU</ulink>, pronounced "guh-noo", software and the <ulink
                    url="&kernel;">Linux kernel</ulink>, pronounced
                &apos;lee-nucks&apos;. A kernel is an important part of
                any operating system, communicating between the computer's
                hardware and the software.</para>
            <para>Linux was brought to life in 1991 by a Finnish student named
                Linus Torvalds. At the time, it would run only on i386 systems,
                and was essentially an independently created clone of the UNIX
                kernel, intended to take advantage of the then-new i386
                architecture. Around the same time, the GNU project, launched in
                1984, was making progress on their UNIX OS clone, lacking, for
                all practical purposes, only a kernel. Linux, unlike the GNU
                project's ideal kernel, Hurd, was, at the time, limited to the
                i386 platform, so it took some time before the two projects
                joined forces.</para>
            <para>Nowadays, thanks to a substantial amount of development
                effort, Linux runs on virtually every modern architecture, and
                GNU software provides the necessary tools to make it useful.
                Conceptually, Linux is the heart of the GNU/Linux operating
                system model, and GNU is the body. Distributions, such as
                Ubuntu, which provide GNU/Linux as well as a number of useful
                programs, are operating systems.</para>
            <para>To summarize that, Ubuntu is an operating system based on the
                GNU/Linux model, with Linux being the kernel.</para>
            <para>However, beyond the technical definition of Linux, there
                exists an entire community of people who believe in the ideals
                of free software and spend their time helping to make open
                source technology as good as it can be.</para>
            <para>People in this community gave rise to initiatives such as
                Ubuntu, standards commitees that shape the development of the
                Internet, organizations like the Mozilla Foundation, responsible
                for creating Mozilla Firefox, and countless other software
                projects from which you've certainly benefitted in the past.</para>
            <para>The spirit of open source, commonly attributed to Linux, is
                influencing software developers and users everywhere, driving a
                community. This is discussed further in the next chapter.</para>
        </sect2>
        <sect2 id="about-gnu" status="review">
            <title>What is GNU?</title>
            <para>The GNU Project was launched in 1984 to develop a complete
                UNIX style operating system which is free software: the GNU
                system. (GNU is a recursive acronym for “GNU's Not UNIX”; it is
                pronounced “guh-noo.”) Variants of the GNU operating system,
                which use the kernel Linux, are now widely used; though these
                systems are often referred to as “Linux,” they are more
                accurately called GNU/Linux systems.</para>
            <para>GNU has a very particular philosophy, which is central to the
                projects that derive from it, such as Ubuntu. It can be
                essentially summarised like this: &quot;Free software is a
                matter of freedom: people should be free to use software in all
                the ways that are socially useful&quot;. &quot;Free
                software&quot; does not mean that you shouldn't have to pay
                for it, it also means that you should be able to use the
                software in any way you wish: the code that makes up free
                software is available for anyone to download, change, fix, and
                use in any way. So apart from the fact that free software is
                often available without charge, this freedom also has technical
                advantages: when programs are developed, the hard work of others
                can be used and built upon. With non-free software, this cannot
                happen and when programs are developed, they have to start from
                scratch. For this reason the development of free software is
                fast, efficient and exciting!</para>
            <para>You can find out more about this philosophy <ulink
                    url="&gnu-philosophy;">here</ulink>.</para>
            </sect2>
            <sect2 id="sect-cd" status="writing">
                <title>Ubuntu Compact Discs</title>
                <indexterm>
                    <primary>Free CDs?</primary>
                    <secondary>CD request status</secondary>
                </indexterm>
                <sect3 id="sect-ver-rel" status="writing">
                    <title>Version and Release Numbers</title>
                    <para>The Ubuntu version numbering scheme is based on the
                        date we release a version of the distribution. The
                        version number comes from the year and month of the
                        release rather than reflecting the actual version of the
                        software. So, our first release (Warty Warthog) was in
                        October 2004, so its version was 4.10. Our second
                        release (Hoary Hedgehog) was in April 2005, so its
                        version was 5.04. The next release (Breezy Badger), the
                        one for which this document was written, will be in
                        October 2005, so its version number will be 5.10.</para>
                    <para>Each Ubuntu release has a unique combination of
                        component versions: kernel, X, Gnome, GCC, libc, etc. so
                        an aggregate version number does not make much sense. We
                        prefer to give an idea of when each release was pushed
                        through the wires.</para>
                    <para>You may ask yourself, &quot;With such a numbering
                        scheme, what happens when the version number reaches
                        2100?&quot;</para>
                    <para>Our answer is, &quot;Our grandchildren should be
                        able to figure that one out. At the moment, we're just
                        focused on the next release :-)&quot;</para>
                    <!-- It would be 100.04. =P (NT) -->
                </sect3>
                <sect3 id="obtaining-cds" status="writing">
                    <title>Obtaining Ubuntu CDs</title>
                    <para>There are a number of methods you may use to obtain a
                        copy of Ubuntu, all of which are described on the Ubuntu
                        Web site <ulink url="&ubuntu-download;">download
                            page</ulink>.</para>
                    <para>The first method is to download an ISO image from a
                        mirror server near you and make an &apos;Install
                        CD&apos; from it.</para>
                    <para>If you don't have a CD burner or you are in a country
                        without a mirror server, limited or expensive bandwidth,
                        we can send you pressed copies of the &apos;Install
                        CD&apos; free of charge. You may request CDs via
                        Shipit, the Ubuntu CD Distribution System also found on
                        the Ubuntu Web site <ulink url="&ubuntu-download;"
                            >download page</ulink>. Please provide full shipping
                        information (including postal address) or we will not be
                        able to send you the CDs.</para>
                    <note>
                        <para>For each release, we define a cut-off date by
                            which orders for the &apos;Install CD&apos;
                            must be received. Any requests made after this date
                            will be considered orders for the next release of
                            Ubuntu.</para>
                    </note>
                    <para>Another method of obtaining Ubuntu is to join a local
                        Linux Users Group (LUG) and ask if somebody could has a
                        copy and would not mind duplicating it. Normally, you
                        will have to replace the CDs used for the duplication
                        and reimburse any postage or delivery costs.</para>
                    <para>If you do not know of an LUG near you, a list can be
                        found at <ulink url="&lugww;">Linux Users Groups
                            WorldWide</ulink>.</para>
                    <tip>
                        <para>Once you have placed an order via
                                <application>Shipit</application>, you can check
                            to see if your request has been sent to the factory
                            by logging into <ulink url="&ubuntu-shipit;"
                                >Shipit</ulink>. We do not have additional
                            information; ordered CDs may take several weeks to
                            leave the warehouse before being shipped. We're
                            sorry, but we cannot provide information on
                            individual shipments.</para>
                    </tip>
			<sect4>
				<title>Burning ISO Files</title>
				<para>In Windows with <application>Nero Burning ROM</application>:</para>
				<para>
					<orderedlist>
						<listitem>
							<para>
								Download the ISO file to your hard drive. (See <xref linkend="obtaining-cds"/> for instructions on obtaining Ubuntu CDs.)
							</para>
						</listitem>
						<listitem>
							<para>Insert a blank CD into your CD writer.
							</para>
						</listitem>
						<listitem>
							<para>Start Nero Burning ROM.</para>
						</listitem>
						<listitem>
							<para>Follow the wizard and select Data CD.
							</para>
						</listitem>
						<listitem>
							<para>When the wizard finishes, click Burn Image on the File menu. 
							</para>
						</listitem>
						<listitem>
							<para>In the Open dialog box, select the ISO
								file, and then click Open. 
							</para>
						</listitem>
						<listitem>
							<para>In the wizard, click Burn to create the
								&ubuntu; CD. 
							</para>
						</listitem>
					</orderedlist>
				</para>
				<para>In Ubuntu with <application>Nautilus</application>:</para>
				<para>
					<orderedlist>
						<listitem>
							<para>
								Download the ISO file to your hard drive. (See <xref linkend="obtaining-cds"/> for instructions on obtaining Ubuntu CDs.)
							</para>
						</listitem>
						<listitem>
							<para>
								Insert a blank CD into your CD writer. Close the popup that opens - you cannot burn ISOs with the "Burn Data CD" option.
							</para>
						</listitem>
						<listitem>
							<para>
								In <application>Nautilus</application>, right click on the ISO file you just downloaded, and choose 
								<menuchoice>
									<guimenu>Write to Disc</guimenu>
								</menuchoice>. The <guilabel>Write to Disc</guilabel> dialog opens.
							</para>
						</listitem>
						<listitem>
							<para>
								In the dialog, choose your CD writer and speed, then click on <guibutton>Write</guibutton>. The <guilabel>Writing Files to Disc Progress</guilabel> dialog opens, and <application>Nautilus</application> starts writing the disk.
							</para>
						</listitem>
					</orderedlist>
				</para>
			</sect4>
                </sect3>
            </sect2>

	</sect1>

	<sect1 id="linux-basics" status="writing">
	<title>Linux Basics</title>
		<sect2 id="terminals">
		<title>Terminals</title>
            <para>Working at the command line is not as daunting a task
                as you would think, there is no special knowledge needed to know
                how to use the command line, it is a program like everything
                else. Most things in Linux can be done using the command line,
                although there are graphical tools for most programs, sometimes
                they are just not enough. This is where the command line comes
                in handy.</para>
    	      <para>The <application>Terminal</application> is located in
                    &terminal;, the terminal is often called the command
                    prompt, or the prompt. In days gone by this was the way the
                    user interacted with the computer, however Linux users have
                    found that the use of the prompt can be quicker than a
                    graphical method and still holds some merit today. Here you
                    will learn to use the terminal.</para>
                <para>The original use of the terminal was a file browser and
                    indeed it is still used as a file browser, in the event of
                    the graphical environment failing you can use the terminal
                    as a file browser to navigate your files and undo the
                    changes that have been made.</para>
		<sect3>
		  <title>Common Commands</title>
                <itemizedlist>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>View Directorys: - ls / dir</para>
                        <para>The interesting thing about these commands is that
                            although they do the same thing ls (LiSt) shows
                            different files in different colors with full
                            formatted text, where as dir (DIRectory) just
                            displays the files in one color with no text
                            formatting at all.
                        </para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Create Directorys: - mkdir (directory name)</para>
                        <para>The <application>mkdir</application> (MaKeDIRectory) command will create a directory.</para>
                    </listitem>
		    <listitem>
		    <para>Change Directorys: - cd (/directory/location)</para>
		    <para>The <application>cd</application> (ChangeDirectory) command will change from your current directory to any directory you specify.</para>
		    </listitem>
		    <listitem>
		    <para>Copy Files/Directories: - cp (file or directory name) (to directory or filename)</para>
		    <para>The <application>cp</application> (CoPy) command will copy any files or folders you specify.</para>
		    </listitem>
		    <listitem>
		    <para>Remove Files/Directories: - rm -rf (directory or file name)</para>
	            <para>The <application>rm</application> (ReMove) command will delete any directory or file name you specify.</para>
		    </listitem>
                </itemizedlist>
		    <para>You can also use wildcards to match one or more files, such as "*" (for all files) or "?" 
		    (to match one character). </para>
		</sect3>
		</sect2>
		<sect2 id="root-and-sudo">
			<title>Root And Sudo</title>
			<para>The use of the root user account is unnecessary in Ubuntu, when having to preform actions on your system that require root privileges the "sudo" application enables ordinary users to preform these actions instead. The first user account you created on your system during installation will, by default, have access to sudo.  You can restrict and enable sudo access to users with the "Users and Groups" application (see uag for more information).</para>
			<para>When you run an application that requires root privileges, sudo will ask you to input your normal user password first. This insures that rouge applications cannot damage your system, and serves as a reminder that you are about to preform actions that can damage your system also.</para>
			<para>To use sudo when using the command line, simply type "sudo" before the command you wish to run. Sudo will prompt you on the command line for your users password, enter it then press the enter key to continue.</para>
			<para>Sudo will also remember your password for a set amount of time. This feature was designed to allow users to preform multiple administrative tasks without being asked for a password each time. It is for this reason that once you have entered your password once, remember that you still have access to damage your system and Ubuntu will not stop you.</para>
			<para>Some other tips to using sudo include:</para>
			<itemizedlist>
				<listitem>
				<para>The root account is disabled in Ubuntu for security reasons</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
				<para>To use a "root" terminal, type "sudo -s" at the command line</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
				<para>The entire group of default configuration tools in Ubuntu already use sudo, so they will prompt you for your password if needed.</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
				<para>To run other applications with sudo use Applications->System Tools->Run as different user and choose "Root" as the user.</para>
				</listitem>
			</itemizedlist>
		</sect2>
		<sect2 id="text-editing">
			<title>Text Editing</title>
			<para>Gedit is the default Ubuntu text editor, which you can launch by clicking Applications->Accessories->Text Editor on the desktop menu system. There are also quite a few terminal-based editors available in Ubuntu, popular ones include VIM and Emacs (the use of each causes much friendly debate within the Linux community).</para>
			<para>At times in this guide, Gedit is run from the command line using Sudo, as most configuration files require root privileges to alter them. It's recommended that you also run Gedit from the command line when shown in this guide.</para>
		</sect2>

		<sect2 id="directories-file-systems">
			<title>Directories and File Systems</title>
			<para>TODO</para>
			<para>In Linux and Unix everything is a file. Directories are files, files are files and devices are files. Devices are usually refered to as a node, however, they are still files.</para>
		</sect2>
		<sect2 id="permissions">
			<title>Permissions</title>
			<para>TODO</para>
			<para>All of the files on a linux system have permissions that allow or prevent others from viewing, modifying or executing. The super user "root" has the ability to access any file on the system. Each file has access restrictions, user restrictions and have an owner/group association.</para>
		</sect2>
		<sect2 id="users-and-groups">
			<title>Users and Groups</title>
			<para>TODO</para>
			<para>Include info on setting up new users and adding them to groups here</para>
		</sect2>

	</sect1>	
	<sect1 id="installing-applications" status="writing">
	<title xreflabel="installing applications">Installing Applications</title>
	    <sect2 id="add-applications" xreflabel="the section on adding applications to your Ubuntu system">
		<title>Add Applications</title>
			<para>Add Applications is a graphical way of installing and removing applications in Ubuntu. It uses the Debian package management system behind the scenes to ensure easy, problem free management of applications. To launch Add Applications click
				<menuchoice>
					<guimenu>Applications</guimenu>
					<guimenuitem>Add Applications</guimenuitem>
				</menuchoice> on the desktop menu system.
			</para>
			<para>Each time you launch Add Applications you will be asked for your password. This is to ensure only users who have the appropriate privileges can add and remove applications from your Ubuntu system. To allow other users other then the first initial user to access Add Applications you need to assign them the necessary privileges using the Users and Groups tool (see Users Groups and Sudo for more information).
			</para>
			<para>To install new applications click the category on the left of the screen, then click on the checkbox for the application you want to install. On the right side of the screen, information about each application will appear to help you choose which applications you need. Once satisfied click Apply, then Add/Remove Programs will proceed to download and install your chosen applications, as well as installing any additional applications that are required. You may be asked to insert your Ubuntu CD-ROM to install some packages also.
			</para>
			<para>Some applications and packages are not available to install using Add/Remove Programs. Within this guide, the additional packages will be installed using apt-get on the command line. Optionally, you can use the advanced package manager Synaptic when required (see installing applications using Synaptic below).
			</para>
		</sect2>
	    <sect2 id="synaptic" xreflabel="the section about the Synaptic Package Manager">
		<title>Synaptic</title>
			<para>Synaptic is an advanced package management application that can install and remove every package available to your system. The interface is graphical but a lot more information is presented to the user, however this means that Synaptic gives you complete control over the package management of your system.
To launch Synaptic, choose 
				<menuchoice>
					<guimenu>System</guimenu>
					<guisubmenu>Administration</guisubmenu>
					<guimenuitem>Synaptic Package Manager</guimenuitem>
				</menuchoice> on the desktop menu system.
			</para>
			<para>The Synaptic screen is divided up into four sections, the two most important being the package categories on the left side, and the packages on the right. To install packages, just choose the category, find the package name in the list, right click on it and choose "Mark this package for installation". Once you are satisfied with your selections click <guibutton>Apply</guibutton> on the top menu bar. Synaptic will then download and install the required packages from the online repositories and from your Ubuntu installation CD.
			</para>
			<para>Alternatively you can click the Search tool bar button, enter the package name in the search text field and click the Search button. Synaptic will now show you a much shorter list from which to select your application for installation. This can be much easier than having to look through the very long list of applications on your own.
			</para>
		</sect2>
	    <sect2 id="extra-repositories" xreflabel="the section about adding the Universe and Multiverse repositories">
		<title>Universe and Multiverse Repositories</title>
			<para>There are thousands of software programs available for installation on Ubuntu. These programs are stored in software repositories (archives) and are made freely available for installation over the Internet. This makes it very easy to install new programs in Linux. To organise the software, Ubuntu repositories are categorised into four groups.
			</para>
				<itemizedlist>
					<listitem><para>Main</para></listitem>
					<listitem><para>Restricted</para></listitem>
					<listitem><para>Universe</para></listitem>
					<listitem><para>Multiverse</para></listitem>
				</itemizedlist>
			<para>These four groups of software are also known as "components." The rational used to determine which software goes into which category, or component, is based on two factors:
			</para>
				<itemizedlist>
					<listitem>
						<para>The level of support software development teams are prepared to provide for a program.</para>
					</listitem>
					<listitem>
						<para>The programs level of compliance to <ulink url="http://www.ubuntulinux.org/ubuntu/philosophy">Free Software Philosophy</ulink>.</para>
					</listitem>
				</itemizedlist>
			<para>The standard Ubuntu Install CD contains a subset of software available from the "main" and "restricted" categories. Once your system is made aware of the Internet-based locations for these repositories, many more software programs are made available for installation. Using the software package management tools already installed on your system, you can search for, install and update any piece of software directly over the network, without the need for physical installation media.</para>

<!-- investigate a way of doing this in gai -->

			<para>To enable the extra repositories, first launch Synaptic by choosing
				<menuchoice>
					<guimenu>System</guimenu>
					<guisubmenu>Administration</guisubmenu>
					<guimenuitem>Synaptic Package Manager</guimenuitem>
				</menuchoice> on the desktop menu system. After you type in your password and Synaptic starts:</para>
			<orderedlist>
				<listitem>
					<para>Choose 
						<menuchoice>
							<guimenu>Settings</guimenu>
							<guimenuitem>Repositories</guimenuitem>
						</menuchoice> from the top menu bar in Synaptic, a list of repositories will appear. Click the Settings button at the bottom and tick Show disabled software sources. Then click the Close button. </para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem><para>Back on the list of repositories, checkboxes will appear next to each one. Simply tick each check box to enable the corresponding repository.  Once you have enabled the repositories, click <guibutton>OK</guibutton> to save your settings.</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem><para>Back in the main Synaptic window, update your list of available packages by clicking <guibutton>Reload</guibutton> on the top menu bar. Once you have updated your package lists many more applications and other packages will be available to install.</para>
				</listitem>
			</orderedlist>
		</sect2>
	    <sect2 id="updates" xreflabel="the section about updating your Ubuntu system">
		<title>Updates</title>
			<para>Sometimes the Ubuntu developers release feature and security updates for applications and packages within the Ubuntu system. When these updates are available, Ubuntu will inform you with a pop-up from your notification area. When you see this pop-up, click <guibutton>Show Updates</guibutton>, enter your password and click <guibutton>OK</guibutton>. The Ubuntu Update manager will list available updates, to download and install these updates click <guibutton>Install</guibutton>. Ubuntu will then download and install the available updates from the Internet.  When Ubuntu Update manager has finished updating your system, click <guibutton>Close</guibutton>, then close Ubuntu Update Manager to finish updating your system. 
			</para>
	   </sect2>
	</sect1>
</chapter>
