<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.3//EN" 
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.3/docbookx.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % globalent SYSTEM "../../../libs/global.ent">
%globalent;
<!ENTITY % cdo-C SYSTEM "../../../libs/cdo-C.ent">
%cdo-C;
<!ENTITY % kde SYSTEM "../../libs/kde.ent">
%kde;
<!ENTITY % kde-menus-C SYSTEM "../../libs/kde-menus-C.ent">
%kde-menus-C;
<!ENTITY % kde-general SYSTEM
"/usr/share/apps/ksgmltools2/customization/obsolete/general.entities">
%kde-general;
<!ENTITY % xinclude SYSTEM "../../../libs/xinclude.mod">
%xinclude;
<!ENTITY language "en">
]>
<article id="system-settings" status="complete">
<articleinfo>
<title>Desktop Configuration</title>
&klegalnotice;
<abstract>
<para>
This section contains information about the System Settings application in
Kubuntu.
</para>
</abstract>
</articleinfo>

<!-- SYSTEM SETTINGS -->
<sect1 id="intro" status="complete">
<title>Introduction to Kubuntu System Settings</title>

<para>
Kubuntu's control panel is known as <application>System Settings</application>.
<application>System Settings</application> allows the user to make
configuration changes to items such as locality, accessibility, appearance,
hardware, printing, networking, and much more. To access <application>System
Settings</application> go to &menusysset;.
</para>

<note>
<title>KControl is still there</title>
<para>
Long time users of KDE are probably used to using the
<application>KControl</application> application for making system settings.
<application>KControl</application> is still available by doing
<keycombo><keycap>Alt</keycap><keycap>F2</keycap></keycombo>, type in
<userinput>kcontrol</userinput> and press the <guibutton>OK</guibutton> button.
</para>
</note>
</sect1>

<sect1 id="general" status="complete">
<title>General System Settings</title>

<para>
The <guilabel>General</guilabel> tab offers users the ability to change the
most common settings. Settings here typically don't require a mass amount of
system knowledge and also allow the user to configure their system to look
anyway that they like.
</para>

<sect2 id="personal" status="complete">
<title>Personal</title>

<variablelist>
<varlistentry><term>About Me</term>
<listitem>
<para>
This section contains settings that allow the user to configure information such
as password, name, email, as well as the ability to change the storage location
of important files (i.e., Desktop, Autostart, and Documents).
</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>

<varlistentry><term>Regional &amp; Language</term>
<listitem>
<para>
This section contains settings that allow the user to configure information
such as regional settings (i.e., language, numeric and time), spell checker, as
well as keyboard layout.
</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>

<varlistentry><term>Accessibility</term>
<listitem>
<para>
This section contains settings that allow the user to configure information
such as bell, modifier keys, keyboard filters, activation gestures, as well as
keyboard hot keys all providing improved accessibility features for challenged
users.
</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>

<varlistentry><term>Default Applications</term>
<listitem>
<para>
This section contains settings that allow the user to configure information
such as default email client, text editor, instant messenger, terminal
emulator, and web browser.
</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
</variablelist>
</sect2>

<sect2 id="look-and-feel" status="complete">
<title>Look &amp; Feel</title>

<variablelist>
<varlistentry><term>Appearance</term>
<listitem>
<para>
This section contains settings that allow the user to configure the way their
system looks and feels. Some settings are color schemes, fonts, icons, widget
style and behavior, window decorations, GTK styles and if installed the
<application>KDM Theme Manager</application>.
</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>

<varlistentry><term>Desktop</term>
<listitem>
<para>
This section contains settings that allow the user to change their desktop
behavior.  It is possible to configure things such as background or wallpaper,
screen saver, desktop behavior, and multiple desktops.
</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>

<varlistentry><term>Splash Screen</term>
<listitem>
<para>
This section contains settings that allow the user to change the KDE splash
screen that is seen when logging into the system.
</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>

<varlistentry><term>Window Behavior</term>
<listitem>
<para>
This section contains settings that allow the user to change the window
behavior as well as window-specific settings.
</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>

<varlistentry><term>Notifications</term>
<listitem>
<para>
This section contains settings that allow the user to change system
notifications, the system bell, as well as storage media notifications.
</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
</variablelist>
</sect2>

<sect2 id="comp-admin" status="complete">
<title>Computer Administration</title>

<variablelist>
<varlistentry><term>Date &amp; Time</term>
<listitem>
<para>
This section contains settings that allow the user to change the local
timezone, their time as well as the date.
</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>

<varlistentry><term>Keyboard &amp; Mouse</term>
<listitem>
<para>
This section contains settings that allow the user to change keyboard settings,
keyboard shortcuts, mouse settings, joystick settings, and touchpad settings.
</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>

<varlistentry><term>Monitor &amp; Display</term>
<listitem>
<para>
This section contains settings that allow the user to change size, orientation,
positioning, color and gamma, hardware settings, as well as power saving
options.
</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>

<varlistentry><term>Sound System</term>
<listitem>
<para>
This section contains settings that allow the user to change network sound,
skip prevention, auto-suspend, enable/disable sound system, and hardware
settings.
</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>

<varlistentry><term>Printers</term>
<listitem>
<para>
This section contains settings that allow the user to change printer and
printing options, add/remove printers, as well as the ability to share a
printer across a network.
</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>

<varlistentry><term>User Management</term>
<listitem>
<para>
This section contains settings that allow the user to change user and group
options, add/remove users, and add/remove groups.
</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
</variablelist>
</sect2>

<sect2 id="net-and-connect" status="complete">
<title>Network &amp; Connectivity</title>

<variablelist>
<varlistentry><term>Network Settings</term>
<listitem>
<para>
This section contains settings that allow the user to change and configure
network connections, proxy, connection preferences, and zeroconf service
discovery.
</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>

<varlistentry><term>Sharing</term>
<listitem>
<para>
This section contains settings that allow the user to change file sharing
options, enable/disable file sharing, and local network browsing.
</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>

<varlistentry><term>Bluetooth</term>
<listitem>
<para>
This section contains settings that allow the user to change and manage
<trademark class="registered">Bluetooth</trademark> services and devices.
</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
</variablelist>
</sect2>
</sect1>

<sect1 id="advanced" status="complete">
<title>Advanced System Settings</title>

<sect2 id="sys-admin" status="complete">
<title>System Administration</title>

<variablelist>
<varlistentry><term>Disk &amp; Filesystems</term>
<listitem>
<para>
This section contains settings that allow the user to change disk options,
filesystem options, as well as enable/disable system disks.
</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>

<varlistentry><term>System Services</term>
<listitem>
<para>
This section contains settings that allow the user to change the way system
services start, enable/disable system services, and run level settings.
</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>

<varlistentry><term>Login Manager</term>
<listitem>
<para>
This section contains settings that allow the user to change the appearance,
font, and background of the login window for KDE. Also included in this section
is shutdown options, users specification for logging in, as well as
convenience settings like auto-login and password-less logins.
</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>

<varlistentry><term>Windows Applications</term>
<listitem>
<para>
This section contains settings that allow the user to change options related to
<application>Wine</application>, the Windows application layer for Linux. This
option is only available to users who have installed
<application>Wine</application>.
</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
</variablelist>
</sect2>

<sect2 id="adv-user-settings" status="complete">
<title>Advanced User Settings</title>

<variablelist>
<varlistentry><term>Audio Encoding</term>
<listitem>
<para>
This section contains settings that allow the user to change options for
encoding, file naming, device specification, and error correction.
</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>

<varlistentry><term>KDE Resources</term>
<listitem>
<para>
This section contains settings that allow the user to add, remove, and manage
resources such as contacts, calendar, and notes.
</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>

<varlistentry><term>Service Manager</term>
<listitem>
<para>
This section contains settings that allow the user to monitor, start, and stop
load-on-demand services as well as startup services.
</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>

<varlistentry><term>Session Manager</term>
<listitem>
<para>
This section contains settings that allow the user to change logout and
shutdown options (confirm, enable and disable), how to react at login, and the
default shutdown option.
</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
</variablelist>
</sect2>

</sect1>
</article>
