<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.3//EN" 
	"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.3/docbookx.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % xinclude SYSTEM "../../libs/xinclude.mod">
%xinclude;
<!ENTITY % globalent SYSTEM "../../libs/global.ent">
%globalent;
]>
<chapter id="commontasks-music">
    <title>Listen to Music</title>
    <sect1>
        <title>Ripping audio CDs with Sound Juicer</title>
        <para>Launch Sound Juicer from the Multimedia section of the applications menu. First, you
            should set where you want your music to be ripped to, so select Preferences from the
            Edit menu. Browse to the location of your stored music, or just create a new folder
            (~/music, for example), and select it for use. Close the Preferences window, and insert
            the audio CD you want to rip. If you have an Internet connection, Sound Juicer should
            fill in the information for the CD you inserted. Otherwise, edit the fields
            appropriately. Now, to rip and encode all the tracks, just click the Extract button. You
            can select tracks to rip using the check boxes to the left of each track, if you wish.
            You will be notified when all the tracks have been extracted, and given the option to
	    eject the disc.</para>
    	<para>
		A more thorough explanation of the ins and outs of <application>Sound Juicer</application> can be found <ulink type="help" url="ghelp:sound-juicer">here</ulink>.
    	</para>
    </sect1>
    <sect1>
        <title>Using the Music Player</title>
        <para>Launch the Music Player from the Multimedia section of the applications menu. If this
            is your first time using the Music Player, a &quot;Welcome to Rhythmbox&quot; window will applicationear.
            Click Next to get started setting it up. It will prompt you for the location of your
            music library - if you haven't ripped any CDs yet using Sound Juicer, then you have the
            option to skip this step. Otherwise just click on Browse, browse to the location of your
            music library (~/music, if you went by my example) and click on forward to proceed.
            That's it - just click on applicationly to start browsing your music library.</para>
        <para>Now you can:</para>
        <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
                <para>Search for artists, albums or individual tracks using the Search box.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Narrow down the track listing by selecting individual artists and albums.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Listen to Internet radio - select Radio in the Source list, and choose from
                    the available channels. Alternatively - if you have support for .mp3 installed -
                        <ulink url="&shoutcast;">SHOUTcast</ulink> is a good place to
                    search for more. If you find a channel you like the sound of, then clicking on
                    the &apos;Tune In!&apos; link and agreeing to open the file in Rhythmbox should connect to
                    the channel and start playing it immediately. (if anyone knows of an Ogg Vorbis
                    alternative then replace the SHOUTcast reference with it)</para>
            </listitem>
       </itemizedlist>
     	<para>
		A more thorough explanation of the ins and outs of <application>Rhytmbox</application> can be found <ulink type="help" url="ghelp:rhythmbox">here</ulink>.
    	</para>
    </sect1>
</chapter>
