<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.3//EN" 
	"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.3/docbookx.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % globalent SYSTEM "../../../libs/global.ent">
%globalent;
<!ENTITY % cdo-C SYSTEM "../../../libs/cdo-C.ent">
%cdo-C;
<!ENTITY % gnome-menus-fi SYSTEM "../../../ubuntu/libs/gnome-menus-fi.ent">
%gnome-menus-fi;
<!ENTITY % xinclude SYSTEM "../../../libs/xinclude.mod">
%xinclude;
<!ENTITY language "en">
<!ENTITY ubuntu '<phrase>Ubuntu</phrase>'>
]>
<chapter id="music" status="complete">
			<title>Music and Video</title>
				<para>This section describes the music and video players available to use with Ubuntu and how to configure them to listen to different types of multimedia files.</para>
			<sect1 id="music-files" status="complete">
					<title>Soita ja järjestä musiikkitiedostoja</title>
				<para>To play and organize your music, Ubuntu comes with		    <application>Rhythmbox Music Player</application>, which looks similar to <application>iTunes</application>. When you first start <application>Rhythmbox</application>, it will scan your home directory for any supported music files you have and add it to the database. To start <application>Rhythmbox</application>, choose &rhythmbox;.</para>
					<para>Ubuntu does not directly support the <emphasis role="strong">MP3</emphasis> format, because it is restricted by patents and proprietary rights. Instead Ubuntu supports the <emphasis role="strong">Ogg Vorbis</emphasis> format out of the box, a completely free, open and non-patented format. Ogg Vorbis files also sound better then MP3 files of the same file size and are supported by many portable music players.</para>
					<itemizedlist>
						<listitem><para><ulink url="http://wiki.xiph.org/index.php/PortablePlayers">Players that work with Vorbis</ulink></para></listitem>
					</itemizedlist>
					<para>You can still play your old MP3 files by installing MP3 support (see <xref linkend="codecs"/>). Instructions for other formats, such as Windows Media Audio (wma/wmv) and other patent-encumbered formats can be found <ulink url="http://wiki.ubuntu.com/RestrictedFormats">on the Ubuntu Wiki</ulink>.</para>
				<para>The <application>Cowbell</application> ID3 tag editor can edit the metadata on your
					mp3 and other music files. To use <application>Cowbell</application>:</para>
				<procedure>
						<step>
							<para>Install the <application>cowbell</application> package from the <quote>Universe</quote> repository (see <xref linkend="add-applications"/>);</para>
						</step>
						<step>
							<para>To run <application>Cowbell</application>, choose
								<menuchoice>
									<guimenu>Applications</guimenu>
									<guisubmenu>Sound &amp; Video</guisubmenu>
									<guimenuitem>Cowbell Music Organizer</guimenuitem>
								</menuchoice>.
							</para>
						</step>
				</procedure>
			</sect1>
			<sect1 id="audio-cds" status="complete">
				<title>Musiikkilevyjen (audio-cd) kuuntelu ja kopiointi</title>
				<para>Kun asetat audio-cd:n asemaan, <application>Musiikkimaija</application> musiikin toisto- ja kopiointisovellus käynnistyy automaattisesti. Toistaaksesi musiikkilevyä, napsauta <guibutton>Toista</guibutton> painiketta tai paina näppäinyhdistelmää <keycombo><keycap>Ctrl</keycap><keycap>P</keycap></keycombo>. Toistaaksesi tiettyjä kappaleita levyltä, kaksoisnapsauta raitaa tai valitse raita ja napsauta <guibutton>Toista</guibutton>.</para>
				<para>Kopioidaksesi raitoja musiikkilevyltäsi, varmista että oikeat kappaleet on valittu ja napsauta <guibutton>Kopioi</guibutton>painiketta tai paina näppäinyhdistelmää <keycombo><keycap>Ctrl</keycap><keycap>Enter</keycap></keycombo>.</para>
					<note>
						<para>If you are connected to the internet, <application>Sound Juicer</application> will retrieve the CD artist, title, and track data from <ulink url="http://musicbrainz.org">MusicBrainz.org</ulink>, a community-maintained database of over 360,000 albums.
						</para>
					</note>
				<para>To start <application>Sound Juicer</application> manually, choose 
				<menuchoice>
					<guimenu>Applications</guimenu>
					<guimenuitem>Sound &amp; Video</guimenuitem>
					<guimenuitem>Sound Juicer CD Extractor</guimenuitem>
				</menuchoice>.
				</para>
				<para>You can use the preferences window to control where the extracted audio files are stored on your computer, the filename of extracted audio files, and the file format and codec used for the files. In the main window, choose 
				<menuchoice>
					<guimenu>Edit</guimenu>
					<guimenuitem>Preferences</guimenuitem>
				</menuchoice>.
				</para>
				<para><application>Sound Juicer</application> can extract audio files to these formats:
					<itemizedlist>
						<listitem>
							<para><emphasis role="strong">Ogg Vorbis</emphasis> - A patent-free lossy audio compression format, which typically produces higher quality and greater compression than MP3.</para>
							<itemizedlist>
								<listitem><para><ulink url="http://vorbis.com/faq/">More about Vorbis from vorbis.com</ulink></para></listitem>
							</itemizedlist>
						</listitem>
						<listitem>
							<para><emphasis role="strong">FLAC</emphasis> - The Free Lossless Audio Codec. It can compress audio files up to 50% without removing any information from the audio stream.</para>
							<itemizedlist>
								<listitem><para><ulink url="http://flac.sourceforge.net/">FLAC Web site</ulink></para></listitem>
							</itemizedlist>
						</listitem>
						<listitem>
							<para><emphasis role="strong">WAV</emphasis> - Typically used for voice recordings. <application>Sound Juicer</application> uses this format for low quality mono audio files. 
							</para>
						</listitem>
					</itemizedlist>
				</para>
				<para>You can also extract CD audio files to the proprietary non-free <emphasis role="strong">MP3</emphasis> format. Instructions on how to rip to the MP3 format are in the help for <application>Sound Juicer</application>. Choose 
				<menuchoice>
					<guimenu>Help</guimenu>
					<guisubmenu>Contents</guisubmenu>
				</menuchoice> and navigate to the <emphasis>Preferences</emphasis> section.
				</para>
			</sect1>
			<sect1 id="burning-cds" status="complete">
					<title>CD-levyjen polttaminen</title>
					<para>When you put a blank CD in the drive Ubuntu will ask if you want to burn an audio or data CD. Clicking on <guibutton>Burn Audio CD</guibutton> will launch <application>Serpentine</application> . To add music to your audio CD, either drag music from your File Browser or use the <guibutton>Add</guibutton> button. You will also need to select the size of your CD (21, 74, 80 or 90 minutes). Serpentine will warn you if you exceed the set limit.
					</para>
					<para>To make a photo or data CD, click <guibutton>Burn Data CD</guibutton>. Ubuntu will open a CD/DVD Creator window. The CD Creator is built into the File Browser, and it allows you to add any file or folder you have permission to access. When you are ready to burn the CD, click <guibutton>Write to Disc</guibutton>. Ubuntu will then prompt you to select the drive containing the blank CD, and give you the opportunity to name the CD and select the write speed. Finally, click <guibutton>Write</guibutton> to create the new photo or data CD.
					</para>
			</sect1>

		<sect1 id="video">
		<title>Video Playback</title>
		<para>To play video, Ubuntu comes with <application>Totem Movie Player</application>, which looks and functions similar to Windows Media Player. Features of
		<application>Totem</application> include custom playlists and DVD playback. 
	        You can start <application>Totem</application> by clicking: &totem; from the desktop menu system.
		</para>
		<para>To read video files, <application>Totem</application> uses the <application>Gstreamer</application> framework. To play some video formats, you may need to add further codec support (see <xref linkend="codecs"/>).</para>
		<para>There are also other multimedia applications available. Examples include <application>Mplayer</application>, <application>Xine</application> and <application>Totem-xine</application> (which uses the <application>Xine</application> framework, instead of the <application>Gstreamer</application> framework). You may benefit from trying alternative video players.</para>
		</sect1>

		<sect1 id="codecs" status="complete">
		<title>Multimediakodekit</title>
			<para>Many applications in Ubuntu use the <application>GStreamer</application> open source multimedia framework. The codec plugins for <application>GStreamer</application> are organised in different packages depending on the licensing that applies to the various codecs. You can see which codecs are contained in which plugin on the <ulink url="http://gstreamer.freedesktop.org/documentation/plugins.html">GStreamer website</ulink>.</para>
			<para>Other applications, such as <application>Mplayer</application> and <application>Xine</application>, do not use the <application>Gstreamer</application> framework. Due to patent and copyright restrictions, codecs for these programs are not included at all in Ubuntu. For more information on these read the <ulink url="&restricted-formats;">Restricted Formats</ulink> wiki page.</para>
			<para>Asenna lisäkodekit <application>Gstreamerille</application>:</para>
				<procedure>
					<step>
							<para>Install the following packages from the <quote>Universe</quote> and <quote>Multiverse</quote> repositories (see <xref linkend="add-applications"/>):
								<literallayout>gstreamer0.10-plugins-ugly
gstreamer0.10-plugins-ugly-multiverse
gstreamer0.10-plugins-bad
gstreamer0.10-plugins-bad-multiverse
gstreamer0.10-ffmpeg
								</literallayout>
							</para>
							<note>
								<para>You will need to use <application>Synaptic Package Manager</application> to install these packages.
								</para>
							</note>
							<warning>
								<para>Jotkut näistä paketeistä voivat olla kiellettyjä joissain maissa: varmista että voit käyttää niitä ennen asentamista.</para>
							</warning>
					</step>
				</procedure>
	</sect1>

			<sect1 id="ipod" status="complete">
			        <title>Using an iPod</title>
				<para>You can play music directly off an iPod with <application>Rhythmbox Music Player</application>. Plug the iPod into the computer, and open <application>Rhythmbox</application>.</para>
				<para>To transfer music files to and from an iPod, you can use <application>gtkpod</application>:</para>
					<procedure>
					<step>
						<para>Install the <application>gtkpod</application> package from the <quote>Universe</quote> repository (see <xref linkend="add-applications"/>).
						</para>
					</step>
					<step>
						<para>To run <application>gtkpod</application>, choose
								<menuchoice>
									<guimenu>Applications</guimenu>
									<guisubmenu>Sound &amp; Video</guisubmenu>
									<guimenuitem>gtkpod</guimenuitem>
								</menuchoice>.
						</para>
					</step>
					</procedure>
			</sect1>
			<sect1 id="edit-audio-files" status="complete">
				<title>Muokka audiotiedostoja</title>
					<para>Audacity on ilmainen, avoimen lähdekoodin ohjelma äänen tallentamiseen ja muokkaamiseen. Käyttääksesi Audacitya:</para>
					<procedure>
						<step>
							<para>Install the audacity package from the <quote>Universe</quote> repository (see <xref linkend="add-applications"/>).
							</para>
						</step>
						<step>
							<para>To run <application>Audacity</application>, choose
								<menuchoice>
									<guimenu>Applications</guimenu>
									<guisubmenu>Sound &amp; Video</guisubmenu>
									<guimenuitem>Audacity</guimenuitem>
								</menuchoice>.
							</para>
						</step>
						<step>
							<para>For further help with Audacity, use Audacity’s <guimenu>Help</guimenu> menu.</para>
						</step>							
					</procedure>
			</sect1>

		<sect1 id="dvdplayback" status="complete">
			<title>DVD -toisto</title>
				<para>The movie players provided in Ubuntu are capable of reading DVDs that are not encrypted. However, most commercial DVDs are encrypted with CSS (the Content Scrambling System) and currently for legal reasons it is not possible to include support for these DVDs in Ubuntu. However it is possible to enable support as follows:</para>
				<warning><para>The legal status of this library is not fully clear. In some countries it is possible that the use of this library to play or copy DVDs is not permitted by law. Verify that you are within your rights in using it.</para></warning>
				<procedure>
					<step>
						<para>Asenna <application>libdvdread3</application> -paketti (katso <xref linkend="add-applications"/>).</para>
					<note><para>Sinun tulee käyttää <application>Synaptic-pakettienhallinta</application> sovellusta asentaaksesi tämän paketin.</para></note>
					</step>
					<step>
						<para>To activate DVD decryption, type the following line into a terminal prompt:<screen>sudo /usr/share/doc/libdvdread3/install-css.sh</screen>
						</para>
					</step>
					<step>
						<para>Soittaaksesi DVD:eitä <application>Totemilla</application> sinun täytyy asentaa joitain lisäkodekkeja (katso <xref linkend="codecs"/>).</para>
					</step>
					<step>
						<para>However, the <application>Gstreamer</application> framework (used by <application>Totem</application>) does not support menus or subtitles for DVD playback. For this reason, you can install a separate DVD player, <application>Xine</application>, which supports these. To install <application>Xine</application>, install the <application>gxine</application> package from the <quote>Universe</quote> repository (see <xref linkend="add-applications"/>).</para>
					</step>
					<step>
						<para>Voit avata <application>gxinen</application> Ääni &amp; Video -valikosta</para>
					</step>
				</procedure>
		</sect1>

			<sect1 status="complete">
				<title>DVD-levyjen varmuuskopiointi</title>
					<para>You can back up your DVDs to files or onto DVD+/- discs with <application>DVD::RIP</application>. To install
<application>DVD::RIP</application>:</para>
					<warning><para>Ennen DVD:n varmuuskopiointia, sinun tulee olla varma että sinulla on lainvoimainen oikeus tehdä siitä kopioita.</para></warning>
					<procedure>
						<step>
							<para>Asenna multimediakodekit (katso <xref linkend="codecs"/>).</para>
						</step>
						<step>
							<para>Enable DVD video playback (see <xref linkend="dvdplayback"/>).
							</para>
						</step>
						<step>
							<para>Install <application>dvdrip</application> and <application>transcode</application> from the <quote>Multiverse</quote> repository (see <xref linkend="add-applications"/>).
							</para>
						</step>
						<step>
							<para>You can run the program using the command <application>dvdrip</application> (see <ulink type="help" url="ghelp:user-guide#tools-run-app">the run application manual</ulink> for help on how to run an application without using the menu). If you wish, you can add a menu entry for the program <application>dvdrip</application> (see <ulink type="help" url="ghelp:user-guide#menu-editor">the menu editor manual</ulink> for help on how to add menu entries). We recommend you enter it in the Sound &amp; Video menu, and that you use the file <filename>/usr/share/perl5/Video/DVDRip/icon.xpm</filename> for the icon.
							</para>
						</step>
						<step>
							<para>To start  <application>dvd::rip</application>, choose
								<menuchoice>
									<guimenu>Applications</guimenu>
									<guisubmenu>Sound &amp; Video</guisubmenu>
									<guimenuitem>dvd::rip</guimenuitem>
								</menuchoice>.
							</para>
						</step>
					</procedure>
			</sect1>
		<sect1 status="complete">
			<title>RealPlayer</title>
					<procedure>
						<step>
							<para>Install the <application>realplay</application> package from the <emphasis>Commercial</emphasis> repository (see <xref linkend="add-applications"/>).</para>
						</step>
						<step>
							<para>To run <application>RealPlayer</application>, choose
								<menuchoice>
									<guimenu>Applications</guimenu>
									<guisubmenu>Sound &amp; Video</guisubmenu>
									<guimenuitem>RealPlayer 10</guimenuitem>
								</menuchoice>.
							</para>
						</step>
					</procedure>
			</sect1>
			<sect1 status="complete">
					<title>Videon muokkaus</title>
					<para><application>Kino</application> is an advanced video editor. It features excellent integration with IEEE-1394 for capture, VTR control, and recording back to the camera. It captures video to disk in Raw DV and AVI format, in both type-1 DV and type-2 DV (separate audio stream) encodings. For more information, see <ulink url="http://www.kinodv.org/article/static/2">the Kino website</ulink>. To use it:</para>
					<procedure>
						<step>
							<para>Asenna <application>kino</application> -paketti (katso <xref linkend="add-applications"/>).</para>
						</step>
						<step>
							<para>To run <application>Kino</application>, choose
								<menuchoice>
									<guimenu>Applications</guimenu>
									<guisubmenu>Sound &amp; Video</guisubmenu>
									<guimenuitem>Kino Video Editor</guimenuitem>
								</menuchoice>.
							</para>
						</step>
					</procedure>
					<para>You can also try the <application>PiTiVi</application> video editor by installing the <application>pitivi</application> package from the <quote>Universe</quote> repository (see <xref linkend="add-applications"/>). <application>PiTiVi</application> is a video editor for the GNOME desktop. It is still in fairly early development, but worth a try.</para>
			</sect1>
	   </chapter>

