<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.3//EN" 
	"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.3/docbookx.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % globalent SYSTEM "../../../libs/global.ent">
%globalent;
<!ENTITY % cdo-C SYSTEM "../../../libs/cdo-C.ent">
%cdo-C;
<!ENTITY % gnome-menus-C SYSTEM "../../../ubuntu/libs/gnome-menus-C.ent">
%gnome-menus-C;
<!ENTITY % xinclude SYSTEM "../../../libs/xinclude.mod">
%xinclude;
<!ENTITY language "en">
<!ENTITY ubuntu '<phrase>Ubuntu</phrase>'>
]>
<article id="desktop-effects" status="complete">
	<articleinfo>
		<title>Desktop Effects</title>
    	&legalnotice;
	</articleinfo>
	<sect1 id="compiz-intro" status="review">
		<title>What are Desktop Effects?</title>
			<para>Ubuntu includes special desktop effects, which are intended to make your desktop more fun and easier to use. These include:</para>
			<itemizedlist>
				<listitem>
					<para>Translucent windows</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>3D desktop capabilities</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>Shadow effects</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>Motion effects and animations</para>
				</listitem>
			</itemizedlist>
			<para>Desktop effects are enabled by default, but it is not necessary to have them turned on. In addition, users of computers with certain graphics cards may find that desktop effects do not work well on their computer, or cause the computer to operate more slowly than it would with the effects turned off.</para>
	</sect1>
	<sect1 id="compiz-configure" status="review">
		<title>Configuring Desktop Effects</title>
		<para>Press &desktop-effects; to change basic options relating to desktop effects.</para>
		<itemizedlist>
			<listitem>
			<para>Select <guilabel>No effects</guilabel> to disable desktop effects.</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
			<para>Select <guilabel>Normal effects</guilabel> to enable basic desktop effects.</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
			<para>Select <guilabel>Extra effects</guilabel> to enable all desktop effects.</para>
			</listitem>
		</itemizedlist>
		<para>When you select a new option, it may take several seconds for the change to be applied automatically. During this time, your screen may flicker briefly.</para>
	</sect1>
	<sect1 id="compiz-configure-advanced" status="complete">
		<title>Advanced configuration</title>
		<para>Further configuration of desktop effects is possible, although less straightforward.</para>
		<orderedlist>
			<listitem><para>Press <keycombo><keycap>Alt</keycap><keycap>F2</keycap></keycombo>, type <quote>gconf-editor</quote> and then press <guibutton>Run</guibutton> to start the <application>Configuration Editor</application>.</para></listitem>
			<listitem><para>Navigate to <guilabel>/apps/compiz</guilabel> and change the relevant settings.</para></listitem>
		</orderedlist>
		<para>It is possible to change many settings relating to desktop effects using the <application>Configuration Editor</application>. See the <ulink url='http://compiz.org/Gconf-Editor'>Compiz documentation website</ulink> for full instructions on how to do this.</para>
	</sect1>
	
	<sect1 id="compiz-problems" status="review">
		<title>Problems with Desktop Effects</title>
		<para>If you experience problems when using desktop effects, it is advisable to disable them by pressing &desktop-effects; and selecting <guilabel>No effects</guilabel>.</para>
		<itemizedlist>
			<listitem>
				<para>If you receive the following error message, it is likely that your graphics card does not currently support desktop effects:</para>
				<para><guilabel>Desktop effects could not be enabled</guilabel></para>
				<para>In this case, you will not be able to use desktop effects.</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para>If your computer runs slowly, disabling desktop effects may improve performance. Desktop effects require more system resources, and so older or less powerful computers may not be able to cope with the extra load.</para>
			</listitem>
		</itemizedlist>
	</sect1>
	
	<sect1 id="compiz-moreinfo" status="complete">
		<title>Further information</title>
		<itemizedlist>
		<listitem>
		<para>See the <ulink url='https://help.ubuntu.com/community/CompositeManager'>Ubuntu Community Support pages</ulink> for more information on desktop effects in Ubuntu. </para>
		</listitem>
		<listitem>
	<para>See the <ulink url='http://compiz.org/Documentation/Documentation'>Compiz documentation website</ulink> for more information on advanced configuration of desktop effects.</para>
		</listitem>
	</itemizedlist>
	</sect1>
</article>
