<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.3//EN" 
	"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.3/docbookx.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % globalent SYSTEM "../../../libs/global.ent">
%globalent;
<!ENTITY % cdo-C SYSTEM "../../../libs/cdo-C.ent">
%cdo-C;
<!ENTITY % gnome-menus-C SYSTEM "../../../ubuntu/libs/gnome-menus-C.ent">
%gnome-menus-C;
<!ENTITY % xinclude SYSTEM "../../../libs/xinclude.mod">
%xinclude;
<!ENTITY language "en">
<!ENTITY ubuntu '<phrase>Ubuntu</phrase>'>
]>
<article>
<articleinfo>
	<title>How to contribute to Ubuntu</title>
	<legalnotice id="Credits-And-License">
	    <title>Credits and License</title>
	    <para>Maintainers for the Ubuntu Documentation Team:</para>
		 <itemizedlist>
			<listitem>
		    <para>Jordan Mantha</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
		    <para>Andreas Lloyd</para>
			</listitem>
		 </itemizedlist>
	    <para>Contributors:</para>
		 <itemizedlist>
			<listitem>
				<para>[...]</para>
			</listitem>
		</itemizedlist>
	    <para>This document is made available under a dual license strategy that includes the GNU Free
 	       Documentation License (GFDL) and the Creative Commons ShareAlike 2.0 License (CC-BY-SA).</para>
	    <para>You are free to modify, extend, and improve the Ubuntu documentation source code under the
 	       terms of these licenses. All derivative works must be released under either or both of these licenses.</para>
	    <para>This documentation is distributed in the hope that it will be useful, but WITHOUT ANY
	        WARRANTY; without even the implied warranty of MERCHANTABILITY or FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR
	        PURPOSE AS DESCRIBED IN THE DISCLAIMER.</para>
	    <para>Copies of these licenses are available in the appendices section. See also the online versions:</para>
	    <itemizedlist>
	        <listitem>
	            <para>&fdl-url;</para>
	        </listitem>
	        <listitem>
	            <para>&cc-attrib;</para>
	        </listitem>
	    </itemizedlist>
	</legalnotice>        &copyright;
	<authorgroup>
		&author-ubuntu-documentation-project;
	</authorgroup>
        <abstract>
		<para>This section deals with how to get involved and contribute to the Ubuntu project.</para>
        </abstract>
        &disclaimer;
        &publisher;
  </articleinfo> 
    <para>Every Ubuntu user can participate in the Ubuntu
    community. Here are some starting points for people who want to
    help shape the direction that Ubuntu takes.</para>
    <para>You can participate in the Ubuntu community on many
    levels, from simply giving advice to fellow Ubuntu users to
    becoming a maintainer of core packages. We welcome new drive
    and ideas and any contributions to improve Ubuntu and spread
    Free Software. Anyone who has made significant contributions to
    the Ubuntu community can be recognized as an Ubuntu Member,
    giving you the right to vote on defining the goals and vision
    that drive us. The membership process is described in detail
    here.</para>
  <section>
    <title>Advocacy</title>
    <para>The easiest way to give back to the Ubuntu community is
    by telling others about Ubuntu and become an Ubuntu
    advocate:</para>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Join or start a 
        <ulink url='http://wiki.ubuntu.com/LoCoTeams'>Local
        Community Team</ulink> and get involved in Ubuntu advocacy,
        activities, talks, help install Ubuntu on new users'
        computers by organizing or attending install parties and
        provide friendly support in your local community and
        language.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Give a talk at your 
        <ulink url='http://lugww.counter.li.org/'>local Linux User
        Group</ulink> or other technical group on Ubuntu! A sample
        of templates, talks and notes given by others in several
        languages are available 
        <ulink url='http://wiki.ubuntu.com/Presentations'>on the
        wiki</ulink>.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Order CDs from 
        <ulink url='http://shipit.ubuntu.com/'>Shipit</ulink> and
        distribute them to people as part of larger groups or on
        your own. Drop them off at LUGs, Internet Cafes or anywhere
        that people use computers. Share the love! But don't fire
        and forget, help people to make the most of the Free
        Software world and to become part of the revolution.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>In general, you should show your friends the power of
        Free Software, spread the word and raise general awareness
        around Ubuntu!</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>Support</title>
    <para>You can make a major contribution to the Ubuntu project
    by helping others use Ubuntu:</para>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Join an email support list or discussion list on the 
        <ulink url='http://lists.ubuntu.com/'>Ubuntu Mailing
        Lists</ulink>. The primary support list is ubuntu-users and
        the primary announcement lists are ubuntu-announce and
        ubuntu-news.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Join the and respond to requests for help
        there.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Join the Ubuntu support and discussion IRC channel:
        #ubuntu on irc.freenode.net</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>Ideas and Feedback</title>
    <para>Help steer the direction we take Ubuntu, by describing
    your vision and ideas for a better server and desktop OS and
    application stack.</para>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Participate in 
        <emphasis role='strong'>discussions and
        brainstorming</emphasis> on the 
        <ulink url='http://wiki.ubuntu.com/'>Ubuntu
        Wiki</ulink> where we work on the fastest-moving documents
        before they are ready for publication on the main web
        site.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Add your ideas to the 
        <ulink url='http://wiki.ubuntu.com/IdeaPool'>Idea
        Pool</ulink> for features you'd like to see in Ubuntu,
        products, marketing suggestions or any other ideas you'd
        like to add here.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    <para>Remember, in the open source world, code counts more than
    talk so try to find friends or link up with people who can help
    turn your vision into reality, or start cutting the code
    yourself if that's your line of interest.</para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>Documentation</title>
    <para>If you get stumped by a problem, chances are good that
    many other people will be frustrated by it as well. If you are
    not in a position to write code to change the situation -- for
    whatever reason -- you can help everyone else out by writing up
    your experience and documenting the solution! Some of the most
    constructive ways to get involved in the Ubuntu documentation
    community might be:</para>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Take notes as you puzzle through a problem and then
        document the solution. Check to see if documentation
        already exists first. If it does, augment or improve
        existing documentation. If it doesn't go ahead and add a
        page in the wiki. Rather than answer a question two or more
        times, write up the answer and make it available to
        everyone in the wiki.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Read through the HOWTOs and other documentation in
        the 
        <ulink url='http://www.ubuntuforums.org/'>Ubuntu
        forums</ulink>, read them over and check them for accuracy,
        and put them in the wiki. Read the 
        <ulink url='https://wiki.ubuntu.com/WikiGuide'>Wiki
        Guide</ulink> for help with this.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>If you are interested in working on the official
        Ubuntu documentation, you can join the Ubuntu Documentation
        Team. Information on getting started with the Documentation
        Team is online at the Documentation team 
        <ulink url='http://doc.ubuntu.com'>website</ulink></para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Help clean, proof read, and test the instructions in
        the community wiki. You can help get an idea of useful
        tasks in the 
        <ulink url='http://wiki.ubuntu.com/WikiToDo'>
        WikiToDo</ulink> for more information.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>Artwork</title>
    <para>If you are more artistic than literary, you can express
    that talent and improve the style and feel of the Ubuntu
    desktop by contributing artwork and helping design the next
    release of Ubuntu.</para>
    <para>If you have skills with wallpapers, Inkscape, icons and
    themes you should contribute to the 
    <ulink url='http://wiki.ubuntu.com/ArtTeam'>Art team</ulink> who
    on icons, themes. You can communicate with the team by joining 
    <ulink url='http://lists.ubuntu.com/mailman/listinfo/ubuntu-art'>
    ubuntu-art</ulink> mailing list.</para>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>You can create and share Ubuntu backgrounds and other
        artwork. You can upload these to any of the following
        places:</para>
        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              <ulink url='http://wiki.ubuntu.com/CommunityArtwork'>
              The Ubuntu Community Artwork wiki page</ulink>
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              <ulink url='http://www.ubuntuforums.org/forumdisplay.php?f=16'>
              The Ubuntu "Art Talk" section of the Ubuntu
              forums</ulink>
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>If your artwork is GNOME based: 
            <ulink url='http://art.gnome.org/'>The GNOME Art
            Center</ulink></para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>If your artwork is designed for Kubuntu: 
            <ulink url='http://wiki.ubuntu.com/KubuntuArtwork'>The
            Kubuntu Artwork Page</ulink></para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>Translation and Localisation</title>
    <para>If your home language is not English but you happen to
    have really good English skills and are comfortable using
    software in English, you can make a huge contribution by
    helping to translate the Ubuntu applications into your home
    language. Even if you just translate a few lines you may make
    all the difference to someone in your own country who is just
    starting to learn about computers and Free Software.</para>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Translate applications that are included in Ubuntu
        into your language using the web-based 
        <ulink url='https://launchpad.net/rosetta'>Rosetta
        translation system</ulink>.</para>
        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>Join the 
            <ulink url='http://lists.ubuntu.com/mailman/listinfo/ubuntu-translators'>
            Ubuntu-Translators</ulink> mailing list to stay in touch
            with other Ubuntu translators.</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Translate documents written by the documentation
        team. This can also be done using 
        <ulink url='https://launchpad.net/products/ubuntu-doc'>
        Rosetta</ulink>.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Translate popular wiki pages within the wiki.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>In order to handle translation, fonts, and other
        issues, you should connect with your 
        <ulink url='http://wiki.ubuntu.com/LoCoTeams'>Local
        Community Team</ulink>. 
        <ulink url='http://docbook.wikiwikiweb.de/LoCo'>
        LoCo</ulink> teams often handle this sort of issue.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>Quality Assurance and Bugs</title>
    <para>Ubuntu, like any piece of software, needs good testers.
    You can contribute to Ubuntu simply by running the latest
    version and reporting bugs and helping follow those bugs until
    they are fixed.</para>
    <para>The first steps in getting involved in Ubuntu QA and
    bug-tracking include:</para>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Running the latest development version of Ubuntu, and
        upgrading regularly.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Subscribing to the 
        <ulink url='http://lists.ubuntu.com/mailman/listinfo/ubuntu-devel'>
        ubuntu-devel</ulink> mailing list online and watching it.
        Many developers post testing and experimental packages to
        mailing list. Testing CDs are often very under-tested. You
        can make an important contribution by following the mailing
        list and reporting bugs and issues that you run
        into.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    <para>Of course, you will run into problems when you run these
    testing and development version of Ubuntu. Using the software
    alone is not a contribution; only when you report the bugs that
    you encounter do you make a meaningful contribution to the
    Ubuntu community.</para>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>When you find bugs, you should report bugs into the 
        <ulink url='https://launchpad.net/distros/ubuntu/+bugs'>
        Ubuntu Malone</ulink>. You can make sure your bugs are more
        useful by carefully reading GNOME projects 
        <ulink url='http://bugzilla.gnome.org/bug-HOWTO.html'>bug
        HOWTO</ulink>.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Look through bugs, especially new bugs, to "triage"
        them and to find, confirm, and close duplicates. This can
        also involve verifying and reproducing bugs adding
        information to the bug description.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Finally, you can make a huge impact by following up
        on bugs in packages that you care about and by fixing
        them!</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    <para>See the documentation on our wiki about 
    <ulink url='https://wiki.ubuntu.com/BugReports'>bug
    reporting</ulink>.</para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>Programming and Packaging</title>
    <para>The final way to make an impact in Ubuntu is by getting
    your hands on the code. You can make technical contributions to
    Ubuntu by writing new software, by packaging additional
    software, and by fixing bugs in software. If you're interested
    in hacking on Ubuntu:</para>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>The first step is to join and begin reading the 
        <ulink url='http://lists.ubuntu.com/mailman/listinfo/ubuntu-devel'>
        ubuntu-devel</ulink> mailing list. This is a requirement for
        anyone who contributes to Ubuntu as a maintainer.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>If you are relatively inexperienced with maintaining
        distribution packages, then you should seek out the 
        <ulink url='http://wiki.ubuntu.com/MOTU'>Masters of the
        Universe</ulink>. The MOTU maintain the packages in
        universe, which has less strict requirements than the core
        Ubuntu components. They also mentor new maintainers on the
        policies and processes of Ubuntu. You can look over the 
        <ulink url='http://wiki.ubuntu.com/MOTUTodo'>MOTU ToDo
        list</ulink> to see which projects need help.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Once you have gained experience with packaging tasks
        (for example, by playing an active role in the MOTU team),
        you will be able to move from a universe-only maintainer to
        an Ubuntu main distribution maintainer, following 
        <ulink url='http://docbook.wikiwikiweb.de/community/processes/newmember'>
        this process</ulink>.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Look through the list of 
        <ulink url='https://launchpad.net/distros/ubuntu/+specs'>
        Ubuntu specifications</ulink>. You can pick one of these
        and there should be enough information to begin with an
        implementation.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>If you are interested in KDE, you may be interested
        in helping with the Kubuntu subproject. There is a list of
        ways to do this on the 
        <ulink url='http://wiki.ubuntu.com/HelpingKubuntu'>Helping
        Kubuntu wiki page</ulink>.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>There are some software projects for Ubuntu that are
        available as paid bounties. You can look through the 
        <ulink url='http://docbook.wikiwikiweb.de/community/bounties'>
        list of bounties</ulink> and then submit a proposal and
        references.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Write and package brand new software for Ubuntu. We
        can get new software into the Ubuntu Universe so that
        people can try it out and give you feedback, and in time it
        may become part of the Ubuntu Main portfolio of
        applications that are available to all Ubuntu users by
        default.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </section>
</article>
